<div type="chapter">
<pb n="26"/>
<pb n="26" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER ONE MAGIC, MYTH, AND NATURE: LANDSCAPES OF PREHISTORIC, EARLY ANCIENT, AND CONTEMPORARY PEOPLES</hi></head>
<figure xml:id="fig-4">
<graphic url="CH1_001.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">T</hi>hroughout the ages landscapes have reflected cosmological notions underlying one of humanity's great imponderables: Where are we? How was the world created, and what is the place and fate of human beings within the contexts of space and time?</p>
<p>In this preliminary chapter our task is not to study, as we will later, the landscapes that express the creation stories of scrip-<lb/>
ture-based religions such as Islam or Christianity, nor those that serve as paradigms of cosmological reason such as the gardens of seventeenth-century <name type="place">France</name>, nor ones that reflect a contem-<lb/>
porary cosmology based upon the science of physics and recent discoveries subsumed under the term chaos theory. Here we must examine something more basic, the rootedness in the human psyche of certain fundamental spatial constructs that relate to our upright posture, directional movement, desire to locate our-<lb/>
selves in space in ways that are charged with societal meaning, and our yearning for connection with the infinite and eternal.</p>
<p>Myth, religion, philosophy, and science are all rooted in cosmogony, the attempt to explain the creation of cosmos out of chaos&#x2014;the transformation of primal disorder and confusion into a universe that is systematically arranged, harmonious, whole. By these means, human beings in all times and all places have sought to confer meaning and perceive structure within the nat-<lb/>
ural world. Only through the human mind's dynamic transfor-<lb/>
mation over the previous several centuries&#x2014;a phenomenon of restless revisionism more characteristic of Western society than of other world cultures&#x2014;have myth, religion, philosophy, and science been teased apart and made separate spheres of belief and knowledge. Here we must try to understand how non-West-<lb/>
ern peoples in widely separated parts of the earth and in periods of time both vastly removed and continuing to the present have created landscape forms of astonishing universality in cultures&#x2014; both prehistoric and extant&#x2014;where cosmology reflects a fusion of mythic, religious, philosophic, and scientific thought.</p>
<p>Over time, the development of geometry, surveying, and structural mechanics gave birth to the art of architecture. But here, too, we must be careful not to assign the technical special-<lb/>
ization and the epistemological segmentation of modern Western culture to societies of the distant past who lived long before many of the practices and values of Western industrial society were established or to those that live today outside its precepts. Fur-<lb/>
ther, in considering our topic, the history of landscape design, it is especially important to understand that the perception of vol-<lb/>
umetric, terrestrial space&#x2014;the foundation of our enterprise in both a practical and a theoretical sense&#x2014;is hugely variable, altering with the cosmological and teleological understanding of each age.</p>
<p>To be more specific, since the Renaissance, the Western mind has presumed a spatial concept based upon perspective and a central vanishing point where all the lines of an imaginary hor-<lb/>
izontal planar grid converge. Particularly after the French math-<lb/>
ematician and philosopher <name type="pname">Ren&#x00E9; Descartes</name> (<date when="1596">1596</date>&#x2013;<date when="1650">1650</date>) expounded his theory of spatial extension&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">res extensa</hi>&#x2014;in the seventeenth century, this notion of value-neutral space as a uni-<lb/>
versal proscenium theater in which objects are arrayed in accor-<lb/>
dance with the laws of perspective has governed landscape design theory and practice. Beginning in the second half of the eighteenth century, designed landscape space in the West became explicitly pictorial. It was consciously invested with the scenic values of landscape painting, which, though less obviously perspectival than the axially geometric gardens of the seventeenth century, nevertheless remained faithful, until the advent of twentieth-cen-<lb/>
tury modernism, to the same underlying principle of pictorial representation. However, the art of such societies as the Chinese, the Byzantine, or Inuit shows that participants in these cultures were uninterested in spatial perspective, not through ignorance, but because of an entirely different attitude toward the interpre-<lb/>
tation and construction of representational space.<ref target="#CH1-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref></p>
<pb n="27"/>
<pb n="27" type="orig"/>
<p>The belief in spatial hierophany&#x2014;the notion that within the larger sanctity of nature some places are especially sacred&#x2014;prac-<lb/>
tically universal in prehistoric cultures and residual in some parts of the world today, militates against the assumption of a spatial continuum ordered purely by mathematics and Western theories of spatial perspective. Prehistoric and ancient peoples joined architecture and sacred forms in nature and in so doing invented, without naming it, the art of landscape design. In terms of three-di-<lb/>
mensional planning employing axes and the measurement of form and spatial distance, the landscapes they created do not merely link or give scale to terrestrial monuments but have cosmological alignment and significance. To understand place-making as a human activity it is important for us to investigate&#x2014;as best we can from contemporary Western society's vastly different, secu-<lb/>
larized, historicized point of view&#x2014;the cultural values of the first shapers of space along with those who have continued to create landscapes that reflect a similar cosmology.</p>
<p>Early societies sought survival through rituals intended to propi-<lb/>
tiate the forces of nature. In their attempts to understand the cos-<lb/>
mos and interpret the all-important seasonal rhythms of nature, these people became Earth's first astronomers. But to imply that they were scientists in the modern sense of the word is wrong; astronomy was indivisibly linked to religion. In contrast to the highly individual and personal nature of contemporary religious faith and the resolutely secular nature of modern science, the ritual and augural ceremonies of prehistoric and early ancient peoples were holistic societal practices, which took place in nature. Although quite probably they considered all of nature to be animated by spiritual forces, as members of human societies they experienced a psychological need to shape space in nature in spiritually significant ways. Almost universally, this meant establishing a relationship of form and alignment between built and natural features as well as an orientation to certain celestial reference points&#x2014;the predictable and calendrically determined positions of sun, moon, stars. These cosmologically referential landscape constructions and ceremonies were considered vital to the continuance of the communities they served. In addition, in their search for harmony with the universe, prehistoric and ancient humans assigned a presiding spiritual force to certain mountains, springs, caves, trees, and animals, ascribing to them sacred mean-<lb/>
ing. Those who subscribe to similar belief systems today invest nature with sanctity and certain sites with religious significance, a concept quite alien to others who view land in secular and util-<lb/>
itarian terms, as a commodity serving economic rather than spir-<lb/>
itual ends.</p>
<p>Paleolithic cave paintings, Neolithic stone circles, Meso-potamian ziggurats, Egyptian pyramids and obelisks, Hindu temples, Cretan nature sanctuaries, Mycenaean citadels, and the pyramids, mounds, and effigy earthworks of pre-Spanish-con-<lb/>
quest Americans&#x2014;these were all expressions of a partnership between human beings and unseen spiritual forces. The creators of these forms, who also invested their landscape settings with symbolical meaning and design intent, invoked the magical pow-<lb/>
ers of spirits&#x2014;those of the beasts whose flesh sustained them and of the gods and goddesses who controlled the cosmos and were responsible for human and animal fertility and the growth of crops. In a highly uncertain world, these creative people watched the skies, studying the rotations of celestial bodies, harbingers of the predictable annual cycle of rain and solar warmth and auguries of victory in battle. In the process, they created the first complex human societies, constructed important ceremonial centers, and evolved the world's earliest cities.</p>
<p>The built environments shaped by these early human cul-<lb/>
tures and many of those that succeeded them reflected their reli-<lb/>
gious preoccupation with the cosmos. What is most striking about these very earliest societies is their fusion of myth-based religion and scientific observation. Limited but certain in their perception of the planet and the cosmos, they rooted themselves firmly and assigned religious meaning to place. When we understand how deeply embedded cosmology once was in religious mythos, we can comprehend cosmological landscape design&#x2014;the shaping of the earth and the erection of monuments to reflect a cosmic par-<lb/>
adigm. The universality of the axis, the pyramid, and the grotto in cultures as distant in space and time as those of the ancient Near East, prehistoric <name type="place">Europe</name>, <name type="place">India</name>, and the pre-Columbian Americas makes sense when we realize that these forms express cosmic concepts that owe their similarity to their origins in the human psyche. This, rather than certain theories of cultural transmission, seems to account for the similarity of landscape constructions as widely separated in site and date as the Egyptian and Mayan pyramids.</p>
<p>The cave, especially, as sanctuary, the womb of Earth, a place of cultic mystery and ritual revitalization, occupies a priv-<lb/>
ileged place in the human imagination. Its many manifestations include the Egyptian tomb carved into the cliff face or nestled within the bowels of a pyramid, the subterranean sanctuaries of the Snake Goddess in prehistoric <name type="place">Greece</name>, the cave beneath the Pyramid of the Sun at <name type="place">Teotihuac&#x00E1;n</name> Shiva cave-temples at <name type="place">Elephanta</name>, <name type="place">Ellora</name>, and <name type="place">Salsette</name> in <name type="place">India</name>, and the <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi> of Puebloan cultures in the American Southwest. Associated with the cave is the rule of an earth goddess, which is rooted in universal myths that recognize the earth as a generative and procreative force, the fertile source of human and animal vitality. The cave, with its labyrinthine passages, suggests the intimacy of the mother's womb, the place from which life was observed to emerge. In addition, caves and crevices in the earth's surface are sources for springs, and shrines at caves or near springs are especially prev-<lb/>
alent in dry lands. Understandably, a psychological attraction toward moist mysterious openings within the earth has persisted down through the millennia. The architectural grotto in ancient Roman villa gardens, which Renaissance garden-builders revived and passed on to subsequent eras and diverse cultures, is a sophis-<lb/>
ticated version of the cave sanctuaries in which prehistoric ances-<lb/>
tors worshipped.</p>
<p>The work of <name type="pname">Mircea Eliade</name>, scholar of world religions and early myths, beliefs, and practices, confirms that among members of prehistoric and some contemporary cultures there exists the conviction that the natural world is imbued with divinity. <name type="pname">Eliade</name>
<pb n="28"/>
<pb n="28" type="orig"/>
points out that the most elemental sacred places constitute a microcosm, "a landscape of stones, water, and trees."<ref target="#CH1-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref> In this way humans evoke the durable potency of stone, the fertility associated with water, and the fecundity of nature as embodied in the liv-<lb/>
ing tree. The notion of an immanent sanctity within earth and sky is culturally pervasive, and from this is derived the concept of <hi rend="italic">genius loci</hi>, spirit of place, and the idea of guardian deities of place.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-5">
<graphic url="CH1_002.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.1. Diagram of <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>One way to explain the similarity and universality of myths and the pictorial con-<lb/>
figurations and landscape constructs that reflect them is to study the psychological theories of <name type="pname">Carl Jung</name> (<date when="1875">1875</date>&#x2013;<date when="1961">1961</date>).<ref target="#CH1-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref> According to <name type="pname">Jung</name>, archetypes&#x2014;formal images that symbolically express quintes-<lb/>
sential meanings&#x2014;cannot be directly iden-<lb/>
tified and subjected to control by the conscious mind. Therefore, they find expression in myths. Just as <name type="pname">Jung</name>'s own teaching is based upon four-bodiedness, or four states of perceiving (thinking, feeling, intuition, sensation), the archetype of quaternity as expressed in the four-part circle and the four car-<lb/>
dinal points can be found in the landscape constructions of many cultures. In addition, the Great Mother, the Tree of the World, and Paradise are examples of Jungian archetypes, and the symbol of the snake, the sphinx, and various helpful animals are also symp-<lb/>
toms of states within what <name type="pname">Jung</name> calls the collective unconscious. The metaphorical nature of landscape design and the prevalence of certain formal means of shaping space and expressing basic mythic concepts through architecture and decoration can thus be analyzed in Jungian terms as archetypal manifestations of primor-<lb/>
dial ideas that continue to resonate within the human imagination.</p>
<p>Creation myths deal with the evolution of cosmos out of chaos. Implicit in this is the act of giving form and place to objects and space. The positioning of Earth in the center of the universe and the centering of human societies within the world are funda-<lb/>
mental constructs within many early cosmologies. Cosmic center-<lb/>
ing involves awareness of three vertical strata: above, below, and a terrestrial middle plane. It also involves cardinal directionality&#x2014; the location of four principal axes along a 360&#x00B0; horizon line in accordance with the movement of the sun and various stars and planets. In diagrammatic terms, this basic image of the cosmos can be illustrated as in figure 1.1.</p>
<p>So firmly fixed is this cosmological model in the human consciousness that it appears not only in widely different parts of the world, but also in many eras, being appropriated through reli-<lb/>
gious syncretism by people of different cultures, including those adhering to Buddhism, Islam, Hinduism, and Christianity. Its ver-<lb/>
tical dimension is an <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi>, which acts like a center pole uniting heaven, Earth, and the underworld. Lakes are watery nether regions located just below the surface of the land, and, like caves, they are places of underworld entrance and exit. These are identi-<lb/>
fied with female procreation and spirits that reside in darkness. The underworld is also the domain of serpent deities prevalent in several cultures. Moun-<lb/>
tains, the realm of air and celestial light, are identified with sky-dwelling gods who con-<lb/>
trol cosmic order and thereby the welfare of human beings. They are sites of celestial communication between these gods and human beings occupying the intermediate terrestrial realm with its broad circular hori-<lb/>
zon.</p>
<p>The apparent east-west rotational movement of the sun across the heavens and the observation of its equinoctial position in relation to the horizon gave human beings their primary orientation on a horizontal plane. The bisection of this axis with a north-<lb/>
south one divided sky and Earth into quad-<lb/>
rants, providing an elemental framework for celestial observation and terrestrial naviga-<lb/>
tion. With these six cosmic coordinates&#x2014; east, west, north, south, zenith, and nadir&#x2014;embedded in consciousness, human societies formed settlements within the expansive earthly sphere through acts of centering.</p>
<p>The siting of places of habitation is governed by such prac-<lb/>
tical considerations as the presence of water and the arability of land. But given these limitations, when Earth was relatively unpop-<lb/>
ulated and there was available a wide range of options, cultural groups also sought to settle themselves in places perceived to have a relationship to divine power, which generally meant in alignment with cosmic coordinates and landforms associated with mythic forces. Many were attracted to karstic formations&#x2014;limestone strata riddled with caves and seeping with springs&#x2014;and to arable valleys near mountains. Often, cultural groups expended enormous human resources constructing a mountain-mimicking pyramid, ziggurat, or temple in order to establish an <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi> that would firmly relate it to a cosmic deity.</p>
<p>No one cared that there were many groups and multiple <hi rend="italic">axes mundi;</hi> what mattered was a representation of the cosmic arche-<lb/>
type, consecration rites surrounding the creation of a cosmic land-<lb/>
scape, and sanctification of the site through worship. Thus centered symbolically in space, more than one city could imagine its cos-<lb/>
mically connected, temple-crowned, human-made mountain as the navel of the earth. In a similar manner, through the repetition of cosmogonic rituals, temporality was displaced by timelessness.</p>
<p>Looking at archaeological sites of former cosmological land-<lb/>
scapes today, we lack the ritual dimension that once gave them religious significance. Only in a few cultures where people still seek cosmic alignment within nature do we find ritual practices that link humans with the cosmos, as for example when dancers re-en-<lb/>
act archetypal gestures and commemorate mythical moments through choreographed movement. We may surmise, however, that all sacred landscapes were once alive with dancing and other ritu-<lb/>
als in which music and chanting dramatized the myth-based cos-<lb/>
mologies that sustained a sense of sacred order in the world.</p>
<div type="section">
<pb n="29"/>
<pb n="29" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Caves and Circles: Sustaining Life and Discerning Cosmic Order</hi></hi></head>
<p>During the eons of Paleolithic habitation of Earth, when a shield of ice still covered parts of the globe that are temperate today, the cunning of a tool-making and weapon-wielding being was pitted against the speed and bulk of large roaming beasts. In this Old Stone Age, the virtually trackless steppes, savannas, and forests were home to small bands of hunter-gath-<lb/>
erers who have left only slight evidence of their pres-<lb/>
ence. Because there is no written record of this time, what we know of their customs, practices, and rela-<lb/>
tionship to the land is based on the scattered and lim-<lb/>
ited finds of archaeologists and paleontologists.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Old World Caves</hi></hi></head>
<p>Such celebrated echoes from the last Ice Age as the caves at <name type="place">Lascaux</name> in the <name type="place">Dordogne region</name> of <name type="place">France</name>, discovered in <date when="1940">1940</date>, <name type="place">Cosquer Cave</name> on the <name type="place">Mediterra-<lb/>
nean near Marseilles</name>, discovered in <date when="1991">1991</date>, and <name type="place">Chau-<lb/>
vet Cave</name> in the <name type="place">Ard&#x00E8;che region</name> of the <name type="place">Rh&#x00F4;ne Valley</name>, discovered in <date when="1994">1994</date>, contain hundreds of images of large animals depicted in charcoal and vegetable col-<lb/>
ors on their walls (fig. 1.2). The vitality of the paint-<lb/>
ings may derive from their association with a propitiatory ritual to ensure the continued fertility of these beasts. One recent archaeological theory, how-<lb/>
ever, explains them pragmatically, as instructional guides transmitted from one generation to the next. In this way, hunter-initiates might have been trained to track individual bison and other large beasts indi-<lb/>
vidually in times when animal populations waned and mass kills of entire herds were impossible.<ref target="#CH1-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref> The por-<lb/>
trayal of hoofprints and other informational clues of particular importance to the hunter, such as large ant-<lb/>
ler size, support the thesis of the paintings' didactic function. Some images indicate animals in a posture of bellowing or emitting their distinctive sounds, a reminder both of the importance of such auditory sig-<lb/>
nals for prehistoric hunters and the degree to which they were responsively attuned to the aural dimen-<lb/>
sions of space.<ref target="#CH1-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref> Finger tracings and hand stencils, found in <name type="place">Cosquer</name> and <name type="place">Chauvet</name>, as well as in such widely separated sites as the <name type="place">Canyon de Chelly</name> in <name type="place">Arizona</name> and a cave in the <name type="place">Laura</name> area of <name type="place">Australia</name>, symbolize the taking possession of such spaces by humans.<ref target="#CH1-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref> The marking over of these nonartistic sym-<lb/>
bols at a subsequent period by others is an obvious indication of assertion of power by a later group.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-6">
<graphic url="CH1_003.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.2. <name type="place">Lion Panel</name>, <name type="place">Chauvet Cave</name>, <name type="place">southern Ard&#x00E8;che</name> (<name type="place">Rh&#x00F4;ne Valley</name>), <name type="place">France</name>. c. 30,000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Though we can never fully comprehend the mentality of the Paleolithic artists who created these paintings nor that of the hunters who derived meaning from them, we can surmise that whatever instructional purpose these images may have served, they were also allied with some kind of religious practice. The fact that they are within caves places them naturally in the rich realm of the human unconscious, with its well-es-<lb/>
tablished repertoire of archetypes. Like the later ancient Greek and Roman practitioners of the Ele-<lb/>
usinian mysteries in which initiates were guided through a series of underground passages as part of a chthonic, or underworld, ritual based upon the legend of <name type="pname">Demeter</name> and <name type="pname">Persephone</name>, the prehistoric people who made the cave art appear to have been sensitive to the spatial aspects of the caves and to have taken into consideration the routes leading into them. Pas-<lb/>
sage and chamber are integral parts of their planning, and an obvious concentration of art in an inner sanc-<lb/>
<pb n="30"/>
<pb n="30"/>
tum gives the impression of a corresponding inten-<lb/>
sity of experience and concentration of ritual there.<ref target="#CH1-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-7">
<graphic url="CH1_004.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.3. <name type="place">Menhirs</name>, <name type="place">Carnac</name>, <name type="place">France</name>. 3rd millennium <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The cave would surely have served as a sound chamber, and we may suppose that its resonant properties would have been exploited in ritual chants and perhaps also the beating of drums.<ref target="#CH1-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref> Fur-<lb/>
ther, it may be wrong to assume that prehistoric cave art is an objective representation of what the artists saw. Rather, we might think of it as animated line, a graphic expression of the life force inherent in nature. The way in which the figures are disposed to take advantage of certain plastic characteristics of walls of the cave is congruent with the notion of haptic, or tactile, rather than straightforward, optical perception, and the conception of space on the part of those who created these dynamic images was surely different from our sense of space as some-<lb/>
thing defined, measurable, and emplaced.<ref target="#CH1-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref> Finally, the universality of religious practice among all soci-<lb/>
eties, and especially, as we must imagine, prehis-<lb/>
toric ones, makes it possible to suppose that the protein diet that the painted animals in the caves represented was obtained with some form of cere-<lb/>
monial enactment sanctifying the spirit embodied by the living creatures.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Old World Menhirs and Circles of Stone and Wood</hi></hi></head>
<p>The evolutionary development of agriculture and animal husbandly in the Neolithic, or New Stone Age, brought with it greater stability and confi-<lb/>
dence. Human beings formed more or less perma-<lb/>
nent settlements and imprinted the land by their occupancy. Boundary as a concept arrived when people began to circumscribe villages and subdi-<lb/>
vide land into fields. Megaliths, giant stones expelled from the maws of the retreating glaciers at the end of the last Ice Age, were upended, the world's first monuments (fig. 1.3).<ref target="#CH1-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref> That these <hi rend="italic">menhirs</hi>, as the huge markers found chiefly in <name type="place">Brit-<lb/>
ain</name>, <name type="place">Ireland</name>, and northern <name type="place">France</name>, are called, pointed a stony finger skyward was not accidental. Settle-<lb/>
ment within agricultural communities brought a new range of fears. Now it was not enough to ensure that animal spirits were propitiated and the lives of the beasts perpetuated. The cooperation of the cos-<lb/>
mos itself was necessary if crops were not to fail and the now-cohesive and increasingly specialized social unit were to thrive. Humans were keenly aware of their dependence upon the sun and also upon the moon and stars. Diligent skywatchers, they associated the positions of various celestial bodies with recurring seasonal patterns.</p>
<p>The awe-inspiring megalithic forms of Stone-<lb/>
henge were erected upon the gently rolling grassland of the <name type="place">Salisbury Plain</name> in southern <name type="place">England</name> in a suc-<lb/>
cession of construction campaigns between 2750 and 1500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> They outline a ritual center that may have functioned as a religious festival space where celebrations relating to its function as an astronom-<lb/>
ical observatory were held (figs. 1.4, 1.5). This impressive work of architecture, sited at the conflu-<lb/>
ence of several lines of hills, originated as an earth-<lb/>
work. The first builders of Stonehenge described a huge circle in the white chalky earth, which they then piled up in two banks broken only in one spot. They flanked this opening with two small upright stones. Beyond these, slightly off-axis with the break, they erected a 35-ton, roughly cylindrical, tapering megalith of sarsen, a gray sandstone from the nearby <name type="place">Marlborough Hills</name>. Called variously the <name type="place">Friar's Heel</name>, <name type="place">Hele Stone</name> (perhaps from the Anglo-<lb/>
Saxon word_<hi rend="italic">helan</hi>, meaning "to conceal"), Heel Stone, Sun Stone, Index Stone, and Petrie's Stone 96, this marker was ascertained by eighteenth-cen-<lb/>
tury scientists to be aligned with an imaginary axis drawn between the rising sun and the center point of the circle on the day of the summer solstice. At least one modern archaeologist has pointed out that in the case of the many photographs depicting this phenomenon, the photographer has stood a few paces away from the center of the circle because the rising solstice sun is not concealed by the megalith but appears a foot and a half to the left.<ref target="#CH1-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref> This does not, however, negate an interpretation based upon archaeoastronomy, relating earthworks with the positions of heavenly bodies at certain important points in the calendrical cycle. The megalith does lie along an axis from the center of the circle to the horizon midway between the major northern moon-<lb/>
rise and the minor northern moonrise, and it may have once aided observers of these lunar events.</p>
<p>Stonehenge served as a ritual center over
<pb n="31"/>
<pb n="31" type="orig"/>
several centuries, and there was evidently enough social cohesion and sufficiently advanced technology for undertaking additional building programs. One generation of laborers constructed a 35-foot- (10.7-<lb/>
meter-) wide avenue, defined by chalk embankments like the original circle. It ran in a straight line along the axis of the megalithic outlier, bending somewhat as it approached the river <name type="place">Avon</name>. The Stonehenge builders next erected monoliths of bluestone weigh-<lb/>
ing up to 5 tons each in a double ring, open at the point of the axis. Although it has long been held that these were quarried from the distant <name type="place">Preseli Moun-<lb/>
tains</name> in <name type="place">Wales</name> and then transported some 300 miles (483 kilometers) by land, sea, and river to the site, an alternative, less heroic supposition holds that boulders plucked by the ice sheet that once moved ponderously across this part of the world carried enough Preseli bluestones as glacial erratics to fur-<lb/>
nish builders with the material they needed for their double ring of megaliths within much closer range.<ref target="#CH1-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-8">
<graphic url="CH1_005.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.4. Stonehenge near <name type="place">Salisbury</name>, <name type="place">Wiltshire</name>, England. c. 2750&#x2013;1500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-9">
<graphic url="CH1_006.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.5. Plan of Stonehenge</hi></figDesc>
<p><hi rend="bold">A</hi> Heel Stone</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">B</hi> Ditch</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">C</hi> Embankment</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">D</hi> Bluestone Ring</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E</hi> Circle of Trilithons</p>
</figure>
<p>In any case, a subsequent generation of builders put these bluestones aside in favor of much larger megaliths of <name type="place">Marlborough</name> sarsen quarried nearby, which they arranged as trilithons&#x2014;two upright "col-<lb/>
umns" with a bridging lintel&#x2014;in a horseshoe pattern with the open side facing the established axis of entry. Sometime prior to this construction campaign, which was probably executed by <name type="pname">Breton</name> immi-<lb/>
grants&#x2014;inasmuch as horseshoe arrangements of megaliths are found commonly in Brittany but only rarely in <name type="place">Britain</name>&#x2014;a rectangle with its sides aligned to the cardinal points was carefully laid out within the circular chalk embankments. Its four corners were at the time marked by megaliths. Around the horseshoe, in a prodigious demonstration of struc-<lb/>
tural sophistication, another building campaign resulted in the familiar ring of slightly tapering sar-<lb/>
sens topped by lintels subtly curved and interlocked so as to form an integral circular architrave about 20 feet (6.1 meters) above the ground. A subsequent rearrangement of the bluestones to emphasize the
<pb n="32"/>
<pb n="32" type="orig"/>
sarsen horseshoe and its surrounding sarsen circle completed the work on this mighty monument.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-10">
<graphic url="CH1_007.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.6. <name type="place">Woodhenge</name>, <name type="place">Cahokia</name>, <name type="place">Illi-<lb/>
nois</name>. 1100&#x2013;1200 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Painting by <name type="pname">Lloyd K. Townsend</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>World-famous as an enigmatic relic of the Stone Age and unique for <name type="place">Britain</name> in several respects, includ-<lb/>
ing its builders' use of lintels, Stonehenge is by no means an isolated example of Neolithic landscape architecture. There are many other stone circles in <name type="place">Britain</name> and <name type="place">Ireland</name> that also provide evidence of Neo-<lb/>
lithic astronomy, ritual need, and social congregation. Not surprisingly, over the centuries their mysterious presence in the countryside has engendered many leg-<lb/>
ends regarding Druidical rites, fairy dances, and witches' sabbaths. The phallic shape of certain stones has encouraged their status as objects of fertility wor-<lb/>
ship, and some New Age spiritualists today believe the stone circles to be cosmic power centers.</p>
<p>In addition to the megaliths arranged in circles, postholes indicating the arrangement of timbers as wooden rings have been found, and these, too, prob-<lb/>
ably functioned, like the stones of Stonehenge, as astronomical markers and the architectural definition of ceremonial centers, often with funerary associa-<lb/>
tions. Such a ring, or rather a series of concentric rings, is found a short distance to the northeast of Stonehenge, and archaeological evidence shows that it almost certainly served as both a place for astro-<lb/>
nomical observation and ritual burial.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">New World Circles and Earthworks</hi></hi></head>
<p>Suggesting perhaps <name type="pname">Jung</name>'s psychology of the collec-<lb/>
tive unconscious&#x2014;rather than astonishing coinci-<lb/>
dence&#x2014;there exists an American timber post circle built around 1050 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> at <name type="place">Cahokia</name> near present-day <name type="pname">St. Louis</name> by the mound-building people archaeologists call <hi rend="italic">Mississippian</hi> (see fig. 1.29).<ref target="#CH1-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref> Here calendrically based religious rites reinforced the authority of the powerful elite over the commoners who tilled the fields and built the mounds. To the west of the most prominent earthwork, <name type="place">Monks Mound</name>, archaeologists in the <date when="1960">1960</date>s discovered four series of post- holes forming rings (fig. 1.6). They found fragments of red-<lb/>
stained cedar posts in some of the holes. The first circle of this complex, dubbed the American <name type="place">Wood-<lb/>
henge</name>, consists of twenty-four postholes. A second circle contained thirty-six posts, and a third, dated around 1000 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, sixty. The fourth circle, which was never completed, had holes for only twelve or thirteen of a planned seventy-two-post ring. The second circle of posts has been reconstructed to resemble the orig-<lb/>
inal forty-eight regularly spaced uprights marking various positions of the Sun including, most spectac-<lb/>
ularly, its rise directly over <name type="place">Monks Mound</name> on the days of the spring and fall equinoxes.</p>
<pb n="33"/>
<pb n="33" type="orig"/>
<p>Earthen circles similar to the one encompass-<lb/>
ing the megalithic monument at Stonehenge are also inscribed on the <name type="place">Ohio</name> landscape. The Hopewell people, who occupied the <name type="place">Ohio Valley</name> in the period between 100 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and 400 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, mounded long ridges of earth to outline large circles, squares, pen-<lb/>
tagons, and octagons. The most monumental com-<lb/>
plex of these geometrical mounds is found at <name type="place">Newark</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>, where more than 7 million cubic feet (198,100 cubic meters) of earth were carried in bas-<lb/>
kets to create two large circles, an octagon, and an almost square enclosure, all connected by broad "avenues" extending over an area of 4 square miles (10.36 square kilometers) (fig. 1.7). The avenues are defined by two parallel walls of earth similar to the linear earthen ridges that define the mysterious "roads" emanating from <name type="place">Chaco Canyon</name> in the American Southwest.</p>
<p>In recent years, the astronomer <name type="pname">Ray Hively</name> and philosopher <name type="pname">Robert Horn</name> have discovered a con-<lb/>
vincing rationale for the alignment of the roads and the large geometric forms at <name type="place">Newark</name> and the High Bank works near <name type="place">Chillicothe</name> by proving that the orientation of the earthworks in these places marks the maximum and minimum degrees north and south of true east of the moon's rising and setting on the horizon during an 18.6-year cycle. They also have shown how, in addition to giving physical expression to this impressive astronomical calcula-<lb/>
tion, the builders of the Hopewell earthworks sited them in relationship to one another in ways that demonstrate their mathematical sophistication. It is likely that the geometric enclosures defined by the mounds were built to serve as spaces in which danc-<lb/>
ing, market fairs, and other ritual and social activi-<lb/>
ties took place.</p>
<p>In addition to this kind of focused spatiality, which projected a relationship between earth and sky, there developed throughout the Neolithic Age a chthonic architecture of enclosure centered upon fertility, death, and the spirits of the underworld. Tombs&#x2014;architectural versions of the cave, such as dolmens, simple chambers formed by two or more upright megaliths with a capstone, and other kinds of more elaborate stone-roofed structures&#x2014;were built as sites for the care of the dead as reverence for ancestors increased. Rudimentary temples were also built as enclosures with shrines, altars for animal sacrifice, and spaces for public assembly.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Neolithic Urbanism</hi></hi></head>
<p>The evolution of Neolithic urban societies occurred during the millennium prior to the construction of Stonehenge. They flourished in the <name type="place">Nile Valley</name> in <name type="place">Egypt</name> and in the area known as the <name type="place">Fertile Crescent</name>, a semicircle of arable land extending from the south-<lb/>
east coast of the <name type="place">Mediterranean</name> around the <name type="place">Syrian Desert</name> north of the <name type="place">Arabian Peninsula</name> to the <name type="place">Tigris</name> and <name type="place">Euphrates</name> river plain in <name type="place">Mesopotamia</name>. There was as well a corresponding development in the <name type="place">Indus Valley</name>. The accretion of power within the hands of a ruling elite, who used religious authority as a means of organizing administrative systems, made possible the division of labor. This led to more efficient agricultural production, the crafting of use-specific items and wares, the beginning of trade, the building of monuments, and the birth of cities. Important technological improvements and the administrative capacity to undertake enormous pub-<lb/>
lic works provided an unprecedented degree of con-<lb/>
trol over nature, leading to the agricultural surpluses that made possible large urban settlements. Yet these prosperous societies adhered to religious cosmolo-<lb/>
gies that made them obedient to priestly rulers who understood the movements of celestial bodies and who performed propitiatory rites to ensure fertility of crops and people. These practices are reflected in the ways these two mighty civilizations designed upon the land.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-11">
<graphic url="CH1_008.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.7. <name type="place">Newark Earthworks</name>, <name type="place">New-<lb/>
ark</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>. 100 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and 400 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="34"/>
<pb n="34" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">II. Architectural Mountains and Earth's First Cities: Landscape as Urban Power in Early Ancient Civilizations</hi></hi></head>
<p>In <name type="place">Mesopotamia</name>, between the <name type="place">Tigris</name> and the <name type="place">Euphra-<lb/>
tes Rivers</name>, urbanism of a lasting kind began between 3500 and 3000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Shortly thereafter, another urban culture evolved within the <name type="place">Nile Valley</name> of <name type="place">Egypt</name>. Administrative structures capable of plan-<lb/>
ning and controlling crops to sustain large popula-<lb/>
tions were essential to the development of cities in these two areas. In both lands, rulers shared power with a priestly elite. In addition to furnishing the ritual structure that sanctified life and brought reli-<lb/>
gious practice and protection to the city's inhabi-<lb/>
tants, priests administered a highly organized governing system. Government officials controlled grain storage and distribution, the division of lands, the construction of dikes, dams, and canals, the col-<lb/>
lection of taxes, and the fielding of armies and other means of organizing labor. They also defended the community and kept peace within an increasingly complicated economic and social sphere.</p>
<p>This methodical governance would have been impossible without the invention of writing and the development of a literate class. Literacy enabled communication and recordkeeping. Mathematical literacy enabled computation and measurement. The many portraits of scribes in Egyptian and Mesopo-<lb/>
tamian art attest to the important role of this official in society.</p>
<p>As the carrier of ideas and concepts, literacy had another important and far-reaching result beyond these necessary practical ones. The written word, whether pictographic or hieratic, is a symbol and, as such, is fundamental to the mental concep-<lb/>
tion of other symbolical constructs, so it is safe to say that, for both practical and ideological reasons, the ziggurat, the pyramid, the temple, and the obe-<lb/>
lisk could not have existed in a preliterate world. And it is, of course, through writing as well as through painting, that we today are vouchsafed a glimpse of the relationship between ancient people and nature and of their esteem, and often reverence, for certain plants and animals.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ziggurats</hi></hi></head>
<p>The association of mountaintops with divinity reflects a universal quest for cosmological meaning. This notion is embodied in the artificial ziggurat "mountain," the symbolical juncture of earth and sky deities. For peoples of the ancient Near East the ziggurat served as an earthly counterpart to the pole star, an axis around which the heavens were believed to revolve. It also manifested a cosmology that pre-<lb/>
vailed throughout the Mesopotamian region under the Sumerian (c. 3500&#x2013;2030 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), Akkadian (c. 2340&#x2013;2180 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), and Babylonian (c. <date when="1750">1750</date> and intermittently to 528 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) cultures. This cosmol-<lb/>
ogy, which was first developed by the Sumerians, is later expressed in the Babylonian creation poem, the <hi rend="italic">Enuma Elish</hi>,_written sometime before the reign of <name type="pname">Hammurabi</name> (ruled c. <date when="1792">1792</date>&#x2013;<date when="1750">1750</date> <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>). In this cos-<lb/>
mogonic account, the primal state of the universe consists of <name type="pname">Tiamat</name> and <name type="pname">Apsu</name>, two kinds of water, salt and fresh. Their commingling provides the matrix out of which the first places emerge, thus causing the primary scission that separates heaven from earth. This separation is enforced when <name type="pname">Marduk</name>, the Babylonian national god, does battle with <name type="pname">Tiamat</name>, utterly dominating and destroying her. From their struggle <name type="pname">Marduk</name> emerges as formgiver, architect, and master builder of the universe. He creates the line of horizon and asserts dominion over the fertile but formless primal matter represented by <name type="pname">Tiamat</name>. From <name type="pname">Tiamat</name>'s dismembered but endlessly procre-<lb/>
ative body, he fashions the arc of the sky, personified by <name type="pname">Anu</name>, lord of heaven and the father of gods. He also sets the firm subterranean foundation that upholds the earth, embodied as Ea, god of waters and the netherworld. In the middle zone between these he stations Enlil, god of air and heaven, who is also identified with the wind. With this <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi> set in place, <name type="pname">Marduk</name> bestows directionality, driving through <name type="pname">Tiamat</name>'s ribs openings to the east and west and setting the zenith at the apex of her belly. <name type="pname">Mar-<lb/>
duk</name>, as architect-sculptor, then models the earth's topography, creating mountains and streams and making the great <name type="place">Tigris</name> and <name type="place">Euphrates</name> flow from <name type="pname">Tiamat</name>'s eyes. By rearing a stepped platform into the sky, Mesopotamian priests could bring the pre-<lb/>
siding deity of the heavens, Anu (An in the Sume-<lb/>
rian cosmos), into contact with Bel (Sumerian Enlil), the earth spirit sheltered within its sacred form, as well as with Ea (Enki in the pre-Babylonian mythology), the supernatural power in charge of the underworld and the subterranean waters that sprang forth, teeming with life, in the fecund marshes.</p>
<p>Mesopotamian religion was grounded in ani-<lb/>
mism, the belief that such elements as wind and water had conscious life and that spirit forces dwelt within trees as well as in birds, fish, reptiles, and mammals. Plants and beasts were therefore believed to have an existence independent of their physical representations. That the ziggurat expressed the human desire to forge a connection between the various spheres of a magic-charged universe is evi-<lb/>
dent from the names of some: Heaven and Storm,
<pb n="35"/>
<pb n="35" type="orig"/>
House of the Mountain, Mountain of the Storm, Bond between Heaven and Earth.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-12">
<graphic url="CH1_009.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.8. <name type="pname">Nanna Ziggurat</name>, Ur (modern Muqaiyir, <name type="place">Iraq</name>). c. 2100&#x2013;2050 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The building of ziggurats and their attendant temple structures was reverently undertaken by the early kings of <name type="pname">Sumer</name> as a means of preserving the often fragile harmony with nature upon which depended the continued life of the community and state. Even as they were built, however, their demise was often foreseen in dedication inscrip-<lb/>
tions referring to a time when they would fall into ruin. Constructed with a central core of trodden clay and mud brick, which was then clad with baked brick, their inward-sloping walls and stepped terraces were created of brick courses interspersed at staged intervals with damp courses of reeds and bitumen. In spite of these damp courses and the presence of weepholes, ziggurats remained permeable to water. In time, this caused the interior core of mud brick to expand, forcing the exterior walls outward until they cracked and broke apart.</p>
<p>The biblical image of the collapsed <name type="place">Tower of Babel</name> was probably based upon real examples of ruined ziggurats observed by captive Israelites. This image of cosmopolitan decadence has offered a compelling metaphor for allegorical storytellers and artists through the ages. Such mounds can still be seen today (fig. 1.8).</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Pyramids</hi></hi></head>
<p>The Egyptian pyramid had a purpose altogether different from that of the ziggurat, for the pyra-<lb/>
mid was both the tomb of the king and the means of his posthumous daily ascension and unification with Re, the Sun God.<ref target="#CH1-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref> The cult of Re furnished the pyramid with its essential meaning. To under-<lb/>
stand its underlying theology, one must attempt to see the annual inundation of the <name type="place">Nile</name> plain from the perspective of the early Egyptian. Each spring, as the flood waters rose and then began to subside, the mound of Elephantine&#x2014;the island below the First Cataract of the <name type="place">Nile</name>&#x2014;appeared to come miraculously alive with vegetation, birds, fish, reptiles, and insects. This primal scene was enacted elsewhere as other rocky and sandy mounds within the river received a rich mantle of silt and sprang suddenly into fecund life. To the early Egyptian, the mound itself seemed to be the autonomous progenitor of this miracle, and thus it became revered as the elemental life force. Irri-<lb/>
gation and the warming rays of the sun together were necessary to continue the earth's renewal and bring about growth. Thus, the creation mound was identified both with the phoenix, the mytho-<lb/>
logical bird of light that dispelled the darkness over the waters, and the god Atum, the Egyptian form of the <name type="pname">Demiurge</name>, <name type="pname">Plato</name>'s name for the force that fashions the material world.</p>
<p>The sun was believed to have emerged from the water to manifest itself first as the light of the sacred <hi rend="italic">ben-ben</hi>, a pyramidal stone symbolizing both the life force inherent in the mound and the petrifaction of the sun's rays. In this manner, the imagery of Atum was conflated with that of Re, the sun god, and the <hi rend="italic">ben-ben</hi> was expanded to monumental scale as the pyramid, the funerary home of Re's earthly representative, the all-pow-<lb/>
erful divine king, later called pharaoh. Thus did pyramids serve as supreme symbols of royal authority and power. When still covered with their
<pb n="36"/>
<pb n="36" type="orig"/>
gleaming casings of Tura limestone, their gold-capped tops sending forth rays like the sun itself, they broadcast to ancient Egyptians a magnificent promise of rebirth beyond the grave as well as annual renewal and earthly well-being through the rituals of divine kingship.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-13">
<graphic url="CH1_010.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.9. Pyramids at <name type="place">Giza</name>, <name type="place">Egypt</name>. Fourth dynasty, c. 2601&#x2013;2515 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Grandeur on this scale was difficult to sustain, as is evident from the diminishing size of the Old Kingdom pyramids of the kings <name type="pname">Khufu</name>, <name type="pname">Khafre</name>, and <name type="pname">Menkaure</name> at <name type="place">Giza</name> (fig. 1.9). Although monumental pyramids did not disappear all at once and some were still commissioned by later kings for their burials, none ever attained any-<lb/>
thing approaching the dimensions of the <name type="place">Giza</name> group. The successors of the pharaohs buried at <name type="place">Giza</name> were laid to rest at <name type="place">Abusir</name> in modest rock-hewn tombs ded-<lb/>
icated to Re. Nevertheless, pyramids built at a min-<lb/>
iature scale remained popular as funerary monuments well into the Christian era, and, as will become appar-<lb/>
ent, the form was revived in <name type="place">Europe</name> and <name type="place">America</name> in eighteenth-century gardens and nineteenth-century cemeteries, especially after archaeology brought neo-Egyptian features into vogue and nonsectarian-<lb/>
ism altered and augmented traditional grave symbol-<lb/>
ism with memorials associated with a vision of the afterlife even older than that of Christianity.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="37"/>
<pb n="37" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Temples as Sacred Caves and Mountains</hi></hi></head>
<p>In <name type="place">India</name> and other lands where Hinduism is prac-<lb/>
ticed, one can still encounter cosmologically sacred sites and structures&#x2014;physical embodiments of places where gods are believed to dwell. Evolved from a very old, pre-Hindu tradition, Hindu cosmol-<lb/>
ogy associates caves and mountains as opposite poles of an <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi> of sacred potency. In Hindu mythology <name type="place">Mount Meru</name> is regarded as the navel of the universe, the cosmological center of a concentric arrangement of the continents, oceans, and celestial bodies. Temple architecture is correspondingly cos-<lb/>
mological both in plan and elevation. Outwardly, the temple takes the shape of a mythological moun-<lb/>
tain, and temple worship is equated with a pilgrim-<lb/>
age to a mountain sanctuary (fig. 1.11). In elevation, the temple conforms to the cosmic <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi> run-<lb/>
ning from the cave in the center of the earth to the celestial space above the mountain apex (fig. 1.10). The temple's dark interior sanctuary is a chthonic focal point, a simulation of the cavelike womb, source of life. It is there that the worshiper comes into the presence of the godhead. From this center, energy is believed to radiate upward along a cosmic axis through tiered vertical space composed of numerous concentric stories to a crowning circular finial that symbolizes the state of total enlighten-<lb/>
ment associated with spiritual perfection and the body's release from periodic reincarnation. This axis also symbolizes the pillar of heaven, identified as <name type="place">Meru</name>, and the trunk of an immortal tree whose wide-spreading branches support the universe. In plan, a temple outlines a mandala, the cosmically significant sacred geometric diagram that portrays the structure of the universe (fig. 1.12). The mandala plan of the temple is strictly oriented to the cardinal points of the compass, generally along an east-west axis, and astronomy and astrology play an important role in its siting and construction.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-14">
<graphic url="CH1_011.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">Above left: 1.10. Diagram of the cosmological elevation of a Hindu temple. Adapted from <name type="pname">George Michell</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Hindu Temple</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-15">
<graphic url="CH1_012.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">Above: 1.11. Hindu temple, <name type="place">Galaganatha temple</name>, <name type="place">Pattadakal</name>, <name type="place">Karnataka</name>, <name type="place">India</name>. 8th century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-16">
<graphic url="CH1_013.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">Right: 1.12. Diagram of one of the mandala forms that serve as the plans of Hindu temples. Mandalas, geometric designs symbolizing the universe, are used as aids to meditation in Hinduism and Buddhism. Hindu mandalas consist of squares arranged concentrically around a central square representing Brahman, the absolute being and sacred power pervading the universe. The surrounding squares are occupied by a hierarchy of lesser divinities.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="38"/>
<pb n="38" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Cities, Parks, and Gardens</hi></hi></head>
<p>At the beginning of the third millennium <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> in the Sumerian kingdom of lower <name type="place">Mesopotamia</name>, and later, sometime in the early second millennium <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, to the north in <name type="place">Babylonia</name>, the antagonism between popula-<lb/>
tions of nomadic animal herders and grain-growing peoples forced the latter to dwell in cities, which they fortified with stout double walls. In <name type="place">Egypt</name>, on the other hand, it is uncertain to what extent large residential cities existed for any significant period of time. Each king would undertake vast building projects as a means of manifesting his divine kingship, and there were workers' and artisans' settlements adjacent to these. In addition, there were administrative centers with palace precincts and residential quarters for the members of the nobility who with scribes and other functionaries managed the government. The Egyptian temple complexes at <name type="place">Memphis</name>, <name type="place">Heliopolis</name>, and <name type="place">The-<lb/>
bes</name> served as festival centers for important rituals. Yet it is still not clear whether the peasants who tilled the crops that provided food for the general populace and wealth for the temple administrations lived in cities or in village settlements in the fields.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-17">
<graphic url="CH1_014.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.13. Wall painting of a garden from a tomb in <name type="place">Thebes</name>, <name type="place">Egypt</name>. c. 1400 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Upper-class residential districts had the same amenities, including gardens, as do affluent suburbs today. Because funerary art represents many of the pleasant accouterments of life, it is from the wall paintings and excavated artifacts of despoiled tombs that one gains evidence of Egyptian garden design and horticultural practices. In a painting from a Theban tomb consecrated during the reign of <name type="pname">Amenhotep III</name> (ruled 1390&#x2013;1352 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), a house sits within a garden surrounded by a wall (fig. 1.13). The garden, which is laid out according to an orthogonal grid plan, could be entered through two gates, one cut into the wall facing a tree-lined path beside a canal, and the other through a porter's lodge. Once inside, the visitor was surrounded by date palms and sycamore trees. A large vineyard, orchards, and four ponds filled with lotus blossoms and ducks and fringed with clumps of papy-<lb/>
rus formed part of the design. Two of the ponds have kiosks, or garden pavilions, beside them. These are set within a series of walled enclosures that divide the space into several garden "rooms" and segregate plan-<lb/>
tations of various tree species.</p>
<p>Floriculture was the source of a lively commerce. Flowers were fashioned into bouquets, garlands, and collars. At religious festivals and funerals, those attending brought floral arrangements as well as bun-<lb/>
dles and heaps of loose flowers. The dead were buried wearing intricately woven floral collars and shrouds decorated with garlands. <name type="pname">Ramesses III</name> helped make <name type="place">Thebes</name> a garden city by planting trees and papyrus plants. In an urban center, which he founded in the <name type="place">Nile</name> delta to the north, he is said to have created vine-<lb/>
yards, laid out walks shaded by fruit trees, and planted flowers from many countries.</p>
<p>Ancient Near Eastern cities were for the most part hierarchical arrangements of space expressing class dis-<lb/>
tinctions. Order, as reflected in geometric regularity, where it existed, was evidence of the authoritarian power of the ruler and the priesthood. This theocratic kingship defined ceremonial axes and controlled the distribution of lands, and there was segregation of specialized func-<lb/>
tions into defined districts. Cosmological considerations governed the organization of axes and the creation of temple precincts.</p>
<p>Sumerian cities took the shape of an organic hive of residential and artisan activity surrounding a religious and palace precinct. At <name type="pname">Sumer</name> and also at <name type="place">Akkad</name>, the city founded by <name type="pname">Sargon I</name> (ruled 2332&#x2013;2279 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) after the Semitic Akkadians conquered <name type="place">Meso-potamia</name> around 2340 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, temples and palaces stood near the center of the city. In these cities and at Ur, sited at the juncture of a large canal and the <name type="place">Euphrates</name>, the principal temple was raised far above the ground atop a massive ziggurat, the pre-eminent image and cosmological symbol of the city (see fig. 1.8). The entire town rose above the surrounding plain on a base of debris from collapsed mud buildings that had accumulated over many generations. Massive gates punctuated the thick enclosing walls.</p>
<pb n="39"/>
<pb n="39" type="orig"/>
<p>The Assyrian cities that subsequently rose in the area to the north of the Tigris<name type="place">-Euphrates</name> plain were also impressive in their monumentality. A cuneiform map of the city of <name type="place">Nippur</name> on the <name type="place">Euphra-<lb/>
tes</name> in the center of <name type="place">Babylonia</name>, dated about 1500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, shows a city intersected by a canal, with moat- and river-bordered walls pierced by seven gates (fig. 1.14). No streets are shown, but its prin-<lb/>
cipal temples are depicted, together with a large park located in an acute angle formed by the walls at the southern end of the city. Parks, the pride of Sume-<lb/>
rian and Babylonian kings, were the prototypes of the Persian <hi rend="italic">pairidaeza</hi>, the walled hunting park. The <hi rend="italic">Epic of Gilgamesh</hi> has a description of what may have been a hunting park in the southern Babylonian city of <name type="place">Erech</name> (called <name type="place">Uruk</name> during Akkadian times). Like their Persian successors, the ancient Near East-<lb/>
ern monarchs brought to their parks exotic trees, which they acquired from other lands by trade or conquest. Especially prized were the myrrh trees of the <name type="place">Hittites</name> from the region that is <name type="place">Syria</name> today. It was the idealized landscape of that hilly country that King <name type="pname">Sargon II</name> (ruled 721&#x2013;705 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) of ancient Assyria (a culture dominant in the region from about 1000 to 612 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) and other rulers wished to recall with the simile "like the Amanus Mountains," which is frequently found in their boastful inscriptions proclaiming their park-building schemes.</p>
<p>In the exceedingly hot climate, the garden of shade trees was a much-appreciated luxury. From bas-reliefs and archaeological remains, it is evident that the Babylonians planted trees in rows and built intricate irrigation channels to water them. They created rush-bordered ponds to shelter wildlife and built pleasure houses on hills or terraces overlooking this panorama of garden scenery. A seventh-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Assyrian relief from Nineveh depicts a royal garden in which <name type="pname">Assurbanipal</name> and his queen are enjoying a feast beneath an arbor of grapes, cele-<lb/>
brating his victory over the <name type="pname">Elamite</name> king whose severed head is hanging from a tree branch (fig. 1.15). The regularly planted trees in this garden include the date palm, which was also grown along canal banks. Dates were cultivated in orchards as well, along with various fruit trees&#x2014;apples, plums, peaches, cherries, figs, and pomegranates.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-18">
<graphic url="CH1_015.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.14. Cuneiform map of <name type="place">Nippur</name> (<name type="place">Iraq</name>), c. 1500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-19">
<graphic url="CH1_016.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 1.15. <name type="pname">Assurbanipal</name> and His Queen Feasting in a Garden, Relief from the Assyrian royal palace at <name type="place">Nineveh</name> (modern <name type="place">Kuyunjik</name>, <name type="place">Iraq</name>). 668&#x2013;627 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> <name type="place">Alabaster</name>. The British Museum, <name type="place">London</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Later generations praised the fabled Hanging Gardens of <name type="place">Babylon</name> as one of the wonders of the ancient world, and the search for them has occa-<lb/>
sioned much guesswork and patient excavation by several archaeologists. According to one of five accounts by ancient writers, they were built by <name type="pname">King Nebuchadnezzar II</name> (ruled 604&#x2013;562 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) for his queen, who was homesick for the mountain mead-<lb/>
ows of her native Media. Other descriptions speak of a series of descending terraces built on top of vaulted galleries. The suggestion has been dis-<lb/>
counted that trees and other vegetation growing in soil beds or tree pits upon the terraces of the ziggurat at <name type="place">Babylon</name> could be what were referred to as the Hanging Gardens because of the insurmountable difficulty of bringing sufficient water in irrigation channels from the <name type="place">Euphrates River</name> to this monu-<lb/>
<pb n="40"/>
<pb n="40" type="orig"/>
ment. Some archaeologists now surmise that raised gardens may have occupied superimposed terraces on what they call the Western Outwork structure between <name type="pname">Nebuchadnezzar</name>'s palace and the <name type="place">Euphrates</name>. Although their claim is not definitive, it is supported by the presence in this location of the kind of deep drains that would have been necessary for extensive irrigation.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-20">
<graphic url="CH1_017.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.16. Temples of <name type="pname">Mentuhotep II</name> (ruled 2009&#x2013;1997 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) and <name type="pname">Queen Hatshepsut</name> (ruled 1478&#x2013; 1458 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), <name type="pname">Deir el-Bahri</name>, <name type="place">Egypt</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Processional Axes</hi></hi></head>
<p>The processional axis, or ceremonial way, developed in conjunction with religious rituals in which priest and populace assembled in precincts before ziggu-<lb/>
rats, pyramids, and temples. A program of ritualistic approach and movement through a series of hieratic spaces necessitated axial arrangements, offering opportunities for kinetic drama. Thus we find the <name type="place">Giza</name> pyramids of the Old Kingdom (2686&#x2013;2181 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) set in the desert verge and linked to riverside temples by long, sloping causeways&#x2014;the pyramid and the mortuary temple at its base being the archi-<lb/>
tectural climax of an axial route that began at a val-<lb/>
ley temple near the banks of the <name type="place">Nile</name>.</p>
<p>At the beginning of the Middle Kingdom (2055&#x2013;1650 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), across the <name type="place">Nile</name> from a temple complex at <name type="place">Karnak</name> (near modern-day <name type="place">Luxor</name>) and on axis with it, <name type="pname">Mentuhotep II</name> (ruled 2009&#x2013;1997 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) built into the monumental rock face of the cliff a large temple-tomb (fig. 1.16). This funerary group-<lb/>
ing had a large forecourt planted with tamarisks and sycamore fig trees. A high, square colonnaded plat-<lb/>
form supported a mortuary temple built in the form of a vestigial pyramid. Behind the mortuary temple, lodged in the cliff itself, stood another narrower court and hypostyle hall. This complex furnished a vocab-<lb/>
ulary of forms for the adjacent temple built five hun-<lb/>
dred years later by a remarkable monarch of the New Kingdom, <name type="pname">Queen Hatshepsut</name>, who reigned from about 1478 to 1458 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></p>
<p>At this point in her long history, <name type="place">Egypt</name> was experiencing a period of wealth and could, without any sacrifice of agricultural labor, build monumental works of architecture and landscape design by using its peacetime anny. Like <name type="pname">Mentuhotep II</name>, <name type="pname">Hatshepsut</name> had her sepulcher carved within the cliff face at <name type="pname">Deir el-Bahri</name>. It formed the terminus of a grand axis that began at the temple complex of Karnak on the oppo-<lb/>
site bank of the <name type="place">Nile</name>, continuing from a riverside temple on the west bank along an avenue of sphinxes, whence it ascended, first one, and then a second mas-<lb/>
sive ramp, each flanked by long colonnades. This axis culminated at last in the great hall of <name type="pname">Hatshepsut</name>'s temple. In the superb wedding of natural and archi-<lb/>
tectural forms, the columns of the colonnade echoing
<pb n="41"/>
<pb n="41" type="orig"/>
the geological verticals behind them, <name type="pname">Hatshepsut</name>'s architect <name type="pname">Senenmut</name> left his mark for posterity.</p>
<p>On the walls of the colonnade of the second of two large terraces, temple sculptors left a record of international trade as well as a fascinating footnote to the history of horticulture. Here reliefs depict an expe-<lb/>
dition to Punt, present-day <name type="place">Somalia</name>, to procure the precious myrrh trees <name type="pname">Queen Hatshepsut</name> wished to plant beside her temple. The resin of this tree was dedicated in measured heaps to the sun god Amon. Scenes of this early botanical conquest show how roots were balled and held in place in baskets sus-<lb/>
pended by ropes tied to poles carried by groups of four or six men, depending upon the size of the tree (fig. 1.18).</p>
<p>Like the Egyptians, the Babylonians honored their deity and manifested their power and prosperity in axial arrangements of landscape space. <name type="pname">Nebuchad-<lb/>
nezzar II</name>, who is remembered as the ruler who cap-<lb/>
tured and destroyed <name type="place">Jerusalem</name> and led the Jews into captivity, aggrandized <name type="place">Babylon</name> through a lavish rebuilding program. His works included, in addition to the Hanging Gardens, the magnificent <name type="place">Ishtar Gate</name> and a great processional way leading to the Temple of <name type="pname">Marduk</name>, which he had plated with gold.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Obelisks</hi></hi></head>
<p>During the Middle Kingdom, the life-giving, sun-<lb/>
blessed mound, the sacred <hi rend="italic">ben-ben</hi>, which the pyramid had symbolized on a grand scale, assumed the form pyramidion, or pyramid in miniature. Elevated upon a tapering base, it became the top of an obelisk. Obe-<lb/>
lisks&#x2014;more massive and squat than the New King-<lb/>
dom "<name type="pname">Cleopatra</name> Needles" with which we are familiar&#x2014;were placed upon high podiums within the open courts of the sun temples at <name type="place">Abusir</name> (fig. 1.17).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-21">
<graphic url="CH1_018.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.17. Obelisk, <name type="place">Abusir</name>, <name type="place">Egypt</name>. This early version of the build-<lb/>
ing-form obelisk is a limestone shaft 118 feet (36 meters) high, set upon a truncated pyramid that rises 65.5 feet (20 meters) from the ground.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-22">
<graphic url="CH1_019.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 1.18. <hi rend="italic">Expedition to Punt</hi>. Relief from the Temple of <name type="pname">Queen Hatshepsut</name>. <name type="pname">Deir el-Bahri</name>, <name type="place">Egypt</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Throughout the period of the New Kingdom (1550&#x2013;1069 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), monumental temples multiplied within the <name type="place">Nile Valley</name>. Some were replacements or additions to earlier temples. Successive pharaohs extended axes, replicating the massive pylons guard-<lb/>
<pb n="42"/>
<pb n="42" type="orig"/>
ing courts and adding new obelisks, which by this time had assumed their elongated form. Thus dra-<lb/>
matized by monuments and architecture, these axes organized spatial sequences of awe-inspiring ritual progression. For example, at the Temple at <name type="place">Luxor</name> built by <name type="pname">Amenhotep III</name> (ruled 1390&#x2013;1352 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), <name type="pname">Ramesses II</name> (ruled 1279&#x2013;1212 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) erected a massive pylon before which he placed two colossal figures of himself and two obelisks (fig. 1.19). One of these was carried to <name type="place">Paris</name> in the nineteenth cen-<lb/>
tury to become the focal point of the <name type="place">Place de la Concorde</name> after these war trophies had become urban status symbols.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-23">
<graphic url="CH1_020.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.19. Obelisks erected by <name type="pname">Ramesses II</name> (ruled 1279&#x2013;1212 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) at temple of <name type="pname">Amenhotep III</name> (ruled 1390&#x2013;1352 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), <name type="place">Luxor, Egypt</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-24">
<graphic url="CH1_021.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">Right: 1.20. Obelisk of <name type="pname">Tuth-<lb/>
mose III</name> (ruled 1479&#x2013;1425 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), Central Park, <name type="place">New York City</name>. Erected in present loca-<lb/>
tion west of The Metropolitan Museum of Art in <date when="1880">1880</date>, this modest obelisk is known as <name type="pname">Cleopatra</name>'s Needle.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The quarrying, erection, subsequent transpor-<lb/>
tation, and re-erection of obelisks in distant parts of the world provides a remarkable footnote in the history of world monuments and city planning. The first obelisks to be transported from <name type="place">Egypt</name> were a pair appropriated in 671 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> as trophies of war by <name type="pname">Assurbanipal I</name>, the Assyrian conqueror of <name type="place">The-<lb/>
bes</name>. Subsequently, Roman emperors garnered them in their Egyptian campaigns. Fifteen hundred years later, the papal planners of <name type="place">Baroque Rome</name> reposi-<lb/>
tioned them as focal points in the <hi rend="italic">piazze</hi> of their rebuilt city.</p>
<p>Borrowing from this example, other countries transported Egyptian obelisks at great expense to dis-<lb/>
tant cities where they became prestigious ornaments within the urban landscape, as the following bit of history makes clear. To celebrate one of the jubilees of his prosperous reign, <name type="pname">Tuthmose III</name> (ruled 1479&#x2014; 1425 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) sent a crew of stonecutters to the quarries of <name type="pname">Aswan</name> for the purpose of extracting twin obelisks from the granite there. Workers chiseled and exca-<lb/>
vated the stone, carving the obelisks on the site. Other workers then dragged the obelisks by sledge to the river and floated them at flood time by barge to <name type="place">Heliopolis</name> where they were placed in front of the Tem-<lb/>
ple of the Sun. Nine hundred years later, in 525 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, the Persians burned and toppled the obelisks during their conquest of <name type="place">Egypt</name>. After another five hundred years, when <name type="place">Egypt</name> had declined to the status of a prov-<lb/>
ince of the Roman Empire, <name type="pname">Augustus Caesar</name> installed them in front of the <name type="pname">Caesarium</name> at <name type="place">Alexandria</name>. In the nineteenth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, a millennium and a half after <name type="place">Rome</name> had fallen, the obelisks made their respective journeys as souvenirs of international diplomacy to the <name type="place">Thames</name> embankment in <name type="place">London</name> and <name type="place">New York City's Central Park</name> (fig. 1.20).</p>
<p>These recycled obelisks illustrate how one civi-<lb/>
lization manifests its wealth and power by borrowing the forms (and in this case, actual objects) of another. For <name type="pname">Assurbanipal I</name>, the Theban obelisks symbolized the subjugation of a rival state. For <name type="pname">Augustus Caesar</name>, the obelisks of <name type="pname">Tuthmose III</name> were ready-made emblems of imperial glory. For nineteenth-century Parisians, the obelisk of <name type="pname">Ramesses II</name> served the same purpose the several obelisks brought to ancient <name type="place">Rome</name> had for <name type="pname">Pope
<pb n="43"/>
<pb n="43" type="orig"/>
Sixtus V</name> and his successors, ennobling the urban land-<lb/>
scape and fixing space within an axial plan. For nine-<lb/>
teenth-century Londoners, the second recycling of one of <name type="pname">Tuthmose III</name>'s obelisks was, as it had been for <name type="pname">Augustus Caesar</name>, a symbol of imperial might. For New Yorkers, its twin was a means of ornamenting a pictur-<lb/>
esque landscape while proclaiming cosmopolitan civic status. Thus was a religious symbol of the sun, sacred to the Egyptians, turned into exotic treasure and appro-<lb/>
priated as civic embellishment, while at the same time becoming a popular form for funerary monuments and architecture as discussed in Chapter Nine (see figs. 9.27, 9.28). We should not, however, lose sight of the fact that the obelisk in its original location was part of a complex, cosmologically focused landscape design. It is important to remember that, whether in the Old World or the New, the natural and cultural landscapes that gave sacred meaning to human life reflected the desire for predictable, life-sustaining order in the uni-<lb/>
verse. This meant agricultural prosperity, dominance of elites over their subjects, and victory over enemies in war. The proper alignment with cosmic forces was therefore considered vital, and both practical and reli-<lb/>
gious objectives furnished motives for the design of landscape space.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">III. Ritual and Landscape in Prehistoric <name type="place">Greece</name>: The Earth Goddess and the Mighty Lords</hi></hi></head>
<p>Unlike the topography of <name type="place">Egypt</name>, which in ancient times consisted of a single ribbon supportive of human habitation in the cliff-walled, desert-bordered <name type="place">Nile Valley</name>, that of <name type="place">Greece</name> is made up of many broad, cradling, spring-fed valleys separated by mountains of impressive though not awesome size. The geologic forces that created the mountains are expressed in their southeastward orientation and their continuation as the <name type="place">Cyclades</name>, <name type="place">Rhodes</name>, and other islands&#x2014;the higher elevations of a drowned mountain system. This orientation and the existence of such an array of island stepping-stones along the coast of <name type="place">Asia Minor</name> gave the peoples who populated the Greek mainland, the Peloponnese, and <name type="place">Crete</name> opportunities for inter-<lb/>
change with the highly developed cultures to the east and south of the Aegean archipelago. At the same time, the sea preserved a strong degree of isolation, which allowed them to develop indigenous patterns of culture and religion.</p>
<p>As we have seen, <name type="place">Egypt</name>'s linear, riverine geog-<lb/>
raphy, because of its connectedness and the need for large-scale management of irrigation, encouraged the development of unified theocratic kingship. The frag-<lb/>
mentation of the Greek landscape and the dependence of Greek settlements upon water from underground springs militated against autocracy and massive bureaucratic administration. Rather, it fostered the creation of several small tribal civilizations among whom hegemony was based upon successful warfare and maritime trade. A pastoral people who measured wealth in terms of livestock, the early Greeks lived in scattered settlements and did not need the mass orga-<lb/>
nization of society necessary for the large-scale culti-<lb/>
vation of grain.</p>
<p>In <name type="place">Egypt</name>, the <name type="place">Nile</name> landscape was a single mighty engine of fertility and life. Divinity resided at the des-<lb/>
ert verge in monumental pyramids and cliff-hewn temples. In <name type="place">Greece</name>, the topographically diverse and dramatically beautiful landscape itself became invested with religious meaning. For ancient inhabi-<lb/>
tants it was the home of powerful goddesses and gods. Foremost among these deities in the remote centuries of prehistory was the Great Goddess, called <name type="pname">Potnia</name> in the Minoan culture of <name type="place">Crete</name>.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="place">Crete</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>The importance of the earth goddess and animal spirit is apparent in sculpture and painting from the Minoan civilization that existed on the island of <name type="place">Crete</name> from about 3000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> until 1000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi><ref target="#CH1-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref> This civilization was contemporaneous with that of <name type="place">Egypt</name> and the Hit-<lb/>
tite Empire of <name type="place">Asia Minor</name>. Although there is evidence of contact with these well-developed cultures, in its nonmilitaristic social values and goddess-worshipping religion, as well as in the sophisticated yet youthful ebullience manifested in its art, it demonstrates an independent development and autonomous nature.</p>
<p>After a millennium of evolution, Minoan civili-<lb/>
zation reached its zenith around 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and main-<lb/>
tained this cultural high-water mark, in spite of massive destruction from earthquakes and fires about 1700 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Subsequently, another, more horrendous episode of geophysical disturbance charted this cul-<lb/>
ture's course toward collapse and extinction. This was the eruption of the Thera volcano about 1470 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, an event that toppled cities and set them ablaze, bring-<lb/>
ing in its wake tidal-wave inundation and a ruinous blanket of white ash over the island that made the soil impossible to cultivate. The disaster may have been compounded by subsequent Mycenaean invasions from the mainland. The principal architectural ruins and artifacts that define Minoan culture therefore date
<pb n="44"/>
<pb n="44" type="orig"/>
from the period between around 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and 1470 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-25">
<graphic url="CH1_022.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.21. Cave sacred to <name type="pname">Zeus</name> on the eastern face of <name type="place">Mount Ida</name>, <name type="place">Crete</name>. The cave plays a part in the Greek myth in which Gaia (Earth) and Uranos (Sky) gave birth to <name type="pname">Kronos</name> and <name type="pname">Rhea</name>, the parents of <name type="pname">Zeus</name>. Jealous to pre-<lb/>
serve his authority, Kronos devoured his offspring. <name type="pname">Rhea</name>'s successful plot to hide the infant <name type="pname">Zeus</name> within the Idaian cave&#x2014;there to be nursed by nymphs and fed goat's milk and honey&#x2014;allowed him to survive, depose Kronos, and become the supreme male god and subsequent ruler of the Greek pantheon. That there was a shrine at this site in Minoan times, is attested by the many artifacts found there, including shields, spears, gold and ivory votive objects, figurines, and clay tablets, as well as deposits of ash and the bones of sacrificed animals.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>There is now considerable archaeological evi-<lb/>
dence showing that Minoans made ritual visits to hill-<lb/>
top sanctuaries and sacred caves. In addition to revering the earth goddess, they probably sought to propitiate the weather gods on high, a religious impulse not unlike that of the Mesopotamians and the pre-Co-<lb/>
lumbian Americans. Public festivals brought congre-<lb/>
gations of worshipers to these dramatically situated, bare, and windswept peaks, where they found stone-<lb/>
paved terraces with altars placed before a <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi>, or holy precinct, outlined by walls and balustrades crowned with sacral horns. Local pastoralists fre-<lb/>
quented these places, seeking protection for their cattle through votive offerings and propitiatory rites. The shrines themselves were well furnished with variously shaped altars, cult images, sacrificial tables, ladles, lamps, and libation vessels. Male and female clay fig-<lb/>
urines were left behind as surrogates for the worship-<lb/>
ers, symbolizing their continuing devotional presence in the holy spot.</p>
<p>The hilly Cretan limestone terrain, a landscape type known to geologists as a karst formation and the source of the underground springs that sustained Minoan and later Greek communities, is riddled with some two thousand caves. A small number, perhaps thirty-five or so, had sacred status, probably because of their association with burial; among these an esti-<lb/>
mated sixteen were used for cult practices (fig. 1.21). Votive gold double-axes and figurines of bronze have been found in sacred caves along with evidence of animal sacrifice and offerings of grain and other pro-<lb/>
duce. There is evidence, too, of ritual dancing and feasting outside the caves. Funeral pyres burned at cave entrances before the performance of the chthonic rites within.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-26">
<graphic url="CH1_023.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 1.22. The Earth God-<lb/>
dess, <name type="pname">Potnia</name>, had a son and consort, Velchanos, or Kouros, a precursor of <name type="pname">Zeus</name>. His ritual death symbolized the annual death and rebirth of nature.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>In addition to the peak and cave sanctuaries, walled enclosures guarded a sacred tree or perhaps marked the site of an epiphany. Some archaeologists surmise that worshipers tore branches or boughs from enshrined sacred trees and venerated them on altars or planted them in sockets between sacral horns. Scenes depicted on seals and other artifacts offer evi-<lb/>
dence of ecstatic dancing by priestesses in these loca-<lb/>
tions.</p>
<p>Symbols of the Great Goddess, <name type="pname">Potnia</name>, were the double-axe, the stone pillar, and the snake. Perhaps it is she who is depicted as a bell-skirted, bare-breasted, snake-wielding figure (fig. 1.22); in scenes on seals and wall paintings she is frequently symbolized by a pillar guarded by rampant lions, a form that clearly relates to that of the famous Lioness Gate, the princi-<lb/>
pal entrance in the wall of the city-state of Mycenae on the Peloponnese (see fig. 1.25).</p>
<p>There were, in addition, other goddesses and gods. Britomartis, an early version of Artemis, the chaste mistress of the hunt and protector of animals, was worshiped in the mountain sanctuaries. Eleuthia, the Cave Goddess, protected women in childbirth; her special sanctuary was the Cave of Eileithyia at <name type="place">Amnisos</name>. The Snake Goddess and the Dove Goddess were also part of the Minoan pantheon, along with the
<pb n="45"/>
<pb n="45" type="orig"/>
Sea Goddess. Often, boundaries between these dei-<lb/>
ties were blurred as they assumed one another's attri-<lb/>
butes. The most powerful and feared god for the Minoans was Potidas, or Poteidan, the sea god who prefigured the <name type="place">Greek Poseidon</name>. His subterranean aspect was that of earth-shaker, lord of seismic trem-<lb/>
ors and tidal waves; his terrestrial form was that of a bull; and his celestial manifestation was as the sun and moon.</p>
<p>The civilization that emerged on <name type="place">Crete</name> was suf-<lb/>
ficiently at peace and advanced enough in shipbuild-<lb/>
ing, maritime skills, and trade to exert commercial supremacy and nonmilitary dominance. Unlike the later fiercely warring city-states of the Greek main-<lb/>
land, which were heavily fortified with walls, <name type="place">Knos-<lb/>
sos</name> and the other cities and towns of <name type="place">Crete</name> were without walls. The Labyrinth, or ceremonial center at <name type="place">Knossos</name>, was the most important reli-gious complex on <name type="place">Crete</name>, was a place of pilgrimage attracting wor-<lb/>
shipers from other parts of the island, and perhaps from other islands as well (fig. 1.23).</p>
<p>Minoans, like Greeks later, possessed a remark-<lb/>
able instinct for siting their religious centers and communities in relationship to natural topography. According to the controversial but here plausible interpretation of the architectural historian <name type="pname">Vincent Scully</name>, the builders of <name type="place">Knossos</name> and <name type="place">Phaistos</name> placed their centers within an enclosed valley, a "natural megaron," like a Minoan-palace great hall with its central hearth and columned porch, along a north-<lb/>
south axis facing a gently mounded conical hill framed by the distant "horns" of a double-peaked or cleft mountain. These natural forms define landscape space and focus it. Further serving ritual needs and their symbolical expression were the labyrinthine passage, the long rectangular court, the columned pavilion, and the cavelike pillared hall. At <name type="place">Knossos</name>, therefore, as one stands at the south propylaia, or gateway, one is facing a breast-shaped mound beyond which looms the cleft summit of <name type="place">Mount Juktas</name>, site of a peak sanctuary and cave shrine where cult rituals were held. Similarly, at <name type="place">Phaistos</name>, the central court is aligned along a north-south axis with twin-peaked <name type="place">Mount Ida</name>, site of the cave sanctuary sacred to <name type="pname">Zeus</name> (fig. 1.24). Like the Puebloan plazas of the American Southwest, this central court with its enclosing archi-<lb/>
tecture replicates at human scale the natural "mega-<lb/>
ron" that appears to contain it. Its alignment with a sacred form in nature, which also corresponds fairly closely to one of the cardinal directions, suggests that, like many Native American peoples, Cretan builders sited according to a combination of topo-<lb/>
graphical foci and cosmological references.</p>
<p>Their axes were not inscribed <hi rend="italic">upon</hi>_ nature, but existed rather as <hi rend="italic">orientation</hi> lines connecting ritual centers with shrines <hi rend="italic">in</hi> nature. Thus, unlike the cere-<lb/>
monial axes the Egyptians and some Native Ameri-<lb/>
cans built for religious processionals, the axes of <name type="place">Greece</name> were invisible lines. On <name type="place">Crete</name>, these axes presumably tied the religious practices involving a Snake Goddess and her representatives in the sanc-<lb/>
tuaries at <name type="place">Knossos</name>, <name type="place">Phaistos</name>, and other Minoan set-<lb/>
tlements with the cultic practices of the mountain caves. The sacral horns surrounding the mountain altars were dramatically evoked by the dancers' dar-<lb/>
ing somersaults through the horns of a living bull in a ritual ceremony that took place within the ceremo-<lb/>
nial court.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-27">
<graphic url="CH1_024.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.23. Plan of "Labyrinth" at <name type="place">Knossos</name>, <name type="place">Crete</name>, <name type="place">Greece</name>. Minoan period, between 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and 1470 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold">A</hi> Storerooms. <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Throne Room. <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Pillar Hall. <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Central Court. <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Grand Staircase. <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Hall of the Double Axes</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-28">
<graphic url="CH1_025.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.24. Central Court, <name type="place">Phaistos</name>, <name type="place">Crete</name>. Minoan period, between 2000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and 1470 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> On one side <name type="place">Phaistos</name> faces the Libyan Sea and on the other, visible in the pho-<lb/>
tograph, twin-peaked <name type="place">Mount Ida</name>.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The intimate connection with local landscape and the desire to invest landscapes with religious
<pb n="46"/>
<pb n="46" type="orig"/>
meaning gradually weakened, and today human beings have, for the most part, discarded a propi-<lb/>
tiatory posture in their relationship with nature. So it is difficult for us to comprehend how deeply felt the connection with the earth goddess&#x2014;Mother Earth&#x2014;once was. Confidence and pride in human prowess caused a slow shift in values as a new god-<lb/>
head emerged, embodying the traits of the masculine hero. Nevertheless, a strong emotional link remained with a primary female goddess throughout antiquity as divinity split apart, becoming the pantheon of male and female deities made familiar by the litera-<lb/>
ture of <name type="pname">Homer</name>.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-29">
<graphic url="CH1_026.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.25. Lioness Gate entrance to the city of <name type="place">Mycenae</name>, <name type="place">Greece</name>. c. 1300&#x2013;1200 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Over the gate the huge stones are corbeled to relieve the weight upon the lintel. Into the triangu-<lb/>
lar space so created was set a monumental tympanum with two rampant lionesses carved in high relief. These lionesses face an altar with a column set upon it; the column was probably an emblematic representation of the Earth Goddess.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Mycenaean <name type="place">Greece</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>The Bronze Age culture with which archaeologists have sought to identify the epic heroes of <name type="pname">Homer</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> is that of the Mycenaean Greeks, whose civili-<lb/>
zation arose on the mainland between 1550 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and 1200 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> There, warrior chieftains, the descen-<lb/>
dants of Indo-European invaders from the <name type="place">Balkans</name> or southern <name type="place">Russia</name>, ruled with might from fortress strongholds such as <name type="place">Pylos</name>, <name type="place">Orchomenos</name>, <name type="place">Mycenae</name>, <name type="place">Tiryns</name>, and <name type="place">Athens</name>. Their trade-based culture was rich enough to support palatial architecture, fine craftsmanship, luxurious furnishings, and lavish burial sites. Contact with <name type="place">East Asia</name> provided new standards of monumental architecture as well as dec-<lb/>
orative motifs. At the same time, their culture was influenced by that of <name type="place">Crete</name>, and they freely borrowed many Minoan forms and practices.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-30">
<graphic url="CH1_027.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.26. Drawing of a seal impres-<lb/>
sion from <name type="place">Knossos</name>. Here the Earth Goddess, emblem of Minoan culture, is depicted as Mother of the Mountains and Mistress of the Animals.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The same chthonic rites and worship of the earth goddess as occurred on <name type="place">Crete</name> were practiced at Mycenaean sites. Apparent, however, in its war-<lb/>
rior culture was an incipient challenge to the earth goddess's supremacy, as Bronze Age men made mil-<lb/>
itary strength and protection of the clan through vic-<lb/>
tory on the battlefield a recognizable benefit on a par with fertility and the protection of the crops. This is evident in a more defensively strategic occupancy of the land. Because of the existence of springs in limestone ridges and the extensive presence of such karstic formations in <name type="place">Greece</name>, the Mycenaeans were able to site their cities on difficult-to-scale high points with long views of the surrounding valleys, plains, and sea. The Athenian Acropolis, which was occupied in Mycenaean times, was furnished with many such springs. Mycenae itself was situated on a hill above the plain of Argos. The population spread out upon the slopes below in convenient proximity to the fissures in the slope where springs were found, but close to the heavily fortified acrop-<lb/>
olis where they could seek safety from invaders. The approach to this stronghold was from the southwest along a path leading to the Lioness Gate within its cyclopean masonry walls (figs. 1.25; cf. 1.26).</p>
<p>In the turbulent period between 1200 and 1150 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, Mycenaean civilization was put to rout by invaders. Although they did not succeed in breaching the massive walls of the citadel, the Dorian newcom-<lb/>
ers from the north managed to topple the authority of the warrior kings there and in the other Myce-<lb/>
naean cities as they infiltrated the countryside, add-<lb/>
ing new traditions to the Helladic cultural base. Trading wealth vanished as did kingship, monumen-<lb/>
tal architecture, and fine craftsmanship in gold and bronze. Mycenaean citadels became shells wherein a remnant population lived amid the ruins of van-<lb/>
ished glory.</p>
<p>Geographical fragmentation abetted the gen-<lb/>
eral impoverishment in bringing about increased political fragmentation. Authoritarian-style rulership disappeared as society broke apart into tribal units. Common interests caused a collection of <hi rend="italic">phylai</hi>, or tribes, to fuse as a <hi rend="italic">demos</hi>. The members of a <hi rend="italic">demos</hi> gradually formed a <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, a communal center for refuge and religious practice. During the four centu-<lb/>
ries of gestation and social transformation that con-<lb/>
stituted the so-called Dark Age in <name type="place">Greece</name>, the <hi rend="italic">agora</hi>, a public space for assembly and debate, and the <hi rend="italic">boule</hi>, a council of nobles, became the seedbed of a-<lb/>
 radically new concept of governance. In this matrix, people cultivated a new respect for the individual. These were the forces at work as <name type="place">Greece</name>, undis-<lb/>
turbed by fresh invasions from the north or a resur-<lb/>
gence of authoritarian influence from the east, moved toward the eighth-century social develop-<lb/>
ment that created new institutions capable of redi-<lb/>
recting human destiny, the landscape expressions of which we shall examine in Chapter Two.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="47"/>
<pb n="47" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">IV. Cosmology in the Landscapes of the Americas: Spirits of Earth and Sky</hi></hi></head>
<p>In looking at the landscapes of pre-Columbian archaeology and the remnant traditions of agricultural and pastoral peoples throughout the Americas, we can find enough parallels among disparate world cultures to support the notion of the universality of certain myths and religious practices. Such trans-<lb/>
cultural beliefs include the divinity ascribed to the sun, the importance of real and artificial mountains as sky platforms to bring a people into closer contact with their gods, particularly those associated with rain and fertility; the cave as the womb of the Earth Mother and a shrine in nature; the importance of both votive and sacrificial offerings; the portrayal of gods and spirits in animal form; the sense of human sub-<lb/>
servience to cosmological power, and the need&#x2014;sat-<lb/>
isfied through drumbeat, communal chant, and dance in designated sacred spaces&#x2014;to communicate with that power.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Cultural Parallels and Universal Patterns</hi></hi></head>
<p>The reverence for mountains and lakes, the belief that there is a numinous energy and life force animating stones and trees as well as living creatures is called <hi rend="italic">teotl</hi> in the Nahuatl language of the Aztecs, <hi rend="italic">huaca</hi> in the Andean tongue of Quechua, or <hi rend="italic">po-wa-ha</hi> in Tewa, the speech of <name type="pname">Santa Clara Pueblo</name> and other pueblos near the <name type="place">Rio Grande</name> in <name type="place">New Mexico</name>. To ensure the flow of this positive energy through their settlements, the precolonial builders in the Americas did not lay out their towns haphazardly. The cardinal points of the compass figure in many creation stories.<ref target="#CH1-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> <name type="place">Pueblo</name> villages, for instance, are oriented with respect to four sacred mountains and, at closer range, four mesas and four village shrines. These have legendary associa-<lb/>
tions with the explo-ratory paths to the north and south, east and west, taken by four pairs of mytho-<lb/>
logical twins as they emerged from a primal subter-<lb/>
ranean lake when Earth was still in formation.</p>
<p>Centeredness within this natural frame is important. The <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi>, or small hole in the middle of the Puebloan plaza, is an <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi> uniting the upper world with the lower, the place whence life emerged and to which it returns. The circular <hi rend="italic">kiva</hi> with its <hi rend="italic">sipapu</hi>, another small hole like the <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi> of the plaza, reinforced the all-pervading theme of cosmic axiality. According to Puebloan belief, a sky-basket, identified with the male principle, over-<lb/>
arches the bowl-earth, associated with the female. Within the earth part of this duality there are four concurrent planes of existence. Puebloan people emerged onto the fourth plane, the world of life and light, at the north opening of the Earth Mother.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, lake bottoms and natural caves are associated with myths of human emergence into this world. For millennia, Native Americans in many localities have made pilgrimages to cave-shrines in their sacred mountains as well as to spirit-inhabited mountain lakes. Because the great Pyramid of the Sun at Teotihuac&#x00E1;n was built sometime between 150 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> and 225 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> above a natural cave probably associated with an origin myth, it is now thought that the city itself was sited with regard to this important natural symbol as well as in relation to <name type="pname">Cerro Gordo</name>, the mountain to the north, the profile of which is echoed by the axially aligned Pyramid of the Moon (fig. 1.27).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-31">
<graphic url="CH1_028.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.27. View from Pyramid of the Moon along Avenue of the Dead with Pyramid and the sun in the middle distance, Teo-<lb/>
tihuac&#x00E1;n, <name type="place">Mexico</name>. c. 150&#x2013;225 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Mimetic architecture&#x2014;structures whose shapes imitate natural land forms&#x2014;is apparent in the diverse cultures of the Americas. Although less predeter-<lb/>
<pb n="48"/>
<pb n="48" type="orig"/>
mined in plan and form than Teotihuac&#x00E1;n, <name type="pname">Taos Pueblo</name>, which is still occupied, bears a mimetic rela-<lb/>
tionship to Taos Mountain like that of the Pyramid of the Moon to <name type="pname">Cerro Gordo</name> (fig. 1.28). But in nei-<lb/>
ther case does the built environment dominate the natural one. The imitative forms are subservient to the natural ones. The former is the locus of human life and ritual ceremony; the latter is the residence of divinity.</p>
<p>Many of the great civilizations of the Americas vanished for reasons that can only be guessed. With-<lb/>
out a literature such as the Homeric epics or the more factually based stories of <name type="pname">Herodotus</name> and other histo-<lb/>
rians, the Aztecs were even more mystified than we about the fate of their predecessors in the Valley of <name type="place">Mexico</name>, the builders of Teotihuac&#x00E1;n. Although they set down their own oral traditions in hieroglyphic accounts, few survived the Spanish Conquest. Archaeology, too, was thwarted as the market value placed upon pre-Columbian artifacts made ancient centers vulnerable to the depredations of looters. Nevertheless, significant progress has been made by recent archaeology in decoding hieroglyphic sym-<lb/>
bols carved in stone and also in the field known as archaeoastronomy, the science that attempts to explain landscape constructions in cosmological terms. Archaeologists and archaeoastronomists have come to realize that by studying the siting of certain monuments and structures in relationship to the posi-<lb/>
tion of the stars, the course of the moon, or the posi-<lb/>
tion of the sun at the time of the spring and fall equinoxes, native peoples in the Americas were practicing what surely must have been landscape design in the broadest possible sense&#x2014;what we might call cosmological landscape architecture.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-32">
<graphic url="CH1_029.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.28. <name type="place">Taos Pueblo</name> with <name type="place">Taos Mountain</name> behind it. <name type="place">Taos</name>, <name type="place">New Mexico</name>. Occupied continuously since c. 1200 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Photographed in <date when="1993">1993</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Mounds and Plazas</hi></hi></head>
<p>Pre-Columbian architecture is essentially an archi-<lb/>
tecture of mass and communal open space. Its con-<lb/>
struction was an administrative and technical feat of considerable magnitude. The scale of earth-moving operations undertaken by the people who built the first earthworks is indeed awe-inspiring, especially when one remembers that there existed no mecha-<lb/>
nized equipment such as that employed by the cre-<lb/>
ators of the modern earthworks discussed in Chapter Twelve, nor did these builders use wheeled vehicles. Like the pyramidal masonry "skyscrapers" of the Maya in <name type="place">Mexico</name> and <name type="place">Central America</name> (250 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>&#x2013;900 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>), the immense earthworks at Poverty Point, <name type="place">Lou-<lb/>
isiana</name> (1800 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>&#x2013;500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), the <name type="place">Hopewell Mounds</name> in <name type="place">Ohio</name> (100 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>&#x2013;400 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>), and the mon-<lb/>
umental mounds of the Mississippian culture at <name type="place">Cahokia</name> near present-day <name type="pname">St. Louis</name> (800&#x2013;1350 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) are meant to be ascended, descended, or walked around (fig. 1.29). Unlike Western architecture since Roman times, these structures do not provide widely vaulted, domed, volumetric interior space. As opposed to basilicas and cathedrals, they are not architectural shells in which to move about freely. Because this is true, landscape space&#x2014;the space defined by both the architecture and the natural forms of the site&#x2014;is fundamental in both a utilitar-<lb/>
ian and a religious sense.</p>
<pb n="49"/>
<pb n="49" type="orig"/>
<p>The earliest evidence in the Americas of a large-<lb/>
scale, well-planned, collaboratively constructed land-<lb/>
scape space occurs in northeast <name type="place">Louisiana</name> where approximately five thousand years ago several series of large earthen mounds were built. At <name type="pname">Watson Brake</name>, the builders of eleven of these early mounds linked them by earthen ridges to form an oval-shaped enclo-<lb/>
sure (fig. 1.30). Their purpose was probably to accom-<lb/>
modate some funerary or other ceremonial practice. The persistence of this central space&#x2014;or plaza, if we adopt the Spanish term&#x2014;as a landscape form is evi-<lb/>
denced, as we have seen, in the extant pueblos of northern <name type="place">New Mexico</name> and <name type="place">Arizona</name>, which have occu-<lb/>
pied their present locations since around 1300 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The spectacular and well-preserved ruins within the shel-<lb/>
tering cliff faces of Mesa Verde in the San Juan Basin of southern <name type="place">Colorado</name> and <name type="place">Canyon de Chelly</name> in north-<lb/>
eastern <name type="place">Arizona</name>, which was occupied as early as the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> by people known as Basket Maker and then between 1100 and 1300 by the ancestral Puebloan people referred to as Anasazi, testify to the harmony between architecture and nature achieved by Native American builders. Even in these creviced locations they managed to fit miniature plazas with <hi rend="italic">kivas:</hi> level, open ledges that served both sacred and quotidian functions (fig. 1.31). Thus, whether the Ciu-<lb/>
dadela at Teotihuac&#x00E1;n, a 38-acre sunken plaza with the huge Temple of the Feathered Serpent at one end, a tiny platform in the wall of a <name type="place">Pueblo</name>-occupied cliff, or a half acre of packed earth forming the <hi rend="italic">bupingeh</hi> (middle-heart place) of contemporary Tewa people, plazas were and remain ceremonially important spaces, places of dance and priestly spectacle, includ-<lb/>
ing, in the <name type="place">Mesoamerica</name> of pre-Columbian times, human sacrifice.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-33">
<graphic url="CH1_030.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.29. <name type="place">Monks Mound</name> and the <name type="place">Great Plaza</name>, <name type="place">Cahokia</name>, <name type="place">Illinois</name>. c. 800&#x2013;1350 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Entrance mural by <name type="pname">Lloyd K. Townsend</name>, <name type="place">Cahokia</name> Mounds State Historic Site, <name type="place">Collinsville</name>, <name type="place">Illinois</name>. Basing his work on extant remains and archaeological evidence, the artist has rendered central <name type="place">Cahokia</name> around 1100 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, viewed from the south with the Twin Mounds in the fore-<lb/>
ground, the <name type="place">Grand Plaza</name>, and <name type="place">Monks Mound</name> in the distance.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-34">
<graphic url="CH1_031.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.30. <name type="pname">Watson Brake</name>, near <name type="place">Monroe</name>, <name type="place">Louisiana</name>. c. 3000 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e</hi> On the Ouachita River to the southwest of Monroe a 3-foot-(approx. 0.9-<lb/>
meter-) high circular embankment studded with eleven roughly conical mounds embraces a plaza that measures approximately 920 feet (280 meters) by 650 feet (198 meters).</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-35">
<graphic url="CH1_032.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.31. Cliff Palace, with apartments, <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi>, and plazas set within the rock face, Mesa Verde National Park, Colorado. c. 5th century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, Basket Maker culture and c. 1100&#x2013;1300 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, ancestral Puebloan cul-<lb/>
ture</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="50"/>
<pb n="50" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-36">
<graphic url="CH1_033.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.32. <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name>, <name type="place">Chaco Canyon</name>, <name type="place">Arizona</name>. c. 860 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>&#x2013;1130 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The numerous large <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi>, axially interconnected rooms, fine masonry workmanship, massive ceiling timbers imported from far away, and sheer scale of the D-shaped structure called <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name> argue its possible function as a major ceremo-<lb/>
nial center.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ancestral Puebloan Settlements Around <name type="place">Chaco Canyon</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>In the Southwest, where the conditions for successful agriculture were especially demanding, native societ-<lb/>
ies were more egalitarian and less hierarchical than those of the great Mississippian, Mesoamerican, and Aztec builders who erected the massive pyramids that arouse our awe today. The peoples of the Southwest fit these structures into their spectacular, dry environ-<lb/>
ment with great ingenuity. In their landscape-con-<lb/>
forming works, economy and beauty go hand in hand. The cavelike <hi rend="italic">kiva</hi>, with its fire pit and <hi rend="italic">sipapu</hi>&#x2014;or emergence hole&#x2014;indented in the floor, was the archi-<lb/>
tectural descendant of the pit house. This barely visi-<lb/>
ble structure was covered by the earthen floor of a plaza that served, as we have already noted, as a daily work space and, in some cases, as a ritual dancing ground.</p>
<p>Above all, the purpose of the <hi rend="italic">kiva</hi> and the plaza above it is to provide a space in which humans can acknowledge and participate in the cosmic connection between the bowl-imaged earth and the basket-sym-<lb/>
bolized sky, affirm the orientation of their community with respect to the cardinal compass points and sacred mountains and mesas, and experience the life breath that flows throughout this universe. Larger pre-Co-<lb/>
lumbian pueblos often had several functioning <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi> to serve the various clans within them. Although built above ground, the <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi> of today are still circular structures without any aspiration toward monumen-<lb/>
tality in the European sense.</p>
<p>Centering according to an <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi> estab-<lb/>
lished at a place of community focus and cosmic ritual could assume vast regional dimensions as illustrated by the great ancestral Puebloan center at <name type="place">Chaco Can-<lb/>
yon</name> (fig. 1.32). Recent archaeological discoveries in the Four Corners area reveal a far-flung road system drawing many ancestral Pueblos, including those at Mesa Verde and Canyon de Chelly, into a spatial rela-<lb/>
tionship with this important ceremonial nexus.<ref target="#CH1-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref>
<pb n="51"/>
<pb n="51" type="orig"/>
Archaeologists refer to this important urban complex as "the Chaco phenomenon." They face many unan-<lb/>
swered questions as they continue to study <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name>, <name type="place">Chetro Ketl</name>, and other Great Houses in the center of the canyon along with the "outliers," ance-<lb/>
stral Puebloan ruins with large ceremonial <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi> and ancillary residential or storage chambers, such as are found at Aztec and Salmon. They have discerned at least seven sets of roads, which collectively comprise nearly 1,500 miles (2,414 kilometers), radiating from Chaco, and some suggest that at least one of the roads, which they call the Great North Road, because of its alignment within one-half degree of true north until it bends to a two&#x00B0; angle to focus upon an important cone-shaped mound, "is a cosmological expression of the Chaco culture."<ref target="#CH1-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref> The fact that this is a road lacking a clear practical destination supports such a conclusion.</p>
<p>Indifferent to topography, the Chacoan roads scale canyon walls by means of wooden stairs or steps carved into bedrock or built of masonry, but, where they change direction, they do so at an abrupt angle, usually at the site of a Great House or at a <hi rend="italic">herradu-<lb/>
ra</hi>&#x2014;a low, horseshoe-shaped enclosure, frequently located at a high point where there is a distant view. Where they traverse slick rock, their course is some-<lb/>
times etched by a single shallow groove. No one knows the exact function of these <hi rend="italic">herraduras</hi>, but they may have been roadside shrines. There is little road-<lb/>
side debris or other evidence of overnight camps such as traders would have left and no evidence that the roads were used after the climax of Chacoan culture around 1140 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e</hi>.<ref target="#CH1-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref> Like the Maya causeways and the Inka roads in <name type="place">Peru</name>, the Chacoan roads were probably used for ceremonial purposes, and concentrations in various roadside locations of ceramic shards that appear to have been ritually broken suggest this pos-<lb/>
sibility. Allied with the roads were mesa-top signaling stations, which may have been used to transmit prac-<lb/>
tical messages, but which also probably functioned as observatories, thus serving a cosmological purpose.</p>
<p>Supporting the conclusion that Chaco was an important festival center in the ancient Southwest is the presence directly opposite <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name>, on the south side of the Chaco Wash, of a <hi rend="italic">kiva</hi> more than 63 feet (19.2 meters) in diameter called <name type="place">Casa Rinconada</name>, possibly the largest <hi rend="italic">kiva</hi> the ancestral Puebloans ever built (fig. 1.33). In its orientation and design, <name type="place">Casa Rinconada</name> appears to symbolize the ancient Puebloan cosmos. The axis running through its north and south doorways is aligned within a fraction of a degree of time north, and the four sockets for the large timber roof supports form a perfect square, each side of which is also true to a cardinal direction within a frac-<lb/>
tion of a degree. On the inside of its circular masonry wall were cut twenty-eight niches, with a possible additional one making twenty-nine. These may have had a relationship to the 29.5-day lunar month. Six larger, irregularly spaced niches were also cut into the wall. The northeastern roof support might have blocked its passage, but archaeologists have noted that a beam of light entering the <hi rend="italic">kiva</hi> today on the day of the summer solstice illuminates one of the larger niches. Within <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name>, window perforations appear to have been positioned to allow light to travel in a pattern across a wall surface in a manner that both predicts and marks the winter solstice. Whether or not Chacoan priests used these features in making their calendrical notations, it is certain that here, as else-<lb/>
where in the region of ancient habitation by Puebloan peoples, they studied the movement of celestial bod-<lb/>
ies and reflected their astronomical knowledge in their lives and in the landscape, timing their ritual and agri-<lb/>
cultural practices and aligning their buildings and roads with the positions of the Sun, stars, and planets in the sky.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-37">
<graphic url="CH1_034.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.33. <name type="place">Casa Rinconada</name>, <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name> and its mounds, and the suggested axis linking these two ancestral Puebloan structures. Plan by <name type="pname">Stephen H. Lekson</name>, <date when="1992">1992</date>. Unlike the <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi> of unit houses or the <hi rend="italic">kivas</hi> within a Great House such as <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name>, <name type="place">Casa Rinconada</name> stands in isolation. If, however, one takes into account an axis running from <name type="place">Casa Rinconada</name> through the two large rectangu-<lb/>
lar mounds at the southern edge of <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name> in alignment with the wall that bisects it into an eastern and a western half, it is apparent that a linkage was intended. The mounds once had strong masonry retaining walls and a flat plastered surface on top, giving them greater archi-<lb/>
tectural importance than that of a typical ancient unit house. Per-<lb/>
haps they were used ritually as ceremonial platforms. In any case, they are the vertical inverse of the sunken architec-<lb/>
ture within <name type="place">Pueblo Bonito</name>. Not only do they heighten the feeling of its enclosure, but they also dramatize the approach from, and connection to, <name type="place">Casa Rinco-<lb/>
nada</name>. Similar mounds, which are not typical midden or refuse mounds but often contain bro-<lb/>
ken ceramics possibly associ-<lb/>
ated with ritual ceremonies, are found at Pueblo Alto and at many outlier sites.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="52"/>
<pb n="52" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-38">
<graphic url="CH1_035.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.34. Aerial view of Lake Titi-<lb/>
caca and the altiplano, <name type="place">Peru</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>At the beginning of the second third of the twelfth century, Chaco's importance as the area's controlling political force suddenly waned. By the middle of the twelfth century, the Chacoans had stopped all construction, and they no longer orga-<lb/>
nized ceremonial festivals in the canyon. At Chaco and its outliers, by 1300 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, many roads had been ritually closed and the ceremonial rooms of Great Houses dismantled and burned. At the same time, new settlements appeared around Black Mesa in what is now northeastern <name type="place">Arizona</name> and in the Rio Grande Valley, and these became the ancestral communities of the Hopi, Zuni, and Rio Grande pueblos of today.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Inka Shrines</hi></hi></head>
<p>The Inka civilization that flourished in the fifteenth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> revered as one of its sacred sites Tiwa-<lb/>
naku, a cosmologically planned city built on the altiplano in the flat basin around Lake Titicaca between around 400 and 1100 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Like other real and imaginary lakes of Native American mythol-<lb/>
ogy, Lake Titicaca played a significant role as the place of human origin. To the ancient inhabitants of the altiplano, its bowl shape and watery depths symbolized the feminine principle and embryonic gestation, whereas the rigid, dry, glaciated peaks around it had an obvious association with mascu-<lb/>
linity (fig. 1.34).<ref target="#CH1-n20"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref> Lake Titicaca, in other words, was a natural form that perfectly represented the womb of earth and its center, while its jagged hori-<lb/>
zon line of mountains helped mark the cardinal points, pinning the sky with its beneficent sun and revolving stars and planets to the landscape plain around it.</p>
<p>Upon ascending the throne, each Inka ruler undertook a major building program as a means of asserting authority. Dynastic power and the cosmic connectedness of the empire, which extended 2,700 miles (4,345 kilometers) from north to south along the Pacific coast of <name type="place">South America</name>, was evident in the four highways emanating from Cuzco's central plaza. From the consequent division of the surrounding countryside the empire took its name, Tahuantinsuyu, "Land of the Four Quarters." A network of highways covering approximately 19,000 miles (30,000 kilometers), over which teams of runners coursed on government busi-<lb/>
ness, allowed the Inkas to maintain their sway. Shrines in nature also helped weave the empire into a cultural unity. The ruined center of Tiwanaku on Lake Titicaca was one of these sacred sites, lending to the Inkas increased authority over the local population and link-<lb/>
ing them with that city's ancient builders. Here, on an island, <name type="pname">Topa Inka</name> (ruled 1471&#x2013;1493 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) enlarged a temple dedicated to the Sun and planted a grove of trees in the sacred precinct that enclosed a rock, believed to be the sun's place of origin and the spot where life began. Ritual processions to this mytholog-<lb/>
ically designated origin rock passed through a series of ceremonial gateways.</p>
<p>Other nature shrines included springs, mountain peaks, and venerated stones called <hi rend="italic">pururuacas</hi>, which were considered to be transformed warriors. Promi-<lb/>
nent and distinctively shaped rocks were often singled out within the landscape and given sacred status. A special boulder would receive an architectural enclo-<lb/>
sure, and a bedrock outcrop could be carved as a royal dais. Mimetic rocks, those whose outlines echoed dis-<lb/>
<pb n="53"/>
<pb n="53" type="orig"/>
tant mountains, might be assigned iconic status (fig. 1.36). Altogether, 328 <hi rend="italic">huacas</hi>, or sacred places, were sited along forty-one sight lines, called <hi rend="italic">ceques</hi>, which emanated like sun rays outward from Cuzco. At these shrines, travelers and pilgrims made votive offerings of beautifully woven cloth, figurines in stone and pre-<lb/>
cious metals, and broken shells. They also deposited food and drink for the indwelling spirits of the <hi rend="italic">huacas</hi>.</p>
<p>In some <hi rend="italic">huacas</hi> sacrificed children were interred. They had served as participants in a ritual designed to bond the far-flung empire into a more secure religious union. The children, aged six to ten and chosen for their beauty and family status from villages throughout Tahuantinsuyu's four quarters, were consigned to the company of priests with whom they traveled the net-<lb/>
work of highways that led to Cuzco, where they were-<lb/>
greeted with pomp. There boys and girls were paired in symbolic marriage ceremonies and paraded sol-<lb/>
emnly around the main plaza, the heart of the Inka universe. After the celebrations were over and the chil-<lb/>
dren had been properly feted, the traveling parties returned to their home villages. But this time they did not journey along the system of highways, but crossed the arduous terrain in straight paths following the sacred <hi rend="italic">ceque</hi> lines. Each group was preceded by chant-<lb/>
ing Inka officials carrying statues and valuable offer-<lb/>
ings. Once they were received back home with honor, the children, dressed in finery and accompanied by figurines and other offerings, were placed in one of the local <hi rend="italic">huacas</hi> and interred alive. In this way the Inka-<lb/>
empire wove space into a fabric of power in which local places and Cuzco were tightly bound by ritual ceremony and pilgrimage along the <hi rend="italic">ceque</hi> lines.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-39">
<graphic url="CH1_036.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.35. Ritual lines with trapezoidal area, <name type="place">Nazca</name>, <name type="place">Peru</name>. c. 200 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>&#x2013;600 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The arrowlike triangles and trape-<lb/>
zoids, which are visible around Nazca from the air, appear to be correlated with the flow of water, while the nexus of converging lines, called ray centers, are thought to be related to the river system. Geoglyphs&#x2014;<lb/>
images etched by exposing the light soil below the oxidized gravel surface of the desert&#x2014;can be inter-<lb/>
preted in terms of a water-based religion. Remarkably, they were constructed by people who could only view their work piecemeal. Geoglyphs had to be conceived as scale models and then enlarged by a point-<lb/>
ing technique as they were scratched onto the earth's surface.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-40">
<graphic url="CH1_037.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">Left: 1.36. Rock shrine within the sacred Inka landscape, <name type="place">Quenco</name>, <name type="place">Peru</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Nazca Lines and Effigy Earthworks</hi></hi></head>
<p>Like the wide Chacoan roads, the mysterious lines in <name type="place">Peru</name> in the area embraced by the Nazca River system in <name type="place">South America</name>, dating from 200 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> to 600 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, raise many unanswered questions, but we can surmise that they also had ceremonial and religious signifi-<lb/>
cance. Archaeoastronomers have discerned alignments of the Nazca lines corresponding to solar events on the horizon and the positions of certain important constel-<lb/>
lations in the sky (fig. 1.35). The delineation of what were probably long-distance pilgrimage ways that also functioned as cosmological reference points in two
<pb n="54"/>
<pb n="54" type="orig"/>
such widely separated desert locations confirms the importance of astronomical observations and their calendrical correlations for ancient peoples.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-41">
<graphic url="CH1_038.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.37. <name type="place">Serpent Mound</name>, <name type="place">Locust Grove</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>. c. 1000&#x2013;1140 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The architects who laid out Great Serpent Mound fitted the writhing body of their nearly quarter-mile long reptile into the curve formed by the creek and its adjacent bluff. The oval form that appears to protrude from the snake's mouth can be read as an egg.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>But how do we attempt to explain the Nazca lines that are not straight: the geoglyphs&#x2014;giant figures of birds, fish, mammals, insects, and even anthropomorphic creatures "drawn" on the hard desert surface as paths 4.5 feet (1.37 meters) to 9 feet (2.74 meters) wide, which were created by scraping away the darker oxidized surface soil and placing it in small outlining ridges while exposing the lighter soil below? Are they clan totems or-<lb/>
etched forms with sacred meaning and ceremonial purpose to be traced with human footsteps as a means of absorbing their talismanic magic? It is easier to interpret the puma outline of the plan for Cuzco as a symbol of the Inka dynasty, but how can we explain the <name type="place">Great Serpent Mound</name> in <name type="place">Ohio</name>, now believed to date about 1000&#x2013;1140 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, and the so-called effigy mounds of the <name type="place">Upper Mississippi Valley</name>, which were built throughout the course of many centuries up until around 1300 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>? These giant earthworks&#x2014;the <name type="place">Great Bear Mound</name> in east-<lb/>
ern <name type="place">Iowa</name> measures 137 feet by 70 feet (41.8 meters by 21.3 meters)&#x2014;are particularly astonishing when one remembers that they were achieved by a people who had no draft animals or carts with wheels and no power equipment other than human sinew (figs. 1.37, 1.38).</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Contemporary Pueblos of the American Southwest</hi></hi></head>
<p>The persistence of cultural memory and tradition is strong among Native Americans, and in parts of the American Southwest it is still possible to find land-<lb/>
scapes where a potent residue of a once-pervasive ethos of place is discernible. A visitor gradually per-<lb/>
ceives that a pueblo&#x2014;a settlement on tribal lands in northern and western <name type="place">New Mexico</name> and northeast <name type="place">Arizona</name>, consisting of multilevel adobe or stone dwellings built by the descendants of indigenous prehistoric peoples&#x2014;is sited not by happenstance but in a particular way that acknowledges the cardi-<lb/>
nal directions and mesa and mountain forms in the near and far distance. Here on certain feast days dancers animate a "heart" place, a central plaza enclosed protectively by attached dwellings, with practiced movements meant to evoke the spirits of animals and the cosmological forces associated with fertility, procreation, and the continuance of life.</p>
<p>Acculturation and the psychological compart-<lb/>
mentalization of two differing systems of belief are characteristic of extant Puebloan cultures, heirs to Catholicism by virtue of the Spanish Conquest. In <name type="pname">Santa Clara Pueblo</name>, as in <name type="pname">San Ildefonso Pueblo</name>, <name type="pname">San Juan Pueblo</name>, and <name type="pname">Santo Domingo</name>, the patron saint is honored with a mass on her or his feast day, but the more significant celebration from an ethnic per-<lb/>
spective is the one that subsequently takes place in
<pb n="55"/>
<pb n="55" type="orig"/>
the pueblo's main and subsidiary plazas. Dances are performed first in one plaza and then another by men and women, old and young, in fine cos-<lb/>
tumes and high headdresses decorated with sym-<lb/>
bolic representions of animals, birds, clouds, and mountains.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-42">
<graphic url="CH1_039.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">1.38. Great Bear Mound, Effigy Mounds National Monument, Marquette, <name type="place">Iowa</name>. c. 350 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and 1300 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The Great Bear Mound is one of several mound formations in the area that today comprises western <name type="place">Wis-<lb/>
consin</name>, southwest <name type="place">Minnesota</name>, and northeast <name type="place">Iowa</name>. The few dozen that remain of what may have been as many as ten thousand before urbanization and agricultural operations eradicated them can be seen primar-<lb/>
ily in Lizard Mound County Park in <name type="place">Wisconsin</name> and Effigy Mounds National Monument in <name type="place">Iowa</name>. The Great Bear Mound in the latter is 137 feet (41.8 meters) in length and measures 70 feet wide (21.3 meters) at the bear's shoulders.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>It is worth looking closely at one of the seem-<lb/>
ingly nondescript spaces where Native American dance ceremonies take place. Recalling her child-<lb/>
hood at <name type="pname">Santa Clara Pueblo</name>, the architectural histo-<lb/>
rian <name type="pname">Rina Naranjo Swentzell</name> has written:
<q>As the pueblo, or human space, was encircled by high mountains, low hills and flat fields, the center point (<hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi>), from which the people emerged out of the underworld, was also gir-<lb/>
dled by different spaces within the pueblo. The <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi>, marked by an inconspicuous stone, was located within the middle-heart place, or the plaza. The plaza was bounded by house structures, which in turn were encircled by the corrals or places where horses, pigs, and chick-<lb/>
ens lived. Beyond that, or sometimes overlap-<lb/>
ping, were the trash mounds. The trash mounds flowed into the fields, and from there the energy moved into the hills and mountains where it entered those far shrines, moved through the underworld levels or existences and re-emerged through the <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi>.</q>
<q>The stories of the old people told us that we came to live on this fourth level of exis-<lb/>
tence with the help of plants, birds and other animals. Once we emerged out of the under-<lb/>
world, we continued to need those other living beings. In order to find the center point, or the <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi>, the water spider and the rainbow were consulted. Water Spider spread its legs to the north, west, south and east and determined the middle of this world. Then, to make sure that Water Spider was right, Rainbow spread its arch of many colors to the north, west, south and east and confirmed Water Spider's center point. There the people placed a stone, and around that stone was defined the middle-heart place. Next, the living and sleeping structures were built in terraced forms, like mountains, with stepped tiers which enclosed and pro-<lb/>
tected the plaza, or the valley of the human place.</q>
<q>The house and kiva structures also emu-<lb/>
lated the low hills and mountains in their con-<lb/>
nectedness to the earth. The adobe structures flowed out of the earth, and it was often diffi-<lb/>
cult to see where the ground stopped and where the structures began. The house structures were, moreover, connected to each other, enclosing an outdoor space from which we could directly connect with the sky and focus on the moving clouds. Connectedness was pri-<lb/>
mary. The symbolic flowed into the physical world as at the <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi> where the <hi rend="italic">po-wa-ha</hi> (the breath of the cosmos) flowed out of the underworld into this world.</q>
<q>The kiva structure was totally symbolic. Its rooftop was like the pueblo plaza space from where we could connect with the sky, while the rooftop opening took us into the kiva structure which was like going back into the earth via the <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi> in the plaza. Within the feminine dark interior, the plaza-space configuration was repeated with the human activity around a <hi rend="italic">nan-<lb/>
sipu</hi>, the earth floor under and the woven-bas-<lb/>
ket roof above, representing the sky. The connecting ladder made of tall spruce or pine trees stood in the middle near the <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi>. Everything was organized to remind us con-<lb/>
stantly of the primary connections with the earth, sky, other forms of life and the cosmic movement. These primary connections were continually reiterated.&#x2026;</q>
<q>Landscaping, or the beautification of out-<lb/>
door spaces, was a foreign concept. The natural environment was primary, and the human structures were made to fit into the hills and around boulders and trees. In that setting, plant-<lb/>
ing pretty flowers that need watering was ridic-<lb/>
ulous.<ref target="#CH1-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">21</hi></hi></ref></q></p>
<pb n="56"/>
<pb n="56" type="orig"/>
<p>Swentzell is telling us, as an aside, that in a land-<lb/>
scape where the human connection to what has been called first nature (wilderness) and second nature (the agrarian landscape of fields and pastures) is para-<lb/>
mount, a "third nature" as represented by the garden (an enclosed landscape space in which art and nature are conjoined) is irrelevant.<ref target="#CH1-n22"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref> Similarly, in discussing the form and function of the <hi rend="italic">bupingeh</hi>, as the plaza is called in the Tewa language, Swentzell remarks, "The emphasis of the <hi rend="italic">bupingeh</hi> is not on the substance but rather on the emptiness&#x2014;consequently, there are no statues, fountains, gazebos, park benches, grass, or flowers to enhance its appeal."<ref target="#CH1-n23"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">23</hi></hi></ref> More than a void, however, the <hi rend="italic">bupingeh</hi> is instinct with life; it is the space for ceremonial dance, "the connecting space between the cosmic energies of the Pueblo world which flow out of the <hi rend="italic">nansipu</hi> through the physical space of the pueblo to the hills, far mountains, and clouds and back into the underworld."<ref target="#CH1-n24"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">24</hi></hi></ref> Thus, the Puebloan today, perceiving symbolism directly in the built and natural forms of a perfectly centered, emo-<lb/>
tionally rich environment does not need to sustain his or her imagination with metaphorically suffused gar-<lb/>
den and park spaces or with ornamental structures and horticultural concerns.</p>
<p>As we have seen, over time, Native North American populations migrated from one site to another in response to climatic changes, resource depletion, war, or other territorial imperatives. Because of their nature-oriented religious views, wherever they estab-<lb/>
lished themselves, site planning centered the commu-<lb/>
nity with one or more sanctified central spaces, often the nexus of axial relationships with both celestial and terrestrial natural phenomena&#x2014;equinoctial and sol-<lb/>
stitial positions of the sun, calendrical maximum and minimum rise and set points of the moon, the predict-<lb/>
ably timed appearance of certain auspicious constel-<lb/>
lations in the night sky, and mountain forms. Usually these directional lines of cosmological connectivity were implied, but in some places, such as the Four Corners areas of the Southwest or on the arid plains of <name type="place">Peru</name>, Native Americans inscribed axes upon the land.</p>
<p>Prayer and propitiation were the necessary, avail-<lb/>
able means with which agricultural people living within the bounds of limited systems of technology addressed uncertainty and the exigencies of their circumstances. Those architectural forms that brought them into closer contact with Sky Father, Sun, Rain God, Earth Mother, and Seed Goddess were the physical manifestation of a belief system that sought above all else fertility and the continuance of life. Eurocentric theorists once pre-<lb/>
sumed that the Maya and the Teotihuac&#x00E1;nos were influ-<lb/>
enced in the construction of their great pyramids by Old World contact, which somehow seeded this build-<lb/>
ing form in the New. A more convincing explanation is the cosmological one that the mountain-mimicking pyramid is a universal human phenomenon, a priestly platform for communication with sky-dwelling gods or a funerary monument for rulers whose divine status ensured the regular rotation of the sun in its diurnal and annual cycles. Circular forms echo the 360&#x00B0; horizon and are an important element of cosmic consciousness. <name type="pname">Jung</name> believed that circles are archetypal, magical rings drawn around that which would be protected as sacred. He pointed out that a mandala, or circle within a square, is like a <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi>, or sacred enclosure, protecting what is magical and holy.</p>
<p>Jungian theory and the cosmological orientation of many early religions would help explain how axial lines, circles, pyramids, and other geometrical forms can be manifested in landscape design in widely diver-<lb/>
gent times and places. By acknowledging the widely shared need among societies to attune themselves to a religiously perceived cosmic power we can explain the correspondence between landscape forms employed for ritual purposes by prehistoric and early ancient peoples in <name type="place">Europe</name> and <name type="place">Asia</name> and their counter-<lb/>
parts, including contemporary native peoples, in the Americas. The important fact to ponder with regard to Mesoamerican pyramids and the Mississippian mounds built by the well-organized culture that flour-<lb/>
ished in the region around <name type="pname">St. Louis</name> between about 750 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> and 1500 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> is not their coincidental similarity to Old World "prototypes," but their sheer size and the amount of human labor their construction entailed. As in <name type="place">Egypt</name> and <name type="place">Mesopotamia</name>, belief in a religion medi-<lb/>
ated by a priestly elite was absolute, and it effectively prevented the subservient populace who built these monumental earth and stone works from refusing to work.</p>
<p>Cave sanctuaries, real and artificial mountains, earthworks, circular definitions of space, and the align-<lb/>
ment of axes with cardinal directions and the calendri-<lb/>
cal positions of celestial bodies constitute the primal components of landscape design dating from earliest times when humans perceived themselves to be embedded in nature and utterly dependent upon cos-<lb/>
mic forces. Gradually, during the first millennium <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, with the development of city-states, there emerged other ideals presupposing a more important role for humans in ordering life according to religious and eth-<lb/>
ical systems that placed them in fuller partnership with their gods. These values, too, dictated the shaping of space and the creation of places in which a newly minted vocabulary of classical forms that have remained influential throughout history was first man-<lb/>
ifested with great beauty.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="57"/>
<pb n="57" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter One</hi></hi></head>
<note xml:id="CH1-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">R. Murray Schafer</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Tuning of the World</hi> (<name type="place">Toronto</name>: McClelland and Stewart, <date when="1977">1977</date>), p. 157. Peripheral vision, rather than perspective focus, can be said to characterize the Chinese depiction of space, causing the eye to traverse from one viewpoint to another within the same work of art, with as much awareness of the peripheral areas as of the center; Byzantine art distorts scale and reverses perspective by increasing the size of distant objects; and Eskimo spatial represen-<lb/>
tation, probably because their landscape is spatially more amorphous than elsewhere, is unfocused in the way that acoustic space is multidirectional and has no fixed boundaries. Besides being analogous to unfocused, non-<lb/>
optical, aural space, Inuit space can be char-<lb/>
acterized as haptic&#x2014;space that is perceived by our own bodily presence within it. <name type="pname">Gilles Deleuze</name> (<date when="1925">1925</date>&#x2013;<date when="1995">1995</date>) and <name type="pname">F&#x00E9;lix Guattari</name> (<date when="1930">1930</date>&#x2013;<date when="1992">1992</date>), drawing on <name type="pname">Edmund Carpenter</name>'s description of Inuit space as having "no middle distance, no perspective, no outline, nothing the eye can cling to except thousands of smokey plumes of snow &#x2026; a land without bottom or edge &#x2026; a labyrinth alive with the movements of crowded people," have charac-<lb/>
terized this type of landscape as "smooth" space in which "there is neither horizon nor background nor perspective nor limit nor out-<lb/>
line orform nor center; there is no intermediary distance, or all distance is intermediary." See <name type="pname">Gilles Deleuze</name> and <name type="pname">F&#x00E9;lix Guattari</name>, <hi rend="italic">A Thousand Plateaus: Capitalism and Schizophrenia</hi>, trans. Brian Massumi (<name type="place">Minneapolis</name>: University of Minnesota Press, <date when="1987">1987</date>), p. 494. <name type="pname">Deleuze</name> and <name type="pname">Guattari</name> distinguish between smooth space&#x2014; as for instance the open sea, arctic wastes, and deserts, the trackless realm of nomads&#x2014; and "striated" optical space, where laws of perspective apply and distance is discernible and measurable. But in the two philosophers' view, much more than being categories of landscape analysis, smooth and striated space are cultural constructs. Because of the natural propensity of human beings to create order out of chaos, there is always a tendency to repli-<lb/>
cate cosmogenesis, to give smooth space a center and directional coordinates, thereby converting it into striated space. The reverse also can occur as when, for instance, we lose perspective in close distance or experience vision as a "sea" of impressions.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Mircea Eliade</name>, <hi rend="italic">Patterns in Comparative Religion</hi>, trans. <name type="pname">Rosemary Sheed</name> (<name type="place">Cleveland</name>: Meridian Books, <date when="1963">1963</date>), chap. 8, sec. 97. This work provides a valuable introduction to the universal reverence among many world cul-<lb/>
tures and early human societies for such sym-<lb/>
bolically potent archetypal forms as monumental stones, sacred trees, Earth Mother, sky gods, water, the sun, and the moon.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Jolane Jacobi</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Psychology of <name type="pname">C.G. Jung</name></hi> (<name type="place">New Haven</name>: Yale University Press, <date when="1973">1973</date>). This work provides a useful over-view of <name type="pname">Jung</name>'s thought and a clear introduction to the subject of archetypes and symbols, image carriers of psychological states, which <name type="pname">Jung</name> posits as residing in the collective unconscious of humankind.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Steven J. Mithen</name>, <hi rend="italic">Thoughtful Foragers: A Study of Prehistoric Decision Making</hi> (<name type="place">Cam-<lb/>
bridge</name>: Cambridge University Press, <date when="1990">1990</date>), chap. 8.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">David Abram</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Spell of the Sensu-<lb/>
ous: Perception and Language in the More-<lb/>
than-Human World</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Pantheon Books, <date when="1996">1996</date>), pp. 140&#x2013;41. According to <name type="pname">Abram</name>, "Without guns or gunpowder, a native hunter must often come much closer to his wild prey if he is to take its life. Closer, that is, not just physically but emotionally, empathically entering into proximity with the other animal's ways of sensing and experiencing. The native hunter must <hi rend="italic">apprentice</hi> himself to those ani-<lb/>
mals that he would kill. Through long and careful observation, enhanced at times by rit-<lb/>
ual identification and mimesis, the hunter gradually develops an instinctive knowledge of the habits of his prey, of its fears and its plea-<lb/>
sures, its preferred foods and favored haunts. Nothing is more integral to this practice than learning the communicative signs, gestures, and cries of the local animals."</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Jean Clottes</name> and <name type="pname">Jean Courtin</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Cave Beneath the Sea: Paleolithic Images at Cosquer</hi>_(<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Harry N. Abrams</name>, Inc., <date when="1996">1996</date>), pp. 59&#x2013;79 and pp. 173&#x2013;175. See also <name type="pname">Jean-Marie Chauvet</name>, <name type="pname">&#x00C9;liette Brunel Des-<lb/>
champs</name>, and <name type="pname">Christian Hillaire</name>, <hi rend="italic">Dawn of Art: The Chauvet Cave</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Harry N. Abrams</name>, Inc.,<date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 110 and plates 25, 26, 28, and 91.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">John E. Pfeiffer</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Creative Explo-<lb/>
sion: An Inquiry into the Origins of Art and Religion</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Harper amp; Row, Publishers, <date when="1982">1982</date>), pp. 102&#x2013;18.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p>According to <name type="pname">Schafer</name>, there is a chamber in the Neolithic cave of Hypogeum on <name type="place">Malta</name> (c. 2400 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) that functions exactly like an arti-<lb/>
ficial cavity-type resonator, producing an ampli-<lb/>
fied, reverberating sound when activated by the low-frequency components of a deep male voice. See <name type="pname">R. Murray Schafer</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Tuning of the World</hi>, pp. 217&#x2013;18.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p>For a good discussion of the haptic nature of nomadic art and space, see <name type="pname">Deleuze</name> and <name type="pname">Guattari</name>, <hi rend="italic">A Thousand Plateaus</hi>, pp. 492&#x2013;500.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Eliade</name>, <hi rend="italic">Patterns in Comparative Reli-<lb/>
gion</hi>. chap. 6, sec. 74, for an interpretation of the archetypal significance of stones. Here he writes: "Above all, stone <hi rend="italic">is</hi>_.&#x2026; Rock shows [the human being] something that transcends the precariousness of his humanity: an abso-<lb/>
lute mode of being. &#x2026; Men have always adored stones simply in as much as they rep-<lb/>
resent something <hi rend="italic">other</hi> than themselves. They adored stones, or they used them as instru-<lb/>
ments of spiritual action, as centres of energy designed to defend them or their dead. And we may say from the start that most of the stones connected with worship were used as <hi rend="italic">instru-<lb/>
ments;</hi> they helped towards getting something, towards ensuring possession of it."</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p>To follow the several phases of the argu-<lb/>
ment proposing and rebutting a solar alignment for this megalith, see <name type="pname">Aubrey Burl</name>, <hi rend="italic">Great Stone Circles</hi> (<name type="place">New Haven</name>: Yale University Press, <date when="1999">1999</date>), pp. 130&#x2013;134.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Burl</name>, op. cit., pp. 110&#x2013;12.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p>For a detailed, recent archaeological record of this important urban center, see <name type="pname">Tim-<lb/>
othy R. Pauketat</name> and <name type="pname">Thomas E. Emerson</name>, eds., <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">Cahokia</name>: Domination and Ideology in the Mississippian World</hi> (<name type="place">Lincoln</name>: University of Nebraska Press, <date when="1997">1997</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p>Eventually the god Re was absorbed into the powerful priestly religion of Amon, the sun god worshipped by the populations of the New Kingdom (1550&#x2013;1069 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p>The name <hi rend="italic">Minoan</hi> derives from <name type="pname">Sir Arthur Evans</name> (<date when="1851">1851</date>&#x2013;<date when="1941">1941</date>), the British archaeologist who unearthed the famous "Labyrinth" at <name type="place">Knos-<lb/>
sos</name>. <name type="pname">Evans</name>, raised like the rest of his genera-<lb/>
tion on the classics and influenced by <name type="pname">Heinrich Schliemann</name>, who had made similar assump-<lb/>
tions in his work at Mycenae, looked to Homeric literature and ancient legend as well as to <name type="pname">Thucydides</name> and <name type="pname">Herodotus</name> for help in interpreting his astonishing discoveries. Thus, he assumed that the vast Labyrinth was the palace of the legendary <name type="pname">King Minos</name> and con-<lb/>
ferred the name "Minoan" on the prehistoric culture of <name type="place">Crete</name>. <name type="pname">Evans</name>, however, correctly identified many chambers and the great central court as spaces dedicated to ritual use. <name type="pname">Rod-<lb/>
ney Castleden</name>'s recent interpretation of the <name type="place">Knossos</name> ruins sugggests that the entire Laby-<lb/>
rinth was a temple under the auspices of a female priesthood serving the great Earth Goddess. See <hi rend="italic">Minoans: Life in Bronze Age <name type="place">Crete</name></hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: Routledge, <date when="1990">1990</date>) and <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place">Knossos</name> Labyrinth</hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: Routledge, <date when="1990">1990</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Alfonso Ortiz</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Tewa World: Space, Time, Being, and Becoming in a Pueblo Soci-<lb/>
ety</hi> (<name type="place">Chicago</name>: University of Chicago Press, <date when="1969">1969</date>). A Native American anthropologist, <name type="pname">Ortiz</name> explains the siting of a group of Rio Grande pueblos including <name type="pname">Santa Clara</name>, <name type="pname">San Ildefonso</name>, and <name type="pname">San Juan</name>, in accordance with Tewa origin myths similar in content to the origin myths of other pueblo communities. The Tewa myths tell of the emergence of six pairs of brothers from an underworld lake when the earth was yet "half-cooked." Remaining below are the first mothers, Blue Corn Woman (the summer mother), White Corn Maiden (the winter mother), and the people awaiting release into the upper world. Each pair of brothers is asso-<lb/>
ciated with a particular color, which in turn is associated with north (blue), south (red), east (white), west (yellow), the zenith (dark), and the nadir (all-colored). Four of the pairs depart, each toward one of the cardinal directions, while the fifth and sixth head for the zenith and nadir. Before returning to the underworld to await the earth's readiness for the emergence of the people, the first four pairs of brothers throw some of the as-yet unbaked earth's mud at each of the four directions, creating the <hi rend="italic">tsin</hi>, or flat-topped mesas. The mesas have caves or tunnels running through them where dwell the supernatural <hi rend="italic">Tsavejo</hi>, or masked whippers. These are also the places where the <hi rend="italic">Towa &#x00E9;</hi>, spiritual guardians of the pueblo, reside. Beyond the mesas lie the sacred mountains, prominent peaks, each associated with one of the four cardinal points. The zenith is associ-<lb/>
ated with a large star, or perhaps Venus, in the eastern sky, and the nadir with the rainbow. Individual pueblos identify their communities with sacred mountains, and they continue to celebrate winter and summer with dances that honor White Corn Maiden and Blue Corn Mother.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Stephen H. Lekson</name>, <name type="pname">John R. Stein</name>, and <name type="pname">Simon J. Ortiz</name>, <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">Chaco Canyon</name>: A Center and Its World</hi> (<name type="place">Santa Fe</name>: Museum of <name type="place">New Mex-<lb/>
ico</name>, <date when="1994">1994</date>). See also <name type="pname">Stephen H. Lekson</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Chaco Meridian: Centers of Political Power in the Ancient Southwest</hi> (<name type="place">Walnut Creek, Califor-<lb/>
nia</name>: Altamira Press, <date when="1999">1999</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Anna Sofaer</name>, <name type="pname">Michael P. Marshall</name>, and <name type="pname">Rolf M. Sinclair</name>, "The Great North Road: A cosmo-<lb/>
graphic expression of the Chaco culture of <name type="place">New Mexico</name>," in <hi rend="italic">World Archaeoastronomy</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>: Cambridge University Press, <date when="1989">1989</date>), p. 365.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p>Ibid., p. 366.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">20.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Alan Kolata</name> and <name type="pname">Carlos Ponce San-gines</name> call <name type="pname">Lake Titicaca</name> "the sacred locus for many indigenous myths of creation," in which "native Aymara Indians referred to the fertile axis formed by the lake as <hi rend="italic">taypi</hi>. the essential con-<lb/>
ceptual and physical zone of convergence between the principles of <hi rend="italic">urco</hi> (associated with the west, highlands, dryness, pastoralism, celestialness, and masculinity) and <hi rend="italic">uma</hi> (asso-<lb/>
ciated with the east, lowlands, wetness, agri-<lb/>
culture, underworld, and femininity). See "Tiwanaku: The City at the Center" in <hi rend="italic">The Ancient Americas: Art from Sacred Land-<lb/>
scapes</hi>. ed. <name type="pname">Richard F. Townsend</name> (<name type="place">Chicago</name>: The Art Institute of <name type="place">Chicago</name>, <date when="1992">1992</date>), p. 317.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">21.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Rina Naranjo Swentzell</name>, "Remembering Tewa Pueblo Houses and Spaces," in <hi rend="italic">Native Peoples</hi> 3:2 (Winter <date when="1990">1990</date>), pp. 6&#x2013;12.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">22.</hi></seg><p>For a thorough discussion of how humans have invested landscape with meaning and how Renaissance humanists derived the con-<lb/>
cept of gardens as a "third nature," see <name type="pname">John Dixon Hunt</name>, <hi rend="italic">Greater Perfections</hi>_(<name type="place">Philadelphia</name>: University of Pennsylvania Press, <date when="1999">1999</date>), chap. 3.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n23" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">23.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Rina Naranjo Swentzell</name>, "Bupingeh: The Pueblo Plaza," <hi rend="italic">El Palacio</hi> 2 (<date when="1994">1994</date>), p. 16.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH1-n24" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">24.</hi></seg><p>Ibid.</p></note>
</div>
</div>
</div>
