<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/html/tei.xsl"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY</title>
                <author>ELIZABETH BARLOW ROGERS</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>HARRY N. ABRAMS, INC.,</publisher>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY by ELIZABETH BARLOW
                    ROGERS</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div type="chapter"><pb n="58"/><pb n="58" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER TWO NATURE, ART, AND REASON: LANDSCAPE DESIGN IN THE CLASSICAL WORLD</hi></head><figure xml:id="fig-43"><graphic url="CH2_001.jpg"/></figure><p><hi rend="bold">T</hi>he term <hi rend="italic">classical</hi> is important to our understanding of landscape history. As used here, it signifies the aesthetic values embodied in Greek and Roman art and architecture: simplicity of form, harmonious proportion, and ornament that draws attention to significant parts of structures. It usually affirms symmetry over eccentricity, seeks the normative, and avoids the florid. <hi rend="italic">Classicism</hi> also embodies the notion of humanism, the system of thought that centers upon the capacities and values of human beings. Also inherent in the mentality of classicism is the ideal of the city as the locus for the good life, its citizens' beneficient mother, a landscape where the human and the natural are united in a bond sealed by divine visitation, bounty, and protection, a place from which exile was an extreme punishment.<ref target="#CH2-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref></p><p><hi rend="italic">Humanism</hi>, in fact, is the term European Renaissance intellectuals applied to their rediscovery of <name type="pname">Plato</name>, <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, and the literary heritage of ancient <name type="place">Greece</name>, which had been preserved in certain Byzantine monasteries and the libraries of Arab scholars, and to the stylistic inspiration they derived both from ancient Latin authors and from Roman ruins and the works of ancient art and architecture. The rationality and order they found in classical architecture and planning expressed human values and human dignity to Renaissance societies. The same kind of regard accounts for the recurring appeal of the classical heritage of <name type="place">Greece</name> and <name type="place">Rome</name>, as witnessed in the Italian Renaissance, the French style of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>, eighteenth- and nineteenth-century Neoclassicism, and its twentieth-century variations, including the appropriation of the classical idiom by Postmodernists.</p><p>Although they are fused into a single legacy, we must not conflate Roman classicism and its Greek antecedents into a single style. They are, in fact, expressions of two separate cultures. Roman classicism is the product of a practical, pragmatic, and technologically advanced society. It is innovative within the bounds of a firmly established, large-scale cultural framework and, in spite of the persistence of cultic worship and superstition, confident of its ability to apply the forces of nature toward human ends.</p><p>In reconstructing the culture of Classical <name type="place">Greece</name>, we are able to consult written sources. History, literature, and philosophy offer an enriched perspective not available for subjects yielding only an archaeological record. With the written word, we have evidence of a people who had a fundamental grasp of the tragic nature of human existence and an enduring, deep interest in the transforming power of art. In their culture, we find myth and magic being challenged by reason. In landscape terms, this is expressed through the balanced tension of geometric forms bound in partnership with nature. The proportions and arrangement of these geometric forms speak to the supremacy ancient Greeks accorded mathematics&#x2014;the primary mode of reason&#x2014;as a means of understanding the cosmos and the natural world.</p><p>Earlier cosmologies were compounded of astronomical observation fused with myth. The first Greek philosophers, such as <name type="pname">Thales</name> and <name type="pname">Parmenides</name>, who lived on the Aegean coast of <name type="place">Asia Minor</name> in a period that spanned the late seventh, sixth, and early fifth centuries <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, sought an underlying principle of rational unity governing all natural phenomena. Abstract rational logic&#x2014;deduction&#x2014;assumed value as a trustworthy means of apprehending the world and attaining cosmological understanding. As these Greeks developed a philosophical, rather than a mythological, approach to viewing the world and themselves, they did not attempt to drain nature of the inherent divinity accorded it by earlier and contemporary people. Instead, they sought divine principles at work in nature. At the same time, their rationalism began the process of transforming the gods into allegorical representations of various ideals&#x2014;military prowess (Athena), reason (Apollo), fertility (Demeter), and family life (Hera)&#x2014;to name certain prominent members of the Greek pantheon.</p><p>Pythagoras, the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> philosopher who created a settlement with his followers at Crotona in southern <name type="place">Italy</name>,<pb n="59"/><pb n="59" type="orig"/>offered an approach to comprehending the world that was both intellectual and spiritual. Although Pythagoreans were sworn to secrecy, we believe that they combined the cultic rites of a mystery religion with the pursuit of truth through understanding mathematical forms, musical harmonies, and the motions of the planets. This pursuit of religious meaning and rational truth at the same time provided an important cornerstone for the development of Western culture. It also aids our understanding of the premium the Greeks put on geometry and harmonic proportion in architecture. Seen in this light, the Parthenon, constructed during the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> on the Athenian Acropolis, demonstrates how they employed rationality to serve an older myth-based religion that had been transformed to allegorize the virtues of the autochthonous, or indigenous, deity, Athena, the namesake city's patron goddess.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi> of <name type="pname">Plato</name> (c. 428&#x2013;347 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) and the <hi rend="italic">Physics</hi> of <name type="pname">Aristotle</name> (384&#x2013;322 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) offer further understanding of how place was conceptualized in antiquity. They provide a philosophical substructure for the shaping of landscape space and the siting of architectural monuments within it. In the dialogue of the <hi rend="italic">Timaens</hi>, <name type="pname">Plato</name> outlines a cosmology in which a nonspecific force called the Demiurge&#x2014;an invisible and all-encompassing God&#x2014;replaces the anthropomorphic deities who create cosmos out of chaos in the mythologies of pre-historic <name type="place">Greece</name> and the Ancient Near East. For material things to exist within the Platonic cosmos, there must be regions of occupancy&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">chora</hi>&#x2014;within the Receptacle, the fertile primary ground for world-being, in which particular places&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">topoi</hi>&#x2014;are located. According to <name type="pname">Plato</name>, the <name type="pname">Demiurge</name>'s task is the fitting of forms, which are based upon abstract, geometrically determined, ideal Forms, into <hi rend="italic">topos</hi>&#x2014;in other words, the location of pattern-based matter <hi rend="italic">in place</hi> within regional space, or <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>.</p><p><name type="pname">Plato</name>'s pupil <name type="pname">Aristotle</name> discarded the concept of objects derived from pre-existing, geometrically based Forms. He sought instead to abstract idealized prototypical Forms from the manifestations of forms in nature. Further, he ignored <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>, regional space, in his <hi rend="italic">Physics</hi>, claiming that "place is coincident with the thing, for boundaries are coincident with the bounded" (Book IV, 30). For <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, things may move from place to place, and place is continually being filled with things, but <hi rend="italic">topos</hi> as the container of elemental form needs no regional context; place <hi rend="italic">is</hi>. For <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, the universe is finite, spherically bounded, and Earth-centered; the cosmos has been so ordered by a Prime Mover, or God conceived as <hi rend="italic">Nous</hi>, pure mind. <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>'s approach is empirical; observation and sensory perception are its basis. But Aristotelian thought, which, though elaborated by later philosophers, remained the primary Western intellectual framework until the sixteenth century, is not open-ended, inasmuch as it presupposes that sensory perceptions and observations can order knowledge within a comprehensive system.</p><p>While philosophical thought does not inevitably dictate landscape design form, we have already seen that the latter does express prevailing ideology, or cultural consensus. Forms may anticipate or follow ideas, but they almost always reflect the value systems that characterize a given society during the course of its existence. It is therefore possible to discern within the landscapes of classical antiquity as well as throughout the rest of landscape design history a substructure of philosophical thought. Myth still plays a role in the Greek landscape, which is everywhere touched by Homeric themes, but, if we choose also to read Greek landscapes as manifestations of the mathematically oriented and spatially descriptive cosmological view found in <name type="pname">Plato</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Timaeus</hi>, philosophy's importance as an intellectual force in shaping them is also apparent.</p><p><name type="pname">Plato</name>'s cosmology has a physical counterpart in the ordering of urban landscape space. This is evident from the earliest development of the Greek city-state beginning in the eighth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> when the center and the outlying environs were conceived as the complementary components of <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>, or regional space.<ref target="#CH2-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref> On the other hand, <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, who tutored <name type="pname">Alexander the Great</name>, had a profound influence upon subsequent Western intellectual development as it was fostered within the crucible of Hellenism. His cosmic view of the inseparable nature of form and <hi rend="italic">topos</hi> was manifested in rationally ordered, enclosed spaces. From late antiquity until the sixteenth century, <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>'s belief in the unity of form and <hi rend="italic">topos</hi>&#x2014;of place as spatial containment&#x2014;prevailed alongside his concept of knowledge as a comprehensive, circumscribed system. To chart the shift from an approach that can be described as the weaving of a loose fabric of regional landscape to Aristotelian place-making is to understand an important aspect of the difference between <name type="place">Greece</name> and <name type="place">Rome</name>.<ref target="#CH2-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref> In the former, temples were sited in nature and worshipers came to them in procession. In the latter, the relationship of architectural forms to nature was of less importance than readily replicated spatial arrangements that symbolically aggrandized rulers of the imperial state.</p><p>As we shall see, the Greek city, or <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, is bipolar. Important civic temples and monuments were located at or near a central gathering place, the <hi rend="italic">agora</hi>,_where political, judicial, and market activities occurred, and religious sanctuaries were located outside the town within the <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>, the regional domain of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>. Where Greeks established colonial cities, imposing their institutions on pre-existing populations, exurban sanctuaries served the purpose of fostering political and social cohesion among disparate peoples. Although a loose girdle of fortified walls protected the Greek city, it had a strong sense of its relationship to its <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>. Enclosed, but not self-contained, the city sent out tentacles in several directions: to the sea as well as to the valley, plain, and hills, where were situated the <hi rend="italic">demes</hi>, the politically affiliated regional villages or towns within the territorial framework of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>. Here in the agrarian countryside were the sanctuaries of the cults that received the members of both the city and villages on the festival occasions. Devotees came in procession to the sacrificial altars where bonds between the civic core and the life-sustaining hinterland were implicitly renewed. In this fashion, the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>_claimed and made manifest its occupation of an entire region of which the fortified city with its civic deities was simply one pole, while the outlying territory of the <hi rend="italic">chora</hi> was the other. Further uniting the urban and the natural landscape were the nature shrines&#x2014;sacred woods, springs, and mountain caves&#x2014;where a <hi rend="italic">daemon</hi>, or genius of the place, drew supplicants.</p><p>By contrast, <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>'s philosophical notion of the particular emplacement of things within a specific locale (<hi rend="italic">topos</hi>) that is<pb n="60"/><pb n="60" type="orig"/>strictly bounded, with exact limits, outlines, and surface planes, finds cultural expression in landscape design terms in the progressive enclosure and definition of urban space throughout the Hellenistic and Roman periods. The result was a multiplication of similarly planned, symmetrically arranged, inward-focused spaces, and the replication of the city itself as such a space through colonization. The Greek urban-exurban continuum, with loosely girdled cities connected to sanctuaries in nature by pilgrimage routes, was gradually abandoned in favor of precisely walled, institutionally self-contained urban centers, which were connected not to sacred sites in nature, but to one another and to the all-important capital of the empire, <name type="place">Rome</name>, by a far-flung network of roads.</p><p><name type="pname">Aristotle</name>'s concept of physics, as well as his notion that all knowledge can be organized within an ultimately finite and therefore self-contained system, is an intellectual approach well suited to imperial objectives in which there is a strong penchant for order and administration. Inevitably, a good deal of the old awe and reverence for landscape forms bequeathed by earlier peoples became less compelling as urbanization and the political machinery for its maintenance assumed paramount value during the course of the empire. Roman urban plans, public spaces, and peristyle gardens evolved from models built in the Hellenistic period, dating roughly from the time of <name type="pname">Alexander</name> the Great (ruled 336&#x2013;323 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) to the accession of the emperor <name type="pname">Augustus</name> in 27 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> At these various scales, Roman landscape design expressed a sophisticated civilization's material wealth, imperial power, apparatus of systematic administration, and sensual enjoyment of plants, water, and openair living.</p><p>New colonial towns, with their paved, sidewalk-bordered streets, demonstrated formulaic axial planning and advanced concepts of engineering. Rectangular and walled, these towns were directed inward toward a center: a forum sited at the intersection of the two principal crossroads. The forum itself was enclosed by a peristyle, a colonnaded, roofed walkway. Unlike the <hi rend="italic">agora</hi> of Greek cities, the forum was not penetrated by through traffic. Roman houses, like their Hellenistic predecessors, had featureless street facades. Their rooms were organized around and faced on an atrium, or central court, which was partly open to the sky. Some affluent Romans also had peristyle gardens, that is, rear gardens surrounded by porticoes.</p><p>To emphasize the interiority of Roman planning is not to say that Romans were indifferent to landscape features or insensitive to natural beauty. Their appreciation of natural scenery can be seen in the siting of buildings, particularly the villas that multiplied as wealth increased in the imperial age, and in the wealth of images drawn from nature that are found in the fresco paintings that decorated Roman walls. For members of the leisure class, the concept of a view became what we think of when we use the term today: an agreeable prospect of local scenery. Superstitions persisted from the centuries when there was less technological skill available for shaping nature to serve human ends, but in this highly urbanized and secularized society, the profoundly felt spiritual link with nature of earlier cultures had been broken. The <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi>, a grotto designed to appear as the abode of nymphs, became the architectural substitute for the goddess-inhabited cave of old.</p><p>Everywhere throughout the Roman empire, the surveyor's line and rod superimposed a <hi rend="italic">human</hi> order upon nature. One has only to think of their hydraulic engineering and aqueduct construction to realize the degree to which the Romans exercised unprecedented control over nature, enhanced the life of cities, and made possible the creation of the ornamental garden.</p><p>Worldly power and earthly pleasure&#x2014;these are the twin messages encoded in Roman town planning and landscape design. But civilization has its price: longing for an imagined lost golden age of innocence in which the bond with nature is not yet broken. The distance between the eighth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> of <name type="pname">Homer</name> and the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> of Virgil is the distance between a view of nature as an epic stage for the drama of gods and humans enacting their mutual fate and a view of nature as the idyllic counterpoint to civilization, the province of pastoral poetry. Not surprisingly, in this period, wealthy people developed an urbane appreciation of rural life. The villa, with its gardens and fountains, is an expression of that taste and a model for subsequent developments in landscape design.</p><p>The villa of the Roman Empire provides evidence of a new cultural role for landscape: the thematic one. Wealth and cosmopolitan urbanity bred the desire to create associational landscapes, places where allusion was made through place-names, architectural replication, and sculptural dramatization to other esteemed landscapes and landmarks or scenes from myth and literature. Thus, the grounds of opulent villas, notably <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s at <name type="place">Tivoli</name> outside <name type="place">Rome</name>, became in effect theaters of the imagination. Although designed as a private retreat for the refined leisure of an emperor rather than as a commercial venture appealing to a mass audience, <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa can be compared to a contemporary theme park in this regard. In Roman times, as imagination began to operate in shaping programs of landscape design, the garden took on the character of an allegorical space. And, as we shall see, it eventually became a metaphor for both the Christian and Islamic visions of paradise, as the philosophy and practices of the antique world were replaced by different beliefs about the nature of creation and the organization of human life.</p><p>In this chapter, then, our task is to trace a course that takes us from a human association with the landscape that assigned divinity to certain sites in nature and placed built structures in relationship to these spirit-inhabited places, to one that created forms that in themselves confidently articulated human aspirations and power within a rapidly urbanizing world. We are thus traversing an important trajectory in the development of Western attitudes. It is one in which an ideology of subservience to nature begins to give way to one of dominance over nature. In this process, the magic once perceived in nature is replaced by confidence in human action. The Greek experience is remarkable for the development of many of the philosophical, social, and political ideas that still resonate within the cultures of contemporary societies as well as a vocabulary of building forms that has been re-employed throughout Western history. For us here, it is remarkable especially for the attitudinal equilibrium it achieved between religious awe in the face of the universe and proud trust in the powers of reason, a tension beautifully expressed in terms of landscape design.</p><div type="section"><pb n="61"/><pb n="61" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Gods and Humans: The New Contract with Nature</hi></hi></head><p><name type="pname">Homer</name>'s great epic poems, the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, composed probably in the eighth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, reveal to us a confident civilization of youthful promise, at a time when it was fashioning for itself a glorious narrative of its history as a diverse but culturally united people. Valor in war, accomplished horsemanship, and the consoling power of a well-developed sense of beauty are intrinsic to this worldview. The worship of trees and aniconic stones&#x2014;nonrepresentational, nonsymbolical forms&#x2014;had been superseded by the personification of divinity. Although the powers and personalities of the gods and goddesses were still in the process of formation, it is clear that they populated the collective imagination not as representatives of an ethical system or figures commanding worshipful love, but rather as projections of the human psyche and personifications of various aspects of human life. As such, they acted as the idealized and worthy guardians of human society and served as socializing forces, bonding disparate peoples into larger territorial groups through common worship.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Greek Myth, Religion, and Culture</hi></hi></head><p>In fashioning their myths, the Greeks took their native inheritance, Minoan and Mycenaean religions&#x2014;which are believed to have been centered upon worship of a Great Goddess or Earth Mother&#x2014;and added to them divinities derived from <name type="place">Asia Minor</name>. Thus, Athena, the majestic patron of the arts and the goddess of reason and justice, probably traced her origin to the Earth Mother in Minoan and Mycenaean cultures. However, <name type="pname">Apollo</name>, the god of light, order, and inspiration, was perhaps the descendant of a god worshiped in the region formerly called Anatolia, the large peninsula now occupied principally by <name type="place">Turkey</name>. These gods can be seen as archetypes of emerging aspects of civilization at a period when primal beliefs were gradually being replaced by a more rational, ethical, and scientific outlook. Greek religion was nevertheless still firmly embedded in the matrix of nature. On the Athenian Acropolis, a shrine for the worship of the rustic god Pan is evidence of the duality implicit in Greek religion, which acknowledged the wild, irrational impulses associated with human sexuality alongside the civilized values personified by Athena.</p><p>There were numerous holidays in which procession, worshipful slaughter, and feasting helped forge the bonds of community and civic pride among all the inhabitants of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> and sometimes between neighboring city-states (<hi rend="italic">poleis</hi>), while placating the divinities that were believed to ensure cosmic order. With the notable exception of <name type="place">Athens</name>, where the reverse was true in the case of its principal festival, the Panathenaia, these processions took the people from the city into the exurban landscape, where many of the important religious sanctuaries were located, thereby affirming the territorial dominance of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> over its surrounding agrarian countryside. These ritual festivals held in nature also served as initiatory rites for adolescents as they became participants in civic life. In ancient Sparta, where the city-state played an especially strong role in the education of children and adolescents, the festivals were connected with the worship of Artemis Orthia.</p><p>The increasing power of the aristocracy spurred the creation of the arts and the organization of athletic competitions. The festivals were characterized by communal procession and sacrifice performed before the sanctuaries of the gods, as well as by dancing and athletic and dramatic competition performed in the gods' honor. <name type="pname">Dionysus</name> became the patron deity of the theatrical arts, and when the plays of <name type="pname">Aeschylus</name>, <name type="pname">Sophocles</name>, and <name type="pname">Euripides</name> were performed, it was at the <name type="pname">Great Dionysia</name>, the important dramatic festival competition held every four years at <name type="place">Athens</name>. At <name type="place">Olympia</name>, the Panhellenic (all-Greek) festival of games sacred to <name type="pname">Zeus</name> was begun in 776 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and continued at fouryear intervals for the next thousand years. <name type="pname">Zeus</name> also presided over the Nemean Games, while Apollo was honored in the athletic festival held at <name type="place">Delphi</name> and <name type="place">Poseidon</name> in the contests that took place at the <name type="place">Isthmus of Corinth</name>. Truces among warring city-states were maintained to allow the contestants and spectators to arrive safely at these Panhellenic celebrations.</p><p>People also made pilgrimages to important shrines, particularly the one at <name type="place">Delphi</name>, to find spiritual guidance. The desire to chart a safe course, whether through the perils of statecraft or one's own lifetime, made oracular consultation a popular religious exercise in a society that saw human activity as drama directed from on high, the plot of which could be discerned by the spirit forces of the earth.</p><p>The Greek political system, with its isolated citystates, accounted for the many festivals of various kinds held throughout the mainland and the Peloponnese, the large peninsula below the <name type="place">Gulf of Corinth</name> that consitutes the southern part of <name type="place">Greece</name>. Altars studded both the rural and urban landscapes, as animal sacrifice, an essential and integral part of every festival including those featuring athletic games, was necessarily performed out-of-doors. Ritual sacrifice was only one manifestation of the interrelationship of the human, animal, and divine in ancient <name type="place">Greece</name>. There was considerable overlap between urban and agrarian spheres, and objects in nature were everywhere<pb n="62"/><pb n="62" type="orig"/>charged with magical meaning. By roadsides, sacred stones glistened with oil where passersby offered libations. Caves and springs, often the sites of votive shrines, served as places of human purification. Frequently sanctuaries encompassed sacred springs, and often there were sacred groves nearby as well. Certain trees became identified with particular divinities: the olive tree was sacred to Athena, and a revered specimen grew on the Acropolis; at <name type="place">Samos</name>, a willow's branches hung over Hera's sanctuary; on Delos, a palm tree commemorated a similar tree upon which Leto had leaned when giving birth to Artemis and Apollo; at Dodona, the oracle imparted wisdom through the rustling branches of an oak; at <name type="place">Didyma</name>, <name type="place">Daphni</name>, and <name type="place">Delphi</name> grew the laurel tree sacred to Apollo (fig. 2.1).</p><figure xml:id="fig-44"><graphic url="CH2_002.jpg"/><figDesc>2.1. The Athenian Acropolis with the olive tree planted to commemorate the presence in antiquity of Athena's sacred tree. It stands in the courtyard of the Erechtheion where it is believed that a charred olive tree managed to sprout leaves, bringing hope of renewal and rebirth of the Athenian <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> after the Persians had burned and razed the buildings of the Acropolis in 480 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> The Erechtheion housed a <hi rend="italic">xoanon</hi>, the ancient cult statue of Athena. The caryatids that form the columns of its south porch overlook the fire-scarred foundation stones of the Old Temple of Athena. Although the Acropolis was rebuilt later in the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> by <name type="pname">Pericles</name>, and the Parthenon became the majestic replacement of the destroyed temple, its site was always considered by Athenians to be hallowed ground.</figDesc></figure><p>The columned temples that began to appear from the eighth century onward throughout <name type="place">Greece</name> were not houses of worship. Instead, they were conspicuous and worthy "residences" of large-scale sculptural representations of gods or goddesses associated with the sacred sites where they were built. These cult figures were occasionally carried in procession, but normally they remained within an interior chamber, or <hi rend="italic">cella</hi>, facing east toward the altar, which was set up within the sacred temple precinct in front of them.</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi>, a sacred landscape marked off by stones or encircled by a wall, might contain one or more temples. From a religious perspective, the motive for establishing a <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi> was the epiphany of a god in a particular spot. It was the sense of the indwelling spirit of the god&#x2014;the god or goddess manifesting himself or herself in a certain place&#x2014;that made that site holy. From a social and political perspective, the sacral landscape provided a means of asserting territorial dominance by a particular <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, which is why the destruction of important exurban sanctuaries in wartime was tantamount to destroying a city itself.</p><p>The sanctification of a particular spot was subject to various political considerations. At some sites, votaries of existing gods were reluctant to admit competition from a new deity. On the other hand, there were economic benefits to the communities where major deities were given residence, for pilgrims brought fees and a brisk production and sale of votive objects. A series of wars was actually fought to gain control of the Panhellenic sanctuary of <name type="place">Delphi</name>.</p><p>Topography and a tendency for siting within a well-chosen frame of the spirit-charged natural world dictated the location of temples and altars. Axiality for its own sake did not govern the planning of pre-Hellenistic Greek temple precincts. Symmetrically laid-out terraces, colonnades, stairways, and altars were devices of the Hellenistic era; prior to the second third of the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, in the Archaic and Classical periods, the approach was less studied, and such axial relationships as existed were implied lines linking temples with particular distant mountains because of their associations of sanctity. The result was often a landscape "design" that we experience as dramatic and picturesque. These impressions, however, are informed by a modern sensibility. The Greeks did not see their temple precincts as we do&#x2014;as an artistic arrangement of bleached ruins haunted by vanished time, with mountains and sea completing the romantic<pb n="63"/><pb n="63" type="orig"/>scene. In their ascendant centuries, the temples were brightly painted, and pilgrimages to them were not those of tourists, but of religious supplicants. Nature and divinity were inextricably fused; landscape was experienced religiously rather than aesthetically.</p><p>The visible echoes of previous ceremony and custom only deepened the sanctity and fame of certain sacred sites. Bloodstains on the altar, oilanointed stones, accumulations of ash, bone, horns, and skulls&#x2014;these signs of others' piety provided the weight of tradition. Votive offerings (the source of lively local industry), valuables of all kinds, including but not limited to the paraphernalia of sacrifice (vessels, axes, roasting spits, and especially, tripod cauldrons of metal) were contributed to the sanctuaries. Grateful victors donated shields and weapons of war. The victorious erected monuments and inscribed tablets proclaiming acts of glory. Various <hi rend="italic">poleis</hi>_built treasuries in the form of miniature temples, notably at <name type="place">Olympia</name> and <name type="place">Delphi</name>, to house valuable offerings and as further gifts to the presiding gods. <hi rend="italic">Stoas</hi>, long colonnades, roofed and with walls and often a series of rooms on the back side, provided shelter from the sun and an opportunity for the placement of more sanctified objects. Wealthy individuals contributed to the construction of stadiums and the many monuments that adorned the site. In this manner, important sanctuaries became crowded with a host of structures, numerous memorial gifts, and votive offerings. Nowhere was this more evident than at <name type="place">Delphi</name>.</p><figure xml:id="fig-45"><graphic url="CH2_003.jpg"/><figDesc>2.2. Reconstructed Plan of Sanctuary of Apollo, <name type="place">Delphi</name>, c. 400 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc><p><hi rend="bold">A</hi> Treasury of the Athenians</p><p><hi rend="bold">B</hi> Rock of the Sibyl</p><p><hi rend="bold">C</hi> Sphinx of the Naxians</p><p><hi rend="bold">D</hi> Temple of Apollo</p><p><hi rend="bold">E</hi> Theater</p></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="place">Delphi</name></hi></hi></head><p>The most dramatic synthesis of site and sanctuary is to be found at <name type="place">Delphi</name>, the spiritual center sacred to all Greeks and a place where rivalries among <hi rend="italic">poleis</hi> were superseded by bonds of Panhellenic identity (fig. 2.2). Some of the architectural forms found here have served as frequently imitated prototypes throughout the history of landscape design. The circular <hi rend="italic">tholos</hi> in the sanctuary of Athena Pronaia at <name type="place">Delphi</name> in the site called Marmaria (the Marbles) along the pilgrimage route to Apollo's sanctuary, is the model for innumerable later garden temples (fig. 2.3). The various treasuries within<pb n="64"/><pb n="64" type="orig"/>the <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi> of Apollo found infinite replication in mausoleums of later times (fig. 2.5). <name type="place">Delphi</name>'s influence, along with that of other important sanctuaries, is visible in our own stadiums and outdoor summer festival theaters.</p><figure xml:id="fig-46"><graphic url="CH2_004.jpg"/><figDesc>2.3. Tholos, Sanctuary of <name type="place">Athena Pronaia</name>, <name type="place">Delphi</name>, perched on a ridge at Marmaria along the approach to Apollo's sanctuary. 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-47"><graphic url="CH2_005.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.4. Rock of the Sibyl and Temple of Apollo, <name type="place">Delphi</name>. 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Pilgrimage to <name type="place">Delphi</name> was made both for the purpose of consulting the Delphic oracle on affairs of state and in order to participate in the sacred games. It was a journey of men rather than women, who lacked an official role in government and did not generally take part in athletic contests. After passing the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> <hi rend="italic">tholos</hi> and the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Temple of Athena Pronaia, marking the sanctuary of the goddess at <name type="place">Delphi</name>, one stopped at the Kastalian Spring, a long-established site of cult worship marking the place known as Pytho because here Apollo killed "the bloated, great she-monster wont to do great mischief to men upon earth," thereby becoming Pythian Apollo according to the Homeric hymn.<ref target="#CH2-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref> It was believed that here Apollo had planted a branch cut from his sacred laurel tree in the Vale of Tempe, and because he had assumed the shape of a dolphin in order to steer the ship of the men from <name type="place">Crete</name> whom he had commandeered as keepers of his temple, he enjoined them to pray to him also as Apollo Delphinius. Pilgrims to his Delphinius altar and participants en route to the Pythian Games, as the Panhellenic athletic contests held in Apollo's honor at <name type="place">Delphi</name> were called, purified themselves with a ritual bathing of their hair in the water of the spring.</p><p>Upon entering the <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi> of the Pythian Sanctuary of Apollo, which is perched on a flank of <name type="place">Mount Parnassus</name> beneath the sacred Korycian Cave and above a steep drop to the valley where the Pleistos River snakes to the sea, they embarked upon the Sacred Way, a switchback path leading to the Temple of Apollo (fig. 2.4). This circuitous approach made access to the temple indirect, and intensified the dynamic relationship of the visitor to it and its dramatic surrounding landscape. Above the temple to the god loom the twin peaks of the Phaedriades, the Brilliant Ones. Though unplanned, this long-established approach route operated as an organizing force in the placement of the many treasuries and<pb n="65"/><pb n="65" type="orig"/>monuments scattered about the site. The reservation of certain portions of the site for particular rituals also helped to create some sense of discipline within the array of monuments and structures.</p><p>At a point where the Sacred Way reversed its course and headed due north, it passed the Rock of the Sibyl. This was believed to be the precise spot where the female voice of Ge, or Gaia, the earth goddess, who had been worshiped here long before Apollo, originally offered oracular wisdom. Behind this boulder once stood the Archaic Sphinx of the Naxians: a crouched lion with eagle's wings and the visage of a woman held aloft on a tall Ionic column. With serene and enigmatic authority, it asserted the ancient rights of female prophecy within Apollo's sanctuary. Above the sphinx stood the peripteral colonnade of the temple, and soaring above these, hornlike, were the twin peaks of the Phaedriades. Upon the temple terrace, engraved marble <hi rend="italic">stelai</hi> (of which one remains) and a fourth-century, 50-foot tall statue of Apollo gave majestic welcome to the pilgrim. Directly in front of the temple stood the Great Altar of Apollo, made of dark marble from the island of Chios, with white marble at its base and top.</p><p>In addition to a central hall, or <hi rend="italic">naos</hi>, the Temple of Apollo contained an inner chamber, called the <hi rend="italic">adyton</hi>, entered from above by steps. Beneath a stone canopy within the <hi rend="italic">adyton</hi> was a round stone covered with fillets woven into a net. This was <hi rend="italic">omphalos</hi>, the "navel" of the world and the "grave" of Dionysus, who was honored by an important biennial Delphic festival and was thus entitled to share with Apollo occupancy of the temple's most sacred area. A large tripod with a cauldron-shaped seat was placed next to the <hi rend="italic">omphalos</hi>. Within the belly of this tripod-cauldron priests stored sacred objects. Upon it sat the Pythia, priestess of Apollo, freshly bathed in the Kastalian Spring, when it was time to utter prophecy. Beside her grew a sacred laurel tree.</p><p>Within the <hi rend="italic">hestia</hi>, or sacred hearth, burned laurel leaves and barley. The fumes from these enhanced the mystical atmosphere of the <hi rend="italic">adyton</hi> and presumably aided the prophetess in achieving a trancelike state known as <hi rend="italic">enthousiamos</hi>, in which the spirit of the god entered into her mind and mouth. Her speech, which was often unintelligible, was "translated" into hexameter verse by priests standing nearby. Thus, this temple, which was holy to all Greeks, was the place where art joined with the old mystical powers of the earth, and Apollonian light hised with the dark impulses of Dionysian spirit.</p><p>Assisting in this process at <name type="place">Delphi</name> was the theater, or rather a succession of theaters, the latest one, which seats five thousand people, dating from the time of imperial <name type="place">Rome</name> (fig. 2.6). Behind a horseshoe-shaped orchestra, 60 feet in diameter, thirty-five rows of seats, broken at the twenty-eighth row by a <hi rend="italic">diazoma</hi>, or inside circular aisle, are set within the contours of the steep hillside. Here choristers sang hymns to Apollo, and playwrights and musicians competed for honor during various festivals, including the Pythian Games.</p><p>After 450 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, a stadium occupied a site farther up the hillside above the sanctuary and theater. Musical contests and, later, games were held there. During Roman imperial times, an Athenian philanthropist gave the stadium its monumental entrance and stone seating for seven thousand spectators.</p><figure xml:id="fig-48"><graphic url="CH2_006.jpg"/><figDesc>2.5. Treasury of the Athenians, <name type="place">Delphi</name>. After 490 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, built following the Battle of Marathon</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-49"><graphic url="CH2_007.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.6. Theater, <name type="place">Delphi</name>. 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><pb n="66"/><pb n="66" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-50"><graphic url="CH2_008.jpg"/><figDesc>2.7. Theater, Epidaurus. c. 320&#x2013;30 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Epidaurus</hi></hi></head><p>Among the most important festival centers of ancient <name type="place">Greece</name> is the sanctuary of Asclepius at Epidaurus, an ancient sanatorium where patients' dreams played a role in their diagnosis and where a special open-air sleeping area served as a therapeutic facility. According to the Greek lyric poet <name type="pname">Pindar</name>, <name type="pname">Asclepius</name>, the son of <name type="pname">Apollo</name> and his mortal lover, <name type="pname">Coronis</name>, was raised by the centaur <name type="pname">Chiron</name>, who taught him the healing arts. While dedicated to Apollonian harmony of mind, body, and spirit, Asclepius was linked to the remote Greek past, and he therefore shares with the Cretan goddess <name type="pname">Potnia</name> the symbol of the snake. It is for this reason that the modern physician's emblem, bequeathed to us from ancient <name type="place">Greece</name>, is a <hi rend="italic">caduceus</hi>, a staff intertwined with snakes.</p><p>To the powerful natural serenity of the site at Epidaurus, cradled in undulating hills, was added the harmony of architectural geometry. <name type="pname">Polycleitus</name> the Younger designed the theater there in the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e</hi>; it was enlarged in the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> (fig. 2.7). The perfect circle of the orchestra is thought to be an outgrowth of the <hi rend="italic">halos</hi>, the circular threshing floor upon which the first ritual dances and dramas of ancient <name type="place">Greece</name> were performed. The ratio of its lower fan of thirty-four rows to its upper twenty-one (34:21), is 1.618, or that of the Golden Section.<ref target="#CH2-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref> The ratio of fifty-five total rows to its original thirty-four (55:34) is also close to 1.618. Further evidence of the use of the Golden Section as the underlying design principle by <name type="pname">Polycleitus</name> and his followers: the sum of the first ten numerical digits added together is fifty-five; the sum of the first six digits is twenty-one; and the sum of digits seven through ten is thirty-four. Even those unaware of Greek mathematics, however, feel intuitively the beauty derived from the combined power of site and geometry, of mountainous majesty and mathematical beauty.</p><p>In the process of enlarging both its form and its meaning, the Greek <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> had incorporated and absorbed its ancient acropolis, the fortified citadel that had once been the home of both the people and their gods. Though, with the important exception of <name type="place">Athens</name>, the residential and civic center was now separated from the outlying sanctuaries set in nature, both together constituted the regional space defined as <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>. Cityscape, or the urbanized landscape, is an important part of our continuing story, and the Greek contribution to landscape design was certainly not confined to pilgrimage centers remote from the everyday haunts of humanity. Because the philosophical notion of <hi rend="italic">chora</hi> was one in which the festival center in nature was perceived as one pole of a spatial continuum and the urban center the other&#x2014;both together constituting the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, or city-state, a regional polity&#x2014;we must now look more closely at the civic component. Inevitably the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> as a governmental institution gave rise to new ideas about urban layout and new urban institutions, enriching the concept of city with customs and structures that reflected an independent, collective society. And, as is common knowledge, the Greek political concept of self-governance and the planning and architectural forms that expressed it have been vastly influential in the West throughout history.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb n="67"/><pb n="67" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">II. Polis and Acropolis: City and Temple in the Greek Landscape</hi></hi></head><p>The Greek <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> was a crucible for a new social order. Democracy, or government by the people, was first conceived in ancient <name type="place">Greece</name>. Although the definition of citizenship was circumscribed and limited to property-owning males, the equality of this political system nevertheless carried with it respect for the individual and an ideal of justice according to stable, published laws. Democracy also embodied the notion of individual rights as well as that of individual responsibility for the collective good. More than simply the expression of a political system, the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> was first and foremost a concept of community. Its actual form of governance&#x2014;monarchy, oligarchy, or democracy&#x2014;was not its distinguishing characteristic so much as the fact that power was exercised responsibly on behalf of the community.</p><p>In the Greek <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, the notion of divine kingship was untenable; the <hi rend="italic">basileus</hi>, or ruler, governed not as a god in the manner of an Egyptian pharaoh, but in partnership with the gods. He was, according to <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, responsible for the conduct of religious rites and traditional sacrifices, athletic contests such as torch races, public lawsuits dealing with impiety, and private ones when the charge was an important crime such as homicide. In <name type="place">Athens</name>, the title of <hi rend="italic">archon basileus</hi> was not hereditary; the office depended upon election by the citizenry and service was for a prescribed annual term. Monuments of grandeur celebrating divine kingship such as are found in the Ancient Near East were therefore completely alien to Greek culture. Thus, it was the much-praised Greek genius for distributing and limiting power through a workable constitution, together with the democratization of education and culture within the relatively small circle of those who met the criteria for citizenship, that gave the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> its highest meaning and mature form. To understand that urban form and the institutions produced by this radical social change, a brief discussion of Greek philosophy and Greek polity as developed in <name type="place">Athens</name>, the most celebrated Greek city-state, is in order.</p><p>The Athenian Acropolis was rebuilt by <name type="pname">Pericles</name> in the middle of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, following a period in which its buildings lay in ruins after being burned in 480 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> by troops under the <name type="pname">Persian king Xerxes</name>. Its reconstruction was more than a manifestation of Athenian hegemony and Greek Classical grandeur. The monuments of the Acropolis, particularly the Parthenon, embodied a new philosophical understanding of the world. Although this building celebrated the great goddess Athena, who presided with serene dignity over the affairs of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, another, more abstract idea of deity was here given architectural expression. Confidence in human reason was superseding blind oracular wisdom. Further, the manipulation of human affairs by the Homeric pantheon according to the particular dispositions of the various gods was now considered by many rational Greeks to be naive. The rule of Necessity (<hi rend="italic">ananke</hi>) alone did not provide an adequate philosophical or spiritual foundation for those who believed that intelligence&#x2014;reason itself&#x2014;was a godlike human gift.</p><p>The Greeks' philosophical quest for a rational understanding of an underlying harmony in nature is epitomized in the spirit of empyrean intellect that infuses the stones of the Parthenon with timeless beauty. It also informs the political concept of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>&#x2014;the rational city-state&#x2014;and the public spaces created for secular public life. Physically, according to <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> should consist of a population and territory large enough to suffice for the purposes of life, but not so large that the settled area could not be taken in in a single view. It should be defensible&#x2014;"difficult of access to the enemy, and easy of egress to the inhabitants"&#x2014;well situated with regard to the sea and the land, and "in size and extent it should be such as may enable the inhabitants to live at once temperately and liberally in the enjoyment of leisure."<ref target="#CH2-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref> It should have a natural abundance of springs and fountains in the town or, lacking these, a system of reservoirs to furnish ample pure drinking water. Straight streets "after the modern fashion which <name type="pname">Hippodamus</name> [fifth-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Greek city planner] introduced" should be laid out for the sake of beauty, but districts of these should be combined with quarters in which old-fashioned tortuous ways provided security because assailants would have difficulty in getting in and would also find themselves baffled in trying to get out. Further, cities should have walls as a precaution against siege, and "care should be taken to make them ornamental, as well as useful for warlike purposes, and adapted to resist modern inventions" with guardhouses and towers at suitable intervals.<ref target="#CH2-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref> In addition to the temples in the surrounding countryside where ritual participants went in procession on feast days, there should be temples and public dining halls for priests and magistrates in the upper "freemen's agora," a place of leisure in contrast to the lower "traders' agora."</p><p>The basic unit of the Greek <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> was the <hi rend="italic">deme</hi>, the regional village or town within the orbit of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Synoecism</hi>, or the amalgamation of several<pb n="68"/><pb n="68" type="orig"/><hi rend="italic">poleis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">demes</hi> into a political unit under the authority of a single <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> gave certain cities broad regional authority. <name type="place">Athens</name> thus subsumed all of the <hi rend="italic">demes</hi> of Attica, and all property-owning males in Attica were considered Athenians. While the intensely competitive Hellenic spirit was responsible for constant rivalry and warfare among <hi rend="italic">poleis</hi>, the security bred of <hi rend="italic">synoecism</hi> made possible urban expansion beyond the high-walled citadels of Mycenaean times.</p><p>As the historian <name type="pname">Fran&#x00E7;ois de Polignac</name> suggests, <hi rend="italic">synoecism</hi> was facilitated by the religious cults that held festivals at sanctuaries set apart from the city.<ref target="#CH2-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref> Thus, in territory where the character of the god or goddess was not forcefully identified with the enfranchised elite of free, property-owning males within a particular <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, women, foreigners, local populations, and members of neighboring <hi rend="italic">poleis</hi> participated in forms of pan-Greek culture that produced a commonality. Although there were festivals at nearby <name type="place">Eleusis</name> and at <name type="place">Sounion</name>, the Attic cape where <name type="place">Poseidon</name> was worshiped, <name type="place">Athens</name> was unique in focusing its spiritual life predominantly within its walls. This practice also helps explain why <name type="place">Athens</name> effectively placed all its bets on its maritime empire, importing grain as tribute, rather than asserting firm control over its immediate agricultural hinterland. Other <hi rend="italic">poleis</hi> also had civic deities, including Athena, who protected the city and resided in sancturaries in the agora or upon an acropolis. But the exurban sanctuaries connected by processional routes to these cities, such as the Artemision of Ephesus or the Heraion of Argos, were of even greater significance to their inhabitants because they encompassed the agrarian sphere that was vital to the city's well-being (fig. 2.8).</p><figure xml:id="fig-51"><graphic url="CH2_009.jpg"/><figDesc>2.8. Argive Heraion, the remains of the Archaic and Classical sanctuary of Hera, the tutelary goddess of the Argolid. c. 420&#x2014;410 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>A new urban nucleus, the agora, appeared as trade expanded and cities grew in population and size at the end of the Dark Age (c. 1100&#x2014;c. 900 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) that ensued after the collapse of Mycenaean civilization. This occurred as they began to spread beyond the zone of their original formation upon an acropolis, recentering themselves on the adjacent lower elevations. Eventually, as the evolving institutions of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> were given physical expression, those of law, justice, and civic ritual were positioned around the agora, which continued to assume importance as a public space. Market and trading functions clustered there. Further, it served as a communal meeting place where assemblies of various kinds could occur. Greek cities in general, but <name type="place">Athens</name> especially, thus came to have two nuclei: the acropolis, the zone of religion and communal tradition, and the agora, the place of government, commerce, and community life. Other functions such as artisans' shops and housing were fitted in between and around these two important centers.</p><p>At <name type="place">Athens</name>, as the residential population abandoned the Acropolis and spread out on the lower ground, temples were located in the vicinity of the Agora as well as in other places deemed appropriate to honor a god. As this occurred, the Acropolis became almost exclusively a religious precinct. The home of patron goddess Athena, whose temple, the Parthenon, was a lofty landmark visible from afar, the Acropolis profoundly embodied the city's commingled spiritual values and civic pride. The Propylon, the gateway separating the sacred space from the rest of the city, led through the entry building complex known as the Propylaia, which includes the beautiful small Temple of Athena Nike. Directly ahead is the ever-after-vacant space and foundation stones whose rosy discoloration is evidence still of the fiery destruction of the first temple to the goddess by the Persians. By contrast, when one is facing outward toward the Saronic Gulf, it becomes evident that the Propylon was sited to frame the view of the island of <name type="place">Salamis</name>, where the Greeks decisively defeated the Persians, in 480 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></p><p>Because Greek architects did not develop a method of building arched foundations and superstructures, the siting of their theaters and stadiums was dependent upon topography. The steep-pitched Greek theater especially needed to be fit within the contours of the terrain, and it is therefore frequently found on the slope of the old acropolis or nestled into a hillside near the edge of town.</p><p>Gymnasiums, although usually operated as private institutions, reflected the <hi rend="italic">polis'</hi> mission of <hi rend="italic">paideia</hi>, the education of its citizenry in body and mind. Gardens and <hi rend="italic">odeums</hi>, small buildings for the performance of music or the recitation of poetry, were part of such important gymnasiums as the Academy in <name type="place">Athens</name>, where <name type="pname">Plato</name> established his school. <hi rend="italic">Stoas</hi>, handsome colonnaded structures serving multiple purposes, were often used for public discourse of a philosophical nature and were features of the gymnasiums as well. Because of their campuslike nature and consequent need for space, gymnasiums were usually<pb n="69"/><pb n="69" type="orig"/>located on the edge of the city outside the town walls, often in association with a stadium and frequently in connection with a shrine dedicated to an appropriately vigorous deity, such as <name type="pname">Hermes</name> or <name type="pname">Heracles</name>, or some hero of local renown. Like the Persian hunting parks seen by Greek soldiers and described by the Greek historian <name type="pname">Xenophon</name> (c. 431&#x2013;c. 352 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), these were well-treed preserves set aside from the routine business of everyday life. The <hi rend="italic">palaestra</hi>, or wrestling ground, was an essential feature of the larger and better-equipped gymnasiums, inasmuch as physical fitness was considered an indispensable part of education. Additional public <hi rend="italic">palaestras</hi> ensured that this important aspect of Greek life was readily available to the male populace as a whole.</p><p>Housing for the populace reflected the emphasis upon public life in the Greek city. Since Greek males spent most of their waking hours engaged in pursuits that were conducted out-of-doors or in structures designed for societal purposes, dwellings were uniformly modest in size and completely lacking in the luxury that would later characterize upper-class Roman homes. Water provision was a critical consideration, and there developed, in addition to wells and cisterns, aqueduct-fed fountains, which were later housed in special structures. Because Greek women had much less access than men to other parts of the public realm, they no doubt used these as informal social centers when they gathered to fill their am-phoras, or water jars.</p><p>Although Greek cities contained similar institutions and building types, they enjoyed a wide variation in design. The most important difference in urban planning was the one that existed between the relatively unplanned growth of such cities as <name type="place">Athens</name> and the development by design of cities like Miletus in <name type="place">Asia Minor</name>. <name type="place">Athens</name>'s resistance to grid regularization even after this type of planning had become common can be explained by the observation that historic circulation patterns are notably resistant to change. The unplanned aspect of a venerable urban center like <name type="place">Athens</name>&#x2014;or <name type="place">Rome</name> itself, for that matter&#x2014;where habitual land uses and hereditary property rights are firmly rooted, is valued above more rational geometric planning paradigms, even after these are routinely practiced elsewhere. For this reason and also because it was important to rebuild quickly in order to accommodate a large returning population, <name type="place">Athens</name> (like <name type="place">London</name> after the Great Fire of <date when="1666">1666</date>) chose to reconstruct itself along irregular, "organic" lines following its destruction by the Persians at the beginning of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></p><figure xml:id="fig-52"><graphic url="CH2_010.jpg"/><figDesc>2.9. Plan of Miletus. Miletus was laid out in the 5th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> as two grids, the more finely textured one with smaller street blocks to the north, and a looser-grained grid with two intersecting principal axes to the south. A band of public spaces containing various temples and a large agora traversed the town between the two grid sections. Descending from the Lion Harbor, which deeply penetrated the northern section of the city, was another arm of public space, and it, too, contained an agora. A long L-shaped <hi rend="italic">stoa</hi> fronted impressively on the Lion Harbor. It was backed by another L-shaped <hi rend="italic">stoa</hi> facing the town on the east. Additional <hi rend="italic">stoas</hi> made this agora in effect a peristyle court. By the middle of the 2nd century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, the considerably larger southern agora of Miletus had been similarly formed by the conjunction of independent <hi rend="italic">stoas</hi>. <hi rend="bold">A</hi> Lion Harbor. <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Northern Agora. <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Theater. <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Southern Agora</figDesc></figure><p>Miletus, on the other hand, presented with the same task of rebuilding after being destroyed by the Persian invaders, faced less immediate population pressure and adopted a grid plan of uniform blocks defined by regular streets of predetermined width crossing at right angles (fig. 2.9). Other Greek cities of <name type="place">Ionia</name> had employed at least a rudimentary version of the grid layout as early as the seventh century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> In fact, the development of orthogonal planning&#x2014;i.e., the laying out of streets at right angles&#x2014;as a coordinated program in which the city itself was the focus and frame, not some pragmatic objective or ceremonial purpose, was a Greek achievement. Adopted by the Romans, who surveyed and divided land into squares according to a process called <hi rend="italic">centuriation</hi>, and promoted by <name type="pname">Thomas Jefferson</name> as the method of giving spatial coordinates to the entire American continent, the grid has proved a convenient way of parceling both rural and urban land and a convenient means<pb n="70"/><pb n="70" type="orig"/>of enabling circulation in cities throughout history.</p><p>Although the invention of the grid was attributed by <name type="pname">Aristotle</name> and others to the planner and urban theorist <name type="pname">Hippodamus</name>, a native of the Ionian city of Miletus, he could not have originated its use. The logical means of subdividing land orthogonally that he employed in the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> had been used, at least for principal streets and temple complexes, by some earlier cultures, notably at <name type="place">Mohenjo-Daro</name> and <name type="place">Harappa</name> in the <name type="place">Indus River valley</name>, in <name type="place">Mesopotamia</name> where archaeologists have found traces of grid planning at <name type="place">Babylon</name> and other ancient cities, as well as in some Assyrian, Egyptian, and Etruscan settlements. <name type="pname">Hippodamus</name> must have worked on the reconstruction of Miletus following the Persian devastation of that city before being called upon by the Athenians in the second quarter of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> to lay out their port city of <name type="place">Piraeus</name>.</p><p>Early colonial practice had placed the grid-divided land, with the exception of the agora and other public spaces, into the hands of a founding elite, with subsequent immigrants assigned the status of tenants. Hippodamian planning, by contrast, was based upon a political system in which the population of a town was divided into three classes&#x2014;artisans, soldiers, and farmers&#x2014;with three categories of land&#x2014;sacred, public, and private&#x2014;allocated either as general civic space or as real property. This early zoning code, as much as the physical layout of the grid, was an innovative concept that influenced later Greek city planning. As for the Hippodamian plan itself, the town was formed <hi rend="italic">per stringas</hi>, a series of bands delineated by a few main east-west thoroughfares crossed by one or more major north-south arteries. Narrow lanes subdivided the rectangular units of land into blocks, which were then further subdivided into building lots. Because the blocks were more or less square, the resulting plan was that of a checkerboard.</p><p>According to <name type="pname">Polignac</name>, both civic cults and cults in nature were of particular importance in colonial cities.<ref target="#CH2-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref> Their establishment invariably necessitated the building of a sanctuary for the Hellenic god or goddess, most frequently Apollo the founder or Athena the protector, who served as the guardian of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> and the symbol of Greek hegemony within the newly claimed territory. In addition to the temple or temples located in the center, sanctuaries and shrines, usually dedicated to <name type="pname">Demeter</name>, <name type="pname">Artemis</name>, and deities associated with fertility and nature, were built in the periurban <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>. These served to claim the territory politically and also helped in the process of incorporating native residents into the culture of Hellenism. In some cases, native populations syncretized the worship of pre-existing native divinities with the imported Hellenic ones. <name type="pname">Demeter</name> and her daughter <name type="pname">Kore</name> (<name type="pname">Persephone</name>) were universally popular because of their association with annual rebirth in nature, and the settlers usually located the shrines of chthonic deities like these where there were caves or springs, places that natives may have already adopted for their religious purposes. As was true in the mother <hi rend="italic">poleis</hi> that founded these new cities, the civic shrines at the center were identified with the dominant ruling class, while the sanctuaries in the <hi rend="italic">chora</hi> served to incorporate into membership within the community at large women, indigenous peoples, other non-Greeks, and the agrarian population in general. The religious access offered by these sanctuaries was an important means of conquest and an essential feature of colonization, serving to meld members of fragile heterogeneous societies into viable communities.</p><p>Heroic monuments also played a role in forging civic identity. Cults based on tombs helped legitimize claims to land, serving to symbolize group sovereignty in the same way as did the rural sanctuaries. Enshrined heroes were often founders of cities, their legendary kings, even though dynastic rulership was not a feature of the mature <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>. Mythical founders were adopted as a means of adding heroic stature to the civic identity of a <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, as in the case of the Athenians, who incorporated the legendary hero Theseus into their urban mythology. In the fifth century, the ruler <name type="pname">Cimon</name> had <name type="pname">Theseus</name>'s putative remains taken from his first <hi rend="italic">heroon</hi>, or civic monument for the celebration of heroes, which stood sentinel at the city gates, and placed in a new <hi rend="italic">heroon</hi> in the heart of the city. Later generations sometimes erected statuary within a rediscovered ancient necropolis, particularly when the site was conterminous with the agora, the city's principal political space. But even without funerary associations, monuments to heroes were placed in important parts of the city, protectively at its entrances or proudly in its center.</p><p>But monumentality as such was not a characteristic of the Greek city in the pre-Hellenistic period. Although the Greeks could achieve monumentality in architecture and sculpture, they did not consider either the organic or the gridded cityscape a planning means toward this end. The tools of urban monumentality&#x2014;formal symmetry and axial layout&#x2014;were not employed until Hellenistic and Roman times. Instead, a combination of forms was pleasingly disposed for convenience and commonsensical ends. The U-shaped arrangement of <hi rend="italic">stoas</hi> did set up certain loose symmetries, but this was more the result of adaptation to the dictates of orthogonal planning in the grid cities than to an intentional desire for grandeur. Temples, agoras, gymnasiums, and other public or semipublic spaces were logically disposed within the frame of the grid, while theaters were placed<pb n="71"/><pb n="71" type="orig"/>according to the dictates of topography. Both "organic" and grid plans could produce aesthetically pleasing results.</p><p>Most apparent in the Greek city, whatever its form, is the primacy its population placed upon public space for public life. While public life in the form of ritual celebrations took place within the larger landscape outside the city, there were within the city temple sanctuaries, particularly those honoring Athena or Apollo&#x2014;protectors of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>&#x2014;as well as other kinds of places for public assembly. As important carriers of public life, the agora, the most important civic space, and the Greek theater, the site where the community's self-image received fullest expression, deserve our attention.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Athenian Agora</hi></hi></head><p>A closer understanding of the Greek urban landscape as an expression of culture necessarily requires a short account of the development of <name type="place">Athens</name> and its civic core, the Agora. According to the archaeologists <name type="pname">John Travlos</name><ref target="#CH2-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref> and <name type="pname">John Camp</name>,<ref target="#CH2-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref> at the end of the seventh century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, on a flat basin of land in the Kerameikos&#x2014;the potters' quarter and cemetery district northwest of the Acropolis&#x2014;a nucleus of eastward-facing public buildings began to take shape alongside the Panathenaic Way where it skirted the low hill of Kolonos (fig. 2.11). Although the Agora's boundaries were formally delimited by <hi rend="italic">horoi</hi>, boundary stones marking the points of entry of the streets feeding into it and underscoring its character as a quasi-sacred space, axial organization and symmetry played no role in the disposition of structures around it. Conceived in piecemeal fashion, it suggested unity and coherence, but these characteristics came from a harmonious architectural design vocabulary, geometrically derived proportions, and similarity of building materials, rather than from an overall plan. Unlike the Roman forum, the Greek agora was not perceived by its builders as a self-contained space, but simply as the nexus of the urban organism.</p><p>Before the end of the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, when the Theater of Dionysus was built on the southeast slope of the Acropolis, the Agora served as an orchestral space where singing, dancing, and plays were performed in front of spectators seated in wooden grandstands. After the transfer of athletic and theatrical events to the Acropolis slope, the open space of the Agora became the site of important commemorative monuments. One of the most important of these was the <hi rend="italic">Tyrannicides</hi>, a marble group by the fifth-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> sculptors <name type="pname">Kritios</name> and <name type="pname">Nesiotes</name> depicting <name type="pname">Harmodios</name> and <name type="pname">Aristogeiton</name>, the heroes who killed <name type="pname">Hipparchos</name>, brother of the tyrant <name type="pname">Hippias</name>, at the end of the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> This work, a replacement for an earlier work by <name type="pname">Antenor</name> that was removed from the Agora in 480 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> when the <name type="pname">Persian king Xerxes</name> plundered <name type="place">Athens</name>, can be seen in a Roman copy in the National Archaeological Museum in Naples. It is an early representation of contemporary heroes and, as such, a precedent for the commemorative monuments of heroic individuals found in public squares and parks to this day (fig. 2.10).</p><figure xml:id="fig-53"><graphic url="CH2_011.jpg"/><figDesc>2.10. <hi rend="italic">Tyrannicides</hi>, 2nd century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Roman copy after 5th-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> bronze sculptures by <name type="pname">Kritios</name> and <name type="pname">Nesiotes</name>, reportedly from <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa. Museo Archeologico Nazionale, Naples</figDesc></figure><p>On the north side of the Agora, facing the Panathenaic Way as it led up to the Acropolis, the Stoa Poikile, or Painted Stoa, was built in the second quarter of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Its name derived from its function as an art gallery, its walls decorated with battle scenes painted by notable painters of the day. It was here, too, that bronze shields were taken to be displayed as trophies of war. The Stoa Poikile functioned as an important meeting place, one frequented by street performers and beggars as well as philosophers. Followers of the philosopher <name type="pname">Zeno</name> (c. 335&#x2013;c. 263 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), who met his pupils in this <hi rend="italic">stoa</hi>, bequeathed to posterity the term <hi rend="italic">stoicism</hi> for his teachings on freedom from passion and a calm acceptance of fate.</p><p>Herms&#x2014;figures we will meet in other landscape settings as garden ornaments&#x2014;were placed throughout <name type="place">Athens</name> at the entrances to private homes, shrines, and important public spaces including the Agora (fig. 2.12). At the northwest corner of the Agora, at the point where it was intersected by the Panathenaic Way, a large concentration of these sculptures presided. A herm was a portrait bust of the god <name type="pname">Hermes</name> set upon a rectangular shaft from which protruded, halfway up, a representation of male genitalia. As symbols of male potency, herms were popular figures. They were often placed as talismans in front of homes as well as in public places<pb n="72"/><pb n="72" type="orig"/><q><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Athenian Agora in the Archaic and Hellenistic Periods</hi></hi></q><figure xml:id="fig-54"><graphic url="CH2_012.jpg"/><figDesc>2.11 a and b. Agora, <name type="place">Athens</name>: (a) in the Archaic period, c. 500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and (b) c. 300 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-55"><graphic url="CH2_013.jpg"/></figure><q><hi rend="bold">A</hi>round 520 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, the citizens built the Enneakrounos, a large public fountain house, the terminus of one of two recently constructed pipelines carrying water from the slopes of the Acropolis. With the drainage of the ground to the east and the construction of other public buildings on the remaining three sides of the open space thus formed, the Agora assumed the general size (10 acres) and irregular square shape that it maintained over several centuries.</q><q>Between 415 and 406 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, a new Bouleuterion was built adjacent to the old one. The Old Bouleuterion probably continued its function as the city archive, and the building became known as the Metroon. As such it was considered the sanctuary of <name type="pname">Rhea</name>, the Mother of the Olympian gods under whose auspices the civic records were guarded and the city's laws protected.</q><q>The Skias, or Tholos, stood immediately to the south of the New Bouleuterion and the Metroon. Its name denoted its round shape, like a <hi rend="italic">skias</hi>, or sun hat. Here the fifty <hi rend="italic">pryataneis</hi>, those senators who were functioning as the executive committee of the Boule, or Council, were served their meals. Approximately one-third of these remained on duty as guardians of the city, sleeping there throughout the night.</q><q>In the southwestern corner of the Agora, in front of some small buildings below the Tholos, was the 4th-century-<hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Monument of the Eponymous Heroes with ten bronze figuress flanked by ten bronze tripods (see 2.14). These represented each of the legendary figures selected by the Delphic Oracle as names for the ten "tribes" into which the people of Attica were divided. The tribes were created by the constitution drawn up by the statesman Cleisthenes at the end of the 6th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> In front of the monument was a barrier of stone posts and wooden railings. Here a citizen could read the civic notices posted beneath the figure representing his tribe. Here also general announcements, including drafts of proposed legislation, were posted. The Monument of the Eponymous Heroes was thus an important information center in ancient <name type="place">Athens</name>, functioning much like the modern press in focusing debate on public issues.</q><q>At the northwest corner of the Agora stood the Royal Stoa (Stoa Basileios) where magistrates swore their oaths of office. Sets of thrones, which originally stood in front of the <hi rend="italic">stoa</hi>, attest to its function as a place of judicial review. Pottery fragments marked as the property of the state denote its use also as a site for official functions involving drinking and dining. It was to the Royal Stoa that <name type="pname">Socrates</name> was summoned in 399 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> to be indicted.</q><q>Directly to the south of the Royal Stoa was the larger Doric Stoa of <name type="pname">Zeus</name>, with two projecting wings and a fa&#x00E7;ade of Pentelic marble, believed to have been built between 430 and 420 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Sacred to the cult of <name type="pname">Zeus Eleutherios</name> (Freedom), the building was a monument to Greek freedom from Persian domination after 479 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Like the Painted Stoa, it served as a communal memorial and was adorned with paintings and trophies of war. Here <name type="pname">Socrates</name> conversed with his pupils.</q><q>Some of the paraphernalia associated with trial by jury, such as the small bronze axles, which served as ballots, have been discovered in and around the Agora. The exact location of the prison has not been confirmed; however, in the ruins of a building at the southwest corner of the Agora, archaeologists have found a cache of small clay medicine bottles, such as were used to dispense the executioner's dose of hemlock, along with a small statuette of <name type="pname">Socrates</name> possibly left as a tribute.</q><q>On the south side of the Agora stood a long <hi rend="italic">stoa</hi>, built during the decade of 430&#x2013;420 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and replaced by another double-colonnaded <hi rend="italic">stoa</hi> in Hellenistic times. This structure housed the weights and measures that ensured honesty in market transactions. Sixteen private meeting chambers behind the colonnade were furnished with dining couches. Nearby was the Mint, a building with the remains of a foundry where official items of bronze, such as the ballots of jurors and the weights and measures of commerce, were fabricated from the 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> on and where coins were struck in the third and second centuries <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Between the Mint and the South Stoa was the fountain house dating from the 6th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></q><pb n="73"/><pb n="73" type="orig"/>and alongside important roads.</p><p>In the second quarter of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, trees were planted in the Agora to provide shade. These were probably plane trees and, like the trees planted at the same time at the Academy, they lined principal walkways and defined an outdoor classroom in which <name type="pname">Socrates</name> and other philosophers walked and talked with their students. Under one plane tree hung the notice board listing fines for women who had behaved in a disorderly manner. Later, beneath another, the Athenians placed a statue of the orator and statesman <name type="pname">Demosthenes</name> (384&#x2013;322 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>).</p><p>In the middle of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, <name type="pname">Pericles</name> focused the wealth garnered from <name type="place">Athens</name>'s hegemony within the Delian League upon the construction of the Parthenon and other temples on the Acropolis. During the last third of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, there was a burst of civic building activity around the Agora, so that, by the time the Athenian treasury was drained by Spartan victory at the end of the Peloponnesian Wars, its defining architecture had assumed the form that housed the city's important institutions throughout most of the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></p><p>Today, the Agora functions as an archaeological park enjoyed by tourists and city residents, and a careful replanting plan undertaken in the <date when="1950">1950</date>s using indigenous plant species common in ancient times provides an approximation of the welcome shade and greenery that this important public space had then. Now, as in antiquity, plants need irrigation to survive in the hot, dry Athenian climate, and the restored trees were planted along the same channels that originally furnished water to the Agora. Cavities excavated in bedrock around three sides of the <name type="place">Temple of Hephaistos</name>, probably in the early third century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> when an aqueduct was built to carry water to this site next to the Agora, served as planting pockets for a tree-shaded promenade. These were replanted with myrtle and pomegranate during the horticultural restoration.</p><figure xml:id="fig-56"><graphic url="CH2_014.jpg"/><figDesc>2.12. Marble herm from the Greek island of Siphnos. Height 26 inches. 520-510 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> National Archaeological Museum, <name type="place">Athens</name></figDesc></figure><p>From literature, history, and archaeology, a portrait of the life of the Agora emerges. To the ancient fountain house in its southeast corner came the women of the city bearing their amphoras. Nearby were the open-air market stalls where farmers sold livestock and produce. Beneath the colonnades of the various stoas a lively crowd mingled, gossiping or engaging in philosophical discussion and doing business of all kinds. At the Monument of the Eponymous Heroes, knots of men gathered to read the latest news (figs. 2.13, 2.14). Within the Bouleuterion complex, lawmakers attended to affairs of state. Courts of law, or a jury assembled outdoors, tried offenders. Upon occasion there would be functions of a sacro-civic nature with burnt offerings and contests performed before audiences seated in temporary grandstands. Among the many festival days of the year when the Agora was thronged with people celebrating or passing through en route to one of the sacred sites inside or outside the city, none was more important than the Great Panathenaia, which occurred in the middle of summer every fourth year.</p><figure xml:id="fig-57"><graphic url="CH2_015.jpg"/><figDesc>2.13. The site of the Monument of the Eponymous Heroes today, with the <name type="place">Temple of Hephaistos</name> in the background</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-58"><graphic url="CH2_016.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 2.14. Drawing of the restored Monument of the Eponymous Heroes, c. 330 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> In front of the monument was a barrier of stone posts and wooden railings. Here a citizen could read the civic notices posted beneath the figure representing his tribe. Here also general announcements, including drafts of proposed legislation, were posted. The Monument of the Eponymous Heroes was thus an important information center in ancient <name type="place">Athens</name>, functioning much like the modern press in focusing debate on public issues.</figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><pb n="74"/><pb n="74" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Theater in <name type="place">Athens</name></hi></hi></head><p>Of scarcely less importance than the Great Panathenaia was the Great Dionysia, which took place annually. In the beginning, celebrants honored Dionysus, patron god of drama and of this festival, in the Agora; later, the Athenians built a theater held sacred to him on the southeastern flank of the Acropolis. It contained a circular orchestra, 66 feet in diameter, with a floor of smooth-packed dirt and an altar in the center. Wooden planks set into the terraced hillside accommodated the audience, and a modest wooden <hi rend="italic">skene</hi>, or scene building, provided the necessary theatrical backdrop.</p><p><name type="pname">Pericles</name>' fifth-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> building program called for a new theater to accommodate the mature Greek drama that Aeschylus had pioneered in the Great Dionysias held in the 470s <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> In order to make room for a larger <hi rend="italic">skene</hi>, the theater was moved farther north to a position near the walls of the Acropolis. It is this theater, improved by the Athenian orator and financier <name type="pname">Lycurgus</name> in the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and extensively remodeled in Roman times, that tourists visit today. To the east of the theater, above the auditorium, <name type="pname">Pericles</name> built a large square building called the Odeion to hold musical contests, which were also part of the Great Dionysia.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Kerameikos Cemetery</hi></hi></head><p>Just outside the Dipylon, or double gateway that formed the principal entrance to the city, lay the Kerameikos Cemetery. Burial at this site dates from the twelfth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, and archaeologists have discovered here enormous eighth-century-<hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> funerary kraters and amphorae decorated in the Geometric style. During the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, incised, painted, and bas-relief grave monuments, together with commemorative sculpture, began to adorn the landscape. By this time the city walls had been built. Athenian law restricted burial to the outer Kerameikos beyond them, while the inner Kerameikos became the district where potters clustered to make the distinctive redand-black Attic pottery that was one of the city's most important commercial wares, thus giving its name to ceramic production ever after.</p><p>Large-scale, carved stone versions of <hi rend="italic">lekythoi</hi>&#x2014;small, slender, ceramic urns&#x2014;became popular grave markers in the late fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> along with memorial altars, inscribed stelai, and sculptures of lions. Plots lining the Academy road, which was especially scenic, became the final resting place of distinguished statesmen and Athenians and their allies fallen in war. In this way a necropolis took shape, becoming, as we shall see in Chapter Nine, an aesthetic inspiration for metropolitan suburban cemeteries in <name type="place">Paris</name>, <name type="place">Boston</name>, <name type="place">New York</name>, and other rapidly expanding cities of the industrial age. After the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, a law was issued forbidding costly sculptural works, and people honored the dead with simple round columns instead.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Athenian Countryside</hi></hi></head><p>The vital sum of all these activities indicates an extraordinary spirit of cultural unity during the centuries of Athenian self-governance. Moreover, even though <name type="place">Athens</name> was unique among Greek cities in the degree to which its religious life was focused inside the city, the connection between the city and its surrounding landscape was palpable and continuously experienced. To the northwest, the Sacred Way became the road to Eleusis, site of an important religious sanctuary. To the northeast lay the road to <name type="place">Mount Pentelicus</name>, 10 miles distant, over which workmen hauled the thousands of tons of marble used to build the Parthenon and other important public buildings. To the southeast, reinforcing the Parthenon's lineage as a temple of the goddess Athena, <name type="place">Mount Hymettos</name>, with its peak sanctuary to <name type="pname">Zeus Omvrios</name>, provoker of rain, reared its twin horns in axial relationship to it. To the southwest lay Piraeus, connected to the city by parallel long walls protecting the transit of people and goods from the Spartan enemy. Between the road to Eleusis and the road to <name type="place">Thebes</name> in the north was the road upon which <name type="pname">Plato</name> journeyed as he went from the city to the nearby shady groves of the Academy. The siting of the city thus, with mountains protectively encircling three sides, while the fourth faced the sea&#x2014;a paradigm that was intuitively repeated by <hi rend="italic">poleis</hi> elsewhere, notably in the plain of Argolis&#x2014;gave the Athenians a much clearer sense of specific territoriality than did their fortifying walls. <hi rend="italic">Polis</hi>_and <hi rend="italic">chora</hi> were an expression of both Mind (<hi rend="italic">Nous</hi>) and Nature, an integrated whole in which a profound ideal of human existence was made manifest.</p><p>In addition to developing an architectural vocabulary of columned, pedimented structures that has remained a living language for builders for more than two millennia, the ancient Greeks enlarged the sense of urban life as a communal undertaking and created institutions such as the theater that expanded the human potential for self-awareness. Though their remarkable experiment in governance proved difficult to perpetuate and replicate, some of their cultural and educational institutions endured, and the language of Classical Greek architecture was expanded by Hellenistic and Roman architects.</p><p>With the Hellenistic Empire the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> as a self-governing civic and religious institution ceased to exist. In its place there arose a new cosmopolitan culture embracing the entire Mediterranean basin and<pb n="75"/><pb n="75" type="orig"/>extending as far east as <name type="place">Persia</name>. Within this far-flung region composed of many interactive urban centers, designers manipulated the forms inherited from <name type="place">Greece</name> in sophisticated ways, creating theatrical spatial compositions that gave a new dynamism to landscape design paralleled by the dynamic movement and high degree of emotionalism Hellenistic sculptors gave to their figural compositions. By Roman times, the relationship of such architectural ensembles to natural settings no longer mattered as much as their employment to frame and contain space. Further, the replication of Roman civic forms was seen as a means of asserting authority and inspiring allegiance in colonial cities throughout an empire of even vaster dimensions than the one created by <name type="pname">Alexander the Great</name>.</p></div></div><div type="section"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">III. Empire: Hellenistic and Roman Urbanism</hi></hi></head><p>Weakened by the long years of warfare with Sparta and assailed by other centers of growing power during the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, <name type="place">Athens</name> saw her hegemony among Aegean city states diminished and her own freedom threatened. Warfare was now a way of life throughout the Hellenic world, and although colonization was one solution to the problem of growing urban populations, within the context of the general Hellenic unrest, colonial outposts were vulnerable offshoots with an uncertain future.</p><p>It is a historical irony that <name type="place">Macedonia</name>, a land power without a significant navy, should have been the engine that propelled <name type="place">Greece</name> toward empire and the subjugation of <name type="place">Asia</name>. Following the murder of <name type="pname">Philip II</name> of <name type="place">Macedon</name> (382&#x2013;336 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), his brilliant son, <name type="pname">Alexander</name> (356&#x2013;323 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), assumed the throne at the age of twenty. Already an experienced campaigner, he found the battlefield his natural home and soon set about completing the Macedonian subjugation of <name type="place">Thessaly</name>, <name type="place">Thrace</name>, and <name type="place">Illyria</name>. After securing lands all the way to the Danube and beyond, he ruthlessly crushed rebellious <name type="place">Thebes</name>. The rest of the Greek city-states fell into line, including <name type="place">Athens</name>, co-conspirator of <name type="place">Thebes</name>, which <name type="pname">Alexander</name> could now afford to treat leniently.</p><p><name type="pname">Alexander the Great</name>'s thirteen-year reign was one of continued whirlwind conquest as his armies subdued the cities of <name type="place">Asia Minor</name>, <name type="place">Syria</name>, and <name type="place">Egypt</name>. With the eastern Mediterranean under his control, he marched into <name type="place">Mesopotamia</name> and, crossing the <name type="place">Caucasus</name>, on into <name type="place">India</name>. In the process of building an empire, he founded several cities, among them <name type="place">Alexandria</name> in <name type="place">Egypt</name>. Although his empire quickly fragmented following his death in 323 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, his great achievement was the creation of a Hellenistic culture and economy that stretched from Gibraltar to the <name type="place">Indus River</name>.</p><p>In this vast matrix, art and trade flourished, and the advances in geography, natural history, and other aspects of science that <name type="pname">Alexander</name> had encouraged continued. In terms of art, <name type="pname">Alexander</name> had appropriated from his tutor <name type="pname">Aristotle</name> an ecumenical attitude, believing the world to be an <hi rend="italic">oikumene</hi>, a place of eclectic exchange in which many cultures contributed form and style to the Greek base. Because of these circumstances, the Greek heritage, now infused with a broad array of disparate cultural influences, was both disseminated and developed, acquiring certain important features that became basic ingredients of much subsequent landscape design. These included axial organization and a new monumentality, potent tools for dramatizing urban power and making the appearance of cities more symbolically expressive.</p><p>In the Hellenistic world, there was a heightened sense of the drama of human affairs. The serene idealism of Classical Greek art was not compatible with the clamor of imperial armies. Power creates its own cultural imperatives: hagiography finds its counterpart in architectural monumentality and portraiture, while the tragedy of brutality and suffering often breeds melodrama. Hellenism's broad sweep across continents was paralleled by an extravagant treatment of space. Buildings were organized into elaborate complexes, and sculpture was no longer self-contained, but full of restless movement.</p><p>The vocabulary of design remained Classical, yet it was accented in new and theatrical ways. The manipulation of vertical space became an important aspect of landscape design as staircases and terraces took on new importance along with the organization of horizontal space through symmetry and axial alignment. Engaged columns, pilasters, and other means of surface articulation animated buildings and increased their dramatic presence. The prosperity engendered by trade and the continued growth and spread of populations through colonization meant that many opportunities existed for experimentation with these elements of urban form.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Hellenistic Urbanism</hi></hi></head><p>The Hellenistic city appropriated the Hippodamian grid as a planning device and exploited it architecturally. <hi rend="italic">Stoas</hi> and, later, colonnades lining principal thoroughfares made the planar orthogonal lines of the city three-dimensional, turning agoras into architecturally defined spaces, and streets into rhythmically punctuated ways (fig. 2.15). Like those of Classical times, the Hellenistic agora functioned as a vital urban<pb n="76"/><pb n="76" type="orig"/>nexus open to all manner of through traffic and did not become a self-contained space segregated from its surrounding streets. Instead, it experienced a transformation akin to that of another important Hellenistic architectural form: the peristyle, or column-enclosed court, as can be seen in Miletus (see fig. 2.9; fig. 2.16).</p><figure xml:id="fig-59"><graphic url="CH2_017.jpg"/><figDesc>2.15. Curetes Street, Ephesus, <name type="place">Turkey</name>. Principal thoroughfares in Hellenistic cities such as Ephesus were often colonnaded, providing visual unity to the streetscape and a precedent for later arcaded streets and squares (see figs. 4.48, 4.49, 6.45).</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-60"><graphic url="CH2_018.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.16. <hi rend="italic">Stoa</hi> facing Lion Harbor, Miletus. 2nd century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Illustrating the versatility and theatrical planning principles that are also inherent in Hellenistic urban design, the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> city of <name type="place">Pergamum</name> forsook the grid entirely for an essay in vertical composition (figs. 2.17, 2.18, 2.20). This suited its location on a narrow mountain ridge near what is now the modern town of Bergama in <name type="place">Turkey</name>. <name type="place">Pergamum</name> under the Attalid dynasty sought to rival the Periclean splendor of the Athenian Acropolis. Athena was the city's patron deity, and its kings, <name type="pname">Eumenes II</name> (ruled 197&#x2013;159 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) and <name type="pname">Attalos II</name> (ruled 159&#x2013;138 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) oversaw a building program that honored both the goddess and themselves. Here, because of the topography of the site, the city's urban planners abandoned the grid and instead produced a fan-shaped layout as they built the city in successive stages over several generations. Their efforts resulted in an extraordinarily scenic composition in which architecture and landscape were fused into a unified dramatic experience.</p><pb n="77"/><pb n="77" type="orig"/><q><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Hellenistic <name type="place">Pergamum</name></hi></hi></q><figure xml:id="fig-61"><graphic url="CH2_019.jpg"/><figDesc>2.17. <name type="place">Pergamum</name>. 2nd century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Reconstructed view by <name type="pname">Richard Bohn</name>. <date when="1888">1888</date>.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-62"><graphic url="CH2_020.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 2.18. Plan of ancient <name type="place">Pergamum</name>, upper town. 2nd century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-63"><graphic url="CH2_021.jpg"/><figDesc>2.19. Altar of <name type="pname">Zeus</name>, erected at <name type="place">Pergamum</name> during the reign of <name type="pname">Eumenes II</name> (ruled 197&#x2013;160 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) to commemorate the city's victory over the Gauls under <name type="pname">Attalos I</name> (ruled 241&#x2013;197 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>). Installed in the Pergamon Museum, <name type="place">Berlin</name></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-64"><graphic url="CH2_022.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.20. Theater, <name type="place">Pergamum</name>. 2nd century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><q><hi rend="bold">A</hi>cting as a pivot for the entire fan of stepped terraces and buildings that constituted the upper city, a large theater was set into the steeply pitched western face of the acropolis ridge (fig. 2.20).</q><q>A long terrace with two levels of buttressed retaining walls anchored the theater into its hillside. The colonnade running the length of the terrace <hi rend="bold">B</hi> established a rhythmical pattern that was echoed in the architecture above. From the theater one ascended into the colonnade-framed terrace that formed the precinct of the Temple of Athena <hi rend="bold">A</hi>. On the terrace below this to the south stood the great Altar of <name type="pname">Zeus</name> <hi rend="bold">C</hi>, which lends its name to the Pergamon Museum in <name type="place">Berlin</name> where it can be seen today in its reconstructed form (fig. 2.19). Its grandiloquent frieze depicts the mythical battle between the Gods and the Giants with the thrusting diagonals and surging movement into space that are characteristic of Hellenistic sculpture.</q><q>Above the Athena terrace stood the library, the palace complex, barracks, and arsenal. The Temple of Trajan, a later Roman addition, occupied its own terrace to the north of the theater, making an effective counterpoint to the great altar and its terrace to the south. Beneath the monumental Altar of <name type="pname">Zeus</name> was the city's upper agora <hi rend="bold">D</hi>; it was at this point that the road, which zigzagged along the hilly south-facing slope above the lower agora and extensive terraced gymnasium complex of the town below, entered the acropolis area and began its rise through the sequence of scenically arranged terraces.</q><pb n="78"/><pb n="78" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-65"><graphic url="CH2_023.jpg"/><figDesc>2.21. Athenian Agora, 2nd century, <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, at the period of its fullest development</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-66"><graphic url="CH2_024.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.22. Reconstruction of the Stoa of <name type="pname">Attalos II</name> of <name type="place">Pergamum</name> (ruled 159&#x2013;138 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), Athenian Agora. The original <hi rend="italic">stoa</hi> was destroyed in 267 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The reconstruction was built in the <date when="1950">1950</date>s to house the Agora Museum.</figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">From Hellenistic to Roman Urbanism</hi></hi></head><p>To understand more fully the forces at work as the Classical heritage of <name type="place">Greece</name> was transformed through Hellenistic culture into that of imperial <name type="place">Rome</name>, it is worth revisiting the Athenian Agora. Although <name type="place">Athens</name> did not offer the underlying organizing principle of a grid plan, which would have facilitated the kind of articulation of public space as is found at Miletus, the agora in its Hellenistic and Roman incarnations nevertheless manifests the trend toward the regularization and inward-focusing of open space (fig. 2.21).</p><p>By the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, <name type="place">Athens</name> was a province of <name type="place">Rome</name>, a renowned center of learning, revered as the fountainhead of Greek culture and home to the most eminent philosophers of the day. <name type="pname">Cicero</name>, <name type="pname">Horace</name>, and <name type="pname">Ovid</name> came there to study, and various Roman emperors bestowed their largesse upon the city's venerable civic core in the form of new buildings. Not surprisingly, the Agora's character as a civic space changed; it lost all remaining identity as a place of democratic assembly and became instead a receptacle for Greco-Roman culture and a repository of the glorious Classical past, which <name type="place">Rome</name> now appropriated.</p><p>The integrity of the original Agora space had been breached by the construction of the Hellenistic Middle Stoa, but this had been done to achieve a more regular spatial definition and accommodate the city's continued commercial vitality. Now there no longer existed any prohibition against encroachment upon the remaining space. Vividly illustrating the Athenian loss of governmental autonomy and the Agora's transformation from civic core to cultural center was the construction of the Odeion in its center. This huge concert hall was probably built at the time of the emperor <name type="pname">Augustus</name>'s visit to the city between 16 and 14 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></p><p>Symptomatic of the decline of Greek power, moreover, was the memorializing of its past. The Agora played a large role in this effort as it became a virtual museum of architectural reconstruction in an early attempt at "heritage theming." <name type="pname">Augustus</name>'s building program included the careful dismantling of the Temple of Ares, a marble structure of the Doric order that is believed to have stood several miles north of <name type="place">Athens</name> somewhere in the foothills of <name type="place">Mount Parnes</name>, and its reassembly in front of the Agora's western range of Classical and Hellenistic buildings. At this time, he had columns and other elements of neglec-ted fifth- and fourth-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> buildings in the depopulated countryside of Attica transported to the Agora for conservation and reuse. From Sounion, from Thorikos, and from elsewhere came handsomely carved building parts, and from other places came small temples and altars. Inscriptions were carved on these, honoring the deified emperor <name type="pname">Agrippa</name>'s and his relatives.</p><p>In keeping with the continued exaltation of the Agora as a center of culture and learning, at the southeast corner along the Panathenaic Way, a private citizen, <name type="pname">Titus Flavius Pantaenus</name>, built a library at his expense in the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Like many Roman buildings, it was given the interior focus of a peristyle courtyard, while Greek-style stoas stood along three sides of the exterior (fig. 2.22).</p><p>On the opposite side of the Panathenaic Way, on the site of the old Mint and next to one of the reconstructed Classical temples, the Nymphaeum, a foun<pb n="79"/><pb n="79" type="orig"/>tain house in the shape of a large hemicycle, was built in the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The curving wall that rose above a series of basins, pools, and fountains seems to have been carved with niches for statues. This elaborate fountain was connected to the great aqueduct that carried water to <name type="place">Athens</name> from the Kephalari Springs on the lower slopes of <name type="place">Mount Pentelicus</name>. The construction of the Athenian Nymphaeum illustrates the ancient Roman practice of celebrating an important public work through symbolic civic display. It was built in the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> during the reign of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>, the emperor-architect who, more than all the others, identified with Greek culture and history. Besides the Nymphaeum, his legacy to the city included the monumental Temple of Olympian <name type="pname">Zeus</name>, a library, a gymnasium, a pantheon, and a shrine of Panhellenic <name type="pname">Zeus</name> and <name type="pname">Hera</name>.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Elements of Roman Urbanism</hi></hi></head><p>Order was the hallmark of Roman urbanism. In its most utilitarian dimension, Roman order meant <hi rend="italic">centuriation</hi>, the division of the territory surrounding a town into squares measuring 2400 feet (731.5 meters) per side. These <hi rend="italic">centuriae</hi> were so named because Roman surveyors subdivided them into approximately one hundred oblong strips of land, arable fields for the most part, which were allocated as private property to the citizens of the town. A similarly utilitarian application of Roman order was to be found in the grid layout of military encampments that often served, as in the case of Florentia (Florence), as the future sites of colonial cities (fig. 2.23). The Roman grid, inherited from both Greek and Etruscan practice, was developed around a central cross axis, the street running north-south being the <hi rend="italic">cardo</hi>, and the eastwest one traversing it being the <hi rend="italic">decumanus</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">insulae</hi>, or blocks formed by the subsidiary orthogonal streets, formed a checkerboard pattern of squares, rather than the oblong units familiar in Hellenistic grid planning. In many cases the <hi rend="italic">cardo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">decumanus</hi> forming the town center would be identical with the intersection of two survey lines of <hi rend="italic">centuriation;</hi> sometimes, however, a Roman town grid might respect the cardinal points of the compass in its orthogonal alignment while <hi rend="italic">centuriation</hi> proceeded&#x2014;as was the case with Florentia where the course of the Arno and the surrounding topography were taken into account&#x2014;in accordance with certain practical considerations.</p><p>In addition to providing a formula for the establishment of a military settlement or a new town, Roman order prevailed in the predictable location of the forums and major civic structures of the town at the intersection of the <hi rend="italic">cardo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">decumanus</hi>. Further, planners subjugated all private building to a zoning code that decreed that no building could be higher than twice the width of the street upon which it stood, an ordinance that was sometimes breached as a town became overcrowded and people needed to erect tall tenements for housing. The manufacture of standardized, kiln-fired bricks, roof tiles, and drainage pipes in many sizes and shapes and the mass production of metal pipes and fastening devices, together with the invention of concrete and the necessary timber-form technology for repetitive pouring of vaults, walls, foundations, and other building parts, made possible the organization of a construction industry capable of operating with military-style efficiency. Indeed, many construction workers were soldiers of the Roman Empire.</p><figure xml:id="fig-67"><graphic url="CH2_025.jpg"/><figDesc>2.23. Aerial view of <name type="place">Florence</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name>. The original grid plan of Florentia, a Roman military encampment and colony, can be detected in the regular layout of the streets around the Piazza della Republica, the old Roman Forum.</figDesc></figure><p>But there was a higher sense of order than that of the pragmatic grid honored by Roman urbanism, an order in which the grid played an ever-diminishing role until its use as a planning tool was virtually phased out in the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> This order might be called imperial order, for it was a means of making manifest&#x2014;through planning and architecture em-ploying common urban spatial arrangements and building types&#x2014;the grandeur, beneficence, and ubiquity of empire. Throughout <name type="place">Asia Minor</name>, <name type="place">North Africa</name>, <name type="place">Iberia</name>, <name type="place">Great Britain</name>, <name type="place">Gaul</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name>, and all the islands of the <name type="place">Mediterranean</name>, a uniform building technology and urban planning mentality provided hundreds of variants upon this theme. Imperial grandeur was be-stowed upon cities as great basilicas and public baths were built. High-based temples and triumphal<pb n="80"/><pb n="80" type="orig"/>arches added more scenographic verticality, and theaters and amphitheaters provided both entertainment and landmark character. Paternalistically conceived, these Roman cities were designed through the machinery of imperial authority as livable habitats for their citizens. With running water, latrines, paved streets, and other amenities, they are the first cities in which modern urban dwellers could have felt at home. Collectively, along with the Roman roads and Roman aqueducts that served them, the cities proclaimed in physical terms the <hi rend="italic">Pax Romana</hi> across the broad sphere of empire. More than anything else, the replication of this order over and over again throughout the Roman Empire's vast breadth manifested its wealth and the power of its highly centralized government.</p><p>What were the elements of the urban rhetoric that effectively and lastingly portrayed Roman imperial order? Although the grid was manipulated and even ignored, axiality itself was more firmly applied than ever before. Bilateral symmetry around strong axes governed the design of major public buildings and their attendant courts. The forum was a highly controlled space. Streets led to its entrances, but, unlike the Greek or Hellenistic agora, it was not traversed by thoroughfares. The Roman forum was thus at once integrated with, and separated from, the circulation system of the town, This street design, together with the firm architectural definition of borders, gave the forum&#x2014;like the great buildings that, with it, constituted the civic core&#x2014;an inward focus.</p><p>Roman architecture and planning were in this way informed by profound space-shaping and place-fixing impulses. As cultural heirs of the Greeks, Romans sometimes paid homage to a local "genius of the place," but the cultural matrix in which they built was one grounded in an Aristotelian worldview and imperial politics. The sense of self-containment, enclosure, and embrace that their buildings and cities displayed denied integration with the greater landscape and, instead, metaphorically proclaimed the values of the entire urbanized commonwealth. These building and urban forms, which were architecturally similar from place to place, were grounded not in their own locales, but rather in the concept of orderly imperial rule. It is thus understandable that the old shrines and sanctuaries in nature ceased to exert their pull, and communal processions to them stopped after the gods took up permanent residence in the cities. Roman temples, like Roman basilicas, were for the most part found in or beside the forum, in the civic centers of towns.</p><p>Unlike the architecturally elaborate Hellenistic shrines at Lindos and Kos, which enjoyed a natural setting, the <name type="place">Sanctuary of Fortuna Primigenia</name>, begun in the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, was an urban shrine. Set into a hillside, it hovers above the town of <name type="place">Praeneste</name> (modern <name type="place">Palestrina</name>) outside <name type="place">Rome</name>, offering a splendid example of the integration of site and architecture (fig. 2.24). It demonstrates, according to architectural historian <name type="pname">Spiro Kostoff</name>, "the cadenced climb in stages, with an artful use of landings, viewing points, and the alternating concealment and revelation of the terminal object, [that] was a special gift of Roman designers."<ref target="#CH2-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref> Behind the colonnades of its lower terraces were rows of shops. Lateral stairs ascend from the ground level to the first of seven terraces; to ascend from one terrace level to the next, one is forced to return to the central axis. Here there are steep stairs or, in the case of the third and fourth terraces, long ramps, which climb from each side and then connect in the center above large barrel-vaulted niches that emphasize the central axis. Shops were placed behind porticoes that run the length of the fifth and sixth terraces on either side of the central stairs. The deep sixth terrace had side porticoes as well. The small semicircular top terrace served as the orchestra for a theater and was therefore surrounded by stepped seating, above which stood as the climax to the whole soaring architectural composition a semicircular double portico and, rising behind it, a small round temple. The organization of the hillside into a series of terraces with stairs arranged to enforce axial movement and the resolution of axial thrust in a climactic semicircular embrace is considered a source of inspiration for Bramante's Belvedere Court at the <name type="place">Vatican</name>, begun around <date when="1505">1505</date> (see Chapter Four, figs. 4.7, 4.8, 4.9), and subsequently through Bramante's example, the work of other Renaissance landscape designers.</p><figure xml:id="fig-68"><graphic url="CH2_026.jpg"/><figDesc>2.24. <name type="place">Sanctuary of Fortuna Primigenia</name>, <name type="place">Praeneste</name> (<name type="place">Palestrina</name>). Early 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><pb n="81"/><pb n="81" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-69"><graphic url="CH2_027.jpg"/><figDesc>2.25. Triumphal Arch, Arausio (Orange), <name type="place">France</name>. 21 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-70"><graphic url="CH2_028.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.26. Arcadian Way, Ephesus, constructed during the reign of the Emperor <name type="pname">Arcadius</name> (395&#x2013;408 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>). This marble-paved street leading from the middle harbor gate to the theater was lined with shops and had wide, covered, mosaic walkways on either side of it.</figDesc></figure><p>Most of the columns that once formed the colonnades of the stepped facades and projecting wings of the <name type="place">Sanctuary of Fortuna Primigenia</name> have been removed, but the remaining structure bears witness to the Roman affinity for a construction technology and design vocabulary in which the arch played a dominant role. The arch has the ability to span distances with balletic grace; its analogue is the leap, whereas that of the seriate column is the measured step. For this reason, the arcaded porticoes of Roman streets provide an altogether different visual rhythm from that set up by the Greek stoa or Hellenistic colonnade. But, as is evident at <name type="place">Praeneste</name>, Roman aptitude for arch construction did not mean forsaking the classical orders of Hellenistic architecture. On the contrary, columns and pediments were used extensively in both old and new ways as architects forged a specifically Roman architectural vocabulary. Peristyle courts increased in popularity, and colonnades were extensively employed to ennoble prominent thoroughfares. Most important, Roman designers applied columns and other sculptural elements decoratively to adorn and articulate the other-wise undifferentiated surfaces of freestanding arches as well as arched entrances and building fa&#x00E7;ades like that of the Colosseum in <name type="place">Rome</name>. The column-ornamented, freestanding triumphal arch erected to celebrate victory in battle became emblematic of <name type="place">Rome</name>, a familiar image appearing on coins and in other ways symbolizing imperial rule (fig. 2.25).</p><p>These elements, which were often employed in conjunction with brick facing, constituted the architectural ingredients of Roman urbanism. Cities throughout the empire established a well-defined and predictable sequencing of commonly established urban forms. The spatial linking of these according to certain conventional formulae, as well as the overall familiarity of the forms themselves, gave the Roman urban landscape its essential character.</p><p>Principal thoroughfares were designed to visually link these forms and spaces. They were differentiated from the byways of the town by their sunken grading, additional width, and an abundance of special features including fountains and, in important cities, freestanding arches and other architectural incidents such as nymphaeums. Sometimes colonnades or arched porticoes extending for several blocks en-hanced the streets' status as principal avenues (fig. 2.26).</p><pb n="82"/><pb n="82" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-71"><graphic url="CH2_029.jpg"/><figDesc>2.27. Via di <name type="place">Stabia</name>, <name type="place">Pompeii</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name>, with stepping stones and fountain at the intersection. Before 62 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-72"><graphic url="CH2_030.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.28. Fountain, House of the Little Fountain, <name type="place">Pompeii</name>. 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> In order to enjoy the abundance of water available in the Imperial Age, Pompeians built showy mosaic fountains. These often took the form of a small pedimented structure containing a semicircular niche. Inside the niche, water cascaded down a miniature staircase or spouted from a jet held by, or contained within, a sculpture. The mosaics that decorated these fountains were formed of sea shells and brilliantly colored tiles.</figDesc></figure><p>These aggrandized thoroughfares were often market streets, as they always led from a principal arched gate within the town wall to the central forum and were therefore arteries of traffic and foci of human activity. Because they were sunk slightly below the level of the buildings on either side, these streets formed curb-lined troughs. This facilitated the runoff of water and waste into drains like those that carry away rainwater and sewage in cities today. The street curbs also gave the roadbed linear definition, clearly marking its axial direction and imposing order upon the adjacent buildings. Although individualistic in their interior planning, these buildings almost invariably respected a uniform building line parallel to the street. Raised blocks at intersections facilitated pedestrian crossing (fig. 2.27).</p><p>The forum, normally at the nexus of the town's principal thoroughfares, might lie astride the street crossing. If that was the case, its sense of spatial enclosure would nevertheless be carefully maintained by its embracing porticoed architecture and the careful articulation of its entry points. More often, the forum lay beside a principal thoroughfare within the arms of one of the angles formed by the major crossing, its entrance prominently marked by architectural elements. Like the principal thoroughfares, it received special emphasis by being sunk slightly below the surrounding grade, with its edges outlined by a few shallow steps. Because the entrance portico was above the grade of the street, passage into the forum was marked by going first up, and then down, one or more stairs.</p><p>With great sophistication, urban planners employed steep flights of stairs within Roman cities to negotiate topographic changes in grade and to ascend the platforms on which Romans set their temples, basilicas, and other monumental structures. In addition to offering formal variety, these stairs and ramps gave a degree of vertical drama. Some flights of stairs rose straight, others laterally from the ends of buildings, still others from the flanks of an axial element. In certain instances where there were several levels, these different methods of ascent were em-ployed in combination, as at <name type="place">Praeneste</name>. Steps could, of course, be used as seats and probably served, as they often do today, as places for informal gathering.</p><p>Noncommercial public space was plentiful in Roman cities. It was one of the hallmarks of imperial urbanism, and its daily use in a variety of instructive and pleasurable ways was a happy perquisite of Roman citizenship. As an institution of Roman life and as a statement of imperial largesse, the monumental public baths were important elements in the social fabric of cities. Their high, vaulted, axially planned and beautifully decorated interiors contained&#x2014;in addition to hot, warm, and cold bathing rooms&#x2014;well-stocked libraries. In addition to offering sensory, mental, and social stimulation, they were centers of physical fitness. Adjacent gardens and palaestrae for exercising were often planned as axially connected peristyle courts. The fusion of the gymnasium and the heated bath manifested the sophisticated cosmopolitanism of imperial times. When not erected by emperors as a means of demonstrating beneficence and gaining public approval, they were built by wealthy patrons. Many Roman baths are early examples of civic philanthropy and bear inscriptions recognizing the donor.</p><p>Although as populations grew and apartment dwellings replaced individual residences within <name type="place">Rome</name> itself and in many other Roman cities, these structures did not make cities feel overcrowded or<pb n="83"/><pb n="83" type="orig"/>disagreeable. There was abundant public space, aqueduct-fed fountains and baths, and a sophisticated infrastructure for sewage disposal. Moreover, cities were beautified with sculptures and ornament. Roman architects became increasingly confident in the handling of light. Polished marble and glittering mosaics reflected light. Light also animated the surface of water. The continual motion and sound of water splashing in fountains and pools and gliding over water stairs set within the niches of <hi rend="italic">nymphaeums</hi> added another important sensory dimension to imperial Roman cities (fig. 2.28). Patterns of light and shade&#x2014;no longer legible because today colonnades and porticoes are bare, unroofed archaeological ruins&#x2014;were also an important part of the sensory experience of street and plaza.</p><figure xml:id="fig-73"><graphic url="CH2_031.jpg"/><figDesc>2.29. House of Pansa, <name type="place">Pompeii</name>. 2nd century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The rear peristyle garden significantly increased the size and amenity of the house, giving it several more well-lit rooms as well as a garden pool.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-74"><graphic url="CH2_032.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.30. The House of the Vettii, <name type="place">Pompeii</name>. Mid-1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> In this house of a well-to-do merchant, the peristyle garden has more sculptural fountains than any other discovered in <name type="place">Pompeii</name>. The lead pipes that furnished the water for these fountains can still be seen.</figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Urban Gardens</hi></hi></head><p>This growing design sophistication is apparent not only in the remains of Roman public buildings and public spaces, but also in the decoration and landscaping of the Roman homes and gardens unearthed by archaeologists. At <name type="place">Pompeii</name> and <name type="place">Herculaneum</name>, the houses of a prosperous merchant class reveal many fine wall paintings and the remains of once-beautiful gardens. The Hellenistic peristyle court provided the design prototype for these peristyle gardens, but whereas the former was surfaced with beaten earth or paving stones, the latter were lush with vegetation (fig. 2.29).</p><p>During the Roman imperial period, beginning with the reign of <name type="pname">Augustus</name> in the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, the construction of an aqueduct had an important effect on the standard of living in <name type="place">Campania</name>, the land on the slopes of <name type="place">Mount Vesuvius</name>. An ample water supply made possible the construction of large public baths as well as curbside fountains on the major streets of its cities, and pools and large gardens at its villas. Irrigation benefited the flower and perfume industry of <name type="place">Pompeii</name> and allowed the planting of greater numbers of perennials and shrubs in gardens than heretofore, since these need more frequent watering than do deep-rooted trees (fig. 2.30). The small villa on the Via dell'Abbondanza, formerly referred to as the House of Loreius Tiburtinus and more recently as the House of Octavius Quartio, provides an example of a<pb n="84"/><pb n="84" type="orig"/><q><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">A Roman Garden</hi></hi></q><figure xml:id="fig-75"><graphic url="CH2_033.jpg"/><figDesc>2.31. Garden Canal (<hi rend="italic">Euripus</hi>), House of Octavius Quartio, <name type="place">Pompeii</name></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-76"><graphic url="CH2_034.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 2.32. House and Garden of Octavius Quartio (formerly called the House of Loreius Tiburtinus), Via dell'Abbondanza, <name type="place">Pompeii</name>. 3rd century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, remodeled with garden extension after earthquake in 62 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> This handsome house, with its large garden stretching the length of the block, was located near the amphitheater. It was converted into an inn, as were other fine old homes in the vicinity during the economically declining years preceding the catastrophe of 79 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> when <name type="place">Pompeii</name> was buried under a rain of volcanic ash from the eruption of <name type="place">Mount Vesuvius</name>. Besides serving as a hotel for the visitors who came to see the gladiatorial games at the amphitheater, it offered, as a modern hotel might, a hospitable place to give a party when one did not have a large enough house in which to entertain friends.</figDesc></figure><q><hi rend="bold">A</hi>t the back of the house, built upon a porticoed terrace overlooking the garden, is a masonry <hi rend="italic">biclinium</hi> <hi rend="bold">B</hi> of two parallel couches, a less usual configuration than the U-shaped <hi rend="italic">triclinium</hi>, or three-person couch arrangement, where upper-class adults typically took their meals. Here the terrace <hi rend="italic">biclinium</hi> set under a vine-covered pergola, consists of a niche framed by two columns and decorated with rocks and seashells, and a small pool upon which servants floated food placed in ornamental dishes. The pool faces a <hi rend="italic">euripus</hi>, a canal running the length of the terrace <hi rend="bold">C</hi>, which was lined with sculptures. This canal may have received water from a fountain in the niche, although no pipes have yet been found.</q><q>The <hi rend="italic">euripus</hi> is crossed in two places by footbridges, one in front of the <hi rend="italic">biclinium</hi> where servants would have stood during meals, and another facing a large fresco-decorated room, which was probably a <hi rend="italic">triclinium</hi>. This footbridge faces a small temple surmounting a <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi> <hi rend="bold">D</hi> and connects the terrace with the garden. Jets of water poured from the stepped base of the temple onto an apron of random-cut paving stones in front of this footbridge, before draining into the <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi> below. At the west end of the terrace there was a <hi rend="italic">zoothecula</hi> <hi rend="bold">A</hi>, a pleasant retiring room where sated diners could nap or relax while looking back across the <hi rend="italic">euripus</hi> and the landscaped terrace.</q><q>Below the temple, water spilled down three steps and flowed into another <hi rend="italic">euripus</hi> <hi rend="bold">E</hi> perpendicular to the one along the terrace and extending the entire length of the garden (see fig. 2.31). This stream is punctuated by a pergola-shaded pool containing an elaborate <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi>-fountain <hi rend="bold">F</hi> designed to make the water falling into the pool <hi rend="bold">E</hi> below ripple and shimmer. Farther along the <hi rend="italic">euripus</hi> there is a second, smaller, temple <hi rend="bold">G</hi>, the optical effect of which, when viewed from in front of the first, is to increase the impression of the garden's size. At the far end of the garden <hi rend="italic">euripus</hi> is another pergola-shaded pool <hi rend="bold">H</hi>.</q><pb n="85"/><pb n="85" type="orig"/>Pompeian garden organized around a series of pools and fountains (figs. 2.31, 2.32).</p><p>Wall paintings and mosaics expressed the ancient Roman's love of nature. Few houses, even outside the apartment-filled metropolis, had extensive gardens like that of the one on the Via dell'Abbondanza, and <hi rend="italic">trompe-l'oeil</hi> paintings of garden scenery were frequently used to extend the illusion of garden space. Though weather and the bombing of several Italian cities during World War II have taken a severe toll on many of these fragile frescoes, a number of tantalizing fragments remain. They show how in some cases an axial view from the atrium into the peristyle garden was prolonged by <hi rend="italic">trompe-l'oeil</hi>_paintings on a rear wall. Attached columns framing these delightful garden scenes made them appear to be natural views seen from a portico. The well-known fresco from the Villa of Livia at suburban <name type="place">Prima Porta</name> was painted as a continuous mural on the four walls of a sunken chamber built as a retreat from the summer heat (fig. 2.33). Here an illusory garden, painted against an azure background, evokes the shrubs, flowers, fountains, birds, and white-painted lattice fencing found in actual Roman gardens of the period.</p><p>Garden paintings often decorated small courtyards and light wells. In addition to these straightforward representations of fountains, flora, and fauna, two other illusionistic subjects&#x2014;the sacro-idyllic landscape and the villa landscape&#x2014;were painted on the walls of Roman houses. The Roman architect and engineer <name type="pname">Vitruvius</name> (active 46&#x2013;30 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) writes of the "images of the gods, or the representations of legends" contained in sacro-idyllic paintings, that is, paintings of gods and other figures in an empyrean landscape. Somewhat more realistic, but closely related in spirit were paintings of villas and porticoes set within a landscape depicting "harbors, headlands, shores, rivers, springs, straits, temples, groves, hills, cattle, shepherds."<ref target="#CH2-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref> These frequently contained figures engaged in rural pursuits such as fishing and hunting. A painting of this type is found on the south wall of the garden in the House of the Little Fountain at <name type="place">Pompeii</name> (fig. 2.34).</p><figure xml:id="fig-77"><graphic url="CH2_035.jpg"/><figDesc>2.33. Detail from a garden scene, wall painting from Villa of Livia at <name type="place">Prima Porta</name>, near <name type="place">Rome</name>. Late 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-78"><graphic url="CH2_036.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.34. House of the Little Fountain, <name type="place">Pompeii</name>. 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>From all this, we can see how, using a standardized architectural vocabulary, Roman builders composed their urban designs in predictable yet highly satisfying ways. The pleasing recombination of conventional geometric forms; the shaping of space around ritual activities and the concomitant use of axial composition and symmetry to enforce notions of order, stability, and place; a love of illusion and theatrical effects; and a sensory approach to physical comfort and aesthetic delight were the attributes of Roman urban design. Through <hi rend="italic">centuriation</hi>, significant portions of nature had become firmly subjugated to Roman order, and now domesticated landscape was to be found within the peristyle garden as well as in the surrounding countryside. We can expect to find these same principles and practices in Roman villas of the Age of <name type="pname">Augustus</name> (27 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>&#x2014;14 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) and during the reigns of the emperors who succeeded him.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb n="86"/><pb n="86" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">IV. Garden and Villa: The Art of Landscape in <name type="place">Ancient Rome</name></hi></hi></head><p>The ideal of a second home in the country, a retreat for what the Romans called <hi rend="italic">otium</hi>&#x2014;a kind of industrious leisure comprised of worthwhile mental and physical pursuits away from the distractions of urban business, politics, and society&#x2014;has exerted a strong appeal in various cultures throughout history. While writers from Horace to <name type="pname">Thomas Jefferson</name> extolled rural values and the wholesome simplicity of rural life, their lives in the country did not require them to engage in rustic toil. Much as they admired the farmer, their affluence and broad intellectual horizons enabled them to adopt an aesthetic attitude different from that of the plowman with his hard daily labors performed under the hot sun.</p><p>Like the term <hi rend="italic">country house</hi>, the word <hi rend="italic">villa</hi> stands for a social ideal as well as an architectural form, connoting a vision of the good life, a life free of sordid care and pecuniary want. But in Republican times and also for those Romans who, like Virgil, romantically yearned for the imagined goodness and simplicity of a pre-Imperial age, the chief purpose of villa life was fruitful husbandry. The <hi rend="italic">villa rustica</hi> is the earliest villa form, ideologically supported by Roman poets, including Virgil, who wrote the <hi rend="italic">Eclogues</hi>, his great pastoral poem, and the <hi rend="italic">Georgics</hi>, a poetic treatise on agriculture, in the second half of the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> For Virgil, the <hi rend="italic">villa rustica</hi> connoted a Golden Age of peace and plenty, and in extolling the virtues of agrarian life, he promoted a kind of Jeffersonian ideal of the independent farmer whose industry can bring a return to simple ancient values.</p><p>This idealistic vision, however, did not match economic and social reality. Many small farmers never returned to the land after being driven away during the Punic Wars in the third and second centuries <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Pillaging armies and the competition of slave labor and cheap imported produce caused the collapse of the old agrarian way of life. The process was completed during the years of civil strife that occurred in the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> when victorious partisans confiscated the properties of the defeated. At the same time, landowners converted land from the cultivation of grain and other crops for domestic consumption to ranches for cattle and sheep grazing and to plantations for wine and oil production.</p><p>The owners of these <hi rend="italic">latifundia</hi>, or large rural establishments, were for the most part city-bred, operating their landholdings for profit with slave labor. If the proprietor was in residence for part of the year, as was often the case, he built for his use a house similar to the ones found at <name type="place">Pompeii</name> and Herculaneum. Because in plan it followed the form of city houses, it was classified a <hi rend="italic">villa urbana</hi>, to distinguish it from the <hi rend="italic">villa rustica</hi>. The two were, nevertheless, usually merged into a single block that was easier to fortify and defend than widely separated structures would have been. Security and practicality, as opposed to aesthetics, thus dominated the architectural character of such country villas as the one in <name type="place">Boscoreale</name> near <name type="place">Pompeii</name>, dating from the beginning of the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, where wine pressing and storage facilities, together with barns and stables, were united within the same walls as a commodious house for the proprietor (fig. 2.35).</p><figure xml:id="fig-79"><graphic url="CH2_037.jpg"/></figure><p>A third villa type, the <hi rend="italic">villa suburbana</hi>, was, as its name implies, one located on the outskirts of the city. In addition, there was the <hi rend="italic">villa marittima</hi>, the seaside villa that became a popular pleasure resort for wealthy Romans in the Imperial Age. The entire area around the <name type="place">Bay of Naples</name> was ringed with the kind of porticoed seaside villas seen in landscape paintings of the period (fig. 2.36).</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Pliny's Villas</hi></hi></head><p>To understand better the villa as a building type during these times of Roman power and prosperity, generations of architectural historians have turned to the letters of Pliny the Younger, a wealthy landowner in the<pb n="87"/><pb n="87" type="orig"/>first century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Pliny was the owner of both a <hi rend="italic">villa marittima</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">villa urbana</hi>. Although <name type="pname">Laurentinum</name>, his maritime villa, was only seventeen miles outside of <name type="place">Rome</name> at <name type="pname">Vicus Augustanus</name>, it offered the same kind of opulent and luxurious life many other members of the Roman aristocracy enjoyed along the beautiful Campanian shore around Naples. In his letter regarding it, he describes its axial sequence of rooms, framed by views of the sea on one end and mountains on the other:<q>There is an atrium at the entrance, simple but not drab, then a <hi rend="italic">porticus</hi> in the shape of the letter "D" which surrounds a small but cheerful court. This makes a fine retreat in bad weather, being protected by windows and still more by the overhanging roof. Opposite the center is the cheerful <hi rend="italic">cavaedium</hi>, and then a rather lovely <hi rend="italic">triclinium</hi>, which runs out toward the shore and, when the sea is whipped up by the southwest wind, is lightly washed by the breaking waves. It has folding doors and windows of equal width so that on the sides and front it seems to command, as it were, three seas. At the rear it looks back through the <hi rend="italic">cavaedium</hi>, with its colonnade, the portico behind, and the atrium onto the woods and distant mountains.<ref target="#CH2-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref></q></p><figure xml:id="fig-80"><graphic url="CH2_038.jpg"/><figDesc>2.36. Fresco painting of a harbor with seaside villas, from <name type="place">Stabiae</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name></figDesc></figure><p>In addition, this luxurious retreat had a series of steam-heated bedrooms off the large dining room where one could retire for a nap after dinner. There were also a gymnasium, two steam rooms, hot and cold baths, a large swimming pool overlooking the sea, and a ball court. In a separate part of the villa, a towered suite contained another dining room with a view of the shoreline and other villas to the north, as well as several more heated bedrooms, presumably for guests. Many windows overlooked a terrace garden on the seaward side, and perhaps half as many opposite faced a flower and vegetable garden. Pliny's own favorite spot at this villa was the <hi rend="italic">heliocaminus</hi>, a small heated sunroom where, even on a winter day, he could sunbathe. Adjacent to this amenity was a small suite of private rooms to which he could retire and enjoy the spectacular view in all directions.</p><p>Like wealthy people who today have vacation homes both at the beach and in the mountains, Pliny had, in addition to <name type="pname">Laurentinum</name>, <name type="pname">Tusci</name>, a villa in Tus<pb n="88"/><pb n="88" type="orig"/>cany on the southern slopes of the Apennines overlooking the Tiber. It was to this <hi rend="italic">villa urbana</hi> that he went in the summer to study and write and, with the labor of slaves, to tend his vineyards and other crops. Here he could gaze at an "immense amphitheatre which only nature could create." There, as he described it:<q>The broad plain is ringed by mountains on the crown of which are ancient stands of tall trees, and various kinds of hunting may be found there. &#x2026; It is a voluptuous experience to look down on this scene from the mountain. You seem to be seeing not real land but rather a painted scene of exceptional beauty, and wherever the eye turns it is refreshed by its variety and precision.<ref target="#CH2-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref></q></p><p>In this spectacular landscape, Pliny created a setting of elegance and luxury akin to that of his seaside villa. There were baths with pools of varying temperatures, comfortable bedrooms, dining suites, peristyle gardens, and promenades. In addition, there was a large hippodrome-shaped garden filled with evergreen and deciduous trees, including various kinds of fruit trees and boxwood topiary in all manner of shapes, probably including the owner's monogram, a popular practice in Pliny's day. In his letter describing his Tusci villa, Pliny mentions other features of this garden: obelisks, roses, and green lawns as well as a central section designed to imitate wild nature. At the curved end of the "hippodrome," there was a <hi rend="italic">stibadium</hi>, or semicircular dining couch with water flowing beneath it. It faced a small pool that served as a basin upon which servants floated dishes toward Pliny and his guests. Behind this arrangement stood a pavilion with a fountain in the center and an alcove bedroom. This one, open to the garden, was entirely faced with marble. It must have been pleasant to lie there in the filtered green light listening to the sounds of birds and the murmurous waters of the fountain.</p><figure xml:id="fig-81"><graphic url="CH2_039.jpg"/><figDesc>2.37. Plan of Villa of <name type="place">Poppaea</name>, <name type="place">Oplontis</name>, a residental suburb of <name type="place">Pompeii</name> (modern Torre Annunziata). 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> with rebuilding and replanting of garden after earthquake in 62 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Within the garden is a diagonal pathway, which is presumably mirrored by a corresponding diagonal path now buried under the pathway along the western edge of the villa. The two diagonal paths would have met a central path at a point that lies under the as-yet-unexcavated volanic debris. It is logical that two other diagonal paths radiated from this point, making the garden rectangular in shape.</figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Villas of the Campanian Plain</hi></hi></head><p>Several architects and historians have given graphic representation to Pliny's descriptions of his two villas, but the archaeological remains have not been identified. At the archaeological site of <name type="place">Oplontis</name>, near <name type="place">Herculaneum</name> on the slopes of <name type="place">Mount Vesuvius</name>, however, one can visit an excavated villa near the coast of Campania that was built and remodeled between the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and the eruption of 79 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> (fig. 2.37). The villa may once have been owned by the emperor <name type="pname">Nero</name>'s second wife Poppaea Sabina, hence its name, the Villa of Poppaea.</p><p>At one end, a monumental pedimented door overlooks a large exterior ornamental garden. Root cavities in the garden reveal hedges, likely of box. Four <hi rend="italic">herms</hi> were placed among plants, probably oleanders. There were, in addition, four sculptural fountains in the shape of centaurs. The villa also has an east wing in which were located four small interior gardens. The apparent size of these charming gardens was increased by wall paintings of vines, fountains, flowers, and birds (fig. 2.38).</p><p>Another attractive garden lies to the south of a large swimming pool measuring 56 feet in width and,<pb n="89"/><pb n="89" type="orig"/>according to excavations to date, 165 feet in length (17 meters wide and more than 50 meters long). This garden could be enjoyed through the open windows of a <hi rend="italic">diaeta</hi>, or livingroom, here designed specifically for enjoying framed views of horticultural or natural landscape vistas. To the east of the swimming pool, and a few feet below it, thirteen statuary bases have been discovered in a garden of uncertain extent. Root casts prove that some of the trees in this garden were lemon trees.</p><p>The Villa of Poppaea at <name type="place">Oplontis</name>, like Pliny's Laurentinum and Tusci, shows that, by the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, the villa was less important as an agricultural establishment and instead was used increasingly as a place for <hi rend="italic">otium</hi>, or refined leisure. In its extensive use of colonnaded porticoes on the outside and its opening of axes to embrace wide vistas beyond the villa itself, it demonstrates the same strong aesthetic appreciation of nature found in Pliny's letters.</p><p>Not far from <name type="place">Oplontis</name>, still buried beneath the hard volcanic ash that covered Herculaneum and nearby parts of the Campanian plain, is the Villa of the Papyri, named for the more than two thousand charred scrolls that were discovered in <date when="1754">1754</date> in one part of its library. <name type="pname">J. Paul Getty</name> built his museum in <name type="place">Malibu</name>, <name type="place">California</name>, in the early <date when="1970">1970</date>s using the plan drawn by <name type="pname">Karl Weber</name>, a Swiss engineer who oversaw the systematic excavation of the villa's rooms during the eighteenth century. For students of ancient gardens, this original Getty Museum provides an instructive modern replica of ancient villa design and gives one a feeling for the colorful ostentation of floors, walls, and ceilings of such villas before time and catastrophe took their toll. There is an inner peristyle garden modeled after the one built in the first phase of the villa's construction during the second century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, as well as a much larger peristyle garden that copies the one added in the following century. Within the latter, set within the boxwood compartments surrounding a 218-foot- (66.5meter-) long pool, are replicas of many of the statues that Weber found.</p><figure xml:id="fig-82"><graphic url="CH2_040.jpg"/><figDesc>2.38. Fresco from Villa of Poppaea, <name type="place">Oplontis</name>. 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Grotto of Tiberius</hi></hi></head><p>Unfortunately for posterity, there are few other remains from the great villa-building period of the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, when the economic prosperity and security of the empire made this kind of construction possible. However, one such villa, a fascinating combination of water, sculpture, and outdoor entertaining, has come to light in recent years: the so-called Grotto of Tiberius at <name type="place">Sperlonga</name> along the Via Flacca, the shore road between Terracina and Gaeta, famous for its villas. Uncovered around <date when="1960">1960</date> during the course of highway construction, the villa, which incorporates into its plan a natural seaside cave, provides a provocative glimpse of the pleasures enjoyed by wealthy Romans in imperial times.</p><p>It is also a testament to the fact that by this period the grotto's function as a holy place was only a dim legacy from the days when people made pilgrimages to cave sanctuaries to worship in nature. Sophisticated Romans now preferred to treat landscape in terms of a poetic and theatrical ideal. Why should not a real grotto serve as the setting for the enactment in sculpture of a favorite Homeric tale, <name type="pname">Odysseus</name>'s visit to the cave of the one-eyed giant Polyphemus?</p><p><name type="pname">Odysseus</name> and his men, imprisoned by the Cyclops in his cave, saved themselves by ramming a sharpened stake into the drunken monster's single eye. This part of the <name type="pname">Odysseus</name> legend formed the theme of an elaborate decoration of the <name type="place">Sperlonga</name> grotto, whose builder is assumed, on the basis of a fragmentary inscription, to have been one Faustinus, a landowner and friend of the poet Martial who lived in the second half of the first century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The cave and its adjacent <hi rend="italic">villa marittima</hi> are close to the scarred cliff face where, according to the Roman historians <name type="pname">Tacitus</name> and <name type="pname">Suetonius</name>, a huge chunk of rock overhanging the entrance to the cave suddenly broke off and fell during a banquet, endangering the life of Tiberius (ruled 14&#x2013;37 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) and thereby conferring on posterity the association of this emperor's name with the grotto.</p><p>The grotto at <name type="place">Sperlonga</name> is a purposeful extension of Hellenistic theatricality through a dramatic combination of landscape, architecture, and sculpture. The cave, hollowed from the cliff by wave action, has been extended architecturally into the landscape (fig. 2.39). Its mouth formerly originated on a spur of the rocky cliff into which was set a huge Hellenistic sculptural<pb n="90"/><pb n="90" type="orig"/>composition depicting <name type="pname">Odysseus</name>'s ship trying to pass through the Strait of Messina, where the sea monster Scylla lay in wait to ensnare travelers in its snakelike coils. This work and others from the grotto have been attributed to <name type="pname">Agesander</name>, <name type="pname">Athenodorus</name>, and <name type="pname">Polydorus</name>, the three Rhodian sculptors who are believed to have created <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Laoc&#x00F6;on</name> and His Sons</hi>, that famous work of Hellenistic sculpture now in the Museo Pio Clementino, one of the <name type="place">Vatican</name> museums. Stylistically, there is certainly a resemblance in the forceful bodies, violent movement, and anguished expressions characteristic of these pieces. But whereas the <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Laoc&#x00F6;on</name></hi> group is nearly intact, the Polyphemus sculptures were badly smashed by zealous Christians when they erected a medieval church on the site. A small museum now houses some of their fragments and several small, charming late Hellenistic sculptures of children that may have decorated the sides of fountains and pools (fig. 2.40).</p><figure xml:id="fig-83"><graphic url="CH2_041.jpg"/><figDesc>2.39. Reconstructed plan, after Eugenia Salza Prina Ricotti. The outlines of the original over-hanging entrance to the cave are defined by line <hi rend="bold">X</hi>-<hi rend="bold">Y</hi>. The Polyphemus sculptural group was set within the stony ledge of the back of the cave <hi rend="bold">A</hi>. Ricotti has also deduced that the round pool <hi rend="bold">B</hi> represented Charybdis, the eddy that helped Scylla destroy seafarers, and that a lateral grotto <hi rend="bold">C</hi> was used alternatively as an additional triclinium, a stage upon which actors, dancers, and musicians could entertain the banqueters, and as a place where guests could assemble and refresh themselves before or after a party. There are, in addition, three alcoves <hi rend="bold">D</hi> to which sated diners could retire for a nap.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-84"><graphic url="CH2_042.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 2.40. Polyphemus group, <name type="place">Sperlonga</name> Museum. 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> More than 7,000 marble fragments have been discovered at <name type="place">Sperlonga</name>, the most important of which belong to several large sculptural compositions depicting various episodes from <name type="pname">Homer</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>. Four such groupings have been identified: <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Odysseus</name> Rescuing Achilles's Corpse</hi>, placed at the mouth of the cave; <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Odysseus</name> with Diomedes and the Palladion</hi>, to the right of this scene; the wreck of <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Odysseus</name>'s Ship Encountering Scylla</hi>, set in the circular pool; and the <hi rend="italic">Blinding of Polyphemus</hi> (shown here), naturalistically positioned inside the grotto to the south of the pool.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-85"><graphic url="CH2_043.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 2.41. Island <hi rend="italic">triclinium</hi>, <name type="place">Sperlonga</name>. 1st century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>A <hi rend="italic">triclinium</hi> for outdoor banqueting stood in the center of a fish pond. The Romans were passionately fond of ornamental fish and, in addition to keeping fish as pets, they also had ponds that served as holding tanks for the table. Today the water level of the pond has lowered, and one can clearly see the holes for rock fish in its sides as well as the island <hi rend="italic">triclinium</hi> where the dining couches were raised above the water upon which servants floated dishes to the recumbent guests (fig. 2.41). This luxurious resort gives one an idea of the wealth of the Roman Empire. But if we are impressed by Faustinus's standard of living and style of entertaining, we are awestruck when we contemplate the remains of the second-century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> villa at <name type="place">Tivoli</name>.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa</hi></hi></head><p>Since the sixteenth century, tourists, artists, architects, and archaeologists have been fascinated by the spectral ruins of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa. Set where the hilly slopes and precipitous gorges cut by the river Aniene, the principal tributary of the Tiber, meet the rolling Campagna plain below the town of <name type="place">Tivoli</name> (Tibur in Roman times), <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa is estimated to have been approximately 300 acres (120 hectares), or slightly<pb n="91"/><pb n="91" type="orig"/>more than one-third the size of <name type="place">New York City's Central Park</name>. This sprawling complex of broken vaults, collapsed domes, crumbling mosaic pavements, and fractured columns, covers an undulating terrain defined by two valleys with a southeast-northwest orientation. It was built between 118 and 138 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, the year of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s death. Although he was abroad for several extended periods during its construction (a philhellene, he spent the winters of 124/125 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> and 131/132 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> in <name type="place">Athens</name>), it may be assumed that <name type="pname">Hadrian</name> often thought about the project as he commissioned copies of ancient sculptures from Greek artists or corresponded with his architects on various aspects of the villa's design.</p><p>In plan and scale it suggests something far grander than the usual villa (fig. 2.42). The ruins are those of large banqueting halls and gardens, theaters and baths, grottoes and pools, private apartments, and quarters for many servants and guests. <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa has sometimes been compared with <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>'s seventeenth-century gardens at <name type="place">Versailles</name>. Similarities include the grandeur and scale of each project, both rulers' desire for a court setting away from the capital, and their personal involvement in the design process. Both used the landscape as a lavish entertainment site and as a means of advertising the richness and depth of their respective cultures. There is, however, a notable design difference. Hierarchical axes order the composition of the gardens of <name type="place">Versailles</name>; <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa, on the other hand, has no principal organizing axis, but rather a series of independent ones that sometimes collide obliquely. Its general plan comprises several independently organized building and garden complexes, each of which embodies the Aristotelian notion of place&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">topos</hi>&#x2014;as defined and contained space. To infer that <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa is simply a series of discrete <hi rend="italic">topoi</hi> and had no overall plan, however, is erroneous. Extensive terracing and a complex infrastructure of underground service routes extending over a large portion of the site indicate a comprehensive vision from the start.</p><p>Though heavily ransacked for building materials in the Middle Ages and robbed by Renaissance popes and connoisseurs of much of its opulent decoration of carved marble, gilded bronze, and ornamental fountains, the villa is nonetheless a text that, with the assistance of recent scholarship, can be read as the summation of imperial Roman architectural expression.<ref target="#CH2-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> More than that, it can be understood as a brilliant essay in Greco-Roman bonding, for <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>, as we have seen, greatly admired Greek culture and was responsible for the civic revival of <name type="place">Athens</name>.</p><p>Although it pays tribute to the greatness of the Classical past, the villa was for <name type="pname">Hadrian</name> a laboratory of architectural innovation. He had the educated eye of a well-traveled connoisseur and oversaw with great particularity the designs he commissioned. Like a present-day theme park, it was eclectically programmed. But unlike a theme park, which is designed to nourish the fantasies of popular culture, <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa was the product of intense personal passion and extensive scholarship. It was a vast and glittering private landscape of allusion filled with indirect references to other places and events in the panoramic sweep of empire as well as to the gods, goddesses, and heroes of the Greco-Roman pantheon. Because the emperor was under no constraint to conform to normative building conventions and was therefore able to push Roman design idioms to expressive heights, the villa should be read as his personal building project, one in which his taste and decisions governed even minute details of decoration as well as creative new spatial volumetrics.</p><p>Like his predecessor, <name type="pname">Nero</name>, <name type="pname">Hadrian</name> disliked the old imperial palaces on <name type="place">Rome</name>'s <name type="place">Palatine Hill</name>. But whereas <name type="pname">Nero</name> had tried to build his fabulous <name type="place">Domus Aurea</name>, or <name type="place">Golden House</name>, in the center of <name type="place">Rome</name>, causing the populace to revolt because of his indiscriminate expropriations of property, <name type="pname">Hadrian</name> chose to carry on his immense building project away from the public eye. Seventeen miles east of <name type="place">Rome</name>, <name type="place">Tivoli</name> was already populated with the kind of aristocratic villas described by Pliny. Most of these were located on the hilly slopes overlooking the Campagna plain, where the Aniene cut a steep gorge and dropped in a dramatic waterfall.</p><p><name type="pname">Hadrian</name> did not, as might have been expected, choose a site for the villa on the wooded heights of <name type="place">Tivoli</name>. Rather, he located it on the flat land 2&#x00BD; miles below the town. This choice, less cool and less inherently scenic than such sites as that of the steeply pitched Renaissance Villa d'Este in the heart of <name type="place">Tivoli</name>, can be explained by the fact that the finest land above was already occupied and a prior villa in the lower location may have been the property of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s wife, <name type="pname">Sabina</name>. The location may also be explained by the ease with which water could be furnished in copious amounts from one of the four aqueducts traversing this region en route to metropolitan <name type="place">Rome</name>.</p><p>More than a country retreat, <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s villa is a thematic summation of the philhellenic emperor's meditation upon the vast, rich, mature civilization over which he ruled. A feat of Roman engineering requiring monumental earth-moving, terracing, and the laying of water lines and other necessary elements of infrastructure, the villa admirably served <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s objective: to create a park that was its own allusive, experiential place of history and cultural memory, an idealized statement of the Greco-Roman heritage. He achieved this through a series of loosely linked archi<pb n="92"/><pb n="92" type="orig"/><q><hi rend="bold"><name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s villa</hi></q><figure xml:id="fig-86"><graphic url="CH2_044.jpg"/><figDesc>2.42. Plan of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa, <name type="place">Tivoli</name>. 118&#x2013;138 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc><p><hi rend="bold">A</hi> North Theater. <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Temple of Venus. <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Library Court. <hi rend="bold">D</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nymphaeum</hi> (Marine Theater). <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Peristyle Pool. <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Canopus</p></figure><figure xml:id="fig-87"><graphic url="CH2_045.jpg"/><figDesc>2.43. Semi-circular Dining Couch <hi rend="italic">(stibadium)</hi>, Canopus, <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa</figDesc></figure><pb n="93"/><pb n="93" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-88"><graphic url="CH2_046.jpg"/><figDesc>2.44. Plan of Scenic Canal and <hi rend="italic">Triclinium</hi>, also called the Canopus. 118&#x2013;138 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> The northwest end of the canal is semicircular. Sculptures placed between columns and pergolas lined the long sides of this canal set within a draw with steep terraced embankments. Its axis was terminated in the large half-dome at the southeast end. This impressive structure, its interior wall once encrusted with mosaic and undulating in a series of alternating radial gores, served as the backdrop for a <hi rend="italic">stibadium</hi>, a semicircular dining couch (fig. 2.43). This <hi rend="italic">stibadium</hi> was rimmed with water, and circular sockets near its base held bronze serving tables. In front of it was space for additional wooden dining couches; these faced a semicircular pool upon which servants floated banquet dishes.</figDesc></figure><q>A honeycomb of small chambers lightened the structure of the canopied vault. The eight at the lower level are faced on the inside of the vault with niches, four for sculpture and four for sets of miniature stairs designed to animate the flow of small water cascades within them. These alternating pairs were interrupted in the center of the vault by an arched opening. Here, barely visible from a distance, the principal axis of the entire Canal-<hi rend="italic">Triclinium</hi> landscape composition drives to its apsidal conclusion in the hillside in a brilliantly conceived grotto. A stone platform, accessible through a series of side chambers, carries one into this <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi>, the walls of which have niches for sculpture. Only the area above the platform is roofed with a barrel vault, leaving two large openings for light to enter this deeply recessed chamber.</q><q>Water channeled by twin aqueduct spurs flowed into the grotto, filling the pools beneath the stone platform. Distributed through a system of pipes, the water cascaded over marble and mosaic and into other channels and pools until it reached the canal.</q><figure xml:id="fig-89"><graphic url="CH2_047.jpg"/><figDesc>2.45. "Marine Theater," <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa. 118&#x2013;138 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc></figure><pb n="94"/><pb n="94" type="orig"/>tectural "events" in which experience was heightened by sequential discovery. These consisted of a number of centrally focused landscapes framed by spatially complex monumental architecture, such as that of the Scenic Canal and Triclinium, often called the Canopus,<ref target="#CH2-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref> a long, partially colonnaded canal terminated by a large hooded vault near the Vestibule, or main entrance hall, which served as a dramatic banqueting setting (figs. 2.45, 2.46). No certain assignment of function has been made for the Island Enclosure, a canal-and-column-encircled space of ingenious design that for many years bore the conventional label "Marine Theater," but its ornamentation, like that of the Canopus, was planned according to a program of allusion that exemplified cosmopolitan Roman culture and its Greek antecedents (fig. 2.44). While serving this thematic end, the villa was also the equivalent of a contemporary spa hotel. There were exercise facilities for both staff and guests, and two baths, similar in design to Roman metropolitan ones with their sequence of hot, warm, and cold pools and rooms for oiling and massage.</p><p>Many of the connective elements that knit these parts into a comprehensive framework&#x2014;colonnades, pergolas, paths, and planting&#x2014;can only be guessed at today. A wealth of ornament and decorative detail, also vanished, helped to unite the whole into an artistic harmony. There were shimmering mosaics and surfaces of richly inlaid marble and a host of sculptural figures in marble and bronze. <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>, in addition to being a creative architectural thinker, was a connoisseur and patron of artists, owning a vast number of ancient Greek marbles and Roman copies of famous Greek sculptures. Sculptures of reclining river gods adorned the villa's many water gardens, and there were statues depicting Diana as mythological huntress and as a fertility goddess. Images of Perseus, Bacchus, Orpheus, Apollo, and other figures from classical mythology joined representations of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s beloved <name type="pname">Antinous</name>, who was portrayed in various godlike guises. These, with portrait busts of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name> himself, were probably placed in niches or beside some of the numerous garden paths of the villa.</p><p>The most important unifying factor is the one we miss most today: water. Hydraulic engineers were responsible for the fountains, pools, and canals that animated space with sky-reflecting mirrors of light. Standing at the Canopus today, we can only imagine the spectacle this part of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa presented when, with light playing on the curved and undulating surface of the moist, glittering, mosaic-covered halfdome and sparkling on the gently moving water of the canal, the most powerful ruler on earth looked out upon the proconsuls, ambassadors, and other dignitaries of the Roman Empire whose banqueting couches were arrayed before him.</p><p>Besides its function as place of entertainment, <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa served as a residence and place where the affairs of empire were dispatched. An original villa residence predating <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s purchase of the property was extensively revised to serve as imperial living quarters, and, inasmuch as the business of government followed the emperor wherever he went, the imperial secretariat required offices. Viewing structures, an East Belvedere and a West Belvedere, which overlooked valleys on respective sides of the property, served as scenic observation points and may have been destinations for conversational strolling.</p><p>For our purposes here&#x2014;the discussion of landscape as an expression of cultural values&#x2014;attention should be drawn to two parts of the villa: the "Vale of Tempe" with its Doric Temple overlooking the eastern valley at the northern end of the property, and the incompletely excavated high ground that is in private ownership, where the South Theater and a network of underground tunnels exist. Modern scholars believe that the steep gorge in the eastern valley of the villa grounds, which was further deepened through quarrying operations, memorialized the Vale of Tempe near <name type="place">Mount Olympus</name> in northeastern <name type="place">Greece</name>.<ref target="#CH2-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref> Dramatically situated above this beautiful spot, overlooking the wider landscape framed by the Tiburtine Hills, stands a small, circular, open-sided Doric garden temple enclosing a Roman copy of Praxiteles' famous statue of Aphrodite of Knidos (fig. 2.46). It was not a temple in any religious sense, but rather an ornamental structure framed by a large <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi> (now vanished), the whole composition forming an architectural tribute to a poetically venerated Greek landscape.</p><p>At the opposite end of the villa grounds was the South Theater, which, according to a recent thesis advanced by <name type="pname">William L. MacDonald</name> and <name type="pname">John A. Pinto</name>, may have accommodated the Eleusinian rites based upon the legend of Demeter and Persephone.<ref target="#CH2-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref> These mysteries, symbolizing immortality of the human soul as well as the annual cycle of death and rebirth in nature, were performed at <name type="place">Eleusis</name> near <name type="place">Athens</name> and involved ritual descent into the Underworld domain of the god Hades. An elaborate network of tunnels connects with the theater, whose complicated infrastructure exceeds the needs of ordinary drama. <name type="pname">MacDonald</name> and <name type="pname">Pinto</name> have suggested that ritual participants may have descended from the stage into these subterranean passages in an initiation ceremony. If this is correct, we may conclude that the replication of the experience one had at a famous religious center outside <name type="place">Athens</name> within an artfully contrived landscape of the Roman Campagna demonstrates that spiritual objectives previously met in unique natural environments to which one made pilgrimage could now be found in synthetic ones built<pb n="95"/><pb n="95" type="orig"/>to recall them.</p><p>The villa's role as a "themed" environment, one enriched by imaginative association with other renowned places, can best be understood in terms of a shift in the relationship between humans and landscape. In the cosmopolitan milieu of the Late Roman Empire it was natural that theatrical versions of earlier myth-impregnated environments should be constructed. Then, as later in history, the garden or park landscape provided an ideal setting for such imaginative re-creations.</p><p>We have seen how the concept of landscape was transformed in antiquity from one in which form directly referenced elements of Earth and sky in an expression of cosmological belief to one in which symbols and the mimesis of other locales set in motion within the human imagination certain ideas and associations. We have seen, too, how urban order came to assume a far greater importance relative to the natural order than was true in the centuries of prehistory and early antiquity.</p><p>The allegorization of landscape was perhaps the most important and lasting contribution that the Late Roman villa designers bequeathed to posterity. The "theming" of a passage from <name type="pname">Homer</name>, as at <name type="place">Sperlonga</name>, wed landscape to literature in a striking tableau; here nature served as stage set, a theater for fantasy. The simulated Hades at <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa was a "virtual reality" experience of its day in which emotion was manipulated toward a religious end&#x2014;if the subterranean galleries there were indeed used in celebrating the Eleusinian mysteries. Landscape had thus become something both more and less than nature. It now was space to be assigned programmatic content rather than place pregnant with intrinsic meaning. Henceforth, landscape design&#x2014;though sometimes purely functional or aesthetic in intent or merely imitative of earlier models&#x2014;was imbued with a narrative impulse. The narrative motive still prevails today in commercial theme parks and certain self-theming historic districts, villages, and old urban centers. Concepts of space and time are continually revised through the agencies of intellect and imagination. History has become a potent source of imagery as population growth and powerful Industrial Age technologies threaten both nature and the built past as never before. <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa is thus ancestor to numerous replications of geographically distant and temporally remote places in landscape design history, including the themed environments of today.</p><p>Ironically, at the same time that landscape was being domesticated and drained of the divinity that it had long embodied at various sacred sites in nature, allegory stood ready to put it into the service of two religious movements: Christianity and Islam. The use of water, sculpture, mosaic, and plants to evoke a spiritual or poetic mood; the interpenetration of indoor and outdoor spaces; a growing interest in architectural siting; a sensuous appreciation of light, color, and sound; topiary design and practice&#x2014;these are some of the things that Roman landscape designers bequeathed to future generations. Where they occupied former parts of the Roman Empire, Islamic garden designers incorporated some classical elements into their plans, blending them with their heritage from <name type="place">Persia</name>. But in the Christian West, life was thoroughly transformed in the centuries following the fall of <name type="place">Rome</name> and before the Renaissance. There no one any longer built villas with sybaritic bathing pools and gardens populated by mythological figures. Nor were there any luxurious town houses with indoor plumbing and gaily decorated fountains. <hi rend="italic">Triclinia</hi>_beneath vine-clad pergolas for long summer dinners disappeared.</p><p>Although luxury and license remained a prerogative of the aristocratic elite in Christian lands, people increasingly turned their eyes heavenward, and some exceptional monks even refused to eat the fruit they grew for fear of breaking their austere Christian vows. The worldly emphasis on three-dimensional space in architecture and painting was lost, but some of the old building forms, notably the peristyle garden, were too intrinsic a part of a basic building vocabulary to vanish completely. Most important, perhaps, the principal gardens after the fall of <name type="place">Rome</name> were no longer gardens in reality, but images of the earthly paradise that existed before the biblical fall of humankind or of the heavenly kingdom where the blessed could attain fruitful ease after the travails of this life.</p><figure xml:id="fig-90"><graphic url="CH2_048.jpg"/><figDesc>2.46. Doric Temple, "Vale of Tempe," <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa. 118&#x2013;138 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> This temple and its picturesque landscape, which echoes in form the larger nearby Temple of Vesta over-looking the dramatic gorge of the river Aniene, was the ancestor of many similar garden temples. The <hi rend="italic">tholos</hi>, or circular temple, became a standard feature in Western garden design of the eighteenth century and a common ornament in the nineteenth-century public park.</figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><pb n="96"/><pb n="96" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Two</hi></hi></head><note xml:id="CH2-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p>The term <hi rend="italic">classicism</hi> appears throughout this book. It refers to the human impulse in all the arts to create through a process of intellect&#x2014;rather than by intuition, emotion, or sensory association&#x2014;an ideal vision that by its nobility, authority, rationality, and harmonious order serves as a paradigm for imitation. These qualities are thought to have characterized the art and general culture of ancient <name type="place">Greece</name> and much of ancient <name type="place">Rome</name>, sources of inspiration to other cultures throughout history. Classicism thus respects tradition over innovation. In architecture and landscape architecture, classicism implies participation in a tradition of measurability and mathematical precision as expressed in balanced, geometrical lines and forms and symmetry, as opposed to irregularity and asymmetry. When the word is capitalized within a sentence, it refers to a specific period, seen by historians as mature and pivotal within a stylistic development. Examples include: the art of <name type="place">Greece</name> in the last three-quarters of the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, or the art created in Renaissance <name type="place">Italy</name> from about <date when="1505">1505</date> to about <date when="1525">1525</date>. <hi rend="italic">Neoclassicism</hi> refers to any of the many revival idioms that evoke the balance, order, symmetry, and stylistic simplicity of classicism, often imitating in period design or detail a style considered as Classical. For example, the BeauxArts style in American architecture and landscape design in the years around <date when="1900">1900</date> is neoclassical, being derived from the &#x00C9;cole des Beaux-Arts in <name type="place">Paris</name>, which based its curriculum upon the principles of French seventeenth-century design; in turn, those traced their origin to the Italian Renaissance and to the Classical monuments in Roman architecture.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p>An excellent explication of this thesis is to be found in <name type="pname">Fran&#x00E7;ois de Polignac</name>, <hi rend="italic">Cults, Territory, and the Origins of the Greek City-State</hi>, trans. <name type="pname">Janet Lloyd</name> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, <date when="1995">1995</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Indra Kagis McEwen</name> draws upon Polignac's text, <hi rend="italic">La naissance de la cit&#x00E9; greque</hi> (<name type="place">Paris</name>: <date when="1984">1984</date>) in <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Socrates</name>' Ancestor: An Essay on Architectural Beginnings</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge, Massachusetts</name>: MIT Press, <date when="1993">1993</date>) to extrapolate the metaphor of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> as "a surface woven by the activity of its inhabitants: the sequential building of sanctuaries over a period of time, which at times stretched over decades, and the subsequent ritual processions from center to urban limit to territorial limit and back again, in what can be seen as a kind of Ariadne's dance, magnified to cover a territory that was not called <hi rend="italic">choros</hi> but <hi rend="italic">chora</hi>," p. 81.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p>"To Pythian Apollo," <hi rend="italic">Hesiod: The Homeric Hymns and Homerica</hi>, trans. <name type="pname">H. G. Evelyn-White</name>, Loeb Classical Library (<name type="place">Cambridge, Massachusetts</name>: Harvard University Press, <date when="1914">1914</date>), p. 345. Apollo's slaying of the snake may be read as symbolizing the supplanting of the powerful snake-wielding earth goddess with a male divinity associated with the sky. The god's association with light, and hence with human reason, is underlined by the fact that acccording to the hymn "on that spot the power of piercing Helios [the sun god] made the monster rot away." Thus, according to <name type="pname">Vincent Scully</name>, "<name type="place">Delphi</name> must therefore have seemed to the Greeks the place where the conflict between the old way, that of the goddess of the earth, and the new way, that of men and their Olympian gods, was most violently manifest," an association he believes to be implied as well in the siting of the temple on a ledge beneath the hornlike, sky-piercing peaks of the Phaedriades, which tower over the temple and the adjacent the gorge from which flows the sacred Kastalian Spring. See <name type="pname">Vincent Scully</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Earth, the Temple, and the Gods: Greek Sacred Architecture</hi> (<name type="place">New Haven</name>: Yale University Press, rev. ed., <date when="1979">1979</date>),_p. 109.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p>The Golden Section is achieved by the division of a plane figure or a line in such a way that the smaller section or linear segment bears the same proportinate relationship to the larger as the larger does to the sum of the two, giving a ratio of approximately three to five. This ratio can also be expressed as a quotient of approximately 1.618 when the larger integer is divided by the smaller.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, <hi rend="italic">Politics</hi>, Book VII: 5. In <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>: The Revised Oxford Translation</hi>, ed. <name type="pname">Jonathan Barnes</name> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, <date when="1984">1984</date>), vol. 2, pp. 2105&#x2013;06.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p>_<hi rend="italic">Politics</hi>, Book VII: 11, vol. 2, pp. 2111&#x2013;12.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p>Polignac, <hi rend="italic">Cults, Territory</hi>, <hi rend="italic">and the Origins of the Greek City-State</hi>, p. 76.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p>Ibid., chap. 3.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">John Travlos</name>, <hi rend="italic">Pictorial Dictionary of Ancient <name type="place">Athens</name></hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Praeger, <date when="1971">1971</date>), pp. 1&#x2013;29, for text and plates showing the evolution and transformations of the Athenian Agora from the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> to the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">John M. Camp</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Athenian Agora: Excavations in the Heart of Classical <name type="place">Athens</name></hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: Thames and Hudson, <date when="1986">1986</date>), pp. 35&#x2013;38.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Spiro Kostoff</name>, <hi rend="italic">The City Shaped: Urban Patterns and Meanings Through History</hi> (<name type="place">Boston</name>: Little, Brown and Company, <date when="1991">1991</date>), p. 229.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Vitruvius</name>, <hi rend="italic">De Architectura</hi>, Book VII, Chapter V, sec. 2, trans. <name type="pname">Frank Granger</name>, Loeb Classical Library, <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">Vitruvius</hi></name> Vol. II (<name type="place">Cambridge, Massachusetts</name>: Harvard University Press, <date when="1934">1934</date>), p. 103.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p>See <hi rend="italic">The Letters of Pliny</hi>,_<name type="pname">A. N. Sherwin-White</name>, trans. (<name type="place">Oxford</name>: Oxford University Press, <date when="1966">1966</date>), pp. 186&#x2013;99. A <hi rend="italic">porticus</hi> is a colonnaded gallery or portico. A <hi rend="italic">cavaedium</hi> is an open quadrangular court formed by the inner walls of the house. The word <hi rend="italic">triclinium</hi> is used to mean a U-shaped arrangement of three dining couches, a dining room, or garden area for outdoor dining.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p>Ibid., pp. 321&#x2013;30.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p>As explained in Chapter Four, in the sixteenth century, <name type="pname">Pirro Ligorio</name>, architect to <name type="pname">Pope Pius IV</name> and <name type="pname">Cardinal Ippolito d'Este</name>, appreciated <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa as an archaeological site, excavating many works of art there, which he subsequently used to embellish villa gardens of his own design, including that of the nearby Villa d'Este.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p>The label Canopus for the Scenic Canal derives from the <hi rend="italic">Historia Augusta</hi>, a none-too-reliable late-fourth-century collection of imperial biographies: "[<name type="pname">Hadrian</name>] fashioned the Tiburtine Villa marvelously, in such a way that he might inscribe there the names of provinces and places most famous and could call [certain parts], for instance, the Lyceum, the Academy, the Prytaneum, Canopus, the Poecile, the [Vale of] Tempe. And in order to omit nothing, he even made an underworld." For a comprehensive inquiry into the assignment of this name to the Scenic Canal and Triclinium see <name type="pname">William L. MacDonald</name> and <name type="pname">John A. Pinto</name>, <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa and Its Legacy</hi>_(<name type="place">New Haven</name>: Yale University Press, <date when="1995">1995</date>), pp. 6&#x2013;7 and pp. 108&#x2013;11.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p>Ibid., p. 59.</p></note><note xml:id="CH2-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p>Ibid., pp. 124&#x2013;38.</p></note></div></div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>