<div type="chapter">
<pb n="125"/>
<pb n="125" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER FOUR CLASSICISM REBORN: LANDSCAPE IDEALS OF THE RENAISSANCE IN <name type="place">ITALY</name> AND <name type="place">FRANCE</name></hi></head>
<figure xml:id="fig-121">
<graphic url="CH4_001.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p>The wall surrounding the Renaissance garden eventually became, metaphorically, a shell to be cracked open. The confi-<lb/>
dence in human reason, which is a lasting legacy of the Renais-<lb/>
sance, profoundly changed humanity's view of nature. Throughout the period examined in this chapter, the garden remained visibly contained within walls. But the emphasis upon axial planning was a first step toward spatial thrust and the apparent extension of its boundaries to the horizon. Although the process of transformation into an outward-focused concept of landscape design was a slow one&#x2014;it began to be obvious only in the seventeenth century&#x2014;it had its origins in the cul-<lb/>
tural rebirth known as the Renaissance and the Neoplatonic separation of the real and the ideal, the world of humans and the world of God.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Dante Alighieri</name> (<date when="1265">1265</date>&#x2013;<date when="1321">1321</date>) prefigured a more expansive human view of landscape in <hi rend="italic">The Divine Comedy</hi>, in which the narrator begins his pilgrimage in a dark wood, guided&#x2014;signifi-<lb/>
cantly&#x2014;by the ancient Roman poet <name type="pname">Virgil</name> through a metaphys-<lb/>
ical landscape, which ultimately offers, after an ascent of Mount Purgatory, the exhilaration of panoramic perspective. <name type="pname">Petrarch</name>, figuratively following in <name type="pname">Dante</name>'s footsteps, attempted what was then unheard of, the actual ascent of Mont Ventoux, a hardship endured because, as he wrote to a friend, "My only motive was to see what so great an elevation had to offer." Here we have, quite literally, a new and much bolder human perspective of the terrestrial landscape than that of medieval individual who, with gaze turned inward, contemplated only the visionary landscape of paradise. <name type="pname">Petrarch</name>'s view from Mont Ventoux prefigures a shift in attitude toward landscape as a response to a new confi-<lb/>
dence in human powers of reason. The resulting liberation of science and the fostering of a spirit of open-ended inquiry found an expressive analogue in the design of actual contemporary landscapes as the inwardly focused, self-contained paradise gar-<lb/>
den gradually gave way to an expansive, outwardly directed, more worldly garden.</p>
<p>More specifically, we can see in the evolution of Renais-<lb/>
sance garden design a reflection of changing cosmological belief.<ref target="#CH4-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref> The humanist philosopher and mathematician <name type="pname">Nicolaus</name> of <name type="pname">Cusa</name> (<date when="1401">1401</date>&#x2013;<date when="1464">1464</date>) posited the concept of spatial neutrality&#x2014;that is, the notion that space is unbounded and the universe has no center&#x2014;a century before <name type="pname">Nicolaus Copernicus</name> (<date when="1473">1473</date>&#x2013;<date when="1543">1543</date>) developed his theory of planetary movement around the sun and two centuries before <name type="pname">Galileo</name> (<date when="1564">1564</date>&#x2013;<date when="1642">1642</date>) improved the tele-<lb/>
scope for astronomical use. In the West, the trend toward land-<lb/>
scape designs that portray seemingly unbounded garden space, tentative and partial at first but fully assured by the seventeenth century, mirrors the progress of cosmological thought from <name type="pname">Cusa</name> to <name type="pname">Ren&#x00E9; Descartes</name> (<date when="1596">1596</date>&#x2013;<date when="1650">1650</date>) as the old Aristotelian spatial paradigm was gradually abandoned and the foundations of modern physics were laid.</p>
<p>In addition to opening the door to modern science, Renais-<lb/>
sance humanism revived the classical forms and practices of antiquity. The publication in 1499 of the immensely influential <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi>, believed to be the work of the archaeologically minded <name type="pname">Francesco Colonna</name>, provided numer-<lb/>
ous illustrations depicting arbors, pavilions, colonnades, foun-<lb/>
tains, grottoes, <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi>, topiary, and other elements of a reinvented classical language specifically directed toward land-<lb/>
scape design (fig. 4.1). <hi rend="italic">De re aedificatoria</hi>, the influential treatise on architecture by <name type="pname">Leon Battista Alberti</name> (<date when="1404">1404</date>&#x2013;<date when="1472">1472</date>), published in 1452, provided a ready reference for a new generation of architects. They turned, as <name type="pname">Alberti</name> did, with reverential enthusi-<lb/>
asm to whatever could still be understood in the writings of the first-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> Roman architect and engineer <name type="pname">Vitruvius</name> and the visible remains of classical architecture&#x2014;the shells of old basilicas and baths, the broken columns of ancient temples and porticoes, the excavated decorative fragments of <name type="pname">Nero</name>'s Golden House and <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa near Tivoli. <name type="pname">Pliny</name> the Younger's
<pb n="126"/>
<pb n="126" type="orig"/>
descriptions of his first-century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Laurentinum and Tusci villas, available in manuscript form in the fifteenth century and pub-<lb/>
lished in 1506, promoted the Renaissance ideal of villa archi-<lb/>
tecture as well as the general notion among great families of the <hi rend="italic">villeggiatura</hi>, summer residence in the country (see Chapter Two).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-122">
<graphic url="CH4_002.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.1. Colonnade with topiary forms, <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili (The Strife of Love in a Dream)</hi>. Text and illustrations probably by <name type="pname">Francesco Colonna</name>. Woodcut from the 1561 French edition</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Using ancient practice as a guide in codifying their own building principles, Renaissance princes revived the use of axial symmetry, and they put their own stylistic stamp on many decorative motifs borrowed from ancient classical structures. In the powerful proportions of old Roman forms as well as in the rich vocabulary of antique classical ornament they found a means to ennoble humanity and to glorify certain men&#x2014;the princes of the Church as well as the secular rulers of the day. Like the ancient Romans, they built villas in the country as retreats from business life, places to cultivate the intellect and sometimes&#x2014;espe-<lb/>
cially in Tuscany and the Veneto, but also in <name type="place">Rome</name>&#x2014;the land.</p>
<p>Wealthy connoisseurs collected antiquities. Classical sculpt-<lb/>
ure, which had lain buried in the ground, was avidly unearthed, and several Renaissance villa gardens were designed as showcases for these works of art. But as there were insufficient ancient works to furnish all the gardens that were being built, Renaissance artists emulated the norms of antiquity in new sculpture and decoration.</p>
<p>The resurrection of ancient sculpture and the revival of antique forms re-established interest in classical deities, making profane sub-<lb/>
jects as important as sacred ones and as useful for artistic purposes. Gods and goddesses took up residence in the human imagination once again. Embraced by popes and cardinals, who interpreted "pagan" mythology as prefiguring Christian religion, the ancient divinities provided garden designers with a reinvented antique imag-<lb/>
ery and classical design vocabulary that superseded the Christian paradise imagery of the Middle Ages. Often these mythological fig-<lb/>
ures were symbolically allied with Christian ideals, as in the case of <name type="pname">Hercules</name>, a figure of virtuous strength and chastity. In landscape design, classical sculpture was arranged in groupings, or tableaux, to convey allegorical messages that flattered the patrons who commis-<lb/>
sioned them, and these were often linked as a series of iconographic statements within a planned garden itinerary.</p>
<p>Astronomy and astrology remained firmly intertwined, and Renaissance intellectuals were as fascinated with mystical symbols as their medieval forebears had been. Within the humanists' conceptual framework, classical myth came to take its place alongside Christian mystery. The arcane symbolism within the <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poli-<lb/>
phili</hi> proved enormously appealing to Renaissance patrons and artists. Sculpture and water were used as elements in increasingly elaborate iconographic programs that celebrated the fruitful partnership human-<lb/>
ity had achieved with nature through art and technology. Indeed, the message-laden garden programs Renaissance humanists developed for their noble patrons can be considered the theme parks of their day. Although the garden still functioned as a metaphor of paradise, it now became something more: a theater for the initiated, those with sufficient human-<lb/>
ist education to enable them to decode allegorical statements as they followed a garden itinerary in which fountains and sculptures told often complex sto-<lb/>
ries that alluded to the patron as the author of a new Golden Age, a facili-<lb/>
tator of a terrestrial paradise benefiting all humankind.</p>
<p>As in other branches of art, so too in landscape design the lofty serenity and stable balance of mature Renaissance composition soon gave way to the more complicated and dynamic spatial organization characteristic of the late Renais-<lb/>
sance of the mid-sixteenth century. Iconography grew ever more allusive and personal. A similar stylistic development as is seen in painting, sculpture, and architecture can be found in the history of landscape design, as we trace its course from quattrocento human-<lb/>
ism through a brief period of classical equipoise in the early years of the sixteenth century into the opulent age of the late Renaissance.</p>
<p>As the Renaissance emerged in <name type="place">Italy</name>, the Reformation and the establishment of various Protestant denominations occurred in Northern <name type="place">Europe</name>. <name type="place">Rome</name>, as the seat of Catholicism, launched the Counter-Reformation in the mid-sixteenth century and, in the con-<lb/>
text of that movement, attempted to inspire faith through artistic means. Thus, in the late sixteenth century, <name type="place">Italy</name> embarked upon a course of design that led to the robust plasticity and florid ornamen-<lb/>
tation of the Baroque style characterizing Italian art and architecture throughout the seventeenth century. Meanwhile, throughout the sixteenth century, Renaissance Italian artistic forms were absorbed in <name type="place">France</name>. There an indigenous Renaissance style developed, which evolved into the grandeur of the French seven-<lb/>
teenth-century version of the Baroque, a more austere form of neo-<lb/>
classicism than the highly theatrical Italian Baroque style. The manifestations of these respective developments in the evolution of Renaissance style in <name type="place">Italy</name> and <name type="place">France</name> will be examined in Chapter Five. Our task here is to trace the rise of Italian humanism and its contribution to the development of a Renaissance style that in <name type="place">Italy</name> reached a climactic stage at the beginning of the sixteenth century, was brilliantly manipulated in a Mannerist mode and adopted by the French, who transformed it into an artistic idiom of their own, even as Renaissance thought was exerting an influence upon the land-<lb/>
scapes of <name type="place">Germany</name>, the Low Countries, and <name type="place">England</name>. Although the process of cultural transmission to other lands was well established by the sixteenth century, we will reserve that discussion for Chapter Six. Because the Renaissance was initiated and carried forward by a small elite of royal and noble patrons influenced by ideas fostered by scholars and expressed by artists, our discussion is necessarily focused upon power centers, the courts of monarchs and princes, the villas and <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teaux</hi> they commissioned, and the cities they sought to beautify.</p>
<div type="section">
<pb n="127"/>
<pb n="127" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">I. <name type="pname">Petrarch</name>, <name type="pname">Alberti</name>, and <name type="pname">Colonna</name>: Humanism and the Landscape</hi></hi></head>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Humanism and the Rebirth of the Villa</hi></hi></head>
<p><name type="pname">Petrarch</name> (<name type="pname">Francesco Petrarca</name>, <date when="1304">1304</date>&#x2013;<date when="1374">1374</date>) fathered the intellectual movement known as humanism. Human-<lb/>
ism to <name type="pname">Petrarch</name> meant the rediscovery of the writings of classical antiquity and the objective, inquiring atti-<lb/>
tude toward the natural world that informed those texts. He believed that Greek and Roman thought were the cornerstones upon which a new future would be built. He further believed in a new morality in which human will, though subservient to divine law, could exercise a greater degree of autonomy than it had during the Middle Ages, when an expansive curiosity was viewed as an affront to theological doctrine. The recovery and study of the classical past, coupled with the intellectual and moral energy released by the new spirit of scientific inquiry and respect for individual achievement, constituted in the minds of the historical protagonists an intellectual rebirth, which they called in Italian <hi rend="italic">rin&#x00E0;scita</hi>, a term that became translated in French and English as <hi rend="italic">renaissance</hi> in the nineteenth century when it gained currency among those examin-<lb/>
ing the art of the sixteenth century. Everything that lay between the fall of <name type="place">Rome</name> and the dawn of the exciting new age was to them an intermediate time, or Middle Age. Thus, these humanists bestowed the name by which we still know the interval of history between the sixth and the mid-fourteenth centuries.</p>
<p>Kept alive by priests and monks, Latin continued to serve as the international tongue of educated Europe-<lb/>
ans throughout this period. Now, however, the human-<lb/>
ists wanted more than the continuation of medieval Latin as the language of the educated class. They actu-<lb/>
ally wanted to write not in the Latin they had inherited from medieval scholastics but in the language and syn-<lb/>
tax of the Roman orator and statesman <name type="pname">Marcus Tullius Cicero</name> (106&#x2013;43 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) and the Roman poet <name type="pname">Virgil</name> (70&#x2013;19 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>). Moreover, humanist scholars wanted not only to write in the tones and style of these eminent ancients, but they also wanted to think about the world in the same ways as they had, examining morality from the perspective of <name type="pname">Plato</name> (c. 427&#x2013;c. 347 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) or inves-<lb/>
tigating the natural world in the manner of <name type="pname">Pliny</name> the Elder (23&#x2013;79 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>). Ironically, success in reviving ancient Latin as a literary language had the effect of promoting vernacular tongues at the expense of medie-<lb/>
val Latin, which fell into gradual disuse.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Petrarch</name> and his followers drew no distinctions between the life of the mind and the life of the city; to serve his countrymen, the contemplative man was morally bound to also be a man of action. The human-<lb/>
ism of <name type="pname">Petrarch</name> was disseminated by men of letters who saw themselves as statesmen along the lines of <name type="pname">Cicero</name>, men whose political programs were informed by intellectual discourse and promulgated with rheto-<lb/>
ric. <name type="pname">Cosimo de' Medici</name> (<date when="1389">1389</date>&#x2013;<date when="1464">1464</date>) captured political control of <name type="place">Florence</name> in 1434, ruling as an enlightened humanist. In 1439, he brought the General Council of the Greek Orthodox and Roman Catholic churches to his city, hospitably subsidizing the gathered prelates who included among them <name type="pname">Gemistos Plethon</name> (c. <date when="1355">1355</date>&#x2013;<date when="1450">1450</date>/<date when="1455">55</date>), the most respected authority on <name type="pname">Plato</name>. The presence in the streets of so many distinguished guests provided the people of the city with a new sense of cosmopolitanism. Some of these ecclesiastics came from <name type="pname">Constantinople</name>, then the wealthiest and most sophisticated city in the world. Founded by <name type="pname">Constan-<lb/>
tine</name> as the new <name type="place">Rome</name> in 330 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, <name type="pname">Constantinople</name> was both the principal seat of Christianity in the <name type="place">Byzantine Empire</name> and the main repository of classical culture after the fall of the Western Roman Empire in 476 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Some Greek Orthodox monasteries had managed to preserve, along with Early Christian manuscripts, cop-<lb/>
ies of certain ancient classical texts. Because the <name type="place">Byz-<lb/>
antine Empire</name> endured until the <name type="pname">Ottoman Turks</name> overthrew <name type="pname">Constantinople</name> in 1453, the Greek Ortho-<lb/>
dox Church still served in <name type="pname">Cosimo</name>'s day as a link in a long chain of scholarship reaching back through van-<lb/>
ished Roman libraries to the ancient Greeks. Humanist scholar <name type="pname">Marsilio Ficino</name> (<date when="1433">1433</date>&#x2013;<date when="1499">1499</date>) thought that <name type="place">Florence</name> could perhaps replace this lost center for ancient Greek scholarship and perpetuate the intellec-<lb/>
tual conversations begun in his city following the 1439 gathering there of so many learned Greek scholars. <name type="pname">Ficino</name> is believed to have founded the Platonic Acad-<lb/>
emy under the auspices of <name type="pname">Cosimo</name> around 1462 at the <name type="pname">Medici</name> patriarch's Villa <name type="place">Careggi</name> near <name type="place">Florence</name>. To this place <name type="pname">Cosimo</name> came "not to cultivate the fields, but my soul."<ref target="#CH4-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>The creation of this society of humanists, which lasted until 1494, signaled a moment of confident ide-<lb/>
alism in Western history. The tenets of humanism became the province of a small but influential group of intellectuals, including officers of the Church. These prelates were increasingly disposed toward its philos-<lb/>
ophy as well as its theories of beauty, which they nour-<lb/>
ished with their literary and artistic patronage. The garden assumed special status as a place of contempla-<lb/>
tion and learning, as well as an architectural space and opportunity for fresh artistic expression.</p>
<pb n="128"/>
<pb n="128" type="orig"/>
<p><name type="pname">Ficino</name>'s Neo-Platonism drew on the works of <name type="pname">Plotinus</name>, the third century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> <name type="pname">Alexandrian</name> philoso-<lb/>
pher who posited a Godhead from which all creation emanates and with which the soul can be mystically united, as well as on the writings of <name type="pname">Augustine</name> and the twelfth-century Neoplatonists. His philosophy gave special status to the soul as the agent of the transcen-<lb/>
dent, cognitive, creative intellect standing at the mid-<lb/>
point between the earthly and the divine, mediating between the higher and lower worlds. For <name type="pname">Ficino</name>, mys-<lb/>
tical love as inspired by <name type="pname">Plato</name>'s theory of love in the <hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Phaedrus</hi>&#x2014;"divine madness"&#x2014;is the source of poetic genius. Its goal is beauty, which is divisible into two oppositional realms: celestial and natural, as personified by the two Venuses often por-<lb/>
trayed in Renaissance art&#x2014;one symbolizing sacred love, the other profane. <name type="pname">Ficino</name>'s philosophy gave new status to the artist, whose task it was to translate pure form&#x2014;ideal beauty&#x2014;into physical reality, a project assisted by mathematical concepts of proportion and harmony.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Ficino</name>'s disciple, <name type="pname">Giovanni Pico della Mirandola</name> (<date when="1463">1463</date>&#x2013;<date when="1494">1494</date>), articulated the then-radical concept of individual free will, which granted the artist enormous creative potential and mimetic power to juxtapose and combine forms in new representations of nature with meanings derived not from doctrinal religion but from the human intellect. Increasingly, the natural sciences informed this enterprise. As the tenets of a static medi-<lb/>
eval scholasticism based on the concept of a closed, rather than an open, universe, were gradually over-<lb/>
turned by this invigorating license to a more open-<lb/>
ended mode of inquiry, the <hi rend="italic">hortus conclusus</hi> became the <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi>, or secret garden, a secluded and enclosed garden room, a place of intimate contact with nature within the larger Renaissance garden. As if in self-conscious recognition of the philosophical nature of this transaction, a principal theme often expressed in the iconography of the Renaissance garden is the syncretism of Art and Nature. Moreover, the <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi> anticipated the botanical garden in which exotic and native plants were collected and displayed in a systematic fashion.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Petrarch</name>, a devout Christian, sought spiritual truth in nature as well as practical knowledge. Toward these ends, he created two gardens near his home at Fontaine-de-Vaucluse, collected rare plants, and con-<lb/>
ducted experiments in growing several plant varieties under varying geographic, seasonal, meteorological, and astrological conditions. One garden, situated on a slope, he referred to as his "transalpine Parnassus." The other, closer to his house and situated on an island in the middle of a fast-flowing river, was accessible "by a little bridge leading from a vaulted grotto where the sun never penetrates." Prefiguring by four hundred years the form and function of <name type="pname">Alexander Pope</name>'s famous grotto at <name type="place">Twickenham</name>, which we will examine in Chapter Seven, <name type="pname">Petrarch</name> said that he believed his grotto "resembles that small room where <name type="pname">Cicero</name> some-<lb/>
times went to recite; it is an invitation to study, to which I go at noon."</p>
<p>The several villas built by <name type="pname">Cosimo</name> and his <name type="pname">Medici</name> successors a century after <name type="pname">Petrarch</name> proved to be pru-<lb/>
dent investments in the rural economy and refuges in times of plague or political strife. They were also cen-<lb/>
ters for intellectual recreation and conversation. For a time, in the buoyant atmosphere of the Renaissance, the Italian villa became once more, as it had been in antiquity for <name type="pname">Pliny</name> the Younger, a philosophical and literary retreat where the aristocracy celebrated the pleasures of rustic life.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Theories of <name type="pname">Alberti</name></hi></hi></head>
<p><name type="pname">Lorenzo</name> the Magnificent (<date when="1449">1449</date>&#x2013;<date when="1492">1492</date>), the grandson of <name type="pname">Cosimo</name>, did not enjoy the same degree of wealth and power as <name type="pname">Cosimo</name> had, conspicuous though he was as a benefactor of <name type="place">Florence</name>. Occupying his time less fully with the banking activities of his family, <name type="pname">Lorenzo</name> threw himself even more energetically into statecraft and the pursuit of the arts. He liked to gather artists, musicians, and members of the Platonic Academy around him at his villas at <name type="place">Fiesole</name>, <name type="place">Cafaggiolo</name>, <name type="place">Careggi</name>, and <name type="place">Poggio a Caiano</name>. Although <name type="pname">Leon Battista Alberti</name> died soon after <name type="pname">Lorenzo</name> came to power, he was influential within this humanist circle, and his treatise on architecture,_<hi rend="italic">De re aedificatoria</hi>, was a constant reference work for <name type="pname">Lorenzo</name>.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Alberti</name> was a versatile polymath, among other things a poet, a scholar of classical literature and phi-<lb/>
losophy, and an author of treatises on perspective and other aspects of painting as well as on sculpture and on villa design specifically. Although he later designed buildings, he avoided direct involvement in the con-<lb/>
struction process, setting himself apart from architects of humbler origins who usually served as both design-<lb/>
ers and supervisors of construction. <name type="pname">Alberti</name> advised <name type="pname">Pope Nicholas V</name> on various urban projects. His theo-<lb/>
ries on architecture merged under one definition of beauty: "that reasoned harmony of all the parts within a body, so that nothing may be added or taken away, or altered, but for the worse," a state he called <hi rend="italic">cocin-<lb/>
nitas</hi>. He saw in geometry nature's order, advocating symmetry and the arrangement of various building parts according to symbolically sig-<lb/>
nificant ratios of proportion, thus translating Neopla-<lb/>
tonic ideals of natural harmonic form into architectural reality.<ref target="#CH4-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p><name type="pname">Alberti</name> derived several of his architectural con-<lb/>
cepts from the principles of order and harmony found in nature and saw nature in its own right as a source of
<pb n="129"/>
<pb n="129" type="orig"/>
pleasure. According to <name type="pname">Alberti</name>, villas should be sited on gentle elevations with a view of the surrounding countryside. Gardens should have porticoes that would afford both sun and shade and also serve as an archi-<lb/>
tectonic link in making garden space continuous with that of the house. For large gatherings he prescribed a festive open space and for quiet pleasure the presence of springs of water. He advised planting boxwood hedges in sheltered locations and was not averse to arranging these in the form of the owner's monogram after the fashion of the ancient Romans. Nor did he disapprove of comic statues in the garden, "provided they are not obscene."<ref target="#CH4-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref></p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> at <name type="place">Fiesole</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>Sometime prior to 1455, <name type="pname">Cosimo</name> commissioned <name type="pname">Mich-<lb/>
elozzo di Bartolommeo</name> (<date when="1396">1396</date>&#x2013;<date when="1472">1472</date>) to design the <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> at <name type="place">Fiesole</name> for his son Giovanni (figs. 4.2, 4.3). Built between 1458 and 1461, the villa's primary function was not as a working farm, but as a setting for intellectual life and a demonstration of aesthetic and ideological values. As architectural historian <name type="pname">James S. Ackerman</name> points out, "<name type="pname">Michelozzo</name>'s simple arcaded cube was the first modern villa designed without thought or possibility of material gain."<ref target="#CH4-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref> Judging from a contemporary fresco painted by <name type="pname">Domenico del Ghir-<lb/>
landaio</name> (<date when="1449">1449</date>&#x2013;<date when="1494">1494</date>), it was covered in off-white stucco. Although devoid of Albertian classical details, it followed the prescription for siting set forth in <hi rend="italic">De re aedificatoria</hi>. Conspicuous from afar, it rose from a terraced embankment in conscious imitation of <name type="pname">Pliny</name>'s siting of his first-century-<hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> villas at Laurentinum and Tusci, where scenic perspective was an important consideration. The <name type="pname">Medici</name> villa at <name type="place">Fiesole</name> with its com-<lb/>
manding view of nearby <name type="place">Florence</name> was the first since ancient times to consciously exploit the potential of its site in this way and was thus a prototype for the Plinian view that would become a significant element in the location, orientation, and design of future Italian gar-<lb/>
dens, which for this and other reasons were situated on hillsides whenever possible.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-123">
<graphic url="CH4_003.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.2. Plan of the <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name>, <name type="place">Fiesole</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Michelozzo di Bartolommeo</name>. Prior to 1455 <hi rend="bold">A</hi> Giardino Segreto <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Loggias <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Terrace <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Lemon Garden <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Pergola <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Lower Garden</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-124">
<graphic url="CH4_004.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.3. Lemon garden, <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name>. 20th-century restoration</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The east front of the villa was an entirely open loggia before one of the bays was walled in. On the west front the loggia remains entirely open, and one can fully appreciate its spatial fusion with a lovely <hi rend="italic">giar-dino segreto</hi>, or secret garden. This is an early example of the way Italian designers, who conceived of villa and garden as integral architectural compo-<lb/>
nents, created indoor and outdoor spaces that interpen-<lb/>
etrated one another. Originally <hi rend="italic">giardini segreti</hi> were
<pb n="130"/>
<pb n="130" type="orig"/>
small enclosed garden rooms, but here, where the scenic potential of the site was exploited, garden and loggia overlook a panoramic view of the Arno Val-<lb/>
ley and the city of <name type="place">Florence</name>, with <name type="pname">Filippo Brunelles-<lb/>
chi</name>'s cathedral dome dominating the skyline.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-125">
<graphic url="CH4_005.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.4. <name type="pname">Sandro Botticelli</name>. <hi rend="italic">Prima-vera</hi>. c. 1482. Galleria degli Uffizi, <name type="place">Florence</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>A gate leads from this garden to a terrace run-<lb/>
ning along the south side of the house. Beyond this terrace, a long pergola overlooks the lower terrace garden with its clipped, cone-shaped magnolia trees (<hi rend="italic">Magnolia grandiflora</hi>) surrounded by lawn and hedges of box. Restored and planted in its current form at the beginning of the twentieth century by <name type="pname">Cecil Pinsent</name> for <name type="pname">Lady Sybil Cutting</name>, as noted in Chapter Ten, this garden and the grassy terrace above are decorated with lemon trees in terra-cotta pots. The grade change between the pergola and the lower terrace garden is not exploited as an opportu-<lb/>
nity for ornamental stairs, as similar slopes were to be in later Italian gardens. The lower garden is, how-<lb/>
ever, cut into the hillside and is sufficiently lower than the upper garden so as not to intrude upon the panoramic view from the upper terrace.</p>
<p>Even though the <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> at <name type="place">Fiesole</name> was built simply as a country retreat rather than as work-<lb/>
ing villa, agricultural scenery abruptly abuts it. This unselfconscious shift from garden formality to olive trees and fields, which had also characterized the ancient villa landscape as described by <name type="pname">Pliny</name>, can be seen in many other Tuscan gardens. Much as mod-<lb/>
ern urbanites enjoy the apple orchards and potato fields around their country houses without them-<lb/>
selves engaging in agricultural pursuits, <name type="pname">Lorenzo</name>'s circle delighted in the bucolic landscape of <name type="place">Fiesole</name>. There the scholar-poet <name type="pname">Angelo Poliziano</name> (<date when="1454">1454</date>&#x2013;<date when="1494">1494</date>) wrote his "Rusticus," a celebration of the pas-<lb/>
toral poetry of such ancient writers as <name type="pname">Horace</name>, <name type="pname">Hesiod</name>, <name type="pname">Columella</name>, and <name type="pname">Virgil</name>. The poem is also a paean to the view of <name type="place">Florence</name> with the silvery Arno in the distance and to <name type="pname">Lorenzo</name>'s patronage and gen-<lb/>
erosity of spirit. In this way, rural values and urban power were harmoniously aligned within the cul-<lb/>
tural matrix of humanism.</p>
<p>The humanist attitude toward nature implicit in the siting of the <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> at <name type="place">Fiesole</name> is also reflected in <name type="pname">Florentine</name> quattrocento painting. The artist's receptivity to natural beauty could not have occurred had not late medieval philosophy as well as the new humanism caused a profound shift in society's overall cultural perspective. Christian faith was not abandoned, but individual excellence and human achievement were increasingly valued. Sci-<lb/>
entific observation and humanistic aesthetics fos-<lb/>
tered an interest in nature and delight in the beauties of landscape. Classical mythology was incorporated into the education of the well-to-do, and allegory using classical themes and images was extensively employed in art and literature.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Sandro Botticelli</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi>, a painting of about 1482, expresses both the naturalistic and arcane aspects of Renaissance humanism (fig. 4.4). Paintings such as this, as well as gardens of the period, were intended as both literal and metaphori-<lb/>
cal paradises. At the same time, they were presented as visual texts to be decoded, as bearers of messages to be deciphered, as stationary dramas for the dis-<lb/>
cerning. While the key to its meaning has been much debated by scholars, it is clear that in the <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi> we have not only an image comparable to the medi-<lb/>
<pb n="131"/>
<pb n="131" type="orig"/>
eval paintings of the <name type="pname">Virgin Mary</name> in a flowery mead, but, more important, a Renaissance interpretation of the paradise or <name type="pname">Venus</name> gardens of ancient literature. The garden over which <name type="pname">Botticelli</name>'s <name type="pname">Venus</name> presides is clearly the garden of love. On the right we see Zephyr, the harbinger of Spring and ravisher of Chloris. The latter, as compensation for having been thus taken, is turned into the adjacent Flora. In the orange trees that form a bower for <name type="pname">Venus</name>, <name type="pname">Cupid</name> points his arrow toward one of the three Graces. Completing the scene is Mercury, a god associated with the month of May. The painting is thought by some authorities to com-<lb/>
memorate the wedding, in <date when="1482-05">May 1482</date>, of a member of the <name type="pname">Medici</name> family.</p>
<p>It is apparent from this and other quattrocento paintings that allegory, for more than a thousand years pressed into the service of the Christian faith, has returned to its classical origins and that classical sub-<lb/>
jects are no longer prohibited by religious authorities intent upon stamping out "pagan" belief. Christian and classical themes now served in a syncretic man-<lb/>
ner as primary subjects for artists for the next three hundred years. Gardens were populated almost entirely by classical deities and mythological heroes, as Christian humanists read new meanings into ancient myths. One explanation for this lies in the extraordinary influence exerted by the <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotoma-<lb/>
chia Poliphili</hi> on garden design.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi></hi></hi></head>
<p>In 1499, the Venetian publisher <name type="pname">Aldus Manutius</name> brought forth an enigmatic and fascinating book with descriptions and woodcut illustrations that were to have a great influence upon garden design. Called <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi>, it is reputedly the work of a Dominican monk and nobleman, <name type="pname">Francesco Col-<lb/>
onna</name> (<date when="1433">1433</date>&#x2013;<date when="1527">1527</date>). At Palestrina, <name type="pname">Colonna</name> was engaged with his father, <name type="pname">Stefano</name>, in restoring the Tem-<lb/>
ple of Fortuna Primigenia, a Greco-Roman goddess associated with Egyptian veneration of the Nile (see fig. 2.24). <name type="pname">Colonna</name> shared the interest of Pico and other Neoplatonists in mystery religions and their ini-<lb/>
tiatory rituals. These involved the decoding of caba-<lb/>
listic messages, which were sometimes in the form of hieroglyphs. Such hieroglyphs were believed to rep-<lb/>
resent the immaterial essence as well as the functional nature of the things they symbolized, the Idea, in Pla-<lb/>
tonic terms, as well as its material form.</p>
<p>Translated by <name type="pname">Jean Martin</name>_in 1546, the <hi rend="italic">Hypnero-<lb/>
tomachia Poliphili</hi>_was published in <name type="place">France</name> as <hi rend="italic">Dis-<lb/>
cours du songe de Poliphile</hi> with a new set of woodcut illustrations in the mannerist style associated with the School of Fontainebleau. When the English edition appeared in 1592, its title was rendered as "The Strife of Love in a Dream."<ref target="#CH4-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref> The protagonist, <name type="pname">Poliphilus</name>, whose name means "Lover of Polia," is the narrator of a many-layered erotic dream in which his passion for architecture and gardens of great intricacy and decorative sumptuousness is fully indulged along with his extravagant devotion to his beloved. <name type="pname">Poliph-<lb/>
ilus</name> journeys to the gardens of <name type="pname">Queen Eleuterilyda</name> and, in the company of Polia, to the island of <name type="place">Cytherea</name>, where he describes the "groves, meadows, gardens, streams and springs" in elaborate detail. In the middle of the island is "<name type="pname">Venus</name>'s fountain with seven precious columns,"<ref target="#CH4-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref> the scene of the climax of Book One in which the naked Goddess of Love is described in delectable detail and <name type="pname">Poliphilus</name> is pierced by Cupid's arrow. Here and in the other imaginary locales visited by <name type="pname">Poliphilus</name>, <name type="pname">Colonna</name> displays his intense interest in ornamental architecture and ingenious devices.</p>
<p>The woodcut illustrations from <name type="pname">Colonna</name>'s book, with their fanciful topiary and knot garden designs and images of grove, grotto, classical pergola, vine-<lb/>
clad arcade, and pseudo-Egyptian esoteric devices, including an elephant with an obelisk mounted in its back, became a source of inspiration for several gen-<lb/>
erations of garden designers. The book was also an important means of disseminating Renaissance gar-<lb/>
den style, especially in the second half of the sixteenth century following the publication of the immensely popular French edition (fig. 4.5).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-126">
<graphic url="CH4_006.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.5. Topiary and knot forms, <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili (The Strife of Love in a Dream)</hi> by <name type="pname">Francesco Colonna</name>. Woodcut probably from the 1561 French edition. Recommended by <name type="pname">Alberti</name>, topiary&#x2014;shrubbery pruned into fanciful shapes&#x2014;was an antique garden practice enthusiastically revived in the Renaissance.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>As in the Renaissance garden, water plays an especially important role in <name type="pname">Poliphilus</name>'s pilgrimage as he progresses from a singing brook past gushing foun-<lb/>
tains, including one in the form of the streaming breasts of a sleeping nymph and another resembling harpies surmounted by Graces, also with water com-<lb/>
ing from their breasts in silver threads (fig. 4.6). According to the cultural historian <name type="pname">Simon Schama</name>, "the fountains of the <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi> con-<lb/>
<pb n="132"/>
<pb n="132" type="orig"/>
trived an effect that was somehow both erotic and philosophical, animal and ethereal. And it was this irresistible combination that cast a spell on the land-<lb/>
scape architects of the Roman and Tuscan villas of the mid and late sixteenth century."<ref target="#CH4-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-127">
<graphic url="CH4_007.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.6. Graces with water streaming from their breasts, <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili (The Strife of Love in a Dream)</hi>. Text and illustrations probably by <name type="pname">Francesco Colonna</name>. Woodcut from the 1561 French edition</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Influenced by the nature of <name type="pname">Colonna</name>'s book, although not by its specific text, in which a clear nar-<lb/>
rative line is difficult to follow, gardens became firmly associated with allegory as places of allusion and meaning. Their paths became prescribed routes through a series of theatrical stops where sculptural or architectural embellishments, often in association with water, posed intellectual riddles and provided answers of a symbolic nature. In attempting to understand their meaning in the Renaissance, it is important to recall not only the intellectual excitement generated by a renewed appreciation of classical mythology but also the interest among certain educated people in the arcanely symbolic imagery derived from Egyptian forms, Neoplatonism, and alchemy.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Poliphilus</name>, like <name type="pname">Dante</name>'s protagonist in <hi rend="italic">The Divine Comedy</hi>, begins his journey in a dense grove of trees. This dark wood symbolizes the lack of certainty that confronts any pilgrim setting out upon a quest. The grove, which in antiquity was associated with sacred places as well as with <name type="pname">Plato</name>'s Academy and <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>'s Lyceum, was revived in the Renaissance in the form of the <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi>, a planting usually of evergreen ilex trees.<ref target="#CH4-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref> The <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> is the realm of nature and the repre-<lb/>
sentation of the Golden Age extolled by the ancient writers <name type="pname">Ovid</name> and <name type="pname">Virgil</name>, an earthly paradise evoking the time when people lived in a hospitable environ-<lb/>
ment surrounded by nature's bounty of berries and nourishing acorns. Its natural forms and deep shade produced an air of wildness and mystery, serving as a foil to the otherwise geometrical garden. Pleasant ref-<lb/>
uges from the hot summer sun, <hi rend="italic">boschi</hi> were integral to the iconographic programs of certain garden land-<lb/>
scapes. They provided appropriate settings in which the visitor could encounter, with a degree of surprise, the symbolical features that had been strategically placed along a prescribed path.</p>
<p>The grotto, like the sacred grove, had ancient associations with mysterious life forces. The well-<lb/>
spring of streams, it was the home of river gods and nymphs. Grottoes such as the one described by <name type="pname">Col-<lb/>
onna</name> became practically obligatory elements in six-<lb/>
teenth-century gardens, and their popularity continued far into the nineteenth century, when they served as Romantic features in many parks and gardens. In the period we are examining here, there were two kinds: those with artificial stalactites and encrustations of colored stones and shells and those of a more architec-<lb/>
tural character, nymphaeums with niched arcades for statuary.</p>
<p>The importance of the <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poli-<lb/>
phili</hi> as a mirror of the Renaissance imagination stems from its fusion of the highly artificial and the natural into a "third nature"<ref target="#CH4-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref> embodying complex and inter-<lb/>
woven sets of symbols that often convey polysemous mythic narratives, allegorical stories with several intended meanings. With its combination of eroticism and idealism, it profoundly expanded the garden's conceptual horizons, making it possible to read into its design multiple texts and individual expressions of imagination.</p>
<p>A new sense of the garden's expressive possibil-<lb/>
ities and a new vocabulary of garden design forms were now at hand. Albertian <hi rend="italic">cocinnitas</hi>, or economi-<lb/>
cally perfect harmony of parts, as manifested in the integration of the elements of the garden plan along clearly defined axes with compositional symmetry of parts, was now fused with <name type="pname">Colonna</name>'s notion of the gar-<lb/>
den as an allegorical environment in which one could follow an itinerary of initiation and revelation.<ref target="#CH4-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref> Math-<lb/>
ematics and mythology, geometry and allegory, were now firmly joined. To exploit this expressive potential in a grammar of landscape art&#x2014;a design style&#x2014;would take genius. Fortunately, genius was at hand in the person of the architect <name type="pname">Bramante</name>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="133"/>
<pb n="133" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">II. <name type="pname">Bramante</name> and the Rediscovery of Axial Planning: Gardens of Sixteenth-Century <name type="place">Italy</name></hi></hi></head>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Establishing the Italian Renaissance Garden Paradigm: Belve-<lb/>
dere Court and Villa Madama</hi></hi></head>
<p>Encouraged by his reading of <name type="pname">Pliny</name> the Younger, <name type="pname">Petrarch</name>'s first somewhat tentative embrace of pan-<lb/>
oramic perspective on Mont Ventoux heralded the scenic appreciation that would later become a hall-<lb/>
mark of Renaissance thought. The Italian word <hi rend="italic">bel-<lb/>
vedere</hi>, meaning "beautiful view," is an important one in the history of landscape design because of its association with a particular type of garden structure. Built in various styles, depending upon time and place, a belvedere may be either an independent tower or part of the villa itself. A belvedere is, quite simply, a lookout whose purpose is the enjoyment of scenery. During the Renaissance, belvederes became an important means of enjoying the view of gardens and the surrounding landscape. The papal villa known as Belvedere, built by <name type="pname">Innocent VIII</name> (papacy <date when="1484">1484</date>&#x2013;<date when="1492">1492</date>) on a hill within the <name type="place">Vatican</name> is important for our discussion here, however, not only because of its original siting with commanding views of the Roman countryside but also because the subsequent treatment of the ground that lay between it and the <name type="place">Vatican</name> influenced the course of garden history.</p>
<p>Bisected in the late sixteenth century by a struc-<lb/>
tural addition to the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Palace, half of the Court of the Belvedere today serves as a parking lot for <name type="place">Vat-<lb/>
ican</name> employees, while the remaining half is a pleasant sculpture garden where visitors can stroll (figs. 4.8, 4.9). Few today therefore, comprehend its significance as a pivotal development in the history of landscape design. Perhaps because so much later Italian, and indeed European, landscape design was derived from <name type="pname">Bramante</name>'s axial terraced composition here, this once-revolutionary garden seems only inevitable, not radical, to us.</p>
<p>The seed for a garden on this spot was sown in the quattrocento. The first humanist pope, <name type="pname">Nicholas V</name> (papacy <date when="1447">1447</date>&#x2013;<date when="1455">1455</date>) was deeply interested in architecture, and he employed <name type="pname">Alberti</name> as his consul-<lb/>
tant on such projects as the reconstruction of Old <name type="pname">St. Peter</name>'s and the integration of this basilica with the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Palace. The plan that <name type="pname">Alberti</name> conceived included a palace garden. Though considerably smaller in scale, in its ambitious program this garden harked back to <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa rather than to any immediate predecessor, for it was not conceived as a series of outdoor rooms where intimate conversation could take place, as were some of the new villa gar-<lb/>
dens near <name type="place">Florence</name>, but rather as a space for public gathering and theatrical entertainment. This plan was abandoned at <name type="pname">Nicholas</name>'s death in 1455, and not until a half century later was a garden program for the <name type="place">Vatican</name> begun in earnest.</p>
<p>Immediately upon his election to the papacy, <name type="pname">Pope Julius II</name> (papacy <date when="1503">1503</date>&#x2013;<date when="1513">1513</date>) began imple-<lb/>
menting a plan for a <name type="place">Vatican</name> garden that was part of a political agenda to increase the importance of the papacy as a power in <name type="place">Europe</name>, with the <name type="place">Vatican</name> serv-<lb/>
ing as the seat of a new Roman empire. The revival of the ancient Roman villa tradition within the walls of the <name type="place">Vatican</name> thus served as a symbolical link to imperial times. To perform this work, the pope chose as his architect <name type="pname">Donato Bramante</name> (<date when="1444">1444</date>&#x2013;<date when="1514">1514</date>), who had recently completed the sophisticated <hi rend="italic">tempietto</hi> adjacent to <name type="pname">San Pietro</name> in <name type="place">Montorio</name> on the <name type="place">Janiculum Hill</name>, and whom he would soon commission to design a new basilica for <name type="pname">St. Peter</name>'s. <name type="pname">Bramante</name>'s first com-<lb/>
mission from the pope was to provide a physical link between the Belvedere of <name type="pname">Innocent VIII</name> on its hill and the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Palace below, creating sheltered commu-<lb/>
nication between the two buildings. At the same time, he was to provide a setting for the pontiff's fine col-<lb/>
lection of antique sculpture and an outdoor theater to serve as a suitable space for papal pageantry. In addi-<lb/>
tion, <name type="pname">Julius II</name> wanted to have a private garden retreat, a place where he could meet and converse with a circle of friends who shared his interest in the redis-<lb/>
covery of the classical world.</p>
<p>In developing his design, <name type="pname">Bramante</name> employed <name type="pname">Alberti</name>'s principles of symmetry and proportion in an axial organization of forms and space that had not been seen since antiquity. He even set about resolving a problem that was generally left unresolved in ancient Roman landscape planning, the harmoniza-<lb/>
tion of two colliding axes.</p>
<p>On the uneven terrain between the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Pal-<lb/>
ace and the Belvedere, <name type="pname">Bramante</name> placed two parallel loggias, which were three stories on the lowest level adjacent to the palace, then two stories as the rising slope was transformed into an intermediate terrace, and finally one story where an upper terrace joined the villa (fig. 4.9). The steps necessitated by these grade changes in the terraced hillside became import-<lb/>
ant design elements in their own right, their double staircases celebrations of ascent. Perpendicular to the broad terraces between the loggias (today's museum galleries) was a strong central axis terminating next to the villa in a raised niche&#x2014;or exedra, so called because of its semicircular form. From the windows
<pb n="134"/>
<pb n="134" type="orig"/>
of the papal apartments the garden appeared as a stage set or painting demonstrating the principles of sin-<lb/>
gle-point perspective, one of the technical discoveries of the Renaissance that theater designers and artists often virtuosically demonstrated in their work. Follow-<lb/>
ing <name type="pname">Bramante</name>, designers planned gardens with elevated terraces or balconies overlooking them in order that the viewer could readily grasp from this vantage point the axes that enabled and made manifest a perspectival treatment of space.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-128">
<graphic url="CH4_008.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.7. Great Niche, north end of the Belvedere Court (Court of the Pine Cone, <name type="place">Vatican</name> Museums). Foreground sculpture, <name type="pname">Arnaldo Pomodoro</name>, <hi rend="italic">Sphere within a Sphere</hi>. <date when="1988">1988</date>&#x2013;<date when="1990">1990</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-129">
<graphic url="CH4_009.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below, left:</hi> 4.8. The southern section of the Belvedere Court today</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-130">
<graphic url="CH4_010.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below, right:</hi> 4.9. The Belvedere Court, designed in successive stages by <name type="pname">Donato Bramante</name>, <name type="pname">Michelangelo Buonarroti</name>, and <name type="pname">Pirro Ligorio</name>. <date when="1503">1503</date>&#x2013;<date when="1561">1561</date>. Engraving by <name type="pname">Hendrick van Schoel</name>. 1579</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The elevated niche and its flanking wings screened the awkward juncture of two axes, that of the Belvedere Court and that of the villa. <name type="pname">Bramante</name> is believed to have modeled this architectural composition along the lines of the terraced Sanctuary of Fortuna Primigenia at Pal-<lb/>
estrina (see fig. 2.24). Around 1550, under <name type="pname">Pope Julius III</name> (papacy <date when="1550">1550</date>&#x2013;<date when="1555">1555</date>), <name type="pname">Michelangelo Buonarroti</name> (<date when="1475">1475</date>&#x2013;<date when="1564">1564</date>) replaced <name type="pname">Bramante</name>'s semicircular Prae-<lb/>
neste-like steps with the double flight of stairs we see today. Paired staircases by then had become ubiquitous in Italian garden design as a means of reinforcing axial symmetry and dramatizing the transition from terrace to terrace. Hillsides were therefore the most desirable sites for garden designers after <name type="pname">Bramante</name> showed at the Bel-<lb/>
vedere Court how designers could successfully exploit steep terrain.</p>
<p>The construction of the Belvedere Court did not occur all at once, but proceeded sporadically over half a century. In addition to replacing <name type="pname">Bramante</name>'s unusual convex-concave stairs in front of the exedra, <name type="pname">Michelan-<lb/>
gelo</name> enclosed the arcade that formed its curving rear and raised the northern wall next to it an additional story. In 1561, <name type="pname">Pius IV</name> (papacy <date when="1559">1559</date>&#x2013;<date when="1565">1565</date>) summoned the architect <name type="pname">Pirro Ligorio</name> (c. <date when="1510">1510</date>&#x2013;<date when="1583">1583</date>) to finish the proj-<lb/>
ect. <name type="pname">Ligorio</name> vaulted the niche to create the Nicchione, or Great Niche, and built its surmounting semicircular log-<lb/>
gia (figs. 4.7, 4.9). At the opposite end of the Court, he
<pb n="135"/>
<pb n="135" type="orig"/>
added a semicircle of tiered stone seats resembling those of a Roman theater to facilitate viewing the tour-<lb/>
naments and other spectacles that took place there (fig. 4.9).</p>
<p>In 1516, <name type="pname">Cardinal Giulio de' Medici</name>, later <name type="pname">Pope Clement VII</name>, commissioned <name type="pname">Raphael</name> (<name type="pname">Raffaello San-<lb/>
zio</name>, <date when="1483">1483</date>&#x2013;<date when="1520">1520</date>) to design the Villa Madama on Monte Mario. <name type="pname">Raphael</name>'s friend and collaborator <name type="pname">Giulio Romano</name> (<date when="1492">1492</date>/<date when="1499">9</date>&#x2013;<date when="1546">1546</date>) helped with the realization of the design, and <name type="pname">Antonio da Sangallo</name>, the Younger (<date when="1485">1485</date>&#x2013;<date when="1546">1546</date>), was probably also involved in the proj-<lb/>
ect. It was the first villa to be constructed on the out-<lb/>
skirts of <name type="place">Rome</name>. Like the Farnesina, the <date when="1508">1508</date>&#x2013;<date when="1511">1511</date> villa designed by <name type="pname">Baldassare Peruzzi</name> (<date when="1481">1481</date>&#x2013;<date when="1536">1536</date>) on the banks of the Tiber, it was intended for supper par-<lb/>
ties attended by popes and cardinals as well as by phil-<lb/>
osophical noblemen and witty courtesans. These entertainments were an important feature of Roman life during the papacy of <name type="pname">Julius II</name> and his successor, <name type="pname">Leo X</name> (papacy <date when="1513">1513</date>&#x2013;<date when="1521">1521</date>). Like the Farnesina, the Villa Madama has a beautifully frescoed loggia that serves as the nexus of interpenetrating indoor and out-<lb/>
door spaces.</p>
<p>Designed in a halcyon era when humanist gath-<lb/>
erings and summer entertainments were still the order of the day, the structures of the villa were subservient to the gardens, which stretched out along lengthy axes. From the entrance on the south, one passes into an entry court and beyond through an entry loggia into the large central court. This axis is projected through another loggia in which recessed niches seem to pull the outdoor space into the architecture of the building, while simultaneously pushing the fabric of the build-<lb/>
ing into the adjacent garden. <name type="pname">Giovanni da Udine</name> (<date when="1487">1487</date>&#x2013;<date when="1561">1561</date>/4), whose beautiful frescoes of garlands embellish the ceiling of the Farnesina, also worked at the Villa Madama, painting the frescoes that decorate the bays of this loggia in the antique style of those found in <name type="pname">Nero</name>'s Golden House (fig. 4.10). Originally the loggia, which is now glassed in, opened directly onto the garden. Lofty loggias with the adjacent gar-<lb/>
den in axial relation to them, the successors of the <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> at <name type="place">Fiesole</name>, help to dissolve the visual separa-<lb/>
tion between building and nature and are among the hallmarks of Italian villa design.</p>
<p>Curiously, the axial orientation of the Villa Mad-<lb/>
ama, unlike that of the Villa d'Este at Tivoli, does not exploit the scenic potential of its lofty site on Monte Mario but runs laterally across the hillside instead of along its gradient. <name type="pname">Raphael</name> planned another perpendic-<lb/>
ular axis that would have accomplished this purpose, but his design for this extension of the garden was never executed. The garden's principal view therefore remains that from the loggia along the villa's main axis as it continues outdoors through a garden of boxwood compartments and a long terrace stretching across the flank of Monte Mario to the north. These two spaces are separated by a tall vine-clad wall pierced with a pedimented gate guarded by a pair of colossal male figures. Parallel to this garden at a lower level is a rectangular fish pond (fig. 4.11). Fish ponds were com-<lb/>
mon in medieval gardens, but the architectural charac-<lb/>
ter of this one introduces us in a preliminary and rudimentary way to what would become one of the chief means of Italian Renaissance garden expression: the use of water as an important design element. Water was employed with great imagination in subsequent sixteenth-century Italian gardens, appearing in foun-<lb/>
tains, pools, water staircases, water <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">giocchi d'acqua</hi>, or droll water games that involved the spectator physically by providing surprise drench-<lb/>
ings from concealed jets suddenly activated. Water in these gardens was a means of providing mesmerizing reflectivity, movement, and excitement. It was meant to connote evanescence, insubstantiality, and tempo-<lb/>
rality, while implying the agrarian bounty achieved when humans harness this vital force of nature.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-131">
<graphic url="CH4_011.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.10. <name type="pname">Giovanni da Udine</name>, Loggia fresco, Villa Madama</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-132">
<graphic url="CH4_012.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 4.11. Fish pond, Villa Madama</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Manipulation of Garden Form and Space in the Mid-Sixteenth Century: <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>The mature Renaissance style of straightforward axial movement and calm, self-contained monumentality seen in the works of <name type="pname">Bramante</name> and <name type="pname">Raphael</name> at the beginning of the sixteenth century yielded to the mid-<lb/>
century manipulation of that style into an idiom of
<pb n="136"/>
<pb n="136" type="orig"/>
sinuous elegance, spatial eccentricity, and compositional ambiguity and tension, as found in the art of the painter, architect, and designer <name type="pname">Giulio Romano</name> (1492?&#x2013;1546) and the painter Parmigianino (<name type="pname">Girolamo Francesco Maz-<lb/>
zola</name>, <date when="1503">1503</date>&#x2013;<date when="1540">1540</date>). The same change can be charted in garden design. Scale and perspective are distorted, and composition is purposely unbalanced, rather than cen-<lb/>
tered.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-133">
<graphic url="CH4_013.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.12. Plan of <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name>, <name type="place">Rome</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Michelangelo Buonarroti</name>, <name type="pname">Giorgio Vasari</name>, <name type="pname">Bar-<lb/>
tolomeo Ammannati</name>, and <name type="pname">Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola</name>. After 1550 <hi rend="bold">A</hi> Portico <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Garden Court <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Loggia <hi rend="bold">D</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nymphaeum</hi> <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Rear Loggia <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Rear Garden</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-134">
<graphic url="CH4_014.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right</hi>; 4.13. Ceiling of portico, <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name>, built for <name type="pname">Pope Julius III</name> shortly after his ascent to the papacy in 1550, is a Renaissance masterpiece. <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name> himself participated in its plan as did the architects <name type="pname">Giorgio Vasari</name> (<date when="1511">1511</date>&#x2013;<date when="1574">1574</date>), <name type="pname">Bartolommeo Ammannati</name> (<date when="1511">1511</date>&#x2013;<date when="1592">1592</date>), and <name type="pname">Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola</name> (<date when="1507">1507</date>&#x2013;<date when="1573">1573</date>). Though stripped of much of its original rich sculptural d&#x00E9;cor, the villa is nonetheless a remarkable sight, demonstrating a sophis-<lb/>
ticated interlocking of interior and exterior space and axial gamesmanship (fig. 4.12). Located in a valley to the west of <name type="place">Rome</name> just outside its walls, it was originally designed as a papal retreat and later served as a stopover and staging area for formal processions by foreign digni-<lb/>
taries approaching the <name type="place">Vatican</name>. As at the Villa Madama, the house was simply an accessory to the garden and intended not as a residence but as a place for papal enter-<lb/>
tainment.</p>
<p>One enters the vestibule and passes immediately into a beautiful semicircular portico embracing a horse-<lb/>
shoe-shaped court. While the wall frescoes imitate the ancient Roman painting that antiquarians were discover-<lb/>
ing at the time, the ceiling frescoes of this curving portico are painted as <hi rend="italic">trompe-l'oeil</hi> flower- and vine-covered trellises (fig. 4.13). These perhaps echo the real arbor that sheltered papal dignitaries and other distinguished guests as they walked to and from the Tiber through the once-ex-<lb/>
tensive gardens. A massive, highly polished, blood-pur-<lb/>
ple porphyry fountain basin, recovered from the Baths of Titus, formerly stood in the center of the garden court, catching the water that fell from the mouth of a swan beside a figure of <name type="pname">Venus</name>.<ref target="#CH4-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Beyond the garden court lies the <hi rend="italic">pi&#x00E8;ce de r&#x00E9;sis-<lb/>
tance</hi>_of the entire design: the <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi>, which <name type="pname">Ammannati</name> artfully screened from direct view, placing it behind a loggia (figs. 4.14 and 4.15). From the back of the loggia a pair of curving staircases sweeps down to <name type="pname">Vignola</name>'s cool subterranean grotto. <hi rend="italic">Topia</hi>, landscape paintings reminiscent of the sacro-idyllic landscapes that decorated ancient Roman villa walls were placed along the sides of the court in front of the <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi>, a grotto inhabited by sculptural representations of nymphs, here serving as caryatids. The <hi rend="italic">topia</hi> are now gone, and gone, too, is the romantic mystery of the moss-padded grotto as it appeared to the American author <name type="pname">Edith Wharton</name>, who wrote about Italian villas and their gardens at the beginning of the twentieth century when they were
<pb n="137"/>
<pb n="137" type="orig"/>
declining into antique picturesqueness. Using a mod-<lb/>
ern algaecide, restorers have recently removed the greenish patina from the marble caryatids of the <hi rend="italic">nym-<lb/>
phaeum</hi>, returning them to their original whiteness.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name>'s spatial treatment compels the movement of the eye along a more tortuous route than does a High Renaissance garden with its clearer axial organization and more static spatial composition. Sur-<lb/>
prise&#x2014;the unfolding of elements not seen or antici-<lb/>
pated in advance&#x2014;has become a device within the garden designer's means, one that assumes kinetic experience, movement through space, as an underly-<lb/>
ing principle. Here the garden has become an itiner-<lb/>
ary, a route that teases as it pulls one along a path. Along the central axis stretching between the entry vestibule and the garden behind the <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi>, space is subtly organized into a series of unexpected events. One passes from the narrow vestibule into the embrace of the horseshoe-shaped court and is drawn irresistibly toward the loggia at the rear. Because the bays on each side of the central portal of this loggia have been opened up, this axial tug is partially relaxed, but one is nevertheless propelled forward.</p>
<p>Inside the open loggia one is surprised to find the precipitous drop to the lower level court. The cur-<lb/>
vilinear staircases wrapping around the sides of this semicircular court echo the curving embrace of the entry court portico. But here is a visual puzzle, for while one can see through a rear loggia behind the <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi> into a garden, the strong axis has become entirely imaginary at this point, and there is no imme-<lb/>
diately visible route leading from the first loggia to the second and out into that garden. To proceed, one must descend one of the curving staircases to the lower court where yet another puzzle presents itself, for here one sees the subterranean grotto with its cary-<lb/>
atids supporting the terrace of the loggia above but finds no visible access to it. Like <name type="pname">Poliphilus</name> in <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia</hi> or Alice in Wonderland, one must, as in a dream, search for the door that opens to the delightful underground grotto where the buxom cary-<lb/>
atids stand on their water-girt platform. <name type="pname">Ammannati</name> placed this secret entrance in the midlevel grotto located beneath the first loggia between the two curv-<lb/>
ing staircases. A pair of staircases leading up to the rear garden hides within a second midlevel grotto beneath the rear loggia.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-135">
<graphic url="CH4_015.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.14. <hi rend="italic">Nymphaeum</hi>, <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name>, as seen in an engraving by <name type="pname">Giovanni Francesco Venturini</name>, plate 7 from <hi rend="italic">Le Fontane ne' Palazzi e ne' Giardini di Roma, con li loro prospetti et orna-<lb/>
menti, Parte Terza</hi>. n.d.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-136">
<graphic url="CH4_016.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 4.15. The same view today</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="138"/>
<pb n="138" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-137">
<graphic url="CH4_017.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.16. Oval court, Villa Pia, <name type="place">Vati-<lb/>
can</name> Gardens, <name type="place">Rome</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Pirro Ligorio</name>. 1560</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Humanism and the Role of Sculpture, Nature, and Symbols of Prestige in Garden Iconography</hi></hi></head>
<p>In <name type="pname">G. B. Falda</name>'s engraving of the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Gardens we see the Villa Pia, also called the Casino Pio, built by <name type="pname">Pirro Ligorio</name> for <name type="pname">Pope Pius IV</name> in 1560. Like the <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name> it has a spatially ambiguous plan that visually pulls one in and through while making physical pas-<lb/>
sage at first appear occluded. At the same time, it provides an example of another important Renais-<lb/>
sance Italian contribution to the tradition of garden design: the <hi rend="italic">casino</hi>, or summerhouse, built as a retreat from the bustle and ceremony of court life. Here the pope held soir&#x00E9;es at which invited scholars sat around an oval court discussing philosophy, poetry, and reli-<lb/>
gion. Discussion groups had become an important part of the intellectual life of Renaissance men of letters, and <name type="pname">Ligorio</name>'s oval, which is embraced by exe-<lb/>
dras of carved stone seats, is an architectural expres-<lb/>
sion of the humanists' pleasure in scholarly conversation (fig. 4.16).</p>
<p>The recovery of the art and architecture of antiq-<lb/>
uity provided villa designers with immediate sources of inspiration. As an archaeologist, <name type="pname">Ligorio</name> himself had thoroughly explored <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa on behalf of the Este family, and the mosaics that embellish the loggia of the Villa Pia and the arched portals entering the court reveal a renewed appreciation of ancient Roman decorative art. Low reliefs in stucco found on ancient Roman baths, palaces, and villas were echoed at the Villa Pia and elsewhere.<ref target="#CH4-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Along with the wall frescoes and mosaics uncovered by sixteenth-century archaeologists, ancient marble sculptures were being excavated from the Roman soil. Several great collections were formed at this time, and to accommodate them the garden began to assume the role of outdoor museum. In addi-<lb/>
tion to the Belvedere Court at the <name type="place">Vatican</name>, <name type="pname">Bramante</name> built a <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi>, the so-called Statue Court, located between the upper court and the Belvedere, for <name type="pname">Pope Julius II</name>'s collection of antique sculpture. In 1584, <name type="pname">Cardinal Fernando de' Medici</name> bought the col-<lb/>
lection amassed some sixty years earlier by <name type="pname">Cardinal Andrea della Valle</name>, sending the freestanding pieces to <name type="place">Florence</name> to embellish the Boboli Gardens and keep-<lb/>
ing the reliefs to decorate the facade of his villa on the Pincian Hill in <name type="place">Rome</name>.</p>
<p>Inspired by the discoveries of classical archae-<lb/>
ology, patrons commissioned new sculpture. The notion became firmly established that the garden was a setting in which white marble figures should be seen against dark green foliage or framed by architectural niches within building facades and garden walls. The humanists' interest in classical mythology furnished artists with thematic material, which they wove into narrative itineraries. Familiar literary themes that found expression in the garden included those of the Golden Age, Elysium, rustic goodness, <name type="pname">Venus</name> presid-<lb/>
ing over the Garden of Love, Apollo, the Muses, Mount Parnassus, and the virtuous hero assigned near-impossible tasks or waylaid by treacherous enchantments.</p>
<p>An important element of Renaissance garden iconography was nature itself. One sees, for instance, in the <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> above the Belvedere Court and the Villa Pia in the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Gardens, the desire for a wildwood, an evocation of the sacred grove in antiquity. Simi-<lb/>
larly, it is reported that <name type="pname">Pope Julius III</name>, with his taste for simple country food, peasant dances, and wine festivals, enjoyed strolling in the untamed parts of his <hi rend="italic">vigna</hi> (literally vineyard, the term contemporaries used for a suburban villa retreat). These were abun-<lb/>
dant with wildlife, melodious with birdsong, and adorned with works of art. Like their ancient prede-<lb/>
cessors, Renaissance villa owners wanted their groves to be haunted by the sculptural representatives of river gods, nymphs, satyrs, Pan, Diana, and <name type="pname">Venus</name>.</p>
<p>Added to this literary agenda was another, more obvious, motive for the development of Renaissance garden iconography: the aggrandizement of the gar-<lb/>
den owners' reputations through symbols, with the implication that the patrons' power was being put to beneficent use for humankind. Increasingly, after the middle of the sixteenth century, Italian gardens became manifestations of princely power. This was true in <name type="place">Florence</name> as well as in <name type="place">Rome</name>, although such Tuscan gardens as the <name type="pname">Medici</name> villa at <name type="pname">Castello</name> remained much more conservative in design than did the dazzling villa creations of the popes and cardinals in and around <name type="place">Rome</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="139"/>
<pb n="139" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Apotheoses of the Renaissance Villa Garden: Villa d'Este and Villa Lante</hi></hi></head>
<p>Although <name type="pname">Castello</name> and the Boboli Gardens contained water features symbolically associated with <name type="pname">Duke Cosi-<lb/>
mo</name>'s reputation as a builder of aqueducts, it is to the Roman Campagna that we must turn to find gardens that apotheosize water and use it with the inventiveness of a choreographer directing the movements of the dance or the creativity of a sculptor exploring the plasticity of clay. These effects were accomplished through the inge-<lb/>
nuity of sixteenth-century <hi rend="italic">fontanieri</hi>, virtuosic hydraulic engineers with an understanding of metaphysics as well as physics and a reputation akin to that of magicians because of the ingenuity of their creations.<ref target="#CH4-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref> In the gar-<lb/>
dens of Villa d'Este water reaches a height of expres-<lb/>
siveness that is analogous not only with dance and sculpture, but with music as well. For it is the drip and gurgle, the murmur and roar, the splash and tinkle, as well as the cooling spray, of water everywhere that has made this garden unforgettable to visitors through the centuries.</p>
<p>Like other superb gardens, Villa d'Este is the prod-<lb/>
uct of a passionate obsession on the part of an owner willing to spend extraordinary sums of money and with the taste to hire the best design talent available. In 1550, the cardinal of Ferrara, Ippolito D'Este (<date when="1509">1509</date>&#x2013;<date when="1572">1572</date>), was appointed governor of Tivoli by <name type="pname">Pope Julius III</name>. Tivoli, an ancient Roman summer resort about twenty miles west of <name type="place">Rome</name>, was not only the site of <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa, but of many other second century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> patrician villas. Its desirability then as later was due to the waters of the Aniene River, which came cascading dramatically down steep precipices; to its salubrious mineral springs; and to the excellent drinking water that was channeled from several sources along the riverbank to four major aqueducts serving the Roman metropolis. An aqueduct carrying water from the Rivellese Spring, the cost of which was borne by both the cardinal and the town of Tivoli, which also benefited, was built in 1561 after work on the garden had begun in earnest.</p>
<p>The governor's palace, a perquisite of the cardinal's appointment, was part of an old Franciscan monastery beside the Church of <name type="pname">Santa Maria</name> Maggiore at the top of a hill adjacent to the western town wall. <name type="pname">Pirro Ligorio</name> was commissioned to oversee the renovation of the palace into a summer residence suitable for <name type="pname">Cardinal Ippolito</name>, the son of <name type="pname">Duke Alfonso I</name> of Ferrara and Lucrezia Bor-<lb/>
gia. But the palace was to be a relatively minor element of the entire project; as the cardinal had already demon-<lb/>
strated at a villa he had rented on the Quirinal in <name type="place">Rome</name>, gardens were his passion. In <name type="pname">Ligorio</name> he had not only a capable designer but also the foremost archaeologist of his day, the person who was responsible for several exca-<lb/>
vations including that of nearby <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa and for the rediscovery of many antique marbles, mosaics, and other artifacts. Being a wealthy humanist collector, <name type="pname">Ippolito</name> had, in fact, put <name type="pname">Ligorio</name> on his payroll as his personal archaeologist in 1550, the year in which he had been appointed to the Tivoli post and had begun to dream of a great hillside garden below the palace. One part of <name type="pname">Ligorio</name>'s job was undoubtedly to garner antique marbles to combine with contemporary sculpture in allegorical compositions throughout the garden.</p>
<p>Although <name type="pname">Ligorio</name> was himself a sufficiently accomplished classicist to develop the various icono-<lb/>
graphic themes that would portray the humanistic ideals of the cardinal, he was probably assisted by the cardi-<lb/>
nal's resident poet, <name type="pname">Marc-Antoine Muret</name> (<date when="1526">1526</date>&#x2013;<date when="1585">1585</date>).<ref target="#CH4-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref> After 1560, <name type="pname">Giovanni Alberti Galvani</name> served as superintending architect in charge of overseeing the con-<lb/>
struction of masonry stairs, fountains, fish ponds, and other features. Professional <hi rend="italic">fontanieri</hi> were hired to develop the water devices that operated the spectacular fountains.</p>
<p>The construction of the gardens of the Villa d'Este continued over a twenty-two-year period until the cardi-<lb/>
nal's death in 1572, when work stopped abruptly. Con-<lb/>
temporary visitors, including the French essayist Montaigne (<date when="1533">1533</date>&#x2013;<date when="1592">1592</date>), lamented their unfinished state, although in the seventeenth century, when inheritance problems engendered by <name type="pname">Cardinal Ippolito</name>'s will were finally resolved, <name type="pname">Cardinal Alessandro</name> d'Este undertook some restoration and improvements. While vegetative growth, alterations, and periodic lack of maintenance have blurred some of the formality seen in a contempo-<lb/>
rary engraving, we can still discern <name type="pname">Ligorio</name>'s design and, with the help of modern scholarship, decode the human-<lb/>
ist themes that are woven into its fabric: Nature's abun-<lb/>
dance and generosity and the relationship between Art and Nature&#x2014;one of the central preoccupations of the Renaissance (figs. 4.17&#x2013;4.20). In parsing the humanist meaning of the garden, which besides expressing the Art-Nature duality has many references to the virtuous mythological hero <name type="pname">Hercules</name>, here identified with <name type="pname">Cardi-<lb/>
nal d'Este</name>, one should remember that the original public entry to the garden was not from the villa, but rather from a gate in the outer wall set in the hillside below.</p>
<p>Standing on the balcony of the villa today, the vis-<lb/>
itor looks beyond the verdant mature tree canopy of the gardens to the distant hills. Below is the <name type="pname">Cardinal's Walk</name> and the rainbow spray of Bernini's seventeenth-century Fountain of the Great Beaker, which mingles visually with the watery plume of the Fountain of the Dragons beneath it. The dragons symbolize the ones guarding the Garden of the Hesperides, which were slain by <name type="pname">Hercules</name>. Descending one of the diagonal ramps, one comes to the Alley of the Hundred Fountains composed of three con-<lb/>
duits symbolizing the three tributaries of the Tiber, which flow from the hills of Tivoli toward <name type="place">Rome</name>. Here
<pb n="140"/>
<pb n="140" type="orig"/>
<q><hi rend="bold">villa d'este</hi></q>
<figure xml:id="fig-138">
<graphic url="CH4_018.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.17. Villa d'Este, Tivoli. Designed by <name type="pname">Pirro Ligorio</name>. 1550&#x2013;72. Panoramic view after an engraving by <name type="pname">&#x00C9;tienne Dup&#x00E9;rac</name>. 1573</figDesc>
</figure>
<q>The traditional plan of most Italian Renais-<lb/>
sance gardens&#x2014;a plan in which there are compartmentalized beds near the villa and, as one approaches the outer limits of the property, a surrounding screen of trees&#x2014;has been reversed here because of the nature of the site. A wooded slope with diagonal paths to accommodate the steep grade lies directly beneath the retaining wall supporting the villa terrace. Where the valley has been remodeled by an extensive process of cutting and filling to create an apron of level terrain and a geometrically pitched northeast side slope, cross-axes divide the garden into square compart-<lb/>
ments.</q>
<q>The relationship between Art and Nature constitutes the principal theme of the garden's iconography. Nature is dramat-<lb/>
ically manifested in the Fountain of Nature, also known as the Water Organ, culminating the water axis on the northeast (fig. 4.18). Following a "concert," which occurred when water pressure was manipulated to trap and release air in its pipes, a <hi rend="italic">fontaniere</hi> would flush the vaulted chambers behind the elaborate facade, and a deluge would spill down the steep slope. This effect was made permanent in the twentieth-century Fountain of the Cascade, an enormous waterfall pouring into the pond below. An earlier cascade was created here by the seventeenth-century architect, sculptor, and fountain designer, <name type="pname">Gianlorenzo Bernini</name> (<date when="1598">1598</date>&#x2013;<date when="1680">1680</date>); it fell in successive stages like a natural waterfall rather than as the dra-<lb/>
matic sheer spill we see today.</q>
<q>The human ability to employ the resources of nature toward fruitful ends constitutes Art, which is celebrated along the second major cross-axis, the Alley of the Hundred Fountains (fig. 4.20). The Alley itself is composed of three conduits sym-<lb/>
bolizing the three tributaries of the Tiber&#x2014;the Albuneo, the Aniene, and the Erculaneo&#x2014;which flow toward <name type="place">Rome</name>. The art of channeling their waters into aque-<lb/>
ducts was an important factor in the life of the recently reborn metropolis. Along the upper rim, water is channeled between carved obelisks, boats, eagles, and <hi rend="italic">fleurs de lys</hi> (the last two forms being emblematic of the Este family).</q>
<q>At the northeast end of the Alley of the Hundred Fountains, within an enclosed piazza, stands the principal fountain of the garden, the Fountain of Tivoli, or as it is now known, the Oval Fountain (fig. 4.19). A colossal statue of Albunea, the Tiburtine Sibyl, presides over the cascade, which is furnished by water from the River Aniene, which flows into an oval basin surmounted by a ball; its spurting jets delineate the Este <hi rend="italic">fleur de lys</hi>. The sources of the Aniene and the Erculaneo are represented as reclining river gods set in naturalistic grottoes built into the surrounding slope. Crowning this artificial rock work is a statue of Pegasus, the magical horse whose hoofprints sup-<lb/>
posedly struck water out of Mount Parnas-<lb/>
sos, thereby creating the fountain of the Muses and proclaiming the power of Art.</q>
<pb n="141"/>
<pb n="141" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-139">
<graphic url="CH4_019.jpg"/>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-140">
<graphic url="CH4_020.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.18. Fountain of Nature, engraving by <name type="pname">Giovanni Francesco Venturini</name>, plate 13 from <hi rend="italic">Le Fontane del Giardino Estense in Tivoli, con li loro prospeti, e Vedute della Cascata del Fiume Aniene, Parte Quarta</hi>. n.d.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-141">
<graphic url="CH4_021.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.19. Oval Fountain</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-142">
<graphic url="CH4_022.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.20. Alley of the Hundred Fountains</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="142"/>
<pb n="142" type="orig"/>
water is channeled between carved obelisks, boats, eagles, and <hi rend="italic">fleur de lys</hi> (the last two forms being emblematic of the Este family) and pours from one basin into another through grotesque animal heads.</p>
<p>After visiting the Fountain of Tivoli and the Fountain of the Rometta, a water feature that was fashioned of stucco-covered brick to represent ancient <name type="place">Rome</name> in miniature, one returns to descend one aim of the sweeping oval staircase and gaze back up at the villa through the spray of the Dragon Foun-<lb/>
tain. Taking the central staircase, which has channels of clear water running down its flanking walls, one arrives at the next level, that of the fish ponds. Here, looking back toward the villa, one realizes that <name type="pname">Ligo-<lb/>
rio</name> has repeated <name type="pname">Bramante</name>'s design for the Belvedere Court as a series of descending terraces organized around a central axis. But there is an important differ-<lb/>
ence: <name type="pname">Bramante</name>'s Renaissance garden could be grasped in its entirety from a single vantage point within the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Palace, but the Villa d'Este cannot be taken in altogether. Not only is it more spatially intricate than the <name type="pname">Bramante</name> prototype, but it is also a programmatic garden, one in which the separate parts are meant to be experienced sequentially as part of a humanist itinerary that celebrates the importance of <name type="pname">Cardinal d'Este</name> and the noble family of which he was the most conspicuous representative. Today, it is shorn of much of the sculptural decoration because the cardinal's fine collection of antique statuary was sold in the eighteenth century. While this loss deprives the villa of iconographic specificity and the-<lb/>
matic continuity, the garden tour that was once enjoyed by the cardinal's guests and subsequent trav-<lb/>
elers nevertheless remains a memorable experience for modern visitors.</p>
<p>Contemporary with the Villa d'Este is <name type="pname">Cardinal Giovanni Francesco Gambara</name>'s garden at Bagnaia, three miles east of the town of Viterbo. It is known today by the name of its seventeenth-century owners, the Lante family. Like the Villa d'Este, it offers a virtuosic expression of Bramantian axial planning combined with a highly imaginative use of water. Also like the Villa d'Este, the Villa Lante is filled with an allusive iconography wedding humanist learning to personal glory and family pride. It bears further similarity in being a garden that is meant not to be taken in all at once, but rather as sequential stops along a prescribed route that move the visitor off the central axis. Here, however, the garden itiner-<lb/>
ary has a prologue as one is meant to pass first through the kind of "dark wood" traversed by certain literary figures as they started out on their journeys of initiation, a device with great appeal to the humanist imagination.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name> was given the bishopric of Viterbo in 1566, and two years later received confir-<lb/>
mation of one of the perquisites of his office, property rights in the old hunting park at Bagnaia. His prede-<lb/>
cessors had enclosed the park, which consisted of the wooded slope of <name type="pname">Monte Sant' Angelo</name>, and had built the aqueduct that brought water to the town as well as to the park. A small hunting lodge was the only structure on the property when the cardinal conceived the notion of building a great villa garden there. In place of the <hi rend="italic">barco</hi>, or park for hunting, there would be a twenty-acre <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> with the kinds of messages of allusion that a humanist scholar steeped in the litera-<lb/>
ture of antiquity would have sought. Continuing this iconographic narrative, there would be a formal gar-<lb/>
den in which Art gained the upper hand over Nature, in celebration of the cardinal's magnificence and benefactions to the people of Viterbo.</p>
<p>The designer of Villa Lante is almost univer-<lb/>
sally believed to have been the architect <name type="pname">Giacomo da Vignola</name>, whose services <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name> begged of his friend <name type="pname">Cardinal Alessandro Farnese</name>, as <name type="pname">Vignola</name> was then engaged upon another important garden commission at the Villa Farnese nearby at Caprarola. Construction proceeded over the next decade, and in <date when="1579-08">August 1579</date>, a lavish banquet was given there for <name type="pname">Pope Gregory XIII</name> (papacy <date when="1572">1572</date>&#x2013;<date when="1585">1585</date>), after which the pontiff promptly canceled Gambara's pension. Knowing that Gambara had been appointed by <name type="pname">Pope Gregory</name>'s predecessor, the reform-minded <name type="pname">Pius V</name> (papacy <date when="1566">1566</date>&#x2013;<date when="1572">1572</date>), and that he was a prominent officer of the Inquisition, we may find it strange that he would build opulently, in a style derived from pagan art and literature. That, however, was the men-<lb/>
tality of a proud and wealthy aristocrat whose appointment had as much to do with politics as with piety.</p>
<p>While the garden is the renowned part of Villa Lante and the park is often neglected by visitors, one should tour the <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> first in order to follow the itin-<lb/>
erary planned by <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>. The <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> evokes the Golden Age myth, investing it with another, that of a punishing flood familiar to readers of the Old Testament. In the classical version, because of human wickedness, Jupiter, like Jehovah in the Hebrew scriptures, became angry and decided to destroy the earth with a flood so mighty that dolphins could be found swimming in the forest. Only two vir-<lb/>
tuous humans were left to repopulate, and their descendants were compelled to labor in order to make the earth fruitful.</p>
<p>The garden spells out the virtues of <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>, who made the surrounding land more bountiful and, in the tradition of classical civilization, was a patron of the arts enabling the human spirit to reach its highest potential. This, in brief, is the mes-<lb/>
<pb n="143"/>
<pb n="143" type="orig"/>
sage of the park and its adjacent garden. It develops through design, as at the Villa d'Este, the age-old theme of relationship among humans, art, and nature, while symbolically portraying the heroic efforts of one man in bringing the three into such an enriching harmony as to constitute a second Golden Age (figs. 4.21&#x2013;4.27).<ref target="#CH4-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> Thus, the humanistic text encoded in its design program gives, as does that of the contempo-<lb/>
rary Villa d'Este, a literary dimension to the garden experience, and the presence throughout the garden of the cardinal's device in the form of a crayfish (a visual pun matching his family name, <hi rend="italic">Gambara</hi>, with <hi rend="italic">gam-<lb/>
bero</hi>, the word for "crayfish" in Italian) suggests his achievement.</p>
<p>Inspired by a sense of ancient geometry and pro-<lb/>
portion as well as by the iconographic program derived from antique themes, the Villa Lante can be seen in plan as a counterpoint of circles and squares. It is finally this balance and harmony of design, and not the mes-<lb/>
sages of a new Golden Age under <name type="pname">Pius V</name> or <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>'s prestige in the guise of humanism, that account for the deep pleasure that so many visitors have experienced in viewing it. In creating a hillside garden built upon a clear, strong axis, its several terraces linked by stairs, <name type="pname">Vignola</name> displayed a debt to <name type="pname">Bramante</name>. But he altered and expanded <name type="pname">Bramante</name>'s design means. His axis is aquatic and can only be traveled visually for the most part; one walks alongside it, perceiving it perhaps more powerfully for this very reason. And, instead of the architectural climax of the Belvedere exedra, here the central axis simply melts into nature as it ends in the Fountain of the Deluge.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-143">
<graphic url="CH4_023.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.21. The Villa Lante, Viterbo. Designed probably by <name type="pname">Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola</name>. c. <date when="1568">1568</date>&#x2013;<date when="1579">1579</date></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Extravagant Epitome of Humanist Allegory: The <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">Sacro Bosco</hi></name> at Bomarzo</hi></hi></head>
<p>We must turn to Bomarzo near Viterbo, the garden of <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>'s friend <name type="pname">Count Pier Francesco Ors-<lb/>
ini</name> (1513?&#x2013;1584), to see the arcane climax of human-<lb/>
ism as a programmatic factor in garden design. The epic poem <hi rend="italic">Orlando Furioso</hi>, completed in 1532 by <name type="pname">Ludovico Ariosto</name> (<date when="1473">1473</date>&#x2013;<date when="1533">1533</date>), as well as <name type="pname">Virgil</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>, <name type="pname">Dante</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, and probably the writings of <name type="pname">Petrarch</name>, provided inspiration for this enigmatic land-<lb/>
scape in which Count Orsini manipulated scale and perspective to create an itinerary of unusual scenes studded with bizarre sculpture and architectural mon-<lb/>
uments forming a series of tableaux, each serving as a riddle to be decoded by his guests.</p>
<p>It was only gradually that Bomarzo assumed its character as an enchanted forest, or <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">sacro bosco</hi></name>, as the count developed one part after another into an itinerary of personal history and symbolical discovery. For instance, the gruesome tableau of a stone giant tearing
<pb n="144"/>
<pb n="144" type="orig"/>
<q><hi rend="bold">villa lante</hi></q>
<figure xml:id="fig-144">
<graphic url="CH4_024.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.22. Plan of the Villa Lante.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-145">
<graphic url="CH4_025.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.23. Fountain of Pegasus</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-146">
<graphic url="CH4_026.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.24. Fountain of the Deluge</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="145"/>
<pb n="145" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-147">
<graphic url="CH4_027.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Above left:</hi> 4.25. Water Chain</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-148">
<graphic url="CH4_028.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Above:</hi> 4.26. River Gods representing the Tiber and the Arno</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-149">
<graphic url="CH4_029.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 4.27. Boxwood compartments and Water <hi rend="italic">Parterre</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<q><hi rend="bold">U</hi>pon entering the Villa Lante, one first encounters the Fountain of Pegasus sur-<lb/>
rounded by Muses <hi rend="bold">F</hi>, perhaps derived from the Pegasus on the rock above the Oval Fountain at Villa d'Este. In both, the winged horse's hoof striking the earth gen-<lb/>
erates the Spring of Hippocrene, symbol of the source of artistic creativity (fig. 4.23).</q>
<q>Along one of the diagonal paths through the park was the Fountain of the Acorns, now vanished, which linked the <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> with the Golden Age, since acorns were, according to <name type="pname">Ovid</name>, a staple in the diet of Arcadian man. Another vanished foun-<lb/>
tain, that of Bacchus, evokes <name type="pname">Virgil</name>'s descriptions of the Golden Age when wine was believed to run freely in streams from the ground. Other trellis-surrounded foun-<lb/>
tains depicting unicorns and dragons sym-<lb/>
bolized the life of virtue and helped establish the identity of the park as the earthly paradise. High up the wooded slope there is a gate through which one can enter the garden at its top. There one is con-<lb/>
fronted by the Fountain of the Deluge <hi rend="bold">A</hi>, a fern-encrusted grotto with six openings from which water drips and pours into a basin where two dolphins are swimming, their forms now almost obliterated by veg-<lb/>
etation (fig. 4.24). This refers to <name type="pname">Ovid</name>'s account of the destruction of mankind by flood. Flanking the Fountain of the Deluge, twin dining pavilions, known as the Log-<lb/>
gias of the Muses, bear the name and cray-<lb/>
fish device of <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>. (The word for crayfish is <hi rend="italic">gambero</hi> in Italian, and his crest is therefore a visual pun referring to his name.) Reinforcing the symbolism of the Deluge, small pipes installed beneath the eaves of the pavilions that frame the Fountain of the Deluge allowed water to rain from above. These also served a sport-<lb/>
ive function, permitting water tricks in which garden visitors were sometimes treated to an unexpected drenching in keeping with the humor of the day. Sym-<lb/>
metrical colonnaded aviaries, modeled probably on descriptions of those in Var-<lb/>
ro's ancient garden, were designed as wings to the Loggias of the Muses, and within them berry-producing plants were grown to attract songbirds.</q>
<q>Around the octagonal Fountain of the Dolphins <hi rend="bold">B</hi>, below some stairs, a stepped ramp leads down to the next terrace. A greatly elongated crawfish, its head and front claws emanating from the middle of the stairs at the top of the ramp and its rear claws hanging over top of the Fountain of the River Gods that stands on the terrace below, forms a <hi rend="italic">catena d'acqua</hi>, or water chain (fig. 4.25; <hi rend="bold">C</hi>). Its linked curves both create and echo the movement of the swirl-<lb/>
ing water that spills over the shallow shell-<lb/>
like basins set within it. Thus, out of the wreck of the Deluge, <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name> can be seen to be harnessing water for human welfare. The water spilling through the beneficent crayfish's claws symbolically becomes the Tiber and the Arno as it falls into the basin flanked by the two great river gods (fig. 4.26). Their cornucopias denote the fertility that water brings to the land, a fertility that is emphasized by the statues of Flora and Pomona standing in niches within the retaining wall near the base of the steps leading from the terrace above. In the middle of this terrace, which is flanked by rows of plane trees, stands the Fountain of the Table. The stone table with its central water channel and bubbling jets provided <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name> and his guests with an experience similar to that of ancient Romans whose banqueting arrangements sometimes included pools upon which ser-<lb/>
vants floated food (see figs. 2.42, 2.46).</q>
<q>The Fountain of Lights <hi rend="bold">D</hi> links the <name type="pname">Cardinal</name>'s dining terrace with the water the-<lb/>
ater below, a concentric construction of upper concave and lower convex steps. One hundred sixty small jets shoot upward from small lamps when the fountain is turned on; water pours from the sides of each step into a channel in the one below. From the terrace of the Fountain of Lights, one gazes down upon a series of garden compartments outlined in boxwood and a central water parterre. Within the water <hi rend="italic">par-<lb/>
terre</hi> <hi rend="bold">E</hi> is a circular island, recalling per-<lb/>
haps the Marine Theater at <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa (fig. 4.27; see fig. 2.44). The loggias of the twin <hi rend="italic">palazzine</hi> open onto the garden, and in them one finds frescoes depicting the Villa Farnese at Caprarola, the Villa d'Este at Tivoli, and the Villa Lante itself. In this part of the garden, wild nature has been thor-<lb/>
oughly tamed by art, and <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name> is seen as the patron of this transformation. <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>'s origi-<lb/>
nal centerpiece of the island terrace, a water-oozing spire (<hi rend="italic">meta sudans</hi>), was replaced in the seventeenth century by four bronze youths holding aloft <name type="pname">Cardinal Ales-<lb/>
sandro Peretti Montalto</name>'s device of three mountains and a star. The surrounding water parterre was meant to evoke an ancient <hi rend="italic">naumachia</hi>, a flooded theater where mock naval battles were held. In each of its four ponds is a small stone boat holding stone arquebusiers. These were engineered to fire jets of water toward the central fountain.</q>
<pb n="146"/>
<pb n="146" type="orig"/>
young man apart is derived from a scene in <hi rend="italic">Orlando Furioso</hi> and may refer to Orsini's grief after being rejected by a young woman; whereas the war ele-<lb/>
phant carrying a dead soldier with its trunk and other fantastical figures grouped around a gaping Hell Mouth bearing an inscription derived from <name type="pname">Dante</name> resemble the monsters at the entrance to the under-<lb/>
world in the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi> (figs. 4.28, 4.29). Like the Villa d'Este and Villa Lante, the <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">sacro bosco</hi></name> of Bomarzo is a domain of allusions. Its architecture and sculpture represent various literary themes, not least of which is the theme of the sacred wood itself, a deity-haunted precinct, an Arcadia, or <hi rend="italic">locus amoenus</hi> like those found in <name type="pname">Ovid</name> or <name type="pname">Virgil</name>. One may approach this curi-<lb/>
ous place therefore with a disposition to look for humanistic literary themes, autobiographical and philosophical allusions, a great deal of epigrammatic didacticism, and a fascination with the antique and the exotic such as propels <name type="pname">Colonna</name>'s narrative in the <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi>&#x2014;indeed, the same kind of Renaissance appetite for marvels as is found in <name type="pname">Shakespeare</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Tempest</hi>.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-150">
<graphic url="CH4_030.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.28. Sculpture of a giant tearing a young man apart, <name type="pname">Sacro Bosco</name>, <name type="pname">Bomarzo</name>. After 1542. Carved from the native rock, this ensemble represents a scene from <hi rend="italic">Orlando Furioso</hi> and is believed to express Orsini's passionate despair over the rejection of his suit by a young woman with whom he had fallen in love some years after his wife's death.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-151">
<graphic url="CH4_031.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.29. <name type="pname">Hell Mask</name>, <name type="pname">Sacro Bosco</name>, <name type="pname">Bomarzo</name>. The legend above the <name type="pname">Hell Mask</name>, drawn from <name type="pname">Dante</name>, reads in translation: "Cast away every thought, you who enter here." But instead of embarking upon a terrifying journey into the underworld, Orsini's guests were actually being invited into a banquet pavilion. The huge stone tongue within the <name type="pname">Hell Mask</name> served as a table and its eyes as windows.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Much of the garden's intended meaning is obvi-<lb/>
ously lost upon the modern visitor who is directed to the garden of the Villa Orsini by signs pointing to the "Parco dei Mostri" (Park of Monsters), an invitation for tourists to stop and gawk at a collection of fantas-<lb/>
tic forms, some of which are carved out of the living rock, a soft tufa. Lacking familiarity with the literary symbolism that was the common currency of human-<lb/>
ist intellectuals, one may at first wonder: Is this an exhibition showing the hallucinations of a deranged brain? Is it a sixteenth-century version of Coney Island with some of the twentieth-century amusement park's topsy-turvy atmosphere and penchant for the freakish, the magical, and the macabre?</p>
<p>Although now exploited commercially as a local wonder, the garden at Bomarzo, in fact, provides a fascinating window on the landscape of the Renais-<lb/>
sance. Count Orsini, a renowned military captain and friend of several eminent men of letters, inherited the property at Bomarzo in 1542. Shortly thereafter he married <name type="pname">Giulia Farnese</name> to whom he was apparently deeply devoted, as evidenced by the small temple commemorating her, which is the culmination of the visitor's itinerary through the garden. Interrupted by the count's military campaigns, the building of the <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">sacro bosco</hi></name> nevertheless became his obsession and occupied his imagination until his death in 1585.</p>
<p>Bomarzo's lack of a tautly geometric plan is explained by the fact that it was built by several different architects who attempted to express the owner's literary and personal passions over a long period of time. The result is a closer approximation in spirit to the multivalent, initiatory, and allegorical character of the <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi> than per-<lb/>
haps any other Renaissance garden. Its disorganized appearance and the discrepancies in scale among its monuments are further explained by the fact that these fantastic forms were carved from various natu-<lb/>
ral boulders strewn about the site. There is even uncertainty as to the point of entry, although logic points to the northeast corner, where two sphinxes bear legends enjoining the visitor to discern with awe and amazement the marvelous character of the works that lie beyond.</p>
<p>Bomarzo is a unique expression of landscape art, and its inherent theatricality points the way to the dra-<lb/>
matic character of seventeenth-century Baroque design, a stylistic development we will trace in the next chapter. Here we will turn our attention to villas of a different character in which abstract mathematical composition and architectural spatial configuration is much more important than humanist iconography.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="147"/>
<pb n="147" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Palladian Villas of the Veneto</hi></hi></head>
<p><name type="pname">Andrea Palladio</name> (<date when="1508">1508</date>&#x2013;<date when="1580">1580</date>) is one of the most influ-<lb/>
ential figures in the history of architecture because of his famous treatise <hi rend="italic">I quattro libri dell'architettura</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">The Four Books of Architecture</hi> (1570), and the Olym-<lb/>
pian beauty of his work. A stonemason by training, he became the prot&#x00E9;g&#x00E9; around 1537 of <name type="pname">Giangiorgio Tris-<lb/>
sino</name>, a Venetian humanist who had formed an academy in his villa near Vicenza where young nobles received a classical education. Vicenza is located in the Veneto, the mainland region in the alluvial plains at the foot-<lb/>
hills of the Alps that Venetians refer to as the <hi rend="italic">terra-<lb/>
ferma</hi> where the city-state of <name type="place">Venice</name> had established control beginning in the fourteenth century. Although still a thriving maritime republic, <name type="place">Venice</name> needed a land base as a means of defense and to control its food sup-<lb/>
ply, a prudent investment and sound economy, too, in an inflationary age. In addition, patrician Venetians were attracted to the charms of rural life, or the <hi rend="italic">villeg-<lb/>
giatura</hi>, as they, like other Italians who sojourned out-<lb/>
side <name type="place">Rome</name> and <name type="place">Florence</name>, called their periodic residence at their country estates. Men such as <name type="pname">Daniele Barbaro</name>, another important patron of Palladio's, found precedent for involving themselves in agricultural affairs in the ancient Roman authors <name type="pname">Cato</name>, <name type="pname">Varro</name>, and <name type="pname">Columella</name>. <name type="pname">Trissino</name> was instrumental in helping Palladio initiate his career as an architect with commissions from the nobility of Vicenza for palaces and villas.</p>
<p>In publishing his <hi rend="italic">Quattro libri</hi> <name type="pname">Palladio</name> had as precedent the books of <name type="pname">Sebastiano Serlio</name> (<date when="1475">1475</date>&#x2013;<date when="1554">1554</date>), issued in six parts between 1537 and 1551. Collected and published posthumously in 1584 as <hi rend="italic">L'Architettura</hi>, these treatises codified the five classical orders&#x2014;Doric, Tuscan, Ionic, Corinthian, and Composite. <name type="pname">Ser-<lb/>
lio</name>'s illustrations were a design resource for <name type="pname">Palladio</name>, and like <name type="pname">Serlio</name>, <name type="pname">Palladio</name> took advantage of <name type="place">Venice</name>'s leadership in the field of printing when he published his own well-illustrated, similarly formatted work. In addi-<lb/>
tion, <name type="pname">Palladio</name> was introduced by <name type="pname">Trissino</name> to the architectural treatise of <name type="pname">Vitruvius</name>, <hi rend="italic">Ten Books of Architecture</hi>, and Barbaro asked him to provide the illustrations for his commentary on this work, which appeared in 1556. <name type="pname">Palladio</name> was, of course, familiar with <name type="pname">Alberti</name>'s treatise, <hi rend="italic">De re aedificatoria</hi>. <name type="pname">Alvise Cornaro</name>, a humanist with an interest in architecture, whom <name type="pname">Palladio</name> met when he lived for a time in Padua, nourished in him a practical approach to design and a respect for <hi rend="italic">santa agricoltura</hi>, blessed agriculture, and the farmers who cultivated the land.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Palladio</name>'s understanding of classical form was wedded to a profoundly architectural imagination. Adorned with pedimented facades like Roman tem-<lb/>
ples, the villas he built in the Veneto dominate the land-<lb/>
scape in a regal manner. <name type="pname">Palladio</name> considered carefully their position in relationship to the landscape. In Book Two of <hi rend="italic">I quattro libri</hi>, he offered these siting instruc-<lb/>
tions: "Don't build in valleys enclosed between hills because buildings in hidden valleys, apart from being invisible from a distance and having no view them-<lb/>
selves, lack dignity and majesty."<ref target="#CH4-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref> As the architectural historian <name type="pname">Caroline Constant</name> explains, <name type="pname">Palladio</name> was interested in scenographic space, or space that is phys-<lb/>
ically discontinuous, an assemblage on the ground plane that is perceptual and therefore unlike perspec-<lb/>
tival space, which is contained and defined by walls. She asserts that "for <name type="pname">Palladio</name> the ground plane was, conceptually, a surface of human manufacture rather than part of the natural world, and hence, a <hi rend="italic">tabula rasa</hi>. It served&#x2014;much as the picture plane did for Cub-<lb/>
ism&#x2014;as a base on which to conduct various experi-<lb/>
ments into the nature of three-dimensional form. By elevating the central block of the villa, <name type="pname">Palladio</name> stressed the idealized nature of the ground plane, creating a new ground from which to survey the surrounding domain. Without the building, we would not see the landscape in the same terms; the architecture gathers the land-<lb/>
scape into its domain and redimensions it."<ref target="#CH4-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>For the papal prelate <name type="pname">Daniele Barbaro</name> and his brother, <name type="pname">Marc'Antonio Barbaro</name>, an important Venetian statesman, <name type="pname">Palladio</name> built the Villa Barbaro at Maser (Treviso) in the Veneto on the plain below the Dolo-<lb/>
mite foothills during the decade of the 1550s (fig. 4.30). Built on the foundation of a medieval <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">castello</hi></name>, the villa's projecting main building block has a stuc-<lb/>
coed Roman-templelike facade and is flanked by ser-<lb/>
vice wings that end in dovecotes. These are elegant renditions of local vernacular architecture, as the <hi rend="italic">barchesse</hi>,_or utilitarian farm building, and the dove-<lb/>
cote were typical constructions in the north Italian rural countryside. Unique among the works of <name type="pname">Palladio</name>, the <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi> here is a hemicycle with sculptural niches. <name type="pname">Palladio</name> may have been influenced in its design by such Roman models as the <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name> and <name type="pname">Pirro Ligo-<lb/>
rio</name>'s plans for Villa d'Este, both of which were roughly contemporary with the Villa Barbaro (fig. 4.31). How-<lb/>
ever, the villa has an entirely different relationship to its landscape surroundings than do Roman or Tuscan villas where walls, rather than the ground plane, artic-<lb/>
ulate and contain space. Placed near the juncture of the arable plain and the wooded hillside, the Villa Barbaro at Maser <hi rend="italic">presides</hi> over its landscape, a beautiful object <hi rend="italic">in</hi> space, with space having priority over object, which nonetheless aggrandizes and confers meaning upon its spatial surroundings. Complementing the Palladian architectural and landscape treatment of the Villa Bar-<lb/>
baro are the magnificent frescoes by Veronese (<name type="pname">Paolo Caliari</name>, <date when="1528">1528</date>&#x2013;<date when="1588">1588</date>), which illusionistically amplify interior space with poetically classical landscapes and
<pb n="148"/>
<pb n="148" type="orig"/>
figures.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-152">
<graphic url="CH4_032.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.30. Villa Barbaro, Maser (Treviso). Designed by <name type="pname">Andrea Palladio</name>. <date when="1549">1549</date>&#x2013;<date when="1558">58</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-153">
<graphic url="CH4_033.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 4.31. <hi rend="italic">Nymphaeum</hi>, Villa Barbaro</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-154">
<graphic url="CH4_034.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Bottom:</hi> 4.32. Villa Rotonda, Vicenza. Designed by <name type="pname">Andrea Palladio</name>. <date when="1565">1565</date>&#x2013;<date when="1569">69</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The reciprocal relationship between Palladian architecture and landscape found at the Villa Barbaro, in which neither gains the upper hand but each gains something from and is enhanced by the other, is even more apparent at the Villa Almerico-Valmarana, called "La Rotonda" or Villa Rotonda, in the rural environs of Vicenza (fig. 4.32). Built between 1565/6 and 1569 for the recently returned papal prelate Paolo Almerico on property he owned outside the city, it may not have been conceived like other nearby villas as a working farm, but merely as a country retreat, although this is a subject of scholarly debate. Villa Rotonda is unusual also in having four pedimented facades, because as <name type="pname">Pal-<lb/>
ladio</name> explained in <hi rend="italic">I quattro libri</hi>, "it enjoys beautiful views on every side."<ref target="#CH4-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref> He described the site as a the-<lb/>
ater, and the villa on its slight hill is in its isolation and lack of ancillary structures like a solo performer within the ring of surrounding hills, the focal point of a larger landscape composition.</p>
<p>Because of his ability to scenographically unite serenely aloof, abstract classical forms and rustic sur-<lb/>
roundings, <name type="pname">Palladio</name>'s villas have served as models from his time to the present for country villas where land-<lb/>
scape statements harmonizing the inherent tension between human reason and nature have been honored within the imagination of a culture or an individual. Palladian influence was especially strong in eigh-<lb/>
teenth-century <name type="place">England</name> where aristocrats such as <name type="pname">Lord Burlington</name> and <name type="pname">Charles Howard</name>, the third earl of <name type="pname">Carl-<lb/>
isle</name>, among others, revered his architectural genius.<ref target="#CH4-n20"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref> The American president <name type="pname">Thomas Jefferson</name> owned four copies of <hi rend="italic">I quattro libri</hi>, and as an architect himself he appreciated and emulated <name type="pname">Palladio</name> when he built his own hilltop residence, Monticello.<ref target="#CH4-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">21</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p><name type="pname">Palladio</name> as well as his predecessors <name type="pname">Colonna</name>, <name type="pname">Alberti</name>, and <name type="pname">Serlio</name> grasped the importance of printing as a means of transmitting architectural ideas and visual information. As we shall see in this and subsequent chapters, both politics and the printing press carried the currents of humanism and architectural theory from <name type="place">Italy</name> into <name type="place">France</name> and then farther afield. At the same time, design ideas first propounded in garden settings soon influenced what we today call city planning, land-<lb/>
scapes on an urban scale.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="149"/>
<pb n="149" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">III. Axial Planning on an Urban Scale: The Development of Renaissance <name type="place">Rome</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>The same popes who were adding verdant charm to the edges of the ancient city with the construction of gar-<lb/>
dens such as those of the <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name> and the Villa Mad-<lb/>
ama were simultaneously applying the principles of landscape design to the rebuilding of <name type="place">Rome</name> itself From its ancient imperial pre-eminence as a world capital, <name type="place">Rome</name> had shrunk during the Middle Ages to a popula-<lb/>
tion of 17,000 housed in a tangle of small dwellings huddled in the elbow of the Tiber that lies opposite <name type="pname">Cas-<lb/>
tel Sant'Angelo</name> and the <name type="place">Vatican</name> (fig. 4.33). The third-century Aurelian walls outlined a much larger area. These contained the ruins of the Palatine, the Col-<lb/>
osseum, the great imperial baths, triumphal arches, commemorative columns, and the moldering remains of the Forum where cattle grazed from late antiquity to the eighteenth century. Within this spectral setting of imperial glory several churches and monasteries had been built during the Middle Ages. Only footpaths con-<lb/>
nected them to one another and the urban core beside the Tiber.</p>
<p>After their return from exile in Avignon in 1377, and following the bull of 1439, which granted hierarchi-<lb/>
cal authority to the bishop of <name type="place">Rome</name>, the popes gradually gathered into their hands the reins of munici-pal power, wresting control over urban affairs from the commune and the warring factions of the nobility. The <hi rend="italic">maestri di strada</hi>, equivalent to modern planning commissioners, were brought into the administrative apparatus of the Church. At the same time, the Church acquired the power of eminent domain and the ability to levy improvement taxes on property owners. <name type="place">Rome</name>, already landmark-studded but with no regular street plan, offered a challenging opportunity for the application of the newly redeveloped principles of axial composition. Given the wealth of the Church and its desire to augment its international position during the Counter-Reforma-<lb/>
tion, it is not surprising that a series of popes eagerly embraced this opportunity.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The <name type="pname">Via Giulia</name>, <name type="pname">Piazza Sant'Angelo</name>, and the <name type="pname">Campidoglio</name></hi></hi></head>
<p><name type="pname">Julius II</name> (papacy <date when="1503">1503</date>&#x2013;<date when="1513">1513</date>) wished to extend the papal administrative, judicial, and financial functions into the Banchi, the business district opposite the <name type="pname">Ponte Sant' Angelo</name>. He therefore commissioned <name type="pname">Bramante</name> (who was already employed on the construction of the Belve-<lb/>
dere Court) to design a straight street with uniform build-<lb/>
ing heights running to the Ponte Sisto. The <name type="pname">Via Giulia</name>, commemorating <name type="pname">Pope Julius</name>, thus opened up this laby-<lb/>
rinthine medieval quarter.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-155">
<graphic url="CH4_035.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.33. Engraving by <name type="pname">N. Beatrizet</name> showing medieval <name type="place">Rome</name>, Aurelian walls, and ancient ruins. 1557</figDesc>
</figure>
<p><name type="pname">Leo X</name> (papacy <date when="1513">1513</date>&#x2013;<date when="1521">1521</date> ), the <name type="pname">Medici</name> pope, and <name type="pname">Paul III</name> (papacy <date when="1534">1534</date>&#x2013;<date when="1549">1549</date>) further regularized the
<pb n="150"/>
<pb n="150" type="orig"/>
area with the construction of three more straight streets that radiated from the <name type="pname">Piazza Sant'Angelo</name>, thereby creating the first Roman example of a <hi rend="italic">trivio</hi>, a place where three ways meet, a form later employed in lay-<lb/>
ing out the Villa Montalto in <name type="place">Rome</name> and the Villa Aldo-<lb/>
brandini in Frascati. These same two popes were responsible for a second <hi rend="italic">trivio</hi> with much longer streets beginning at the Piazza del Popolo. Subse-<lb/>
quently the <hi rend="italic">trivio</hi> was employed in <name type="place">France</name> where a three-pronged set of radial avenues was called a <hi rend="italic">patte d'oie</hi>, or goose foot.</p>
<p>The point of juncture between the city of the glo-<lb/>
rious imperial past and the modern city of the popes, the Capitoline Hill, one of the seven hills of <name type="place">Rome</name>, was in the time of <name type="pname">Paul III</name> a muddy, forlorn open space. When the <name type="pname">Holy Roman Emperor Charles V</name> (ruled <date when="1516">1516</date>&#x2013;<date when="1556">1556</date>) planned to visit the papal city in triumph following his victory over the Turks in Tuni-<lb/>
sia in 1536, <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name> was summoned to turn it into a place of dramatic greeting and Roman pride. The genius with which he carried out his assignment, which was not completed until long after his death, provides us with an incomparable example of the the-<lb/>
atrical imagination at its most sober and profound, for the spatial drama and urban scenography of his <name type="pname">Cam-<lb/>
pidoglio</name> remain unrivaled in the history of urban plan-<lb/>
ning (fig. 4.34).</p>
<p>Considered by ancients Romans to be the <hi rend="italic">caput mundi</hi>, the center of the world, the Capitoline Hill, site of the Palace of the Senator<ref target="#CH4-n22"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref> and still the nominal home of Roman city government, was designated as a major point along the imperial route leading down the old Appian Way and through the Forum to the inhabited city, then across the river at the <name type="pname">Ponte Sant'Angelo</name> to <name type="pname">St. Peter</name>'s and the <name type="place">Vatican</name>. <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name>'s commission was to create a dignified new hilltop piazza, despite the austere flank of <name type="pname">Santa Maria</name> in Aracoeli on the north and the old unprepos-<lb/>
sessing medieval guild hall to the south of the Palace of the Senator.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-156">
<graphic url="CH4_036.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.34. <name type="pname">Campidoglio</name>, <name type="place">Rome</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Michelangelo Buonarroti</name>. 1536. The original bronze equestrian statue of <name type="pname">Marcus Aurelius</name> that was the focus of <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name>'s design has been moved to the Capitoline Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The great equestrian statue of the Roman emperor <name type="pname">Marcus Aurelius</name>, once thought to be a repre-<lb/>
sentation of <name type="pname">Constantine</name>, the first Christian emperor, and therefore saved from being melted down along with many monumental pagan bronzes, was trans-<lb/>
ported to the <name type="pname">Campidoglio</name> from the Lateran Palace, its home throughout the Middle Ages. Set upon <name type="pname">Michel-<lb/>
angelo</name>'s modest yet authoritative pedestal in front of the Palace of the Senator, it served as the calm center and as a spring activating the dramatic tension and tremendous spatial energy of his design.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Michelangelo</name>'s solution to the incoherent space defined by the perimeter structures of the <name type="pname">Campidoglio</name> was one of camouflage through the design of a pair of opposing twin facades. On the south, that of the Pala-<lb/>
zzo dei Conservatori gave the old medieval guild hall the appearance of a Renaissance structure, and, on the north, that of the Palazzo Nuovo&#x2014;not built until the papacy of <name type="pname">Innocent X</name> (<date when="1644">1644</date>&#x2013;<date when="1655">1655</date>) and now known as the Palazzo del Museo Capitolino (Capitoline Museum)&#x2014;successfully screened the awkward wedge of land beside <name type="pname">Santa Maria</name> in Aracoeli. Although only two stories in height, both fa&#x00E7;ades are given monumentality by <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name>'s inventive giant order of pilasters running from the porticoed ground floor to the cornice line. Because the existing guild hall was set at an 80&#x00B0; angle to the Palace of the Senator, he skewed both of his fa&#x00E7;ades 10&#x00B0; from the 90&#x00B0; norm, thereby creating a trapezoidal piazza. The space, though contained, is thereby made dynamic and destabilized, and the eye is allowed to slide past the sides of the Palace of the Senator into the great field of ruins beyond, where the <name type="pname">Campidoglio</name> slopes down to the Forum.</p>
<p>The spatial dynamism is further increased by the paving pattern, a twentieth-century replica of the orig-<lb/>
inal one laid according to <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name>'s design. The heroic sculpture sits within a slightly sunken oval and in the middle of a twelve-ray star, the points of which form the coordinates of a radiating design. When read from above, this design gives a spherical appearance to the oval, as if it were a dome and the sculpture its crowning ornament.</p>
<p>But the greatest element of this scenographic
<pb n="151"/>
<pb n="151" type="orig"/>
drama is not the piazza, but the ascent to it via the Cordonata, a broad stair ramp with wide treads that are as gently cadenced as the adjacent steps of <name type="pname">Santa Maria</name> in Aracoeli are penitentially steep (fig. 4.35). Over-life-size ancient Roman statues of the horse tamers, the mythological twins <name type="pname">Castor</name> and <name type="pname">Pollux</name>, excavated in 1560 near the Capitoline, stand at the top, Olympian honor guards with the serene disinterested gaze of immortals, framing the perspective <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name> cre-<lb/>
ated.</p>
<p>In 1561, <name type="pname">Pius IV</name> (papacy <date when="1559">1559</date>&#x2013;<date when="1565">1565</date>) promoted the axial reordering of medieval <name type="place">Rome</name> with the build-<lb/>
ing of the Via Pia (now Via XX Settembre) from the papal palace on the Quirinal to the Porta Nomentana, the city's northeastern gate. <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name> was again summoned to produce an urban design. Here he gave a dignified focus to the palace approach with another monumental pair of sculptures of <name type="pname">Castor</name> and <name type="pname">Pollux</name>, turning their half-tamed horses to face the street near its entrance. At the opposite end, he screened the ancient fortifications of the Porta Nomentana with a purely scenic gate scaled to harmonize with the vista enclosed by the walls of the villa gardens on either side (fig. 4.36).</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Plan of <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>Although unsurpassed as urban scenography, the <name type="pname">Cam-<lb/>
pidoglio</name> and the Via Pia, with their artfully framed vistas, represent a piecemeal approach to city planning. Uniting the city's streets into a well-ar-<lb/>
ticulated circulation system and composing its already extraordinary existing landmarks into a series of views worthy of <name type="place">Rome</name>'s growing reputation as a tourist des-<lb/>
tination, required a comprehensive vision and forceful leadership for its realization. A visionary leader pre-<lb/>
sented himself in late-sixteenth-century <name type="place">Rome</name> in the person of <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name> (papacy <date when="1585">1585</date>&#x2013;<date when="1590">1590</date>). Indeed, all previous efforts to improve the cityscape of <name type="place">Rome</name> were but overtures to the great symphony of urban improvements that was orchestrated during the short Sistine papal term.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-157">
<graphic url="CH4_037.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left</hi>; 4.35. Cordonata leading to the <name type="pname">Campidoglio</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-158">
<graphic url="CH4_038.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Above</hi>; 4.36. Via Pia (modern Via XX Settembre) with Porta Pia; <hi rend="italic">La Via Pia</hi>, fresco painting by <name type="pname">Cesare Nebbia</name>, <name type="pname">Salone dei Papi</name>, Lateran Palace, <name type="place">Rome</name>, c. 1588</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Born of Dalmatian peasant stock, the great future pope of the Counter Reformation, Felice Peretti, rose through the ranks of the Church to become <name type="pname">Cardinal Montalto</name>, building the Villa Montalto with the reve-<lb/>
nues that went with his elevation to high office. There he nurtured his plans during the thirteen years of <name type="pname">Greg-<lb/>
ory XIII</name>'s papacy. Located in the developing eastern suburb of the settled city at the base of the Esquiline Hill on the site of the present railway station, the Villa Montalto later became the hub of a bold urban design. This plan, which Felice commissioned from the archi-<lb/>
tect and engineer Domenico Fontana (<date when="1543">1543</date>&#x2013;<date when="1607">1607</date>) as soon as he was elevated to the papacy, carried the urbanization of <name type="place">Rome</name> to the boundaries of its ancient walls and even, where possible, beyond. No contem-<lb/>
porary drawing exists for Fontana's master plan of <name type="place">Rome</name>, but a dramatic, if somewhat inaccurate, bird's-<lb/>
eye rendering of it in fresco decorates one of the walls of the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Library (fig. 4.37). The web of long arrow-straight thoroughfares had important signifi-<lb/>
cance within the context of the Counter-Reformation: linking the Colosseum, the Pantheon, the Forum and other prominent monuments of ancient <name type="place">Rome</name> and,
<pb n="152"/>
<pb n="152" type="orig"/>
more importantly, its seven major churches, with one another, they inscribed on the face of the ancient city a highly visible itinerary of tourism and pilgrimage that served to enhance its prestige as the original and con-<lb/>
tinuing center of the Catholic Church.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-159">
<graphic url="CH4_039.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.37. Perspective of <name type="place">Rome</name> according to the Plan of <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name>. <name type="place">Vatican</name> Library. Fresco. <date when="1585">1585</date>&#x2013;<date when="1590">90</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Not since the days of the Roman chariots had equally smooth, wide, and regular urban arteries been built. Moreover, they were to be paved in order to facil-<lb/>
itate the movement of the newly invented spring-sus-<lb/>
pension carriage. As yet, there were no sidewalks, and pedestrians and vehicles occupied the same street space. The word <hi rend="italic">corso</hi>, signifying a principal thorough-<lb/>
fare, assumed new meaning in <name type="place">Rome</name> as carriage driv-<lb/>
ing became a fashionable recreation for the upper echelon of society. The Via Pia, the longest straight road built to that date, bore daily witness to <name type="place">Rome</name>'s pre-em-<lb/>
inence as the world's first city to accommodate these new vehicles in large numbers. <name type="place">Rome</name> indeed was expe-<lb/>
riencing another modern urban "first": traffic conges-<lb/>
tion. The cardinals and their immense ecclesiastical retinues, the dignitaries of the embassies from other countries now posted to <name type="place">Rome</name>, the courtesans, the tens of thousands of pilgrims who came every year, the tour-<lb/>
ist contingent newly awakened to the wonders of the classical past, the foreign artists and artisans&#x2014;all these thronged the city, congesting its narrow medieval byways and crowding its new thoroughfares. The long-slumbering metropolis was once again lively as horses, carriages, cattle, and pedestrians jostled one another in the burgeoning cosmopolitan setting.</p>
<p>But more than roads were needed to facilitate transportation and stimulate the regrowth of <name type="place">Rome</name>. It was necessary to reconstruct the ancient aqueducts if the untenanted, ruin-studded stretches of the city were to be repopulated. Other popes had begun this process, but none had solved the problem of carrying water to the heights of <name type="place">Rome</name>'s famed hills. That was the assign-<lb/>
ment <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name> set for himself, and within only eighteen months, the plan he had nurtured for the Acqua Felice (so named because of the pope's first name, Felice) came to fruition with the completion of a conduit span-<lb/>
ning 7 miles of overhead arches and 7 miles of under-<lb/>
ground tunnels. Its successful opening brought water to the Villa Montalto in 1586 and three years later to twen-<lb/>
ty-seven public fountains located throughout <name type="place">Rome</name>. Utilitarian at first, many of these were later transformed into the ornamental fountains for which <name type="place">Rome</name> has remained famous.</p>
<p>The Acqua Felice also made possible the con-<lb/>
struction of a public laundry beside the Baths of Dio-<lb/>
cletian. And where the already reactivated Acqua Vergine brought water to the site of the present Foun-<lb/>
tain of Trevi, <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name> installed a basin for the washing of wool.<ref target="#CH4-n23"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">23</hi></hi></ref> With the water problem solved and the nexus of the new street system located in the area where he owned property he was in a position to gain financially from his program of public works.</p>
<p>As a landscape designer working at a city-<lb/>
planning scale with a visionary patron, Fontana proved his talent in engineering and urban scenography. Together pope and architect created the skeleton of modern <name type="place">Rome</name>, a circulation network of interconnecting streets and focal points, the whole comprising a series of vista corridors punctuated with landmarks old and new. As with the Acqua Felice, <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name> bestowed his name on the longest and most important of these unify-<lb/>
ing thoroughfares, the Strada Felice. This avenue con-<lb/>
nected <name type="pname">Santa Maria Maggiore</name> with <name type="pname">Santa Trinit&#x00E0; dei Monti</name> on the brow of the Pincio Hill. A final stretch downhill to the Piazza del Popolo was never con-<lb/>
structed, and the Spanish Steps linking Santa Trinit&#x00E0; with the Corso below were not built until the eighteenth century. But the Strada Felice's extension on the other side of <name type="pname">Santa Maria Maggiore</name> all the way to Santa Croce in Gerusalemme was carried out, thereby creat-<lb/>
ing a straight span of about 2 miles across the breadth of <name type="place">Rome</name>. Intersecting the Strada Felice at almost a right angle was <name type="pname">Michelangelo</name>'s Via Pia, the two creating a symbolical cross, referred to as the "<hi rend="italic">bellissima croce</hi>."</p>
<p>In the fresco of the <name type="place">Rome</name> of <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name> one sees the impulse to untangle the tortuous labyrinth of medieval <name type="place">Rome</name> with the Strada Felice and other roads slashing across the built and as-yet-unbuilt landscape. One also sees the celebration of <name type="place">Rome</name>'s incomparable history
<pb n="153"/>
<pb n="153" type="orig"/>
through the new prominence given to its landmarks. In addition to the pilgrimage churches, the Colos-<lb/>
seum and the Columns of <name type="pname">Marcus Aurelius</name> and Tra-<lb/>
jan are focal points of the plan. To set these off, <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name> removed the structures around them and regularized the building lines of those remaining to form squares. Elsewhere he created new squares. Fontana and his patron hit upon the happy idea of resurrecting several of the old Egyptian obelisks, exotic souvenirs of ancient campaigns, which had long ago toppled here and there about the city, and using them as markers to center space or temporarily arrest the eye and punctuate its journey along a vista corridor.</p>
<p>The 82-foot-tall obelisk marking <name type="pname">Nero</name>'s race-<lb/>
track near <name type="pname">St. Peter</name>'s had, remarkably, remained standing throughout the Middle Ages next to the south side of the church. Fontana directed the feat of moving this 320-ton monument to its present position in front of <name type="pname">St. Peter</name>'s, thus defining the center of the ovoid piazza, which Bernini later embraced with his great curving fourfold colonnades. Fontana had the obelisk lying in the Circus Maximus erected in the center of the space that became the Piazza del Popolo, giving focus to its converging trident of new streets (fig. 4.38). Two more obelisks were set up along the Strada Felice, one at its midpoint in front of <name type="pname">Santa Maria Maggiore</name>, the other at its southeastern termi-<lb/>
nus in front of Santa Croce in Gerusalemme. To incorporate them into the religious symbolism of the Counter-Reformation's triumphant Catholicism, the pope had each of the four Sistine obelisks surmounted with a globe bearing a cross. Thus, an ancient Egyp-<lb/>
tian form, developed to stand in sentinel pairs at tomb entrances, became an isolated freestanding object centering urban open space, a felicitous borrowing that would be copied in other times in other lands, often without the Church's triumphant cross.</p>
<p>Sixteenth-century Italian landscape design not only manifested the humanists' interest in reviving ancient forms and themes, but it also served as a means of asserting prestige and displaying wealth and power. The same humanist iconographies into which were encoded messages of family and personal pride within a garden setting could be applied on an urban scale to proclaim the power of the Church or of a ruler. The garden, in effect, served as a design studio wherein problems of axial layout and scenography were solved in ways that were simultaneously applied to city planning. For example, Fontana's develop-<lb/>
ment of the triangular piazza in front of <name type="pname">Pope Sixtus V</name>'s Villa Montalto as a garden <hi rend="italic">trivio</hi>_with three ave-<lb/>
nues radiating outward from an open space near the Church of <name type="pname">Santa Maria Maggiore</name>, in a manner that both ennobled the entrance to the <hi rend="italic">casino</hi> and sug-<lb/>
gested the breadth of the gardens behind it, shows how closely connected were the principles of land-<lb/>
scape design within and without the garden (fig. 4.39).</p>
<p>This means of stabilizing architectural forms in relationship to a particular setting and suggesting ter-<lb/>
ritorial possession through spatial extension, devel-<lb/>
oped here as part of Fontana's plan for the villa, became a widely used device wherever monumental planning occurred. Fontana's role as city planner is thus pivotal. He conceived the design of the Villa Montalto's <hi rend="italic">trivio</hi> within the comprehensive frame of cityscape. By linking it and other radial compositions of axes, such as those emanating from the <hi rend="italic">trivio</hi> at the Piazza del Popolo, to form a transurban network, he created a plan for an entire city, something that had not occurred in the West since ancient Roman times and then only for colonial cities and not the capital.</p>
<p>As the unification of garden space through axial layout became increasingly the objective of garden designers in the seventeenth century, their royal employers saw the symbolic value of reordering old cities and building new ones according to the same principles. It is not surprising that these principles, which served effectively as a spatial metaphor for princely grandeur and dominion, were eagerly absorbed by ambitious monarchs elsewhere, notably in <name type="place">France</name>. However, before the lessons of <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name>'s plan were applied in an urban setting in that country in the early seventeenth century during the reign of <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> (ruled 1589&#x2013;1610), a gradual process of replacing French medievalism with the new Renais-<lb/>
sance style imported from <name type="place">Italy</name> had necessarily ensued. This stylistic evolution, begun in the Loire Valley, reflected the political relations between the two countries over the course of the sixteenth century as Italian influence in <name type="place">France</name> alternated with the development of an independent French Renaissance style.<ref target="#CH4-n24"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">24</hi></hi></ref></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-160">
<graphic url="CH4_040.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.38. Egyptian obelisk, erected in the Circus Maximus during Roman imperial times and resurrected in the Piazza del Popolo, <name type="place">Rome</name>. <date when="1585">1585</date>&#x2013;<date when="1590">90</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-161">
<graphic url="CH4_041.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 4.39. Villa Montalto, <name type="place">Rome</name>. Designed by Domenico Fontana. Engraving by <name type="pname">Giovanni Battista Falda</name>, plate 14, <hi rend="italic">Li giardini di Roma con le loro Piante Alzate e Vedute in Prospettiva</hi>. n.d.</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="154"/>
<pb n="154" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">IV. Currents of Fashion: The Transformation of the Italian Garden in <name type="place">France</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>Italian humanism laid the groundwork for the devel-<lb/>
opment of French garden style in the sixteenth cen-<lb/>
tury. <name type="pname">Alberti</name>'s treatise and the publication in 1546 of a French translation of <name type="pname">Colonna</name>'s influential <hi rend="italic">Hypnero-<lb/>
tomachia Poliphili</hi>, carried certain currents of Renais-<lb/>
sance thought northward. Equally important was the invasion of the kingdom of Naples in 1494 by the <name type="pname">French king Charles VIII</name> (ruled <date when="1470">1470</date>&#x2013;<date when="1498">1498</date>) in an attempt to reassert an old dynastic claim to the throne. <name type="pname">Charles</name>'s occupation lasted only five months, but <name type="pname">Alfonso II</name>'s state-of-the-art gardens at Poggio Reale, overlooking the Bay of Naples and with a view of Mount Vesuvius, made a lasting impression on him and on the nobles in his retinue.</p>
<p>Following the capture of <name type="pname">Castel del Uovo</name>, <name type="pname">Charles</name> took up residence there and had ample oppor-<lb/>
tunity to marvel at the straight <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> approaching the castle on all sides, the orange and other fruit trees sur-<lb/>
rounding it, its large walled garden, ingenious hydrau-<lb/>
lic system, fountains, ornamental fish ponds, canals, aviaries, and game-filled hunting park. Though it has long since disappeared and its design cannot be accu-<lb/>
rately reconstructed, we know that this pleasure palace was square with corner towers and had a sunken court that could be flooded for water spectacles. When <name type="pname">Charles</name> returned to his own palace at <name type="pname">Amboise</name> in October, he brought with him Italian artists and crafts-<lb/>
men, including, the Neapolitan priest-gardener <name type="pname">Pacello de Mercogliano</name>.</p>
<p>The appearance of the palace and garden at <name type="pname">Amboise</name>, as well as that of other great ch&#x00E2;teaux of the Loire Valley, was recorded between 1576 and 1579 by the architect <name type="pname">Jacques Androuet du Cerceau</name> (c. 1520&#x2013;c. 1584) in a monumental series of engrav-<lb/>
ings, which were published in several editions of <hi rend="italic">Les plus excellents Bastiments de <name type="place">France</name></hi>, an invaluable reference work for garden historians inasmuch as almost all sixteenth-century French gardens have disappeared. The work is important, moreover, as a record of the French transformation of Italian Renais-<lb/>
sance gardening principles into a unique design idiom. The ch&#x00E2;teaux engraved by du Cerceau were those that had been built during the several preceding decades of the sixteenth century when French design-<lb/>
ers were appropriating the lessons of <name type="place">Italy</name> and refash-<lb/>
ioning them into expressions of their own aristocratic culture.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-162">
<graphic url="CH4_042.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.40. Blois. Engraving by <name type="pname">Jacques Androuet du Cerceau</name>, <hi rend="italic">Le Second Volume des plus excellents Bastiments de <name type="place">France</name></hi>. 1579. The main gate leading to the principal axis of the garden is approached through a dogleg passage connecting with a covered bridge that leads from the palace. The expert craftsmanship of the joiner is evident in the octagonal wooden pavilion with its tall domed latern covering a marble fountain and in the galleries formed by wooden trallises. These galleries were high and wide enough to accomodate riders on horseback.</figDesc>
</figure>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sixteenth-Century Ch&#x00E2;teaux: <name type="pname">Blois</name>, <name type="pname">Fontainebleau</name>, <name type="pname">Ancy-le-Franc</name>, <name type="pname">Anet</name>, <name type="pname">Chenonceaux</name></hi></hi></head>
<p><name type="pname">Charles VIII</name> died suddenly in 1498, but his nephew and successor <name type="pname">Louis XII</name> <date when="1498">1498</date>&#x2013;<date when="1515">1515</date>) was equally enthusiastic about the new princely pastime of garden-making. He continued to make improvements at <name type="pname">Amboise</name> and the other royal ch&#x00E2;teaux he had inher-<lb/>
ited. At Blois, he placed the garden outside the castle walls, and this permitted a considerable expansion in size over the one at <name type="pname">Amboise</name> (fig. 4.40). Its design, however, made no attempt to unite the ch&#x00E2;teau and garden visually by aligning them along a common axis as was being done in <name type="place">Italy</name>.</p>
<pb n="155"/>
<pb n="155" type="orig"/>
<p><name type="pname">Louis XII</name> was succeeded by his nephew <name type="pname">Francis I</name> (ruled <date when="1515">1515</date>&#x2013;<date when="1547">1547</date>). The sister-in-law of the new king became the duchess of Ferrara, which, as the home of the Este family's gardens and parks, was an important site of garden design. This connection with <name type="place">Italy</name> per-<lb/>
haps, along with <name type="pname">Francis</name>'s favorable disposition toward the new cultural developments there, fostered the burgeoning French Renaissance.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Francis</name> sought to conquer <name type="place">Italy</name> and become Holy Roman Emperor, but was checked by <name type="pname">Emperor Charles V</name> (who was also king of <name type="place">Spain</name>) in 1525. Upon <name type="pname">Francis I</name>'s return to <name type="place">France</name> the next year, following imprisonment in <name type="place">Spain</name>, he decided to abandon his Loire Valley <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teaux</hi> and to establish the court in the environs of <name type="place">Paris</name> as part of a political alliance he sought with the bourgeois class. In 1528, he began rebuilding the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> at Fontainebleau (fig. 4.41). The master mason Gilles de Breton was put in charge of the work. He built a new triple-story entrance to the Court of Honor and a new courtyard with an Ital-<lb/>
ian-style gallery overlooking a trapezoidal lake. On the shore opposite the elm-lined causeway leading to the main entrance of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>, the Jardin des Pins was laid out as a series of square beds with a pine-bor-<lb/>
dered central axis.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Francis</name> imported Italian artists to assist in the decoration of Fontainebleau, and the presence of these talented men in <name type="place">France</name> gave additional impetus to the spread of Renaissance art and humanism. <name type="pname">Francesco Primaticcio</name> (<date when="1504">1504</date>&#x2013;<date when="1570">1570</date>), one of the Italian painters and architects summoned to <name type="place">France</name>, is reputed to have designed the grotto at Fontainebleau. In this way, the development of the Renaissance landscape in <name type="place">France</name> continued with direct assistance from designers trained in <name type="place">Italy</name> during the generation in which a new artistic idiom was being forged and refashioned into a style that was identifiably French.</p>
<p>The Italian Renaissance architect <name type="pname">Sebastiano Serlio</name> was also invited to <name type="place">France</name> by <name type="pname">Francis I</name>. Better known as a theoretician and architectural consultant, he is credited with the design of <name type="pname">Ancy-le-Franc</name> in Bur-<lb/>
gundy (fig. 4.42). The project, begun under his direc-<lb/>
tion in 1546, firmly established axial symmetry and the unity between house and garden probably for the first time in <name type="place">France</name>.</p>
<p>The preference for Italian architects and garden designers did not endure for long in <name type="place">France</name>. French national pride was responsible for diverting commis-<lb/>
sions from <name type="pname">Serlio</name> and his compatriots as native design-<lb/>
ers grasped the principles of Renaissance architectural composition. Foremost among the first generation of such designers was <name type="pname">Philibert de l'Orme</name> (c. <date when="1510">1510</date>&#x2013;<date when="1570">1570</date>). De l'Orme went to <name type="place">Rome</name> to study antiquities between 1533 and 1536. There he was introduced to the circle of humanists, collectors, and artists who were excavat-<lb/>
ing <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>'s Villa and beginning to build the new villas that were to exert a powerful influence on future generations of designers. Upon his return to <name type="place">France</name>, he exercised his talent in the service of <name type="pname">Cardinal Jean du Bellay</name>, whom he had met while in <name type="place">Rome</name>, and shortly after <name type="pname">Henry II</name> became king in 1547, de l'Orme was appointed superintendent of all royal buildings.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-163">
<graphic url="CH4_043.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.41. Fontainebleau. Engraving by <name type="pname">Jacques Androuet du Cer-<lb/>
ceau</name>, <hi rend="italic">Le Second Volume des plus excellents Bastiments de <name type="place">France</name></hi>. 1579</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-164">
<graphic url="CH4_044.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 4.42. <name type="pname">Ancy-le-Franc</name>. Engraving by <name type="pname">Jacques Androuet du Cerceau</name>, <hi rend="italic">Le Pre-<lb/>
mier Volume des plus excel-<lb/>
lents Bastiments de <name type="place">France</name></hi>. 1576. <name type="pname">Serlio</name> used the terrace of the medieval moat surrounding the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> as an overlook from which to view the twelve compartments contained within the rectangular garden. A hedge and a canal both outline the garden. Beyond it is a <hi rend="italic">bosquet</hi> similar to the <hi rend="italic">boschi</hi> of contemporary Italian gardens. Within it, along an axis perpendicular to the main axis running through the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and the garden, a broad grassy swath has been carved. On either side of it are green byways and small secluded areas.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p><name type="pname">Henry</name>'s mistress, <name type="pname">Diane de Poitiers</name>, a widow eighteen years his senior, held sway over the king's
<pb n="156"/>
<pb n="156" type="orig"/>
affections. Instead of allowing <name type="pname">Anet</name>, the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> in which <name type="pname">Diane</name>'s husband had held a lifetime interest, to revert to the crown as it was supposed to upon his death, <name type="pname">Henry</name> made a present of it to her. <name type="pname">Philibert de l'Orme</name> was immediately appointed architect of its reconstruction.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-165">
<graphic url="CH4_045.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.43. <name type="pname">Anet</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Philibert de l'Orme</name>. Engraving by <name type="pname">Jacques Androuet du Cerceau</name>, <hi rend="italic">Le Second Volume des plus excellents Bastiments de <name type="place">France</name></hi>. 1579. The Court of Honor is enclosed by the U-shaped <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and entrance structure, in this case an impressive gatehouse. Stretching on either side of this gatehouse, symmetrical small <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi> and terraces terminate in mirror-image pavilions. The moat surrounding <name type="pname">Anet</name> has been enlarged to form a semicircular pool encompassing a pavilion for theatrical spectacles. The crescent-shaped pool perhaps echoes the shape of the moon, the device of Diana the Huntress. Because this mythological goddess is also associated with the woods, the stands of trees on either side of the entrance may represent one of her groves.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-166">
<graphic url="CH4_046.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.44. Diana Fountain, <name type="pname">Anet</name>. Engraving by <name type="pname">Jacques Androuet du Cerceau</name>, <hi rend="italic">Le Second Volume des plus excellents Bastiments de <name type="place">France</name></hi>. 1579. This elegantly elongated image boldly portraying a nude <name type="pname">Diane</name> de Poitiers as Diana the Huntress can be found in the Louvre Museum today.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Although he had to preserve the existing house, de l'Orme incorporated it within a symmetrical plan as he applied the lessons he had learned in <name type="place">Italy</name> in a rational, comprehensive ordering of space (fig. 4.43). The garden was enclosed and inward-focused, but its size and impressive surrounding gallery gave it a very modern appearance at the time. Twin pavilions over-<lb/>
looked its far end, and in these musicians played for the king, his mistress, and members of the court. Also at the far end of the garden stood a pavilion for theat-<lb/>
rical entertainment, a new feature of French Renais-<lb/>
sance garden design. As at nearby Gaillon, the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> built in 1502 by <name type="pname">Georges d'Amboise</name>, archbishop of Rouen, the garden pavilion rose from a pool of water.</p>
<p>Ostensibly built as a memorial to <name type="pname">Diane</name>'s late husband, <name type="pname">Anet</name> actually glorified <name type="pname">Diane</name> herself and celebrated her liaison with the king. Not only was this done in typical Renaissance style with monograms and coats of arms fashioned out of boxwood in the garden compartments but also with the kind of deco-<lb/>
rative program seen at the Villa d'Este and the Villa Lante. At <name type="pname">Anet</name>, the thematic program refers to <name type="pname">Diana</name>, goddess of the hunt, in such sculpture as the stag and hounds crowning the main entrance portal and in the elegant Mannerist fountain (now removed from the entry court) depicting a reclining, nude <name type="pname">Diane de Poitiers</name> in the guise of the mythological <name type="pname">Diana</name> (fig. 4.44).</p>
<p>In spite of <name type="pname">Henry II</name>'s attachment to his mistress, he fathered ten children with <name type="pname">Queen Catherine de M&#x00E9;dicis</name>, among them three future kings of <name type="place">France</name>. The daughter of <name type="pname">Lorenzo de'Medici</name>, duke of Urbino, and Madeleine de La Tour d'Auvergne (a Bourbon princess), <name type="pname">Catherine</name> had been orphaned almost at birth. She was raised by nuns and married at the age of fourteen to <name type="pname">Henry</name>. When, after a few years, she began to bear royal children, she lived quietly and pri-<lb/>
<pb n="157"/>
<pb n="157" type="orig"/>
vately, supervising their education until, following <name type="pname">Henry II</name>'s sudden death in 1559, she was catapulted onto the stage of history as regent and queen mother during the reigns of her sons <name type="pname">Francis II</name>, <name type="pname">Charles IX</name>, and <name type="pname">Henry III</name>. Well-read, politically astute, viva-<lb/>
cious, artistic, and energetic, she was an enthusiastic parti-cipant in the new fashion for <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> remodel-<lb/>
ing and garden building that was gathering force in <name type="place">France</name> during the second half of the sixteenth cen-<lb/>
tury.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-167">
<graphic url="CH4_047.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.45. Chenonceaux. Drawing by <name type="pname">Jacques Androuet du Cerceau</name>. The original owner, <name type="pname">Thomas Bohier</name>, had built an enclosed garden with the trellised galleries and square compartments associated with the period of transition between medieval and Renaissance style. It can be seen in the right foreground of du Cerceau's engraving. To the left of the entrance, <name type="pname">Diane</name> of Poitiers ordered a high moat-surrounded terrace on which was laid out a considerably larger rectangular garden of twenty-four beds arranged around a principal cross-axis. Planted with the assistance of the archbishop of Tours, it contained many different kinds of fruit trees, musk roses, lilies, and vegetables. The axis of the bridge de l'Orme had built to span the river extended as a tree-lined <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> to connect with a new garden commissioned by <name type="pname">Catherine de M&#x00E9;dicis</name>. De l'Orme placed the bridge slightly to one side of the main axis of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>, thereby preserving the principal view of the river from the entrance corridor without forsaking an impression of axial linkage.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>During the King's lifetime, <name type="pname">Diane</name> de Poitiers was mistress of the royal <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> at Chenonceaux, dating from 1512 and defensively sited within the river Cher (figs. 4.45, 4.46). After the king's death, <name type="pname">Catherine</name> claimed this remarkable structure for her own. She took an interest in the garden that <name type="pname">Diane</name> had begun and directed the construction of a new south garden. She probably retained <name type="pname">Philibert de l'Orme</name>'s services for this project.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Catherine</name> used the enlarged gardens of Che-<lb/>
nonceaux for political ends, staging elaborate pag-<lb/>
eants and festivals within them to celebrate the peace treaties that punctuated the bloody religious wars that raged during the reigns of her sons. There were festi-<lb/>
vals, too, at Fontainebleau and at the Tuileries. The use of these gardens as settings for various allegorical pageants marked the beginning of an enduring tradi-<lb/>
tion. As will become evident in the next chapter, the gardens of French monarchs increasingly assumed the role of theaters for court life, and certain spaces were built within them to accommodate the specta-<lb/>
cles and plays that were regularly staged as entertain-<lb/>
ments for royalty and nobility. The politicization of the garden was paralleled by the design of cities as didactic expressions of royal prestige as <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> began the impressive transformation of <name type="place">Paris</name> from a medieval to a modern city.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-168">
<graphic url="CH4_048.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.46. Chenonceaux</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="158"/>
<pb n="158" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">V. The Evolution of French Urbanization and Garden Style: <name type="place">Paris</name> in the Time of <name type="pname">Henry IV</name></hi></hi></head>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Transformation of <name type="place">Paris</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>With the extinction of the Valois royal line following the death of <name type="pname">Henry III</name>, the complicated French laws of succession led to the selection of a distant cousin, the Bourbon king of Navarre, as king. The ascension of this Protestant soldier to the throne as <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> in 1589 eventually marked the end of the bloody reli-<lb/>
gious wars of the second half of the sixteenth century, but his authority was established only after a strug-<lb/>
gle. Detennined to quell the rebellious Catholics who denied his legitimacy, <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> first laid siege to their stronghold of <name type="place">Paris</name>, and when this was unsuc-<lb/>
cessful, with his famous pronouncement that <name type="place">Paris</name> was worth a mass, he converted to Catholicism and thereby gained the city. His peripatetic Valois prede-<lb/>
cessors had migrated from one to another of their Loire Valley and <name type="pname">&#x00CE;le-de-France</name> <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teaux</hi>, chosen principally by individual royal preference for spe-<lb/>
cific hunting parks. But <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> had to consolidate his victory and establish <name type="place">Paris</name> as the indisputable royal capital. He turned his attention to projects that would improve the city's appearance, stimulate its economy, address its issues of public sanitation, and increase its opportunities for both ceremonial state-<lb/>
ment and residential amenity. His campaign to accomplish these objectives was based upon the cre-<lb/>
ation of new architectural works and public spaces larger in scale than any hitherto seen in <name type="place">Europe</name> out-<lb/>
side of <name type="place">Italy</name>&#x2014;spaces that would glorify the institu-<lb/>
tion of monarchy and the growing supremacy of <name type="place">France</name> as the dominant social and political power in <name type="place">Europe</name>. The origin of <name type="place">Paris</name> as a modern city and <name type="place">France</name> as a modern nation owes much to this ener-<lb/>
getic monarch whose list of urban and state achieve-<lb/>
ments would have been even more impressive had his life not been cut short by an assassin in 1610.</p>
<p>The rebuilding of <name type="place">Paris</name>'s badly battered walls was not one of these achievements, nor was it to be counted among those of his successors. With the increasing security of French borders attained by the bastioned outpost citadels constructed first by <name type="pname">Henry IV</name>'s engineers and much later by the brilliant <name type="pname">S&#x00E9;bas-<lb/>
tien Le Prestre de Vauban</name> (<date when="1633">1633</date>&#x2013;<date when="1707">1707</date>), <name type="place">France</name> was becoming territorially confirmed as a nation-state. This meant that <name type="place">Paris</name> could dispense with its ancient fortifications and exist henceforth as an open city. To execute his building program for the capital as well as the border defense fortifications and to supervise the increasingly centralized administration of finances that made such large-scale, nationalistic projects possible in the first place, <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> appointed as his chief minister the duke of <name type="pname">Sully</name>, <name type="pname">Maximilien de B&#x00E9;thune</name> (<date when="1560">1560</date>&#x2013;<date when="1641">1641</date>). Among the several titles he held, <name type="pname">Sully</name> was invested with a newly created one, that of <hi rend="italic">Grand Voyer;</hi> the officer who regulated transportation and integrated planning of all roads, bridges, canals, city streets, and public places. An astute politician and talented administra-<lb/>
tor, <name type="pname">Sully</name> created a revenue budget and organized a corps of engineers to design forts, maintain bridges and roads, and map territory. His road reports led to the building of a centralizing web of highways focused on <name type="place">Paris</name>, while the maps he commissioned not only assisted in increasing royal control over tax-<lb/>
ation, commerce, and transportation, but also pro-<lb/>
moted a new cartographic image of the nation-state as a geographic unit with well-defined boundaries.</p>
<p>For <name type="pname">Henry IV</name>, <name type="pname">Sully</name> played the role that <name type="pname">Colbert</name> would later play for <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>: that of supervising the works that would turn <name type="place">Paris</name> into a dignified royal capital.<ref target="#CH4-n25"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">25</hi></hi></ref> With <name type="pname">Sully</name>'s assistance, <name type="pname">Henry</name> initiated a new urban scale, opened up the city both visually and spatially, and introduced significant preliminary improvements in its circulation. In this effort, mon-<lb/>
arch and minister were clearly inspired by <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name>'s plan for <name type="place">Rome</name>. The result was the reordering of parts of medieval <name type="place">Paris</name> and the creation of new public spaces in conjunction with the development of their surrounding real estate.</p>
<p>The king's first step upon gaining control of <name type="place">Paris</name> was to turn the old stronghold of the Louvre, the fortress castle that his predecessors had already begun to modernize, into a fitting royal residence and symbolically assertive seat of government. Noble architecture alone was not enough to accomplish this task; his_plan, only partially fulfilled during his life, called for the integration of the space between <name type="pname">Cath-<lb/>
erine de M&#x00E9;dicis' Tuileries</name> Palace and the Louvre into one vast courtyard, the largest open space ever before seen or planned in <name type="place">Paris</name> and the precursor of an entirely new urban scale (fig. 4.47).<ref target="#CH4-n26"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">26</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>In building the Grande Galerie connecting the two palaces on the south, <name type="pname">Henry IV</name>'s architects removed part of the old fortification wall that ran along the Seine, thereby providing sweeping river views from the palace while simultaneously present-<lb/>
ing it as an object of admiration from afar. Architec-<lb/>
tural improvements to the Tuileries and the removal of much of the medieval clutter of nonroyal struc-<lb/>
tures between it and the Louvre provided the sought-<lb/>
for unity among the southern ranges of the palace complex. But the entire space did not begin to receive
<pb n="159"/>
<pb n="159" type="orig"/>
its final form until the nineteenth century when <name type="pname">Napo-<lb/>
leon</name> built the western half of the northern gallery of the Tuileries and transformed <name type="pname">Henry IV</name>'s New Gar-<lb/>
den between the palace and the Renaissance-era Square Court into a new courtyard with its center-<lb/>
piece, the Arc de Triomphe du Carrousel, placed on axis with that of the Tuileries. (Only with the comple-<lb/>
tion of the rest of the north gallery in the mid-nine-<lb/>
teenth century was the area between the two palaces finally cleared of the clutter of the remaining struc-<lb/>
tures. Then, following a devastating fire in 1871, the Tuileries, with the exception of its end pavilions, was removed, thereby configuring the space as we know it today.)</p>
<p><name type="pname">Henry IV</name>'s urban planning aspirations went beyond royal aggrandizement. He wanted to stimulate the economy of <name type="place">Paris</name> and stem the drain of capital to foreign lands by fostering native production of luxury goods, especially silk. Along the northern edge of the Tuileries Gardens he planted an <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> of mulberry trees, and near the northeastern wall of the city on vacant crown land, the former site of the H&#x00F4;tel Royale des Tournelles, he provided inducements to a group of investors to build a silkworks containing spinning mills and workers' housing.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-169">
<graphic url="CH4_049.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.47. Plan of <name type="place">Paris</name> by <name type="pname">Michel Turgot</name>. 1734. Because of a drafting error that failed to account for a slight discrepancy in scale when earlier drawings of the Louvre and Tuileries were amalgamated into a new plan of spatial unification, the axes of the two palaces were misaligned. But this problem only became noticeable in the nineteenth century when the intervening structures remaining from medieval <name type="place">Paris</name> were removed. If the axis of the Louvre had been congruent with that of the Tuileries, the Louvre's new entrance, the Pyramid designed by <name type="pname">I. M. Pei</name>, would be aligned with the Arc de Triomphe and other important monuments that punctuate the Champs Elys&#x00E9;es.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-170">
<graphic url="CH4_050.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 4.48. Place des Vosges (formerly the Place Royale), <name type="place">Paris</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<p><name type="pname">Sully</name> advanced the king's plan to build artisans' residences on the rest of the site, the whole complex forming a square known as the Place Royale (fig. 4.48). To finance the construction of houses on the remaining three sides of the square adjacent to the silkworks, the king donated building lots to his polit-<lb/>
ical allies. The lots were granted with the stipulation
<pb n="160"/>
<pb n="160" type="orig"/>
that the owners build houses according to a predeter-<lb/>
mined uniform facade plan; they could later rent or sell them for a profit. The result was the city's first planned large open space, an early example of urban architectural uniformity. By rewarding his friends with the opportunity to become developers, the king also provided a model and catalyst for later specula-<lb/>
tion in Parisian real estate.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-171">
<graphic url="CH4_051.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.49. Pont Neuf and Place Dauphine, <name type="place">Paris</name>. Detail from Plan of <name type="place">Paris</name> by <name type="pname">Michel Turgot</name>. 1734</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>In addition to providing housing attractive to for-<lb/>
eign artisans, the Place Royale (rechristened by <name type="pname">Napo-<lb/>
leon</name> the Place des Vosges, as it is called today) was also planned with a recreational objective. It was to be a place for social promenading, an increasingly popu-<lb/>
lar Parisian pastime with ritual implications that required an architecturally defined setting. Intended for the general populace, not merely for local residents, this new kind of urban space was also meant to be a stage for court ceremonies, jousting tournaments, and public celebrations. In permanent demonstration of this function, a royal pavilion was created in the center of the south side of the square with an arched portal opening from the rue de Birague, the axis of entry.</p>
<p>As it turned out, the investors built residences for themselves and their friends, rather than the housing intended for artisans. Although some artisans did take up residence in the Place Royale, it quickly became an enclave for the nobility, and much of the ground floor space, which had been planned as a shopping arcade, was closed in as new <hi rend="italic">h&#x00F4;tels</hi> were fashioned from two or more units of the original scheme.</p>
<p>Upon discovering the profitability of the residen-<lb/>
tial real estate, the investors in the silkworks requested the king's permission to relocate it and close in the north end of the square with another range of houses in keeping with those on the other three sides. How-<lb/>
ever, because of its ambiguous social intent and in spite of the royal pageants and tournaments held within the square and the placement by <name type="pname">Cardinal Richelieu</name> of an equestrian statue of <name type="pname">Louis XIII</name> in its center, the Place Royale never became fully given over to the nobility, but remained instead a popular resi-<lb/>
dence for an increasingly eclectic group of tenants.</p>
<p>The religious wars of the sixteenth century had defeired a long-cherished plan to span the Seine and provide a direct access to the western end of the &#x00CE;le de la Cit&#x00E9;, home of the Parlement of <name type="place">Paris</name>. To finance the completion of the Pont Neuf, as the new bridge has been called ever since, a tax was imposed on wine. As it was being constructed, the king put forth a scheme for the Place Dauphine, a square in the form of an irregular triangle conforming to the prowlike shape of the end of the island. Opposite the Place Dauphine, a buttressed platform juts westward like a balcony over the river to form a small square on the bridge itself (fig-4.49).</p>
<p>In the cramped walled cities of the period, where land was scarce and the sides of new bridges offered prime building sites as well as a revenue source for their builders, this bridge was an anomaly. The Pont Neuf, like the slightly earlier Ponte Santa Trinit&#x00E0; in <name type="place">Florence</name>, was built without any structures on it, except for a pumping station designed to bring water to the Tuileries. By keeping the bridge clear of struc-<lb/>
tures, the king promoted public appreciation of <name type="place">Paris</name>'s already considerable scenic potential. With its open views in all directions, the bridge offered those cross-<lb/>
ing it the spectacle of the river and its traffic, the Grande Galerie and other structures of the Louvre-Tu-<lb/>
ileries complex rising on its Right Bank, the buildings opposite giving the Left Bank its own archi-<lb/>
tecturally significant character, and, in between, beyond the Palais de Justice where the courts and offices of the Parlement were housed, the spires of Notre Dame at the eastern end of the &#x00CE;le de la Cit&#x00E9;.</p>
<p>As at the Place Royale, the houses at the Place Dauphine were intended for residents of the merchant and artisan classes. However, perhaps to avoid the situation that had occurred at the Place Royale with the amalgamation of the building lots by aristocrats into larger <hi rend="italic">h&#x00F4;tel</hi>-size units, here the king had <name type="pname">Sully</name> convey the entire site to a single developer, his loyal
<pb n="161"/>
<pb n="161" type="orig"/>
follower <name type="pname">Achille de Harlay</name>, the seventy-one-year-old president of the Parlement, whose own house lay adjacent to the future square; <name type="pname">Harlay</name> was obligated to build the housing ensemble as designed for tradesmen within a period of three years or find others who would buy the lots and do so. Although not in strict alignment for reasons of geography, the ensemble&#x2014;bridge, sculpture, and square&#x2014;was conceived as an urbanistic unit, signifying a new integrative approach to the planning of cities, one that exploited the visual relationships of objects in space.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">French Garden Style</hi></hi></head>
<p>The period of <name type="pname">Henry II</name> and <name type="pname">Catherine de M&#x00E9;dicis</name> had been one in which French designers thoroughly assim-<lb/>
ilated the lessons of <name type="place">Italy</name>. During the reign of <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> (<date when="1589">1589</date>&#x2013;<date when="1610">1610</date>) and the lifetime of his queen and widow <name type="pname">Marie de M&#x00E9;dicis</name>, they forged a distinctive garden style, one that nevertheless was firmly rooted in Italian precedent and developed as a translation of the basic vocabulary of Italian design into a native idiom. Because of the king's connection through mar-<lb/>
riage with the <name type="pname">Medici</name> family, the period of his reign marked another wave of Italian influence, sometimes referred to as the Second School of Fontainebleau in recollection of the designers brought north by <name type="pname">Francis I</name> in the 1530s. Beginning in 1598, members of the <name type="pname">Francini</name> family of hydraulic engineers, sent by <name type="pname">Grand Duke Ferdinando de' Medici</name>, came north bearing knowledge of contemporary <name type="pname">Medici</name> garden design at the Boboli Gardens where <name type="pname">Marie de M&#x00E9;dicis</name> had spent her childhood and where there was a splendid grotto, at <name type="pname">Castello</name> where there was also a fanciful grotto, and at Pratolino where there was a long avenue lined with fountains leading to the villa. They were also familiar with the mechanical equipment needed to propel jets in the contrivances known as <hi rend="italic">giocchi d'aqua</hi>, or water games, found in the gardens of the <name type="pname">Medici</name>, and to pump and manage the flow of water in the foun-<lb/>
tains and other aquatic features that adorned the Villa d'Este at Tivoli, the Villa Lante at Bagnaia, the Villa Farnese at Caprarola, and the Villa Aldobrandini at Frascati. In <name type="place">France</name>, they created at <name type="pname">Saint Germaine-<lb/>
en-Laye</name> grottoes and automata modeled on those of the <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> at Pratolino. These both frightened and intrigued the Dauphin, the future <name type="pname">Louis XIII</name>, when he was a child growing up at <name type="pname">Saint Germaine-<lb/>
en-Laye</name>. <name type="pname">Alessandro</name> (<name type="pname">Alexandre</name>) <name type="pname">Francini</name> is believed to have designed the ornamental grotto for <name type="pname">Marie de M&#x00E9;dicis</name> in the <name type="place">Luxembourg</name> Gardens, and his 1631 book of architectural drawings contains elaborate ornamental doorways that evidently served as models for several found on French architectural grottoes of the seventeenth century (fig. 4.50). A <name type="pname">French Huguenot</name>, <name type="pname">Salomon de Caus</name> (1576?&#x2013;1626), who traveled extensively in <name type="place">Italy</name>, published his treatise on garden hydraulics, <hi rend="italic">Les Raisons des forces mou-<lb/>
vantes</hi> in 1615, when the enthusiasm for automata had begun to wane.</p>
<p>Although the grotto, the ornamental cascade, the architectural fountain, and the fountain arrangement known as a <hi rend="italic">buffet d'eau</hi> remained in vogue as French garden style matured under <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>, the ingenious Italian-derived hydraulics that were fashionable in the time of <name type="pname">Henry IV</name> and <name type="pname">Marie de M&#x00E9;dicis</name> fell into dis-<lb/>
use. As <name type="place">France</name> readied itself to become the supreme European power in the second half of the seventeenth century, French designers, having thoroughly incor-<lb/>
porated Italian influence, codified&#x2014;through treatises on garden theory and in engravings published in pat-<lb/>
tern books&#x2014;their own distinctive and subsequently influential style of landscape design. Perhaps the most original feature of the new French garden was the <hi rend="italic">parterre de broderie</hi>, an embroidery like design of decorative scrolls, palmettes, and arabesques in herbs, boxwood, or clipped grass, often with the addition of a monogram, which replaced the geometrically con-<lb/>
figured beds in Italian gardens (fig. 4.51). Several <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> patterns are found in the <hi rend="italic">Trait&#x00E9; du jardinage selon les raisons de la nature et de l'art</hi> (1638) by <name type="pname">Jacques Boyceau de la Baraudi&#x00E8;re</name>, <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Mollet</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Le Jardin de plaisir</hi> (1651), and <name type="pname">Claude Mollet</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Le Th&#x00E9;atre des plans et jardinages</hi> (1652).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-172">
<graphic url="CH4_052.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.50. Entrance to a grotto, from <hi rend="italic">Livre d'Architecture</hi> by <name type="pname">Alexan-<lb/>
dre Francini</name>. 1631</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The Mollets were royal gardeners residing and working in the Tuileries, along with members of the <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> and <name type="pname">Desgots</name> families, who also formed sev-<lb/>
eral generations of gardeners in the service of the
<pb n="162"/>
<pb n="162" type="orig"/>
crown. Under their care the Tuileries became a kind of laboratory in which the French garden style, with its axial <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi>, intricate <hi rend="italic">parterres de broderie</hi>, clipped cone-shaped yews and space-defining tall hedges, called <hi rend="italic">palissades</hi>, was matured and perfected (fig. 4.52).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-173">
<graphic url="CH4_053.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.51. Design for a <hi rend="italic">parterre de broderie</hi> in the style of <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Mollet</name>. Engraving from <hi rend="italic">Trait&#x00E9; du Jardinage</hi> by <name type="pname">Jacques Boy-<lb/>
ceau</name>. 1638</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-174">
<graphic url="CH4_054.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 4.52. <hi rend="italic">Palissades</hi>, plates 4 and 6 from <hi rend="italic">Le Th&#x00E9;atre des plans et jardinages</hi> by <name type="pname">Claude Mollet</name>. 1652</figDesc>
</figure>
<p><name type="pname">Jacques Boyceau</name> was not a gardener in the same practical mold as these. He was a <name type="pname">Huguenot</name> warrior and aristocratic intellectual who had been made an official of the king's chamber even before he was granted the posi-<lb/>
tion of <hi rend="italic">intendant-general</hi> of the king's gardens, including those of the <name type="place">Luxembourg</name> Palace (figs. 4.53, 4.54). A friend of some of the most notable intellectuals of his day, he aimed to produce in his <hi rend="italic">Trait&#x00E9;</hi> something more signif-<lb/>
icant than a trade book. Like <name type="pname">Alberti</name> before him, he found in nature's forms the perfection and symmetries to guide human artistic creation. The mastery of these laws, or at least a thorough practical acquaintance with them, formed for him one of the essential ingredients of the gardener's education. <name type="pname">Boyceau</name>'s chief importance to the history of landscape design is his role in articulating the principles governing a new landscape idiom and the influence he exerted in supervising such talented practi-<lb/>
tioners as the Mollets and <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tres</name>.</p>
<p>In addition to furnishing many elegant parterre pat-<lb/>
terns, <name type="pname">Boyceau</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Trait&#x00E9; du jardinage</hi> enunciated what might be called the first professional curriculum of land-<lb/>
scape design, thereby recognizing gardenmaking as a
<pb n="163"/>
<pb n="163" type="orig"/>
distinct profession. Trained gardeners, according to <name type="pname">Boyceau</name>, needed instruction in geometry, drafts-<lb/>
manship, architecture, and aesthetics besides learn-<lb/>
ing practical horticulture through apprenticeship. He sought to instill in them through this curriculum a thorough understanding of perspective and pro-<lb/>
portion. His work both laid the groundwork for future developments in French landscape design and exemplified the developments that had taken place in <name type="place">France</name> during the past century as the les-<lb/>
sons of <name type="place">Italy</name> were thoroughly absorbed. With its confident repertoire of patterns for elaborate <hi rend="italic">par-<lb/>
terres</hi> of boxwood "embroidery" and axial means of organizing landscape space, his treatise served <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>'s royal gardener <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> so well that the latter never felt compelled to write a treatise of his own.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-175">
<graphic url="CH4_055.jpg"/>
<figDesc>4.53. Plan of <name type="place">Luxembourg</name> Gardens drawn before 1627. Though <name type="pname">Jacques Boyceau</name>'s role in the creation of the <name type="place">Luxembourg</name> Gardens for <name type="pname">Marie de M&#x00E9;dicis</name> cannot be proved, a certain design maturity is evident here. There is a fine sense of proportion in the relationship of path width to <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> and <hi rend="italic">palissade</hi>, a generosity of scale, the manipulation of the ground plane for optical effect, calculated diversity within a framework of carefully balanced symmetry, and the use of eye-catching features&#x2014;fountains, sculpture, orange trees in boxes, balustrades, and stairs&#x2014;to break up space with rhythmical accents, thereby creating measurability.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-176">
<graphic url="CH4_056.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 4.54. <name type="place">Luxembourg</name> Gardens</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="164"/>
<pb n="164" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Four</hi></hi></head>
<note xml:id="CH4-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Dante</name>'s cosmology in <hi rend="italic">The Divine Comedy</hi> was, like that of <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>, one of hierarchical space, Earth-centered and spherically bounded. Heaven was positioned somewhere within the luminous celestial ring that consti-<lb/>
tutes the upper "band" of Earth's ether, a place where physical laws governing the terrestrial world no longer apply. Here dwelled, according to the medieval Christian cosmology to which <name type="pname">Dante</name> was heir, the divinity of godhead, angels, saints, and beatified souls. Because of the doctrine of resurrection, those who were redeemed had a transcendent, yet corporeal, existence_within this immaterial, yet real, realm. By contrast, <name type="pname">Nicolaus</name> of <name type="pname">Cusa</name>'s treatise <hi rend="italic">On Learned Ignorance</hi> posited a theory of limit-<lb/>
less, uncentered space, which rendered <name type="pname">Dan-<lb/>
te</name>'s concept of a hierarchy of spheres invalid. <name type="pname">Cusa</name>'s discovery implied the idea of infinite axial extension that was later anticipated by <name type="pname">Ren&#x00E9; Descartes</name>.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p>Quoted in <name type="pname">James S. Ackerman</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Villa: Form and Ideology of Country Houses</hi> (<name type="place">Princ-<lb/>
eton, New Jersey</name>: Princeton University Press, 1990), p. 73.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Leon Battista Alberti</name>, <hi rend="italic">De re aedificatoria</hi>. trans. <name type="pname">Joseph Rywert</name>, <name type="pname">Neil Leach</name>, and <name type="pname">Robert Tavernor</name> (<name type="place">Cambridge, Massachusetts</name>: MIT Press, 1988), p. 295.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p>Ibid., p. 300.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Ackerman</name>,_op. cit., p. 78.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p>The author of this edition is surmised to have been <name type="pname">Sir Robert Dallington</name> (<date when="1561">1561</date>&#x2013;<date when="1637">1637</date>), a courtier and man of letters. His translation, which is incomplete and very inexact, has been superceded on the five-hundredth anniversary of the work's original publication by the <name type="pname">Aldine Press</name> in <name type="place">Venice</name> by a thorough and highly read-<lb/>
able translation by <name type="pname">Joscelyn Godwin</name>, Professor of Music at Colgate University. Now, at last, scholars of garden history who read English can not only admire the illustrations that inspired many aspects of Renaissance garden design but can also comprehend the pleasure <name type="pname">Colonna</name> and his contemporaries, many of whom were churchmen like him, felt in appro-<lb/>
priating from antiquity the licence to celebrate eroticism in its many aspects, ranging from sexual love to love of beautiful art and architecture. See <name type="pname">Fran-<lb/>
cesco Colonna</name>, <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi>. trans. <name type="pname">Joscelyn Godwin</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Thames &amp; Hudson, 1999).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Francesco Colonna</name>, <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poli-<lb/>
phili</hi>. trans. <name type="pname">Joscelyn Godwin</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Thames &amp; Hudson, 1999), p. 6.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Simon Schama</name>, <hi rend="italic">Landscape and Memory</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Alfred A. Knopf, 1995), p. 274.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p>For <name type="pname">Colonna</name>'s description of the twenty groves of trees on the Isle of <name type="place">Cytherea</name>, see <name type="pname">Francesco Colonna</name>, <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poli-<lb/>
phili</hi>. trans. <name type="pname">Joscelyn Godwin</name>, pp. 294&#x2013;99.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p>The concept of "third nature" is one of the constructs of the Renaissance mind. A com-<lb/>
plex topic, it may be explained in simplified terms as follows: "First nature," or <hi rend="italic">natura natur-<lb/>
ans</hi> (nature's vital force), plus "second nature," or <hi rend="italic">natura naturata</hi> (nature's created sub-<lb/>
stance), when influenced by the human mind and hand, becomes "third nature," nature with the added component of design. For a good explanation of the Renaissance derivation of the concept of "third nature," see <name type="pname">Claudia Laz-<lb/>
zaro</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Italian Renaissance Garden</hi> (<name type="place">New Haven</name>: Yale University Press, 1990), pp. 9&#x2013;10.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p>As <name type="pname">Professor Godwin</name> points out in his intro-<lb/>
duction to his translation of <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi>. although <name type="pname">Colonna</name> was undoubtedly familiar with both <name type="pname">Alberti</name>'s treatise and that of <name type="pname">Vitruvius</name> and appropriated <name type="pname">Alberti</name>'s term <hi rend="italic">linea-<lb/>
menta</hi> to signify architectural details, his cast of mind was scarcely mathematical, and "when he deals with dimensions or geometrical con-<lb/>
structions, he is soon out of his depth." While <name type="pname">Colonna</name>'s vivid, detailed, enthusiastic descrip-<lb/>
tions and graphic illustrations were obviously inspirational, the <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia</hi> was hardly "the manual of a practitioner." See <name type="pname">Francesco Colonna</name>, <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili</hi>. trans. <name type="pname">Joscelyn Godwin</name>, pp. xi&#x2013;xii.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p>This remarkable basin is now to be found in the <name type="pname">Sala Rotondo</name> of the Museo Pio Clemen-<lb/>
tino within the <name type="place">Vatican</name> Museums.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p>Here <name type="pname">Ligorio</name>'s archaeology is evident in his use of antique coins and reliefs as inspiration for these stucco designs.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p>For a complete discussion of the role of these important <hi rend="italic">fontanieri</hi> in creating and main-<lb/>
taining the fountains of the Villa d'Este, see <name type="pname">David Coffin</name>, <hi rend="italic">Gardens and Gardening in <name type="pname">Papal Rome</name></hi> (<name type="place">Princeton, New Jersey</name>: Princeton Uni-<lb/>
versity Press, 1991), pp. 54&#x2013;55.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p>For instance, the central stairway in the garden is interrupted half-way up by the oval Dragon Fountain, framed by gracefully curving stairs. The four dragons within the fountain basin are doing double iconographie duty. <name type="pname">Car-<lb/>
dinal Ippolito</name> identified himself with the virtues chosen by the mythological hero <name type="pname">Hercules</name> when he slew the dragon that was guarding the Garden of the Hesperides and then picked the three golden apples symbolizing temperance, prudence, and chastity. The dragon was also the crest of <name type="pname">Pope Gregory XIII</name>, and the fountain with its four dragon heads was hastily com-<lb/>
pleted in honor of his visit to Tivoli on <date when="1572-09-27">Septem-<lb/>
ber 27, 1572</date>, shortly before the <name type="pname">Cardinal</name>'s death.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">David Coffin</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Villa in the Life of Renaissance <name type="place">Rome</name></hi> (<name type="place">Princeton, New Jersey</name>: Princeton University Press, 1979), pp. 358&#x2013;59 and <name type="pname">Reuben M. Rainey</name>, "The Garden as Myth: The Villa Lante at Bagnaia," in <hi rend="italic">Union Seminary Quarterly Review</hi>. 33:1 &amp; 2, (Fall/Winter <date when="1981">1981</date>&#x2013;<date when="1982">82</date>), pp. 98&#x2013;99.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p>Quoted in <name type="pname">Ackerman</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Villa</hi>, p. 98.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Caroline Constant</name>, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="pname">Palladio</name> Guide</hi> (<name type="place">Princeton</name>: Princeton Architectural Press, 1985), pp. 9&#x2013;10.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p>Quoted in <name type="pname">Ackerman</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Villa</hi>, p. 106.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">20.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Burlington</name> built his villa at <name type="place">Chiswick</name> as a scaled-down version of the Villa Rotonda (see fig. 7.1), and <name type="pname">Howard</name> commissioned the archi-<lb/>
tect <name type="pname">Sir John Vanbrugh</name> to design the Temple of the Four Winds also in imitation of the Villa Rotonda (see fig. 7.11).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">21.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Jefferson</name> borrowed ideas derived from English Palladianism at Monticello, and his work at his Poplar Forest estate is an exercise in geometrical form and mathematical harmony that owes a clear debt to <name type="pname">Palladio</name> (see figs. 7.43, 7.44).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">22.</hi></seg><p>This building was originally known as the Palazzo dei Senatori but renamed the Palazzo del Senatore, or Palace of the Senator, when after 1358 the papacy assumed control over civil <name type="place">Rome</name> and the Senate was reduced to a single representative appointed by the pope.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n23" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">23.</hi></seg><p>To stimulate the Roman economy through the production of silk and woolen cloth, <name type="pname">Sixtus V</name> enacted a law commanding the widespread planting of mulberry trees and also established a wool-spinning factory within the Colosseum, a project that languished only because of his death.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n24" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">24.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Kenneth Woodbridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Princely Gar-<lb/>
dens: The Origins and Development of the French Formal Style</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Rizzoli, 1986), for an excellent discussion of this subject. I am indebted to this source for much of what fol-<lb/>
lows in Section IV.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n25" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">25.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Hilary Ballon</name>, <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place">Paris</name> of <name type="pname">Henri IV</name>: Architecture and Urbanism (The <name type="place">Paris</name> of <name type="pname">Henri IV</name>: Architecture and Urbanism</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge, Massachusetts</name>: The MIT Press, 1991), for a lucid, scholarly study that portrays the birth of modern <name type="place">Paris</name> and explains Parisian land spec-<lb/>
ulation in the early seventeenth century. Here, the reader will find a detailed narrative of the creation of various streets, squares, and build-<lb/>
ings and watch, as it were, the Louvre, the Pont Neuf, and other now-familiar landmarks rising out of the ground.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH4-n26" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">26.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Ballon</name>, op. cit., pp. 36&#x2013;39.</p></note>
</div>
</div>
</div>
