<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/html/tei.xsl"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY</title>
                <author>ELIZABETH BARLOW ROGERS</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>HARRY N. ABRAMS, INC.,</publisher>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY by ELIZABETH BARLOW
                    ROGERS</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div type="chapter"><pb n="311"/><pb n="311" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER NINE EXPANDING CITIES AND NEW SOCIAL INSTITUTIONS: THE DEMOCRATIZATION OF LANDSCAPE DESIGN</hi></head><figure xml:id="fig-373"><graphic url="CH9_001.jpg"/></figure><p>The designs of many of the landscapes studied thus far derive&#x2014; sometimes overtly, sometimes implicitly&#x2014;from cosmological beliefs. The desire to perceive order and meaning in the universe is pervasive throughout human history and continues to govern some of our most deep-seated psychological and religious attitudes. In the West, however, as the Scientific Revolution gained momentum through the eighteenth century and political revolutions discredited entrenched power structures, the impulse to reflect in landscape terms a cosmological paradigm proclaiming divine order and elite authority diminished. As the theories of Newton were proved and extended by later scientific endeavor and became incorporated into the general cultural consciousness, intellectuals increasingly abandoned the quest for teleological meaning, concentrating instead on empirical explanations of the material world. Faith in reason and individual human action resulted in the substitution of personal judgment for blind obedience to authority, with significant political consequences as monarchies were toppled or their powers severely curtailed in favor of republican forms of government. For some people, faith in scientific progress displaced faith in supernatural powers and divine intervention in earthly affairs. For them, and for those who reconciled science with faith, the betterment of the conditions of life on Earth, not preparation for the hereafter, became the business of humankind.</p><p>Science assumed the authority previously enjoyed by religion and philosophy, which were demoted from their position as allencompassing, culture-defining thought systems to being spiritual and intellectual disciplines. The unprecedented knowledge and technological results achieved by the Western pursuit of science, voyages of global exploration, and colonial expansion made Europeans, though arrogant in their presumption of world hegemony, at least more cognizant of other cultural perspectives. Travel also furthered the growing interest in natural science, and with the philosophical shift from teleology to scientific materialism, chemistry, biology, geology, and botany began to be pursued with the same fervor as the study of celestial bodies had been in former centuries when astrology was believed to govern human fate.</p><p>This pursuit of natural science had profound consequences for religion and philosophy, especially after <name type="pname">Charles Darwin</name> (<date when="1809">1809</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>) published <hi rend="italic">The Origin of Species</hi> in <date when="1859">1859</date>. Galileo had long ago made it clear that Earth was no longer the center of the universe, but it now became apparent that humans were products of an evolutionary biology that linked them with the rest of the animal kingdom. Though bitterly resisted in some quarters, the same science that had caused human beings to modify their notions of their own nature and that of the cosmos also held the promise of untold material benefits.</p><p>But the power of people acting on their own behalf was often limited by their mistakes and misbegotten ideologies. In addition, humanity's growing power to control its destiny sometimes produced results that were not necessarily beneficial to Earth or even humankind in the long term. Darwin's theories necessarily took into account geological time and a dynamics of Earth in which forces of crustal uplift and erosion shaped the land, which was continually being recarved by wind, rain, and ice. Circumstances of geography and climate created ecological niches for species.<ref target="#CH9-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref>Now, in the nineteenth century, it became apparent to a few that the human species was capable of destroying other species and limiting its own future welfare as it continued to modify the environment by felling trees and clearing land for agriculture. This removal of native vegetation destroyed natural drainage systems, accelerated erosion, and altered climate.</p><p><name type="pname">George Perkins Marsh</name> (<date when="1801">1801</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>), American diplomat and early environmentalist, wrote <hi rend="italic">Man and Nature</hi> (<date when="1864">1864</date>) as a stern warning against this calamitous course of unchecked abuse of nature. Just as Darwin's theories made some people revise their understanding of the Biblical creation story and regard it as myth<pb n="312"/><pb n="312" type="orig"/>and metaphor instead of gospel, so Marsh's views made unworkable the notion of the Creator making Earth solely for humanity's exploitation. For Western Christian societies, to look at landscape in ecological and conservationist terms as Marsh did was to question the wisdom of the scriptural injunction in Genesis 1:28 to "fill the earth and subdue it." Dominion without enlightened husbandry, according to Marsh, spelled destruction.</p><p>The difficulty that practicing Christians and Jews in the nineteenth century had reconciling their beliefs with the challenging new theories of science and humanity's role as God's partner and steward of Earth rather than His mere ward should not be minimized. Intellectually and morally, the late eighteenth century had in the nations of the West consolidated the Scientific Revolution that had begun in the sixteenth, while at the same time giving birth to the Industrial Revolution. Now, in the nineteenth century, the unsettling vision Goethe had limned in <hi rend="italic">Faust Part II</hi> of nature overmastered by humanity in the form of the engineer and the developer was becoming a palpable reality. Romantics, following Rousseau and Wordsworth, found in wild nature the scenery of the sublime, a source of spiritual solace no longer available to those who had begun to question the premises of inherited religion. At the same time, the longing for the promise of redemptive salvation offered the faithful in earlier Christian centuries continued, and churchgoing remained a strongly rooted social convention and religious belief a personal need and cultural habit for many in the West.</p><p>The English writer and pioneer art critic John Ruskin (<date when="1819">1819</date>&#x2013;<date when="1900">1900</date>) promoted an aesthetics that was rooted in the study of nature, which he equated with Truth. By preaching a philosophy of Beauty with the same fervor as ministers of the Evangelical tradition in which he had been raised, Ruskin furthered the modern notion that the appreciation and practice of art could serve as a source of spiritual life rather than simply as a manifestation of it. Like others of his generation, Ruskin was appalled by the dehumanization he perceived to be a result of industrial capitalism's advance, and he sought to revive the artisanship associated with the medieval period, a time when craft guilds flourished and Gothic stone carvers' close observation of nature resulted in a vigorously vital style of ornamentation. The American writers Ralph Waldo Emerson (<date when="1803">1803</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>) and Henry David Thoreau (<date when="1817">1817</date>&#x2013;<date when="1862">1862</date>) met science's challenge to religion with transcendentalism, the literary and philosophical movement that advocated intuition as a mode of perception transcending empiricism.</p><p>Whether reacting against or incorporating the implications of modern science and Darwinism, few in the nineteenth century reckoned that further blows to humanity's self-esteem and relationship with past tradition had yet to be assimilated. But the insights of Friedrich Nietzsche (<date when="1844">1844</date>&#x2013;<date when="1900">1900</date>) and Sigmund Freud (<date when="1856">1856</date>&#x2013;<date when="1939">1939</date>) established the intellectual climate of much of the twentieth century, a radical modernity in which people no longer looked to past traditions for inspiration and a sense of continuity with history; instead, they looked to the present and future as the only reliable basis for knowledge and human advancement. Even those who remained religious in outlook increasingly considered themselves their own best earthly guides. Humanitarian social consciousness thus pervaded Western ideology, and utopian schemes flourished. This, abetted by widespread religious skepticism and atheism, helped create a cultural climate that gradually became receptive to, and more tolerant of, religious and social pluralism.</p><p>The consequences for landscape within the secular, highly energetic, increasingly cosmopolitan framework of nineteenthcentury Western culture were enormous. In terms of landscape history, the public parks movement is a signal contribution of the nineteenth century to modern urbanism. As more purely aesthetic values supplanted ideological ones in landscape design, the eighteenth-century Picturesque idiom remained viable for the creation of nineteenth-century parks and gardens. Many aristocrats destroyed the geometrical gardens of their ancestral seats as the <hi rend="italic">jardin anglais</hi> continued to be popular throughout nineteenthcentury Europe, an emblem of the social progressiveness of their owners. At the same time, theorists and practitioners adopted a more catholic approach to landscape aesthetics, and the doctrinal fervor and invective that had characterized the design disputes of the eighteenth century were replaced by an eclecticism in which individual taste was given increasingly broad license. History as a cultural value in its own right and an intellectual framework for preserving and imitating past styles replaced commitment to a single style reflecting a consensual ideology. Geometrical design was allowed back into English gardens, and the display of exotic plant material became a mark of the Victorian style called <hi rend="italic">Gardenesque.</hi></p><p>From our own historical vantage point, the nineteenth century's faith in scientific progress and planning as a means toward utopian human fulfillment seems overconfident, a heady and overweening attitude that produced unforeseen consequences. The hypocrisies and inequalities of this extraordinary age are all too glaring. Although the Industrial Revolution fostered capitalist economies in the West, which produced a broad middle class and brought a cornucopia of goods and comforts to many, it was wrenching for others, causing large-scale migrations that tore people away from their homes and homelands. Those dispossessed from an immediate connection with landscapes of important sentimental and psychological value often endured, in addition, squalid living conditions in rapidly growing cities. Republican governments proved no more immune to corruption and class distinctions than those based upon aristocratic privilege and social hierarchy. Colonialism, which reached its zenith in the nineteenth century, was generally callous in its disregard of native cultural values, attempting to establish Western mores as universal while relegating nonEuropean races to inferior status. Even after it became a sovereign nation, the United States accomplished the settlement of its continental territory under a similar cultural imperative.</p><p>At the same time, this period in Western history demonstrated the benefits of science as the foundations for modern medicine were laid, public sanitation victories achieved, better living conditions established, and faster means of transportation and communication developed. Scientific technology fostered an abundance of new inventions, constantly improving the processes of industrial production and accelerating its pace, making goods cheap and readily available. The potential danger to all human life consequent<pb n="313"/><pb n="313" type="orig"/>upon the splitting of the atom and widespread industrial degradation of the environment still lay in the future. In the nineteenth century, the energies of humanitarian reformers were focused on the unprecedented problems that attended the birth of mass society rather than on such global issues as these. Cholera, caused by contaminated drinking water, and other illnesses were associated with overcrowding. The use of industrial technology to build aqueducts, sewers, and other important elements of a new urban infrastructure was essential if populations were to survive in cities grown to a metropolitan scale. Further, parks and transportation lines connecting the commercial center with outlying residential suburbs needed to be built in order to maintain contact with nature otherwise lost to large-scale urban growth. The new immigrants pouring into cities in search of better lives posed special problems in terms of housing, education, and medical services. Responses to their suffering illuminated religion's revised role for many as an ethical, rather than a metaphysical, system.</p><p>Industrial capitalism and humane practicality went hand-inhand. Jeremy Bentham (<date when="1748">1748</date>&#x2013;<date when="1832">1832</date>) and James Mill (<date when="1773">1773</date>&#x2013;<date when="1836">1836</date>) enunciated the doctrine of utilitarianism, the ethical theory that sees utility as a measure of economic and social value, directing all action toward the goal of achieving the greatest happiness for the greatest number of people. Imbued with democratic principles and utilitarian concepts of social justice, civic and political leaders undertook prison and burial reform, established public education, and created cultural institutions and large municipal parks for the social improvement and recreation of the population at large.</p><p>The creation of public parks and rural cemeteries were linked nineteenth-century phenomena. The rise in the numbers of dead in growing municipalities forced speedy disinterment of bodies in order to make room for new burials. Sectarian minorities without burial grounds advocated nondenominational public cemeteries. They were joined by sanitary reformers who saw urban churchyards as a source of groundwater contamination, fostering the spread of cholera and other infectious diseases. P&#x00E8;re-Lachaise Cemetery in <name type="place">Paris</name>, established in <date when="1804">1804</date>, became an international model for municipal cemeteries elsewhere. In <name type="place">America</name>, the first public cemeteries, <name type="place">Boston</name>'s Mount Auburn and <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>'s GreenWood, served the function of public pleasure grounds in advance of the establishment of public parks, and their popularity did much to promote the municipal parks movement.</p><p>Within a repertoire of inherited design idioms featuring geometric, Picturesque, and gridiron layouts, which they often employed in combination, nineteenth-century designers strove to incorporate the newly discovered plants made available through expeditions of botanical discovery and the establishment of commercial nurseries. Through the publication of books and journals and as designers, such horticultural and landscape writers, editors, and practitioners as the Scot John Claudius Loudon (<date when="1782">1782</date>&#x2013;<date when="1843">1843</date>) and the American Andrew Jackson Downing (<date when="1815">1815</date>&#x2013;<date when="1852">1852</date>) democratized culture. They accomplished this by showing the aspiring members of the newly wealthy middle class how to attain the trappings of gentility, including homes and gardens similar, although on a smaller scale, to those of the aristocracy. The operative word in their works was <hi rend="italic">taste,</hi> a discerning sense of what was excellent, harmonious, and beautiful&#x2014; the quality that gave gentility visible form.</p><p>Increasingly, as living standards rose, commercial nurseries catering to the needs of the head gardeners on large estates were also able to bring horticulture within reach of other social strata. With the growth in home ownership, domesticity became a significant cultural value. The ornamental garden assumed new importance as an adjunct to the house, and even the humble cottage garden came to be regarded as an aesthetic object, rather than simply a utilitarian one. On great estates, owners ceased to remove cottages and sometimes whole villages, previously thought to blight the view of naturalistically arranged scenery. Increasingly toward the end of his career, Repton had found room for vernacular architecture in his designs, and Loudon now displayed the conscience of the times by illustrating his text on agrarian structures with sketches of cottages that provided both warmth and comfort for those who dwelt within and scenic charm for those who viewed them from without.</p><p>The nineteenth century signaled the separation of living space from the workplace as cottage manufacturing was replaced by industrial production in large factories. The middle-class interest in the private realm of house and garden could not have occurred without new, efficient means of public transportation after the invention of macadam paving and the railroad steam engine. These made possible the creation of residential suburbs, and landscape planners exploited this opportunity with considerable ingenuity. As the nineteenth-century metropolis became a regional-scale municipality, it encompassed its former rural environs, thereby accomplishing the ultimate ungirdling of cities and the final removal of old fortification walls.</p><p>Encouraged by <name type="pname">Mill</name>, <name type="pname">Bentham</name>, and the generally enterprising and practical temper of the times, people in the nineteenth century were disposed to admire utility. Although conservatives such as Ruskin found the new industrial building materials hideous, others equated the useful with the beautiful. While there was debate about the siting of the new-style conservatory at the Royal Botanic Gardens at Kew within the principal line of view, the technological ingenuity of its architecture was in fact a source of pride, and its immediate popularity justified its conspicuous location (see fig. 9.4). People soon attuned their eyes to the novel form and materials of such great glass structures, engineered to span unprecedented widths, and they became architectural icons of the age, employed in the construction of railroad stations and in the Crystal Palace of the Great Exposition held in <name type="place">London</name> in <date when="1851">1851</date>, followed by one built in <name type="place">New York</name> City two years later.</p><p>In other ways, technology played an important role in landscape design. The lawn mower was patented by Edwin Budding in <date when="1830">1830</date>. This efficient machine made possible a landscape aesthetic that put a premium upon the smooth, evenly sheared lawn as scythe mowing was abandoned (see fig. 9.6). The coming of railroads not only created the planned suburb, but brought quickly and cheaply nonlocal building materials and horticultural plants to urban centers. Innovations multiplied as inventors took out patents on a host of new materials: portland cement, asphalt paving, the wrought<pb n="314"/><pb n="314" type="orig"/>iron sash bar for conservatory panes, sheet glass. Cast-iron construction, the revival of terra-cotta casting, and the manufacture of encaustic tiles increased the range of opportunity for ornamental expression. Steam, hot-water, and eventually gas heating systems provided comfort and convenience to people and protected tender plants. Applications of technology to the built environment had important effects on landscape design and the appearance of cities.</p><p>Increasingly, the garden became the laboratory of horticultural science. Not only were exotic species displayed as choice specimens of garden art, but also grafting, training, and hybridization produced plants in new forms, shapes, and colors. Competitive exhibitions such as the Chiswick Show were organized to judge their merits. Commercial nurseries thrived as botanical interest became widespread.</p><p>Garden encyclopedias replaced treatises on aesthetics. Numerous periodicals sprang up to serve an audience eager for advice on the practical aspects of landscape design and infor\mation about the latest developments in botany and horticulture. Horticultural societies, botanical gardens, and certain wealthy persons continued to send plant explorers to remote parts of the globe in search of uncatalogued species. Botanical illustration reached its apogee as an art form, and many beautiful colored engravings by such talented artists as <name type="pname">Pierre-Joseph Redout&#x00E9;</name> (<date when="1759">1759</date>&#x2013;<date when="1841">1841</date>), <name type="pname">Francis Bauer</name> (<date when="1758">1758</date>&#x2013;<date when="1840">1840</date>) and <name type="pname">Ferdinand Bauer</name> (<date when="1760">1760</date>&#x2013;<date when="1826">1826</date>), and <name type="pname">James Sowerby</name> (<date when="1757">1757</date>&#x2013;<date when="1822">1822</date>) were reproduced in the proliferating horticultural magazines (see fig. 9.1). Some of their names&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">The Botanic Garden, Botanical Magazine or Flower-Garden Displayed, Gardeners' Magazine of Botany, Paxton's Magazine of Botany and Register of Flowering Plants, Horticultural Journal and Florists' Register of Useful Information Connected with Floriculture, The Floricultural Cabinet, Florists'Magazine</hi>&#x2014; suggest the nineteenth century's fascination with flowers newly available to gardeners through the efforts of ingenious hybridizers and intrepid explorers.</p><p>The competition among these periodicals in a time when literary piracy and plagiarism were common generated considerable editorial invective. The passions that ran high in their pages were symptomatic of an intense and broadening interest in horticulture and landscape design. In <hi rend="italic">Gardener's Magazine, and Register of Rural and Domestic Improvement,</hi> the earliest general horticultural publication, Loudon forthrightly delivered his candid opinions between <date when="1826">1826</date> and <date when="1844">1844</date>. As we shall see in Chapter Eleven, by the end of the century, after the Victorian garden had incorporated the botanical riches of the age, new design wars erupted in <name type="place">England</name>, pitting advocates of informal impressionistic arrangement of herbaceous borders, such as the horticultural writer and editor William Robinson and the Arts and Crafts gardener, photographer, and author Gertrude Jekyll, against those who practiced "bedding out," the arrangement of plants according to precise patterns for seasonal display. At the same time, Sir Reginald Blomfield championed Italianate geometrical style in <hi rend="italic">The Formal Garden in <name type="place">England</name></hi> (<date when="1892">1892</date>), fiercely opposing Robinson's naturalistic approach. Thus was the debate between Art and Nature once again joined within the context of landscape design.</p><p>The rapidly industrializing cities of the northeastern United States looked to <name type="place">England</name> for landscape design models at the same time as the American frontier was being pushed westward. The street grid proved the most practical means for parceling and conveying real estate in new cities, but preceptors such as <name type="pname">Andrew Jackson Downing</name>, who instructed the growing middle class in the principles of horticultural management and Picturesque landscape design, began to pose an alternative. Downing gave the term <hi rend="italic">rural</hi> new meaning by creating a middle landscape of suburban "villa" and cottage architecture&#x2014;a built landscape that was neither wholly agrarian nor wholly urban.</p><p>Frederick Law Olmsted (<date when="1822">1822</date>&#x2013;<date when="1903">1903</date>), in partnership with the English-born architect Calvert Vaux (<date when="1824">1824</date>&#x2013;<date when="1895">1895</date>), directed the Picturesque idiom toward democratic ends in creating America's first public parks. The parks that Olmsted and Vaux designed, first in <name type="place">New York</name> and then in other cities, were mostly naturalistic essays in which they replicated rural and wilderness scenery in order to create a poetic mood that would lift the spirits of careworn city dwellers. Olmsted and Vaux also became the country's first urban planners on a metropolitan scale, conceiving of parkways as a means of linking parks together into a citywide system and providing carriage drives to America's first suburbs. The curvilinear layout of the suburbs they designed posed a Picturesque alternative to the grid, heretofore the standard plan for new streets. Still other forces at the end of the nineteenth century set the country on a different course, as the designers for a Gilded Age imitated the historic architecture and planning forms of Renaissance and seventeenth-century <name type="place">France</name> and <name type="place">Italy</name>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Indefatigable</hi> and <hi rend="italic">industrious</hi> are adjectives often connected with the names of many nineteenth-century figures. Herculean were the labors of those who created the botanical gardens and other scientific and cultural institutions, meticulously recorded the observations of their difficult voyages to distant parts, built the parks and park systems that we still enjoy, and conceived and built the transportation and sanitary engineering infrastructure to support large cities&#x2014;all the while corresponding voluminously and publishing profusely without the convenience of present-day communications technology. Our chronicle of the period begins with a discussion of the careers of several important figures who personify the human energy that flourished spectacularly at this time.</p><div type="section"><pb n="315"/><pb n="315" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold">I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Botanical Science, the Gardenesque Style, and People's Parks: Landscape Design in Victorian England</hi></hi></head><p>Eighteenth-century Enlightenment science opened the door to the passionate pursuit of natural history in the nineteenth century. The real "discovery" of <name type="place">America</name> had been the discovery by Europeans of unbounded economic opportunity, a good deal of which was based at first on a single plant, tobacco. A happy bonus had been the introduction to botanical science of a wealth of hitherto unknown ornamental species. The plant exchanges that occurred first in the colonial era and then in the federal period prepared the way for the explosion of horticultural activity in the nineteenth century. The taxonomic classification system developed by Linnaeus, in which Latin provided a universal language of binomial references for individual plant species, made it possible for members of a growing international scientific community to develop a common knowledge base and communicate intelligibly with one another.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Royal Botanic Gardens at Kew</hi></hi></head><p>At the center of much of this botanical activity and forming the bridge between the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries stood Sir Joseph Banks (<date when="1743">1743</date>&#x2013;<date when="1820">1820</date>), the president of the Royal Society from <date when="1778">1778</date> until his death and, as botanical advisor to George III, de facto director of the Royal Gardens at Kew. Wealthy, politically well-connected, and with three years of experience collecting plants on the <hi rend="italic">Endeavour</hi> voyage as credentials for projects of this nature, Banks was able to attract royal and aristocratic patronage for naturalists attached to ships bound for distant lands. He assessed the professional skills and industriousness of young men in training at Kew, and from their ranks selected candidates such as Allan Cunningham and James Bowie for the arduous work of plant hunting in the wilds of South Africa, <name type="place">Australia</name>, the Americas, and China. Banks enjoined these and other explorers to keep journals recording the climatic conditions and soil quality of native plant habitats. The greatest difficulty occurred in transporting seeds and specimens on long ocean voyages where cold, mildew, sea spray, vermin, and natural disaster took a significant toll.</p><p>It was not until <date when="1838">1838</date> that <name type="pname">Nathaniel Ward</name> (<date when="1791">1791</date>&#x2013;<date when="1868">1868</date>) of <name type="place">London</name>, a doctor and naturalist, stumbled upon an invention that proved of great utility to future plant collectors. After burying a chrysalis in soil placed in the bottom of a covered glass jar, he soon discovered that the seeds in the soil began to germinate because condensation produced by plant respiration within the jar created a moist, self-sustaining environment. He published his discovery in a treatise titled <hi rend="italic">On the Growth of Plants in Closely Glazed Cases</hi> (<date when="1842">1842</date>), and the Wardian case&#x2014;in effect a miniature greenhouse&#x2014;soon became part of the standard equipment of all plant hunters. Meanwhile, collectors in the field, whose passage and pay were funded by the Horticultural Society of <name type="place">London</name>&#x2014;founded in <date when="1804">1804</date> to advance botanical science and garner foreign plant material for English gardens&#x2014;ingeniously devised new methods and materials for packing their precious cargoes, albeit with statistically disappointing results. Nevertheless, enough plants survived, and <name type="place">England</name>'s ambitions as a colonial power assured continuing opportunities for botanists to attach themselves to vessels bound for exotic locales. To Banks belongs credit for establishing the eminence of the Royal Gardens at Kew as a repository for dried specimens and botanical data, a center for the global transfer of plant material, and the imperial nexus of a growing number of colonial botanical gardens.</p><p><name type="pname">William Townsend Aiton</name> (<date when="1766">1766</date>&#x2013;<date when="1849">1849</date>), the superintendent of Kew after <date when="1793">1793</date> and one of the founders of the Horticultural Society of <name type="place">London</name> (later the Royal Horticultural Society), assisted Banks in ensuring that specimens of plants collected from various sources were sent to Kew. Banks's visionary leadership, combined with his ardent imperialism, set the agenda. He requested diplomats, army and navy officers, captains of merchant vessels, foreign missionaries, and colonial correspondents to foster Kew's botanical collections. As a result, in <date when="1789">1789</date>, Aiton published <hi rend="italic">Hortus Kewensis,</hi> a three-volume catalogue of the plants at Kew, prepared with the help of <name type="pname">Daniel Solander</name>, a former pupil of <name type="pname">Linnaeus</name>, and <name type="pname">Jonas Dryander</name>, another professional botanist from <name type="place">Sweden</name>. Engravings from watercolors by <name type="pname">James Sowerby</name> (<date when="1757">1757</date>&#x2013;<date when="1822">1822</date>) illustrate this handsome and monumental work (fig. 9.1).</p><figure xml:id="fig-374"><graphic url="CH9_002.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.1. <hi rend="italic">Phaius tankervilleae,</hi> a tropical orchid iotroduced into <name type="place">England</name> in <date when="1778">1778</date>. Engraving after a watercolor by Janies Sowerby. Plate 12, Volume 3, of the <date when="1789">1789</date> edition of <hi rend="italic">Hortus Kewensis,</hi> published by William Townsend Aiton</hi></figDesc></figure><p>By the <date when="1820">1820</date>s, Kew's preeminence was being eclipsed by more progressive and active botanical organizations, notably the Horticultural Society of <name type="place">London</name>, which in that decade was sponsoring plantcollecting expeditions to <name type="place">China</name>, <name type="place">Africa</name>, <name type="place">Mexico</name>, parts of <name type="place">South America</name>, and the Pacific coast of the United States. As botanical gardens proliferated at universities and in the newly wealthy manufacturing cities, Kew stagnated. Visitors noticed its decline, and <name type="pname">John Claudius Loudon</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Gardener's Magazine</hi> commented with asperity on the situation. However, in <date when="1841">1841</date>, the British Treasury assumed support of Kew, renaming it the Royal Botanic Gardens. <name type="pname">William Jackson</name><pb n="316"/><pb n="316" type="orig"/><name type="pname">Hooker</name> (<date when="1785">1785</date>&#x2013;<date when="1865">1865</date>) was appointed director. By then, Loudon had traveled extensively, visited botanical gardens in <name type="place">England</name> and abroad, and was well established as the country's leading spokesperson on horticulture. His remarkable career as a scientific farmer, landscape gardener, inventor, writer, and editor epitomizes the creative energy, scientific appetite, technological aptitude, encyclopedic knowledge, and humanitarian conscience that fueled the cultural developments of the nineteenth century in general and the field of landscape design in particular.</p><figure xml:id="fig-375"><graphic url="CH9_003.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.2. "East Front of Tew Lodge," from Loudon's <hi rend="italic">Designs for Laying Out Farms,</hi> <date when="1812">1812</date></hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">John Claudius Loudon</hi></hi></head><p><name type="pname">John Claudius Loudon</name> (<date when="1783">1783</date>&#x2013;<date when="1843">1843</date>),<ref target="#CH9-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref>typified his age in his sympathy for the mass of humanity, his idealism, his ability to give physical expression to the conceptual, and his propensity for thinking in long-range and largescale terms. He was in effect a metropolitan planner several decades before <name type="place">London</name> and other British cities were organized governmentally to accept this kind of vision. An admirer of Thomas Jefferson whose term <hi rend="italic">self-government</hi> he borrowed upon occasion, he looked forward to the day when public improvements were undertaken by general consensus and in a comprehensive and rational manner, not piecemeal at the behest of the wealthy and powerful. He felt that tunnels, bridges, and other works of utilitarian engineering were nobler monuments to a society's genius than the grandest examples of purely heroic architecture and sculpture. Sanitary engineering and the conquest of distance by rail transport excited his imagination as he dreamed of livable cities and the measures that would enable the worker to be more conveniently united with a job and the middle-class homeowner with a plot of suburban greenery. He had the idea of shaping metropolitan growth and relieving congestion with a series of concentric greenbelts long before <name type="pname">Ebenezer Howard</name> (<date when="1850">1850</date>&#x2013;<date when="1928">1928</date>) and subsequent planners proposed this type of controlled urbanism.</p><p>Loudon, the eldest son of a Scottish farmer, arrived in <name type="place">London</name> in <date when="1803">1803</date> at the age of twenty, well educated and with practical experience in hothouse design and embankment construction for land reclamation. A letter of introduction from a former professor introduced him to Sir Joseph Banks, who generously befriended him. He also became acquainted with the botanical artist <name type="pname">James Sowerby</name> and with <name type="pname">Jeremy Bentham</name>, whose theory of utilitarianism and whose ideological range and systematic intellectual approach had a lasting influence upon him.</p><p>Loudon's first literary effort in <name type="place">London</name> was a proposal to apply Picturesque principles to the planting of hardy trees and flowering shrubs within the city's squares. He followed this essay with <hi rend="italic">Observations on Landscape Gardening</hi> (<date when="1804">1804</date>), which helped him attract clients seeking his professional advice. Between <date when="1808">1808</date> and <date when="1811">1811</date>, he resided at Tew Lodge Farm, Oxfordshire, where, in addition to proving to the landowner and his client, General <name type="pname">George Frederick Stratton</name>, the profitability of a new system of leasehold arrangements, Loudon directed numerous improvements paid for by the general, aspiring here to create <name type="place">England</name>'s premier <hi rend="italic">ferme orn&#x00E9;e.</hi> He removed some hedgerows in order to plant new ones as shelters against the prevailing winds, had rough fields regraded and installed with drains, and built a farmhouse in an innovative design that emphasized practicality, comfort, and technology over ornament and style; yet he made these elements of economy and convenience compatible with elegance and refinement (fig. 9.2). His farm roads followed the contours of the land in a Picturesque manner, and around his new house he planted shrubs and trees in irregular masses, once again according to the system of Jussieu. Although he did not coin the term <hi rend="italic">Gardenesque</hi> until twenty years later, here he put into practice the principles of his later definition by incorporating exotic species into his landscape design and displaying all plants, whether foreign or native, in such a way that each could reveal itself to advantage. Botanical display was a central focus for Loudon, and his intention at Tew Lodge Farm and elsewhere was to acknowledge landscape as nature, art, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> science.</p><p>From the beginning of his career, Loudon saw education as one of his missions. At Tew Lodge Farm he established an agricultural college to teach the sons of the landed gentry and prospective estate agents his new methods of scientific farming. Moreover, he was progressive in his concern for farm laborers, paying particular attention to the quality of their housing and food. But being not yet thirty, Loudon was more interested in demonstrating a successful experiment than in settling permanently at Tew Lodge Farm. However<pb n="317"/><pb n="317" type="orig"/>challenging the life of a scientific farmer and educator might have been, his phenomenal energies and intellectual curiosity required a larger sphere of activity. After two and a half years, when General Stratton offered to buy back his lease, Loudon accepted.</p><figure xml:id="fig-376"><graphic url="CH9_004.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.3. "The Polyprosopic Hothouse," one of the sketches by <name type="pname">John Claudius Loudon</name> of various methods of designing glasshouses, from <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on the Theory and Practice of Landscape Gardening.</hi> According to Loudon, "The Polyprosopic Hot-house resembles a curvilinear house, but differs in having the surface thrown into a number of faces, the chief advantages of which are, that by hinging all the different faces at their upper angles, and by having rods connecting the lower outside corners of the faces terminating in chains, which go over pulleys in the top or above the back wall, the whole roof, including the ends, may be opened or raised sympathetically, like Venetian blinds, either so as each sash or face may be placed in the plane of the angle of the sun's rays at the time, or to the perpendicular, to admit a shower of rain."</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-377"><graphic url="CH9_005.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.4. Palm House, Kew, Richmond, designed by Decimus Burton and Richard Turner. <date when="1844">1844</date>&#x2013;48</hi></figDesc></figure><p>With the Napoleonic wars in Europe drawing to a close, he now seized the opportunity to travel abroad, journeying across northern Europe during a nineteen-month period in <date when="1813">1813</date> and <date when="1814">1814</date>. Letters of introduction from <name type="pname">Sir Joseph</name> Banks gained him access to aristocratic estates and professional societies where his knowledge of French, German, and Italian made it possible for him to speak fluently with head gardeners, architects, and others. In Russia, he was impressed with the pineapples, cherries, peaches, plums, apples, pears, and grapes that were being grown under glass on noblemen's estates. It was with a technical eye that he studied the construction of greenhouses or remarked on the heat-retention capabilities of the Russian stove. These observations served him well when, upon returning to <name type="place">London</name>, he turned his thoughts toward an examination of how the construction of greenhouses could be improved through technology.</p><p>In this effort he was not alone. In <date when="1812">1812</date>, <name type="pname">Thomas Andrew Knight</name> (<date when="1759">1759</date>&#x2013;<date when="1838">1838</date>), the younger brother of <name type="pname">Richard Payne Knight</name> and a member of the Horticultural Society of <name type="place">London</name>, published a paper in which he suggested that a purely functional hothouse in which the greatest amount of light could be admitted through the least expanse of glass, one that in addition could be efficiently heated, would offer horticultural and economic advantages over hothouses designed in the conventional manner. Conservatories at this time were still being designed in the tradition represented by Chambers's Orangery at Kew, with large arched windows set into masonry walls. Experimenting with different shapes and structural techniques in his Bayswater garden, in <date when="1816">1816</date> Loudon invented a curvilinear sash bar of wrought iron. His experiments also led him to propose a "ridge and furrow," or double-meridian, glazing system in which the glass panes of the conservatory were angled so as best to catch morning and afternoon light while preventing the scorching of leaves by the direct rays ot the noonday sun. He also conceived a "polyprosopic design of hinged surfaces that could be adjusted by chains and pulleys in the manner of Venetian blinds to gain a more desirable angle in relation to the sun or to let in fresh air and summer rain showers (fig. 9.3). As curved-glass conservatories for tender plants became common on estates after the lifting of the British tax on glass in <date when="1845">1845</date>, their juxtaposition with the eclectic neotraditional architecture of the Victorian mansion was sometimes ridiculed, but following Loudon (see fig. 9.2), these popular status symbols were given pride of place in Victorian landscaping schemes.</p><p><name type="pname">Joseph Paxton</name>'s ridge-and-furrow-style conservatory at Chatsworth, the great Palm House at Kew designed by architect Decimus Burton (<date when="1800">1800</date>&#x2013;<date when="1881">1881</date>), with ironmaster Richard Turner, as a series of sheer, taut-skinned agglomerated hemispheres, and Paxton's iconic Crystal Palace built for the Great Exposition of <date when="1851">1851</date> in Hyde Park&#x2014;all owe a debt to Loudon's pioneering work in glasshouse construction (fig. 9.4). Now Loudon's fertile genius, excited by technology, projected other innovations as well, including schemes for industrial workers' housing and a solar heating system, which he published in <date when="1822">1822</date> in his comprehensive, detailed, and well-organized <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of Gardening.</hi></p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia,</hi> which ran to several editions and revisions over the course of fifty years, and the widely read <hi rend="italic">Gardener's Magazine</hi> gave Loudon a forum for his progressive, reform-minded ideas. In <date when="1825">1825</date> at the age of forty-two, he lost his right arm and the ability to write and draw, but this did not deter him from<pb n="318"/><pb n="318" type="orig"/>focusing his career primarily upon these and other important subsequent literary endeavors. With the help of contributors, draftsmen, relatives, and his wife, who served as his amanuensis and editorial assistant, he produced <hi rend="italic">The Green-House Companion</hi> (<date when="1824">1824</date>), <hi rend="italic">An Encyclopaedia of Agriculture</hi> (<date when="1825">1825</date>), <hi rend="italic">An Encyclopaedia of Plants</hi> (<date when="1829">1829</date>), <hi rend="italic">Loudon's Hortus Britannicus</hi> (<date when="1830">1830</date>), <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of Cottage, Farm and Villa Architecture and Furniture</hi> (<date when="1833">1833</date>), <hi rend="italic">Arboretum et Fruticetum Britannicum; or the Trees and Shrubs of Britain, Native and Foreign</hi> (<date when="1838">1838</date>), and <hi rend="italic">Self-instruction for Young Gardeners, Foresters, Bailiffs, Land-Stewards, and Farmers</hi> (<date when="1845">1845</date>).</p><figure xml:id="fig-378"><graphic url="CH9_006.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.5. Plan, Derby Arboretum, <date when="1839">1839</date>, by <name type="pname">John Claudius Loudon</name></hi></figDesc></figure><p>In all these works he combined an ardent humanitarian interest in improved working conditions and educational opportunities for gardeners with matters of scientific and technological interest, practical horticultural advice, aesthetic theories, and critical descriptions of gardens, which he visited regularly on his travels through <name type="place">England</name> and Europe. His audience consisted of <name type="pname">Oxford</name> and <name type="place">Cambridge</name> dons, country vicars, doctors, directors of botanical gardens, architects, engineers, landscape designers, and head gardeners on the estates of the nobility. Lords and ladies read his works, too, as did, he hoped, his target audience: young gardeners who, not being able to afford the two-shilling cost of a copy of <hi rend="italic">The Gardener's Magazine,</hi> had to borrow it.</p><p>Although as a young man eager to establish his own reputation, Loudon had taken issue with some of the design principles of the doyen of landscape gardeners, Humphry Repton, in <date when="1840">1840</date> he served as the editor of a new edition of Repton's collected works. Loudon realized, as had Repton, that publication was a surer route to far-reaching professional influence than commissions to landscape the properties of the wealthy But commissions, especially those that served a public interest, were an important means of demonstrating the principles and practices he advocated in his books and magazines. He was therefore delighted to be summoned to the industrial town of Derby in the spring of <date when="1839">1839</date> to lay out an 11-acre arboretum, the gift to the town from its former mayor, <name type="pname">Joseph Strutt</name>. Here, in the smoky Midlands, thanks to Strutt's philanthropy, Loudon had an opportunity to demonstrate his belief that a landscape containing the most beautiful specimens of nature could edify the general populace, relieve the misery of the working poor, and produce among the mingled classes sentiments of mutual respect and civic pride.</p><p>Although Loudon had integrated the awkwardly shaped parcel with an efficient circulation system, concealed its boundaries with dense planting, and made less apparent its cramped dimensions with a series of linear mounds that focused the view on the immediate surroundings and screened people and objects elsewhere on the grounds, as a design, the Derby Arboretum drew mixed reviews (fig. 9.5). But as a social experiment, it was an unqualified success. Three days of public revels attended its opening, and according to contemporary reports not a single plant was harmed. It remained a popular attraction, drawing on Sundays throngs of working-class people, some of whom traveled in the third-class railway carriages from as far away as Sheffield, Birmingham, and Leeds. When they arrived, they could refresh themselves at the entry lodge, where there were toilet facilities and hot water for tea. Then they were free to stroll along serpentine paths, admiring the shrubs and trees arranged according to the Jussieu system,<ref target="#CH9-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref>which were identified by labels giving botanical and com<pb n="319"/><pb n="319" type="orig"/>mon names, country of origin, mature height, and the date of introduction into Britain. Loudon also had the specimens of the Derby Arboretum numbered, and these numbers were keyed to information in a pamphlet he produced containing much scientific and anecdotal information, which visitors could purchase at the lodge. Those who preferred simple relaxation to botanical edification could walk on one of the two broad, straight gravel paths that constituted the Arboretum's cross axis. Pavilions at the ends of the crosswalks provided shade or shelter from a shower. Benches, with footboards as an accommodation to the aged and infirm, offered seating along the paths. Altogether, the Derby Arboretum was an impressive and progressive accomplishment in <date when="1840">1840</date>, a forerunner of the work of Joseph Paxton, Frederick Law Olmsted, and other later park builders.</p><p>Loudon's marriage at the age of forty-seven to Jane Webb (<date when="1807">1807</date>&#x2013;<date when="1858">1858</date>) was rewarding for both partners. Her kind spirit and literary abilities were tested to the utmost as she set about helping him write and publish his lifework, the handsomely illustrated, vast, and taxing <hi rend="italic">Arboretum et Fruticetum Britannicum.</hi> Later, as a widow, she undertook to pay off the remaining debt that this immense and costly endeavor had imposed on them. Her reward was pride in his place in history and lasting renown in her own right. Loudon, who advocated the pursuit of horticulture by women, had encouraged her activities as a practical gardener as well as a writer, and she was instrumental in turning other women's time and physical energies to this healthful employment. Her <hi rend="italic">Gardening for Ladies</hi> ran to several editions and was edited for American publication by Andrew Jackson Downing. With her last book, <hi rend="italic">My Own Garden; or The Young Gardener's Year Book</hi> (<date when="1855">1855</date>), she introduced children to the pleasures that she and Loudon had shared with their daughter Agnes or observed on their travels as a family.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Victorian Garden</hi></hi></head><p>Under the influence of the Loudons, the Victorian garden perpetuated the Picturesque tradition while also displaying the results of botanical science. Combined with expression of the Romantic spirit of the age was a bent toward practicality and desire to employ industrial materials that anticipated the functional landscape aesthetic of twentieth-century modernism (see Chapter Thirteen). But unlike modernist designers who sought to elevate functionalism to the status of aesthetic principle, Victorian landscape gardeners were unreservedly eclectic. They cloaked their functionalism in period costume&#x2014;"the Styles that Le Corbusier as a polemical modernist would famously rail against. The search for cultural coherence where none could be found in the face of society's growing secularism and rapid technological change fostered this historicism. People who cared about such things looked nostalgically to the architectural vocabularies of other times and places as embodiments of various truer meanings than what they believed existed in nineteenth-century <name type="place">England</name>. Followers of John Ruskin, for instance, developed the Victorian Gothic style with its evocation of medieval Christian values. Other Victorians, ambitious for Britain's growing imperial power, favored Neoclassical design idioms based on French and Italian models as appropriate means of advertising wealth and status. Imitations of the <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> beds found in seventeenth-century <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teaux</hi> gardens proved admirably suited to their lavish, patterned floral displays.</p><p>Even such a prominent practitioner of the Picturesque as Repton modified his style at the end of his career to reflect a greater tolerance for period elements, such as terraces with balustrades. With practical considerations in mind, he abandoned the illusionary technique of the ha-ha with which he had, following Brown, fostered an impression of unbroken rural scenery extending from distant pastures to the walls of the mansion. He even designed Gardenesque flower beds in its immediate environs (see fig. 7.25). Repton's collected works, thanks to the <date when="1840">1840</date> edition edited by Loudon, were now a ready reference for those who came to feel that the eighteenthcentury approach to the Picturesque had been overly zealous in its eradication of traditional forms. Even Price regretted having removed the terraces of his country house, Foxley, in his youth. People now saw that terraces offered foreground interest and a pleasing transitional element between the necessary geometry of the house and the carefully contrived naturalistic character of its grounds.</p><figure xml:id="fig-379"><graphic url="CH9_007.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.6. Lawn-mowing machine as illustrated in Loudon's <hi rend="italic">Gardener's Magazine,</hi> 8 (<date when="1832">1832</date>)</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Efficiency, a virtue of the new industrial age, was a demonstrable value in the landscape as well, with new attention being given to maintenance. The invention of the lawn mower made hand-cut grass and the bucolic lawn cropped by cattle things of the past (fig. 9.6). Scythes were laid aside, and large swards<pb n="320"/><pb n="320" type="orig"/>of closely mowed green turf became highly desirable. Macadam paving now smoothed formerly rutted roads, which no longer meandered needlessly, if picturesquely, to their destination. The general air of neglect that had overtaken estates during the turmoil of the Napoleonic wars was erased as owners instituted modern maintenance practices and employed technology to improve their land.</p><figure xml:id="fig-380"><graphic url="CH9_008.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.7. Terrace knot garden, Hatfield House, Hertfordshire, original restoration design by the second Marquess of Salisbury. <date when="1840">1840</date>s. Restored again by the Marchioness of Salisbury in the early <date when="1980">1980</date>s</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Although there were periods of economic distress in the nineteenth century, on the whole English prosperity was such that, at the prevailing low wages, small armies of gardeners could be put to work on the great estates. The head gardeners, who commanded these workers while attending and informing the landscaping tastes of their lordly masters, became important purveyors of the several Victorian garden styles as the trend toward imaginative historicizing brought several older design vocabularies&#x2014;-Jacobean English, Renaissance Italian, and seventeenth-century French and Dutch&#x2014;back into vogue. With this labor force and with railroad transportation to deliver materials from afar, including huge boulders for the rock gardens that became fashionable at this time, dukes and earls vied in the creation of gardens where spectacular effects and horticultural virtuosity were important ends.</p><figure xml:id="fig-381"><graphic url="CH9_009.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.8. Levens Hall, Westmorland, Topiary Garden, created c. <date when="1700">1700</date>; restored and maintained by head gardener Alexander Forbes, active <date when="1810">1810</date>&#x2013;62</hi></figDesc></figure><p><name type="pname">William Barron</name> (<date when="1801">1801</date>&#x2013;<date when="1891">1891</date>), the head gardener to the earls of Harrington at Elvaston Castle in Derbyshire, achieved renown for his tree-transplanting expertise and for creating a famous topiary garden. In assembling the unusual mature specimen trees and already shaped tall topiary shrubs for Elvaston's landscape, he introduced the technique of moving plants with a large ball of earth still attached to their roots. Grafting, too, was a specialty at Elvaston and other gardens where composite trees assumed forms and vegetal characteristics never before seen in nature.</p><p>Landscape restoration often went well beyond what archaeology might have dictated in cases of period reconstructions in the Elizabethan and Jacobean manner, such as the one at Hatfield House, where the second marquess of Salisbury had knot gardens and a maze constructed (fig. 9.7). At Levens Hall in Westmorland, Alexander Forbes, the head gardener, set about restoring the topiary garden of around <date when="1700">1700</date>, and the apparent antiquity of this reconstruction may have persuaded even such an astute observer as Loudon of its being the original one rather than its re-creation (fig. 9.8).</p><p>Italianate gardens swept back into vogue as broad terraces and staircases with balusters and urnshaped finials spilled gracefully down to English lawns dotted with floral beds. Besides this use of stepped terraces as transitional elements in the intermediate zone between the house and the extensive landscape beyond, there was with the work of William Andrews Nesfield (<date when="1793">1793</date>&#x2013;<date when="1881">1881</date>) a revival of the French <hi rend="italic">parterre de broderie.</hi> Nesfield often based his designs on those provided in the pattern book of Dezallier d'Argenville, but he was versatile and enjoyed experimenting with Tudor knot gardens as well. He worked at Kew between <date when="1844">1844</date> and <date when="1848">1848</date> in association with Decimus Burton. For this important commission, Nesfield adopted a style reminiscent of the period of William and Mary as he created a <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> terrace platform for the Palm House, laid out a <hi rend="italic">patte d'oie</hi> radiating from it into a new Pinetum, or arboretum of coniferous evergreens, reconfigured the pond, and redesigned the Broad Walk (fig. 9.9).</p><p>Display fountains had long ago ceased to play in English gardens. To bring the delight of animated water back into the landscape, Capability Brown had created the woodland cascade, one of the few Brownian elements not attacked by the proponents of the Picturesque. Now, with industrial technology at hand, there was renewed interest in fountain construction,<pb n="321"/><pb n="321" type="orig"/>and some remarkable waterworks were created, such as <name type="pname">Joseph Paxton</name>'s Emperor Fountain at Chatsworth (see fig. 9.11).</p><figure xml:id="fig-382"><graphic url="CH9_010.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.9. Plan of Kew Gardens from the <date when="1850">1850</date>s, showing Nesfield's alterations</hi></figDesc></figure><p>The green landscape took on myriad hues as brightly colored flowers from countries such as Mexico made their spectacular appearance in Victorian gardens. Color theory became one of the head gardener's job requirements. Not only did carpet beds&#x2014; mosaiclike seasonal display beds&#x2014;have to be designed for similarity of flower height and simultaneity of bloom, but they also had to be laid out according to artistic principles dictating the juxtaposition of solid floral masses of contrasting and complementary rather than similar tones.</p><p>The challenge facing nineteenth-century designers was how to assemble all of these interesting, useful, and charming objects&#x2014;botanical specimens, historical ruins, glasshouses and summerhouses, rock gardens and kitchen gardens, flowers and fountains&#x2014;within a coherent framework. Loudon's designs owed their coherence to what he called the axis of symmetry. As he explained it:<q>In the simplest kind of symmetry, the two sides are equal and alike, and the axis is, of course, easily discovered; but in cultivated and refined symmetry, the sides are unequal, and so combined and varied with the centre, that it requires the eye of a philosophical artist to detect the axis.<ref target="#CH9-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref></q></p><p>Thus, Loudon sought a sense of balance, not a mirror imaging of parts, and his axes were not necessarily visible, but sometimes merely implied. With the axis of symmetry as an organizing principle, he arranged garden features and vegetation in various ways to produce a balanced effect.</p><p>Design harmony could also be achieved through congruity. Congruity meant respecting the character of the existing landscape as much as the abilities of the gardener, choosing local stones for boulders in rock gardens, placing water bodies in lowlying areas where they would naturally be found, banning sculpture and architecture of a purely associative nature, avoiding discordant juxtapositions in the arrangement of exotic plants, and developing zones of transition between distinctly different parts of the garden, as for instance the area between a smooth lawn and a rock garden.</p><figure xml:id="fig-383"><graphic url="CH9_011.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.10. Carpet bed, Kew Gardens. <date when="1870">1870</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Except in cases where the intent was a historicizing one, Victorian designers usually avoided straight lines. They were inspired by the curvaceous Rococo lines of Batty Langley The circle was a much favored form and one advocated by both Repton and Loudon. Planting beds were frequently mounded in order to eliminate difficulties in viewing them from a ground-level perspective and to display their intri<pb n="322"/><pb n="322" type="orig"/>cate carpetlike designs to better advantage (fig. 9.10).</p><p>But rules are made to be broken, and contrast, rather than congruity, was the aim in some cases. In the hands of Joseph Paxton, some startlingly imaginative effects were achieved through unexpected juxtapositions of the seemingly natural and the highly artificial. Though not a landscape theorist and social philosopher like Loudon and with a practical man's distrust of intellectuals, Paxton more than any other immediate successor developed Loudon's vision in wedding technology to horticulture by designing one of <name type="place">England</name>'s earliest municipally funded public parks, Liverpool's Birkenhead Park.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph Paxton</hi></hi></head><p>The life of <name type="pname">Joseph Paxton</name> (<date when="1801">1801</date>&#x2013;<date when="1865">1865</date>) illustrates how technological aptitude, design creativity, and energetic industriousness offered upward mobility in the increasingly prestigious field of horticulture. The son of a farmer, Paxton worked as a gardening hand in his youth before going to <name type="place">London</name> at the age of twenty. Employed in the Horticultural Society's demonstration garden at Chiswick, located on property leased from the sixth duke of Devonshire, he impressed the duke, a frequent visitor, with his intelligence and abilities. In <date when="1826">1826</date>, the duke offered him the position of head gardener at Chatsworth, his Derbyshire estate. The subsequent flowering of Paxton's genius, combined with the duke's largess, soon made Chatsworth a seat of horticultural renown. Ignoring Loudon's advice to restore the grounds&#x2014;a Capability Brown landscape with surviving seventeenthcentury features&#x2014;to a more naturalistic appearance, young Paxton set about repairing and improving the garden's original waterworks. He quickly met the challenge of reactivating the "Weeping Willow," an artificial tree and joke fountain that sprayed the unwary from eight hundred miniature jets of water. He did not, however, re-create the setting of the original as it appeared in the late seventeenth century, designing instead a woodland glen and rockworks as a naturalistic environment for this surprising hydrological feature. Paxton's mature landscape style continued to be characterized by the same independence from aesthetic theory and easy synthesis of artificial and natural.</p><figure xml:id="fig-384"><graphic url="CH9_012.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.11. Emperor Fountain, Chatsworth, Derbyshire, designed by Joseph Paxton. <date when="1843">1843</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>His on-site education in landscape design history occurred in the <date when="1830">1830</date>s as he accompanied the duke of Devonshire on tours of Versailles and other gardens near <name type="place">Paris</name>, the gardens of <name type="place">England</name>, and Italian villa gardens. Studying the waterworks in these places, he perfected his hydrological skills, becoming the foremost English fountain engineer of the day after the creation of the Emperor Fountain at Chatsworth&#x2014;then the world's tallest (fig. 9.11). In Paxton's fountain designs, technology and art were one. Unlike earlier fountains, these did not usually include sculpture; the rainbow effect of light-struck spray and the choreographic pattern of multiple dancing jets created interest enough for Paxton and his patrons. His reputation ultimately rested on an even more spectacular demonstration of technology's uses in the garden, for his Great Stove at Chatsworth, an enormous greenhouse, won him international renown. This huge conservatory was built between <date when="1836">1836</date> and <date when="1840">1840</date> following Loudon's ridge-and-furrow design principle but using wood instead of wrought iron for the framing of its glass panes.</p><p>Paxton's growing reputation put him in the front rank of landscape designers receiving commissions from two sources. The first was private developers who saw the relationship between communal pleasure grounds and the surrounding real estate in economic terms; the second was sanitary officials and humanitarians who saw the benefits of parks from public health and recreational perspectives. Nash's design for Regent's Park in <name type="place">London</name> had set a precedent for the former type of park development, and in <date when="1842">1842</date> a member of the Yates family, which had large landholdings in Liverpool, asked Paxton to come there to design Prince's Park, a speculative amenity that Yates hoped would make the adjacent house lots attractive to middle-class residents. Here Paxton created rows of terrace housing facing a curvilinear belt drive encircling a meadow with scattered clumps of trees and a serpentine lake (fig. 9.12).</p><p>Prince's Park remained in private ownership until <date when="1908">1908</date> and therefore was of little consequence in the growing parks movement as reformers in city after city, particularly in <name type="place">England</name>'s industrial Midlands, advocated "green lungs" within the swelling urban mass.<ref target="#CH9-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref>Paxton's next park, in Birkenhead on the opposite side of the Mersey River from Liverpool, was also undertaken with the hope of attracting members of<pb n="323"/><pb n="323" type="orig"/>the merchant class, but because of the circumstances of its creation, its accessibility to the general public, and the publicity that it received, it provided a far more influential model for future parks.</p><figure xml:id="fig-385"><graphic url="CH9_013.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.12. Plan for Prince's Park, Liverpool, designed by <name type="pname">Joseph Paxton</name>. c. <date when="1842">1842</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Municipalities had not yet been granted broad authority to acquire land, but citizen action to create public parks was nevertheless under way. In <date when="1842">1842</date>, a group of businessmen constituting Birkenhead's Improvement Commission lobbied for a parliamentary bill that would allow them to purchase 70 acres of land "for the Recreation of the inhabitants."<ref target="#CH9-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref>In the event, they purchased more than 200 acres, of which approximately 124 were designated parkland, with the remainder reserved for building sites. Although not, strictly speaking, the first public park, Birkenhead, which opened in <date when="1847">1847</date>, was the first to use public funds for parkland acquisition and development and to pay back this cost with the proceeds from the sale of the adjacent building lots. In addition, the municipality assumed responsibility for its maintenance, establishing the precedent of using for this purpose earned income derived from grazing rights and the auctioning of hay.</p><p>As at Prince's Park in nearby Liverpool, at Birkenhead Paxton arranged blocks of terraces around the sinuous loop of a circuit drive embracing a large meadow, the outlines of which were defined by scattered groups of trees. Here the meadow was bisected by a principal artery, Ashfield Road. Paxton placed an irregularly shaped lake in each half, and in order to make it impossible to see the boundaries of the entire shoreline in a single view, he introduced islands in the lakes. Their dredging spoil was used to construct rocky berms that varied the topography and restricted the view lines, thereby creating a more intimate lakeside environment. Further, Paxton designed an independent path system for strolling through this landscape separate from that of the macadamized circuit drive, which was intended for carriages.</p><p>From their inception, parks were popular venues for sports as well as places for leisurely strolling in scenic surroundings. This caused difficulty for landscape designers like Paxton, whose bias was to exploit the scenic potential of the site, as well as for administrators and park managers, who were often forced to modify original designs to accept a variety of play facilities and who had to write regulations and deal with the consequences of sports use on the landscape. Sponsors sometimes even gave the active recreational motive primacy. In the case of two parks planned and built simultaneously in Manchester in the <date when="1840">1840</date>s, Philips Park and Queen's Park, the entrants in the design competition had to include gymnasiums, grounds for archery, and alleys for skittles and quoits. Further, they were instructed to remember the <hi rend="italic">public</hi> nature of the commission and the need to accommodate large gatherings of promenaders. Refreshment rooms, numerous park benches, drinking fountains, and lodges for caretakers were also part of the design program. Ball-playing and shuttlecock<pb n="324"/><pb n="324" type="orig"/>grounds and playgrounds with rope swings were included in the final designs. By contrast, <name type="pname">James Pennethorne</name>, the original designer, and John Gibson, a former Paxton employee at Chatsworth and superintendent after <date when="1849">1849</date>, developed <name type="place">London</name>'s Victoria Park along scenic principles, using a rich palette of horticultural materials. But it, too, had to incorporate seesaws, climbing bars, and other play equipment and to permit, or at least tolerate, the use of its lakes for bathing, skating, boating, and dog washing.</p><figure xml:id="fig-386"><graphic url="CH9_014.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.13. Main entrance, Birkenhead Park, Liverpool, designed by Lewis Hornblower and John Robertson. <date when="1847">1847</date>. This gate is a Victorian version of a Roman triumphal arch with massively scaled Ionic columns commemorating not military victory but civic pride in the park's construction.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-387"><graphic url="CH9_015.jpg"/><figDesc>Below: 9.14. The Victoria Drinking Fountain, Victoria Park, <name type="place">London</name>. <date when="1862">1862</date>.</figDesc></figure><p>As at Stowe, Stourhead, and other eighteenthcentury models, the architects at Birkenhead incorporated historic English features and Palladian influences into the park's design vocabulary. Their versatility was apparent in their eclecticism, producing lodges in the castellated Gothic, Tudor, and Italian styles, in addition to the Greek Revival "Norman" ones set into the entrance gate (fig. 9.13). Here as elsewhere the influence of William Chambers lingered, and both Birkenhead and Victoria Parks had pagodas. Even as the popularity of pagodas faded, nineteenth-century building technology produced a cast-iron version, one example of which was shown at the <name type="place">Paris</name> and <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> Exhibitions of <date when="1876">1876</date> before being permanently installed at Chapel Field Gardens in Norwich.</p><p>The Turkish kiosk, combined with elements derived from the Chinese pagoda, furnished a distinctive architectural idiom for the bandstand made of wood or cast iron and set on a tall masonry base. This type of raised, open, ornamental pavilion became a feature of many parks. Musicians played mostly classical music, which was enthusiastically promoted by reformers as a civilizing influence and means of elevating mass culture, although Sabbatarians tried to proscribe concerts and other forms of recreation by having parks closed on Sundays. Temperance societies sponsored drinking fountains, and elaborate ones such as the Victoria Fountain in Victoria Park bore biblical and moral inscriptions implying the superiority of water over stronger drink (fig. 9.14).</p><p>As part of the reformers' agenda to wean the working class away from gin parlors, gaming, and other unedifying forms of recreation, sponsors deemed parks appropriate places for libraries and museums of art and natural history, and these were often combined with refreshment rooms. As more parks were created, commemorative monuments celebrating local benefactors, national leaders, and victory at war found a natural home amid their greenery, often serving as centerpieces of floral beds. Notables, royalty, and military heroes usurped the pedestals once graced by classical sculptures not only in <name type="place">England</name> where the parks movement originated, but elsewhere as it rapidly spread (see fig. 7.48). Public toilets, a much-debated amenity, were installed in several parks, and once this practice was established, manufacturers began to produce cast-iron urinals. Winter gardens, or palm houses, modeled on the one at Kew and Paxton's Crystal Palace, provided microclimates for the palms, bromeliads, and other tropical plants that drew swarms of nineteenth-century park patrons. These also served, to the dismay of superintendents, as warm places where the homeless sought shelter in cold weather.</p><p>The mid-nineteenth century ushered in an era of international expositions, at which the increasingly mobile and educated middle class enjoyed displays of scientific technology and industrial arts. Steam and rail transportation made these events accessible for large numbers of people and therefore financially feasible. Leading the parade was <name type="place">London</name>'s Great Exhi<pb n="325"/><pb n="325" type="orig"/>bition of <date when="1851">1851</date>, for which Paxton built the world's most modern exhibition hall, the Crystal Palace, in Hyde Park. As <name type="place">New York</name> attempted to emulate <name type="place">London</name> with a Crystal Palace of its own in <date when="1853">1853</date>, Paxton set about transferring his hugely popular building, for which he received a knighthood, to a new site in <name type="place">London</name> at Sydenham. Conceived as a refined version of the pleasure ground, with operating costs paid from admission fees, Crystal Palace Park showed a different side of Paxton the park designer from the one demonstrated at Birkenhead. Here, instead of treating the landscape in a naturalistic manner, he chose a plan of neo-Rococo geometric formality with a Picturesque fringe around the edges (fig. 9.15).</p><p>Paxton's place in landscape design history is an important one, linking the inventiveness, horticultural interest, and humanitarian social vision of Loudon with the growing parks movement in rapidly industrializing countries. With its republican government founded on the principle of social equality, <name type="place">America</name> was the ideal testing ground for municipal parks and other kinds of democratic institutions.</p><figure xml:id="fig-388"><graphic url="CH9_016.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.15. Crystal Palace Park, Sydenham, <name type="place">London</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Joseph Paxton</name>. <date when="1856">1856</date>. Watercolor by James Duffield Harding</hi></figDesc></figure></div></div><div type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Redefining Rural <name type="place">America</name>: The Influence of Andrew Jackson Downing</hi></hi></head><p>Much of the American landscape design vocabulary applied to parks and private estates in the early decades of the nineteenth century was derived from <name type="place">England</name>. There were, however, important differences in both the natural and the social climates of the two countries as well as the vastly disparate geographic scales of the island and the continental nation, one with a centuries-old habit of land husbandry and the other with a vast expanse of sparsely occupied prairie and woodland. These factors help account for the gradual evolution of an independent approach to landscape on the part of nineteenth-century AngloAmericans.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Botanical Discovery of America</hi></hi></head><p><name type="place">North America</name> remained a fertile ground for Britishbased botanical exploration during the first half of the nineteenth century. Thomas Nuttall (<date when="1786">1786</date>&#x2013;<date when="1859">1859</date>), a printer from Liverpool, immigrated to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> where he became interested in botany and plant collecting. Following the routes of fur traders and other explorers of the American wilderness, he traversed the northern region of the Missouri River between <date when="1810">1810</date> and <date when="1812">1812</date>. He published the results of his botanical labors in this region in <hi rend="italic">Genera of North American Plants</hi> in <date when="1818">1818</date> before turning south to collect plants in Arkansas. In <date when="1822">1822</date>, he accepted an appointment as curator of the botanical garden at Harvard and remained in this post until <date when="1834">1834</date>, finding it possible, however, in <date when="1833">1833</date> to join an expedition to the Rocky Mountains.</p><p>In <date when="1823">1823</date>, <name type="pname">David Douglas</name> (<date when="1798">1798</date>&#x2013;<date when="1834">1834</date>), a Scottish botanist trained by <name type="pname">William Jackson Hooker</name> at the University of Glasgow, visited Nuttall at <name type="pname">Harvard</name> and <name type="pname">William Bartram</name> in Philadephia under the sponsorship of the Horticultural Society of <name type="place">London</name>. The following year, under the aegis of the Hudson's Bay Company, he sailed to the West Coast, and at Fort Vancouver established a base of operations for his exploration of parts of Oregon and British Columbia. He spent the next three years in the evergreen forest that blanketed this region, discovering the Douglas fir <hi rend="italic">(Pseudotsuga menziesii)</hi> and many other coniferous and deciduous trees, flowering shrubs, and perennials. A return trip between <date when="1830">1830</date> and <date when="1834">1834</date> took him back and forth between <name type="place">California</name> and Hawaii, where he met his untimely death in the field.</p><p>American botanists as well as those in Britain and other European countries were eager recipients of the seeds and cuttings that came from these sources as well as from the plant hunters foraging in other parts of the globe. Bartram's Nurseries in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> continued to offer for sale species collected by an earlier generation of plant hunters represented by <name type="pname">John Bartram</name> and his son William as well as the new varieties explorers were introducing to horticulture. In <date when="1801">1801</date>, a <name type="place">New York</name> physician, <name type="pname">David Hosack</name>, established the Elgin Botanic Garden on the site of present-day Rockefeller Center, then the property of Columbia University. The garden was intended as a teaching resource for Columbia medical students since botany and its sister course, <hi rend="italic">materia medica,</hi> were still closely allied. It also contained a glasshouse for tender exotic plants, and many ornamental shrubs were prop<pb n="326"/><pb n="326" type="orig"/>agated there as well. <name type="pname">Thomas Jefferson</name> often sent Hosack some of the seeds he regularly received from the Jardin des Plantes in <name type="place">Paris</name>, and plant hunters such as <name type="pname">Franois Andr&#x00E9; Michaux</name> (<date when="1770">1770</date>&#x2014;<date when="1855">1855</date>) frequented the Elgin Botanic Garden. Unable to support its upkeep, Hosack closed the garden in <date when="1811">1811</date>, but he continued to collect plants at his Hyde Park, <name type="place">New York</name>, estate overlooking the Hudson River, where he employed the landscaping talents of Andr&#x00E9; Parmentier (<date when="1780">1780</date>&#x2013;<date when="1830">1830</date>), whose brothers were distinguished professional gardeners in Belgium.</p><p>Parmentier had emigrated to <name type="place">America</name> in <date when="1824">1824</date> to become a nurseryman in <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>. On a site overlooking <name type="place">New York</name> Harbor, he established an ornamental garden with rustic seats and arbors, which he called the Linnaean Botanic Garden, as a showcase for his own plant collection. Although, as we have seen, Jefferson and <name type="place">Washington</name> were both familiar with Picturesque principles of landscape design, Parmentier gained wide recognition as the originator of this style in <name type="place">America</name> when he published an article describing naturalistic gardening in the <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">New England</name> Farmer</hi> magazine. Andrew Jackson Downing, who amply earned his biographer's epithet, "apostle of taste,"<ref target="#CH9-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref> said that he considered "Parmentier's labors and examples as having effected, directly, far more for landscape gardening in <name type="place">America</name>, than those of any other individual whatever."<ref target="#CH9-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref> Downing, in turn, through his books and magazine indirectly effected far more change in landscape gardening in <name type="place">America</name> during the middle decades of the nineteenth century than any other individual.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Andrew Jackson Downing: Tastemaker for a Young Nation</hi></hi></head><p>The generation to which <name type="pname">Andrew Jackson Downing</name> (<date when="1815">1815</date>&#x2013;<date when="1852">1852</date>) belonged was astutely observed by his contemporary Alexis de Tocqueville (<date when="1805">1805</date>&#x2013;<date when="1859">1859</date>), who covered 7,000 miles of the settled and wilderness portions of the United States and <name type="place">Canada</name> by steamer and stagecoach and on horseback during a ninemonth period beginning in May <date when="1831">1831</date>. Tocqueville's <hi rend="italic">Democracy in America</hi> is much more than a traveler's description of the physical characteristics of the country with its settled colonial villages, burgeoning new cities, and frontier outposts. Although there are trenchant observations of all these things, his work is, as its title suggests, a political treatise. As such, it was not designed merely to limn the national character of the Americans as a simple narrative of their manners, mores, and economic circumstances would have done. Instead, its purpose was to foretell the consequences of the profound social transformation then in progress as the nations of Europe passed from aristocratic to democratic governance.</p><p>Downing had read the second volume of <hi rend="italic">Democracy in America</hi> as it rolled off the presses in <date when="1840">1840</date> His job, as he saw it, was to counter the restless instability of his fellow citizens that Tocqueville had noted with visions of home as a cherished domain and place of charm. He wished to educate their taste, which would then make manifest republican virtue in the nation's landscape. He hoped that through a new vision of domestic comfort and refinement the "moderate amount of happiness" available to all men in a democratic society might be attained. His idealistic prescriptions were overrun during the post&#x2014;Civil War transformation of American capitalist culture into something that more closely resembled the class stratification evident in the nations of Europe. But during his lifetime, he securely occupied the middle ground between Jefferson's Federalist generation&#x2014;whose democratic principles were compromised by patrician values&#x2014;and the generation of opulent materialistic display that gave the "villas" and "cottages" he promoted a new scale and meaning. Downing was, in short, a champion of the middle class, and he held a strong faith in the ability of education to raise people, if not to economic equality, at least to a sentimental equality in their appreciation and enjoyment of beauty.</p><p>Downing occupied the middle ground in a literal sense. Deploring both the rude, ax-scarred utilitarian landscapes that were a product of a frontier mentality and the cramped insalubrious atmosphere of the noisy commercial and industrial cities, he implied in his use of the word <hi rend="italic">rural</hi> the concept of the suburb. To the freestanding middle-class dwelling and its adjacent grounds, and even the humble workingclass dwelling with its surrounding small plot of land, Downing directed owners and landlords to pay the same prideful attention as that lavished by the wealthy on their country seats. He saw these homes, outside but accessible to urban centers by new means of transportation, as part of a larger, inherently Picturesque American landscape, and he believed that if his architectural and landscaping recommendations were followed, residents of this middle ground would be making a patriotic contribution to the nation's overall beauty while increasing their own personal comfort and enjoyment.</p><p>His congenial mind did not reckon that rural privacy might become retreat from community. A product of the American rural town, as a professional horticulturist and citizen, Downing promoted village beautification by tree planting. More important, he did not ignore the city. His reformer's cry, more ardent than any other's, championed the public park as the fundamental civilizing institution of American democracy in the <date when="1840">1840</date>s.</p><pb n="327"/><pb n="327" type="orig"/><p>Downing illustrated an aspect of American life shrewdly observed by Tocqueville: citizen initiative. There was no higher authority than the people in a democracy, so there were no <hi rend="italic">royal</hi> academies. Public libraries, colleges, lyceums, museums of art and natural history, botanical gardens, horticultural societies, rural cemeteries, and public parks&#x2014;all these educational and cultural institutions were founded by the vision of individuals, the action of community organizers, and the will of legislators who were elected by the people. Downing's role as citizen advocate and spokesman within this context was an especially important one.</p><p>Downing, the youngest son of a nurseryman in Newburgh, <name type="place">New York</name>, was a self-taught botanist and student of the Picturesque. After his marriage at age twenty-three to Caroline DeWint of Fishkill Landing, he designed and built a home on the family property in Newburgh (fig. 9.16). This house and its grounds epitomized the life of rural refinement he wished for all Americans of moderate affluence. It represented as well his belief that as <name type="place">America</name> came of age, its rootless, restlessly moving people should sink down roots, beautify their properties, and build communities that were more than commercial crossroads. Although similar to buildings in the "pointed" style recommended by Loudon, Downing's home had a particularly American feature&#x2014;the veranda, or piazza, as contemporaries called it&#x2014;which Downing promoted throughout his career in even his humblest samples of domestic architecture.</p><p>Thus situated, Downing could enjoy the commercial advantages of bustling Newburgh and the lively social intercourse made possible by the arrival at the town landing of friends traveling by river sloop and steamboat or at his door via train and carriage. He was within an easy three-hour train ride to <name type="place">New York</name> City, where he met with his publisher or conducted other business. At the same time, he could preserve the illusion of living in nature, never having to see town or road, only foliage-framed views of Hudson River scenery. In attempting to come to terms with the nineteenth-century phenomenon of rapid metropolitan growth, Downing was perhaps unwilling to admit the degree to which the agricultural economy of the young republic was being rapidly superseded by an industrial one. For this reason he used the word <hi rend="italic">rural</hi> to denote his vision of the <hi rend="italic">sub</hi>urban landscape that constituted the middle ground between city dwelling, with its noise, congestion, and extremes of wealth and poverty, and the equally unappealing alternative of hardscrabble farm life.</p><figure xml:id="fig-389"><graphic url="CH9_017.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.16. Residence of Andrew Jackson Downing in Newburgh, <name type="place">New York</name>, as it appeared shortly after it was built in <date when="1838">1838</date>&#x2013;39</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Downing's vision for a new American scenery to overlay the rough, agrarian landscape of frontier farms hacked from the wilderness was in the timehonored pastoral mode in which art and nature were held in perfect balance. He dreamed of an American Arcadia, for, like Thomas Jefferson, he saw the oppor<pb n="328"/><pb n="328" type="orig"/>tunities inherent in the country's immense and immensely fruitful natural landscape. Husbandry combined with taste could capitalize upon <name type="place">America</name>'s natural beauty, turning the countryside into a collage of Picturesque scenery. But opposing forces were at work, and the discordant aspects of the American dream&#x2014;the industrial smokestacks of the city and the train tracks running beside the river&#x2014;had to be screened from view, if the pastoral imagery of the garden were to appear intact. In nineteenth-century <name type="place">America</name>, as in <name type="place">England</name>, ambivalence about the Industrial Age was expressed by placing utilitarian technology and a highly eclectic architectural vocabulary of period styles within the same cultural embrace. Downing may have shared with others of his generation a sense of anxiety as the machinery of capitalism focused its energies on enterprises that would eventually destroy much of the picturesque character of aspiring rural towns, elm-canopied village greens, well-tended fields, and rich pastures fringed with woods. Nevertheless, as a reformer, a republican idealist, and a progressive Anglophile, he necessarily accepted both the democratic, technological future and the tradition-rooted, agrarian past. Whatever fears he may have harbored, he did not reveal them but optimistically projected a vision of universal betterment through the agency of good design.</p><figure xml:id="fig-390"><graphic url="CH9_018.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.17 and 9.18. "Example of the Beautiful in Landscape Gardening" and "Example of the Picturesque in Landscape Gardening," as portrayed in Andrew Jackson Downing's <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Theory and Practice of Landscape Gardening, Adapted to <name type="place">North America</name>,</hi> <date when="1841">1841</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>In <date when="1841">1841</date>, while still running his nursery business, Downing published his first major work, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on the Theory and Practice of Landscape Gardening.</hi> Its clear prose and conversational tone soon gained him widespread public recognition and reputation as a horticultural authority and tastemaker. The first sections of the book demonstrate the breadth of his reading, particularly of works by Loudon and Repton. His knowledge of such landscape theoreticians as Whately, Price, and Gilpin is apparent in the contrast he draws between the beautiful and the Picturesque. In the second edition of the <hi rend="italic">Treatise</hi> (<date when="1844">1844</date>), he had his engraver depict the beautiful, or "graceful" as he alternatively calls it, as a female-inhabited environment with gently curving paths, softly rounded tree forms, and gracious Neoclassical architectural details, while directing him to portray the Picturesque with spirelike conifers, steeply pitched eaves, and other signs of spirited irregularity, ruggedness, and angularity that presumably accord with the masculinity of the huntsman and his dog who complete the scene (figs. 9.17, 9.18).</p><p>The architecture compatible with the beautiful was "Italian, Tuscan, or Venetian," whereas builders in the Picturesque style had as appropriate models "the Gothic mansion, the old English or the Swiss cottage" and were free to incorporate in their schemes various rustic features. Downing reiterated Repton's three underlying principles of good design&#x2014;"UNITY, HARMONY, AND VARIETY"&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">unity</hi> being a controlling idea based on the nature of the site and "some grand or leading features to which the others should be merely subordinate,"<ref target="#CH9-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref><hi rend="italic">variety</hi> the development of spectator interest through intricacy and ornamental details, and <hi rend="italic">harmony</hi> the principle that ordered variety and made it subservient to the overall unity of the composition. Further, he tempered picturesqueness with practicality, declaring that "[f]irm gravel walks near the house, and a general air of neatness in that quarter, are indispensable to the fitness of the scene in all modes."<ref target="#CH9-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref>Concurring with Loudon, he maintained that "the <hi rend="italic">recognition of art"</hi> was "a first principle of Landscape Gardening . . . and those of its professors have erred, who supposed that the object of this art is merely to produce a fac-simile of nature."<ref target="#CH9-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref></p><pb n="329"/><pb n="329" type="orig"/><p>A large section of the <hi rend="italic">Treatise</hi> comprises a descriptive catalogue of deciduous and evergreen ornamental trees. Here Downing does more than display his impressive store of botanical knowledge, dwelling upon aesthetic, rather than scientific, characteristics such as "the lights and shadows reflected and embosomed in [the oak's] foliage" and the "pleasing richness and intricacy in its huge ramification of branch and limb"<ref target="#CH9-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref>in the manner of Gilpin, whose works he had studied well.</p><p>In <date when="1846">1846</date>, when Luther Tucker of <name type="place">Albany</name> invited Downing to become editor of <hi rend="italic">The Horticulturist,</hi> this new journal of "Rural Art and Rural Taste," Downing gained a platform for his expanding ideas. Here, in an editorial he wrote each month, he propounded his landscape theories; shared observations gleaned from his travels; gave advice on rural architecture, transplanting trees, growing hedges, enriching soil, manuring orchards, improving vegetables, and producing wine; mingled poetry and instruction in a rhapsody on roses; provided detailed instruction on the building of greenhouses and ice houses; argued the case&#x2014;exercise, fresh air, health&#x2014;for women to garden; and sermonized on the mistakes of city folk new to country life&#x2014;all in a conversational voice and anecdotal style that endeared him to his readers. <hi rend="italic">The Horticulturist</hi> reached a large audience. In it he promoted the planting of shade trees in villages, towns, and cities; lobbied for an agricultural college in <name type="place">New York</name> State; and drew the attentions of his fellow citizens to such public parks as Munich's Englischer Garten.</p><p>In his column of <date when="1851-08">August 1851</date>, Downing warmed to the subject of a mayoral proposal for a 160-acre park in <name type="place">New York</name>, arguing that the city had "until lately, contented itself with the little door-yards of space&#x2014;mere grass-plats of verdure" and concluding that a park of even 160 acres was too small, that at least 500 acres were needed to serve the city's fast-growing population, which then stood at half a million. His vision for the new park was equally bold in its outlines. Not only would it have carriage drives, bridle trails, secluded walks, and "a real feeling of the breadth and beauty of green fields," but it would also be a place for commemorative statues, a winter garden like the Crystal Palace "where the whole people could luxuriate in groves of the palms and spice trees of the tropics, at the same moment that sleighing parties glided swiftly and noiselessly over the snowcovered surface of the country-like avenues of the wintry park without." Zoological gardens would also find a home there, as would spacious buildings for expositions of the arts. Above all, Downing extolled the social implications of the proposal. The park would be a republican institution, "a broad ground of popular refinement," raising "the working-man to the same level of enjoyment with the man of leisure and accomplishment."<ref target="#CH9-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref></p><p>The summer before, Downing had gone to <name type="place">England</name>, delighted that his reputation had preceded him and that he was welcome at Chatsworth and many other great estates. His purpose in traveling there was not merely to tour the English countryside and visit the Royal Botanic Gardens at Kew. In <hi rend="italic">The Horticulturist</hi> and in the books that followed his <hi rend="italic">Treatise&#x2014;Cottage Residences</hi> (<date when="1842">1842</date>), <hi rend="italic">Fruits and Fruit Trees of <name type="place">America</name></hi> (<date when="1845">1845</date>), and <hi rend="italic">The Architecture of Country Houses</hi> (<date when="1850">1850</date>)&#x2014;architectural illustrations played an important role. He had sold his nursery business as his focus centered more and more upon the literary efforts that were turning him into a tastemaker to the nation. The people who now sought him out wanted plans as well as advice, and with these prospective clients in mind and having failed to interest the American architect <name type="pname">Alexander Jackson Davis</name> (<date when="1803">1803</date>&#x2013;<date when="1892">1892</date>) in entering into a professional partnership with him, he wished to find a young English architect with whom he could open a design firm. In <name type="place">London</name>, he observed the drawings of Calvert Vaux at an exhibition of the Architectural Association and asked to meet him. The immediate impression of both men was such that a week later Vaux had wound up his affairs in <name type="place">England</name>, said good-bye to friends, and boarded ship for <name type="place">New York</name> with Downing.</p><p>The new firm immediately began to receive commissions, including one from the brewer Matthew Vassar to improve the grounds of his 40acre farm, Springside, near Poughkeepsie, <name type="place">New York</name>. There was a subsequent important commission from Daniel Parish to build a "marine villa" in <name type="place">Newport</name>, <name type="place">Rhode Island</name>, and other domestic projects. In the Newburgh office, which Downing and Vaux built as an addition to the Downing residence, Vaux translated the Gothic Revival style he had learned in <name type="place">England</name> into a more distinctly American idiom, often using board-and-batten construction and wooden verge boards and designing deeply hooded windows, covered entrance porches, and broad verandas. From Downing he must have also learned to appreciate the Picturesque possibilities of the American landscape.</p><p>In the fall following the return of the two men from <name type="place">England</name>, Downing was invited by President Millard Fillmore to prepare a plan for the improvement of the public grounds around the Capitol in <name type="place">Washington</name>, where L'Enfant's intentions for a grand avenue had never materialized. Downing eagerly seized this commission as an opportunity to demonstrate the first <hi rend="italic">"real</hi> park in the United States."<ref target="#CH9-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref> Although vexed by congressional infighting, the project received initial funding. On the L-shaped site encompassing the<pb n="330"/><pb n="330" type="orig"/>present-day Mall and grounds of the White House, Downing developed an extensive pleasure ground and botanical showcase, a series of six Picturesque and Gardenesque episodes linked by curvilinear carriage drives and paths. Directly behind the White House, the plan called for a President's Park, entered through a marble triumphal arch. Also called the Parade, this was where various public and military functions would take place. Surrounding the <name type="place">Washington</name> Monument, still in construction, Downing envisioned a meadowlike park of American specimen trees and grass. The Tiber Canal flowed between these two parks. The plan proposes to connect them by means of a suspension bridge. It also calls for an Evergreen Garden, a showcase for such nondeciduous species as rhododendrons, laurels, and magnolias. Smithsonian Park is a naturalistic campuslike space, with evergreens complementing <name type="pname">James Renwick</name>'s neomedieval building. To the east, is Fountain Park containing both a fountain and a small artificial lake.</p><p>In <date when="1852">1852</date>, Downing was commuting to <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, on a monthly basis when his life was suddenly cut short as the <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Henry Clay</name>,</hi> a Hudson River steamboat on which he was traveling, caught fire, causing the passengers to jump overboard and many, including him, to drown. Without his periodic on-site supervision and advocacy of the plan's construction, party politics, exacerbated by the impending crisis of the Civil War, mired the project.</p><p>Extensively eulogized, Downing nevertheless died encumbered with debt. The house he had built&#x2014;for fourteen years a center of hospitable friendship, his office, and a manifestation of the Picturesque and Gardenesque taste he advocated&#x2014;had been mortgaged and was soon sold. His books, however, continued to be published into the twentieth century, and the editorials he had written for <hi rend="italic">The Horticulturist</hi> were collected in a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Rural Essays,</hi> which also enjoyed wide readership.</p><p>Downing's position in landscape history is a pivotal one. He was both an imitator of the styles developed by Repton and Loudon and an innovator, translating their Picturesque vocabulary, particularly in architecture, into a new American idiom. But his influence was more as an "apostle of taste" than as a designer, rhetorically setting the course that others would follow. The term <hi rend="italic">landscape architect</hi> had not yet been adopted by Calvert Vaux and Vaux's future partner, Frederick Law Olmsted as a professional tide.<ref target="#CH9-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref> Neither of these men ever forgot his debt to Downing as together they forged a landscape style in which broad passages of pastoral and woodland scenery gave the beautiful and the picturesque a more thoroughly American dimension than had Downing's transitional style with its Loudon-derived emphasis on horticulture and architecture. The park that they designed for <name type="place">New York</name> was essentially different from the image Downing had painted for his readers in his essay in <hi rend="italic">The Horticulturist,</hi> but his prescience in promoting it as a vital democratic institution was one that they fully embraced as they in turn developed a new vision for the nineteenth-century city.</p></div></div><div type="section"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">III. Honoring History and Repose foR the Dead: Commemorative Landscapes and Rural Cemeteries</hi></hi></head><p>The taste that Downing had promoted and the humanitarian consciousness he had displayed in championing the public park were, as we have seen, manifestations of the cultural shift that Tocqueville observed not only in his own country and the United States where there had been revolutions abolishing rule by monarchy, but also throughout Europe where court-dominated aristocratic culture was being superseded by more broadly based, egalitarian forms of governance. Socially conscious tastemakers such as Loudon and Downing were important precisely because the city itself was becoming a far-flung middle-class institution. As <name type="place">London</name> had already demonstrated a century earlier, the city and the private estates that were its rural outposts, not the court, determined culture, and the bourgeoisie who were now primary cultural consumers welcomed the reformers' advice that refined them and elevated them above those less fortunate.</p><p>Although <name type="place">Italy</name> and <name type="place">Germany</name> were slow to become unified states, the trend toward nationalism had been set in motion, and bonds of cultural commonalty among their respective principalities, dukedoms, and city-states were reinforced through language, art, trade, and travel as well as by military alliance. The growth in nationalistic spirit paralleled the growth in importance and size of urban centers. With the diminution of the power of kingship, of the prestige of the Church, and of the wealth of aristocracy, the monuments that had once broadcast the supremacy of these institutions lost meaning. As societies rebuilt themselves along more democratic and sectarian lines, they felt compelled to create images of <hi rend="italic">constitutional</hi> monarchs, revolutionary heroes, and the honored dead as icons of national status and civic pride, replacing older monuments of kings and religious figures.</p><div type="subsection"><pb n="331"/><pb n="331" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Commemorative Landscape</hi></hi></head><p>Commemorating national heroes assumed importance as nineteenth-century nations sought to institutionalize recently formed governments or cloak their military adventures abroad in a mantle of imperial glory by celebrating them in a public and permanent manner. This patriotic agenda called for the renaming of important urban places and the erection of monuments within them. For this reason, in <date when="1841">1841</date>, the English raised a 185-foot high column by <name type="pname">William Railton</name> in <name type="place">London</name>'s Trafalgar Square to honor <name type="pname">Admiral Horatio Nelson</name>, the hero of the <date when="1805">1805</date> Battle of Trafalgar. In a similar fashion, the French commemorated Napoleon's campaigns of <date when="1805">1805</date>&#x2013;<date when="1805">1805</date> with a basrelief column modeled after Emperor Trajan's column in <name type="place">Rome</name>. It was erected in <name type="place">Paris</name> in the Place Vendme, formerly the Place Royale, where the equestrian statue of Louis XIV had long since been toppled by a revolutionary mob (fig. 9.19).</p><p>In <name type="place">Germany</name>, as we have seen, the <hi rend="italic">Volksgarten</hi> was an expression of cultural pride, and the sculptures there were intended to foster patriotic sentiment. We have noted as well how <name type="pname">Rousseau</name>'s remains, at first entombed on the estate of an <hi rend="italic">ancien r&#x00E9;gime</hi> liberal aristocrat, were removed to the Church of Saint Genevi&#x00E8;ve, which was deconsecrated and rechristened the Panth&#x00E9;on when it became a hall of fame for French national heroes. Many objected to the transfer of the great man's bones to the Panth&#x00E9;on in <name type="place">Paris</name>, preferring instead the notion of pilgrimage to the tomb designed for him by Hubert Robert on the Isle of Poplars at Ermenonville (see fig. 7.36). The Enlightenment had bred a new secular spirit, and the French Revolution had seriously undermined the authority of the Catholic Church, making rural, rather than churchyard, burial an appealing alternative, especially given the Romantic sentimentalism of the day in which many found in deified Nature a spiritual substitute for Church dogma.<ref target="#CH9-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> In the same spirit as that of the Europeans who turned the grave site at Ermenonville into a shrine and even replicated <name type="pname">Rousseau</name>'s tomb in numerous other Picturesque gardens, Americans patriotically sought remembrance of George <name type="place">Washington</name>. Many made pilgrimages to his rural tomb at Mount Vernon (fig. 9.20). Citizens in both <name type="place">Baltimore</name> and <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, commissioned <name type="pname">Robert Mills</name> (<date when="1781">1781</date>&#x2013;<date when="1855">1855</date>) to design impressive monuments in <name type="place">Washington</name>'s memory (fig. 9.21).</p><figure xml:id="fig-391"><graphic url="CH9_019.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.19. Napoleonic Victory Column, Place V&#x00EA;ndome, <name type="place">Paris</name>, constructed by Denon, Gonduin, and Lep&#x00E8;re. <date when="1806">1806</date>&#x2013;10</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-392"><graphic url="CH9_020.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below left:</hi> 9.20. <name type="pname">George</name> <name type="place">Washington</name>'s grave as redesigned in the Gothic revival style by <name type="pname">William Yeaton</name> in <date when="1835">1835</date>. Engraving by W.Woodruff, c. <date when="1839">1839</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-393"><graphic url="CH9_021.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below right:</hi> 9.21. <name type="place">Washington</name> Monument in <name type="place">Baltimore</name>, designed by Robert Mills, who also designed the <name type="place">Washington</name> Monument in <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name> <date when="1829">1829</date>. Engraving by <name type="pname">W. H. Bartlett</name>, <date when="1835">1835</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Although the Federalist generation in <name type="place">America</name> had eschewed large-scale public works because of their cost and association with European authoritarian pomp, which they felt to be inappropriate in a republic, the generation that prospered in the first decades of the nineteenth century sought to employ its wealth for public ends, ennobling their country's brief history with public monuments to the Revolution that had turned former colonies into a nation. In <name type="place">Boston</name>, Henry Dearborn, a notably public-spirited citizen and the first president of the <name type="place">Massachusetts</name> Horticultural Society, formed the Bunker Hill Mon<pb n="332"/><pb n="332" type="orig"/>ument Association, which led to a subscription campaign to purchase the Revolutionary War battlefield site and underwrite "a simple, majestic, lofty, and permanent monument,"<ref target="#CH9-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref>an obelisk of Quincy granite, which was erected between <date when="1825">1825</date> and <date when="1843">1843</date> (fig. 9.22).<ref target="#CH9-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref>No small amount of municipal and state rivalry was involved as <name type="place">Boston</name> competed with <name type="place">Baltimore</name>, the southern city that had assumed the lead in the race for monumental magnificence by adding to its landscape&#x2014;already adorned with Mills's <name type="place">Washington</name> Monument&#x2014;Maximilien Godefroy's <date when="1835">1835</date> Battle Monument, a column resting on a pyramidal Egyptian Revival base and topped with a statue of a female figure symbolizing the city (fig. 9.23).</p><figure xml:id="fig-394"><graphic url="CH9_022.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.22. Bird's-eye view of <name type="place">Boston</name> by <name type="pname">John Bachman</name>. <date when="1850">1850</date>, with Bunker Hill Monument near the left edge of the lithograph. The domed building to the left of center is Charles Bulfinch's State House on Beacon Hill of <date when="1795">1795</date>. The process of filling in the Back Bay has begun, and the city's aspirations to elegance are apparent in the planting of trees lining the paths and perimeter of the Common and in the artist's projection of an ornamental landscape on the ground reserved for the Public Garden, which was not built until <date when="1857">1857</date>.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-395"><graphic url="CH9_023.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 9.23. <name type="place">Baltimore</name> Battle monument, by Maximilien Godefroy. <date when="1835">1835</date>. Engraving by W. H. Bartlett</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-396"><graphic url="CH9_024.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.24. Mourning picture for Captain <name type="pname">John Williams</name>, aged 36 (d. <date when="1825-04-01">April 1, 1825</date>). Pen and watercolor drawing by an anonymous artist</hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Birth of the Rural Cemetery</hi></hi></head><p>The waning of ecclesiastical authority and the growth of Romantic sentiment among a rapidly broadening middle class brought new attitudes toward death and the desire to commemorate upstanding community members and loved ones as well as heroes. Added to this cultural imperative was the public health motive, about which there was much debate, for the crowding that accompanied population increases in nineteenth-century cities was noticeable not only in the festering urban slums, but also in the churchyard cemeteries that were filled to capacity so that corpses were periodically exhumed to make room for new ones. The resulting stench of putrefying flesh caused passersby to hold their noses as physicians argued inconclusively over whether "miasmas" from decaying animal matter bred disease.</p><p>The notion of a permanent resting place where the dead could be visited by the living and remembered individually did not accord with either Catholic or Calvinist belief. Both held that mortal flesh, even in life, was corrupt and an encumbrance to the spirit, which, freed of mortality, could join God. Viewed in this light, the collective sight of the dead served as a reminder of the transitory nature of earthly life and a warning against vanity and pride. The equation of the afterlife with an Edenic gardenlike paradise did not figure in pre-nineteenth-century Western theology, and tree planting in cemeteries was considered an encouragement of latent tendencies toward pantheism, which priests and ministers wanted to stamp out. Not the living tree but the death mask was depicted on Puritan tombstones in <name type="place">New England</name> graveyards: this <hi rend="italic">memento mori</hi> was meant to discourage worldly ambition and individualism. Only with the decline of Puritanism did the symbolism of vegetative endurance and cyclical rebirth manifest itself in the substitution of the sweetly melancholy willow-tree-and-urn motif, also found in mourning pictures, for the death mask on some slab gravestones (fig. 9.24).</p><p>The creation of the extramural "rural" cemetery demanded a significant change in societal values involving the secularization of death and the granting of dignity to the individual life as well as the right to associative sentiment on the part of families and friends. In the aftermath of <name type="place">London</name>'s Great Fire of <date when="1666">1666</date>, both John Evelyn and Christopher Wren had urged the discontinuance of churchyard burial, and the eighteenth-century Whig garden, replete with emblems of commemoration, offered an important prototype for the cemetery amid shady groves. Wordsworth's Romantic poetry evoked a mood of elegiac remembrance in images of country graveyards, while in a prose essay he instructed that "when<pb n="333"/><pb n="333" type="orig"/>death is in our thoughts, nothing can make amends for the want of the soothing influences of nature, and for the absence of those types of renovation and decay, which the fields and woods offer to the notice of the serious and contemplative mind."<ref target="#CH9-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref></p><p>It was not in <name type="place">England</name> but in <name type="place">France</name>, however, that the first metropolitan rural cemetery came into being. There, the post-Revolutionary invention of new institutions to replace discredited old ones and the growing fashion (initiated by Rousseau's tomb at Ermenonville) for memorials set in nature provided the impetus for a change in burial customs. In addition, new scientific theories of photosynthesis supported the practice of tree planting as conducive to urban health, and people began to desire the sight of cemeteries with grass lawns rather than bare earth. Historic preservation also played a role in those turbulent times when many royal monuments had been recently removed from churches and public places. Preservationists such as Antoine-Chrysostome Quatrem&#x00E8;re de Quincy argued for incorporating the salvage into cemeteries as proud relics of French cultural heritage. In <date when="1796">1796</date>, the National Institute of Sciences and Arts called for papers on new customs and sites for burying the dead. In his prizewinning essay, the classical scholar Amaury Duval evoked the custom of antiquity as precedent for extramural burial, for in ancient Athens burial of notables took place in the Kerameikos, the pottery-making district outside the Dipylon Gate, and in ancient <name type="place">Rome</name> the dead of prominent families were laid to rest in tombs along the Appian Way. He declared that for himself, he wished a grave in nature like Rousseau's.</p><p>The argument was echoed by others. There were proposals for the burial on private property of those, such as farmers, who owned land, and for those who did not, the authorities were encouraged to set aside dignified public burial grounds outside the city where family tombs would receive the remains of the departed, which would no longer be placed anonymously in common graves. In <date when="1801">1801</date>, legislation was passed authorizing the communes of <name type="place">France</name> to purchase land outside their boundaries for public cemeteries, and two years later the Department of the Seine created the first one on a high escarpment near the eastern edge of <name type="place">Paris</name>. Known as the Cemetery of the East but called P&#x00E8;re-Lachaise after the Jesuit priest P&#x00E8;re Franois de La Chaise, Louix XIV's confessor, who had once owned the land, it was laid out according to a plan developed by the architect AlexandreTh&#x00E9;odore Brongniart (<date when="1739">1739</date>&#x2013;<date when="1813">1813</date>) in a manner that combined axial geometry and monumental focal points with the picturesqueness of a serpentine circuit path and naturalistic plantings. A central <hi rend="italic">tapis vert</hi> led the visitor to the site of a chapel, designed as an Egyptian pyramid, which was never built because work was halted by the Napoleonic wars. To the left of this greensward axis were the plots reserved as grave sites for the masses, where five-year and tenyear leaseholds replaced the common burial pits of former times. On the higher terrain was institutionalized the concept of freehold ownership in perpetuity for families who wished to purchase plots.</p><figure xml:id="fig-397"><graphic url="CH9_025.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.25 and 9.26. P&#x00E8;re-Lachaise Cemetery</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-398"><graphic url="CH9_026.jpg"/></figure><p>Although common folk immediately began to bury their dead in the leasehold area, the sale of the perpetual plots was slow at first, gathering momentum after monuments purporting to be the tombs of <name type="pname">Ab&#x00E9;lard</name> and <name type="pname">H&#x00E9;loise</name>, <name type="pname">Moli&#x00E8;re</name>, and <name type="pname">La Fontaine</name> were installed and then joined by the actual ones of such contemporary celebrities as <name type="pname">Fr&#x00E9;d&#x00E9;ric Chopin</name>. Civic pride rose with the burial of other cultural and political heroes, and by the <date when="1820">1820</date>s, as they laid departed family members to rest, many denizens of the fashionable world sought the services of the funerary architects, stonecutters, iron-fence makers, and florists who had set up shop nearby. Mausoleums occupying entire plots soon gave P&#x00E8;re-Lachaise the appearance of a miniature city of handsome stone dwellings, rather than that of a pastoral landscape of memory, as it was intended to be. Nevertheless, because of the famous names on many of the tombs and in spite of its overbuilt appearance, P&#x00E8;re-Lachaise continues to be both a mecca for tourists and a tranquil refuge for contemporary Parisians (figs. 9.25, 9.26).</p><pb n="334"/><pb n="334" type="orig"/><p>Americans, like the French at this time, were developing civic institutions that accorded with their republican ideals. They, too, wanted to create cemeteries that honored their brief national history, dignified the dead, and consoled the living. Their means of achieving this end was not by government decree as in <name type="place">France</name> but, in a tradition Tocqueville recognized, through voluntary associations of citizen-reformers, who in this case developed a vision, enlisted support, formed a corporation, and sold burial plots.</p><p>Many people at the time resisted the placement of the dead outside town boundaries, inasmuch as maurading wolves were a still-recent menace and burial within insecure extramural precincts would facilitate the work of "resurrection men" who harvested corpses for medical dissection. However, as early as <date when="1796">1796</date>, <name type="pname">James Hillhouse</name> persuaded his fellow citizens to subscribe to a burial ground on Grove Street immediately north of <name type="place">New Haven</name>'s original ninesquare grid. Connecticut passed legislation establishing the first private corporation in <name type="place">America</name> for that purpose, and under Hillhouse's direction, poplars were planted and freehold plots sold in perpetuity. Unlike the rural cemeteries that followed a generation later, the New Burying Ground in <name type="place">New Haven</name> was remarkable for the precedent it set rather than for its design, which was, like the rest of the town, a straightforward grid plan offering convenient circulation for hearses and visiting families but little in the way of Romantic picturesqueness.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Mount Auburn Cemetery</hi></hi></head><p>Such was not the case in <name type="place">Boston</name>, where the builders of Mount Auburn Cemetery exploited the potential of a naturally picturesque site across the Charles River on the border between <name type="place">Cambridge</name> and Watertown. Here again, an energetic and visionary individual spearheaded the citizen effort responsible for launching the cemetery project in <date when="1825">1825</date>. Botanist, physician, and community leader Dr. <name type="pname">Jacob Bigelow</name> interested the <name type="place">Massachusetts</name> Horticultural Society in sponsoring the project. Earlier, Mayor Josiah Quincy had been a vocal proponent of a public cemetery somewhere on the outskirts of the city, but it took Bigelow's advocacy of the cause, combined with the enthusiastic participation of Henry Dearborn, the president of the <name type="place">Massachusetts</name> Horticultural Society, to bring the concept to fruition.</p><p>The cultural climate of <name type="place">Boston</name> provided strong impetus to the cemetery movement in <name type="place">America</name>. There patriotic sentiment was strong, voluntary associations numerous, and religion liberalized through the agency of the Unitarian pulpit. <name type="place">Boston</name> was, moreover, within the intellectual orbit of Concord where Thoreau and Emerson projected the philosophy of transcendentalism and preached as well as practiced communion with nature. The American poet William Cullen Bryant (<date when="1794">1794</date>&#x2013;<date when="1878">1878</date>), along with Wordsworth, touched a responsive chord in the breasts of New Englanders such as Bigelow and Dearborn, for whom the word <hi rend="italic">sentimental</hi> denoted the manly emotion of remembrance with pleasurable melancholy, not maudlin excess, in a period when many fathers mourned the death of young wives and children. Bryant's most famous poem, "Thanatopsis" (<date when="1817">1817</date>), gave voice to Bigelow's medically and horticulturally informed opinion that the rapid dissolution of the uncoffined body laid to rest in nature constituted a sweet surrender of individual existence. At the same time, memory of the individual life lived within the bosom of family and community would be honored in epitaphs inscribed on monuments, and these would inspire others to lives of goodness and achievement.</p><p>The site for the new cemetery was secured in <date when="1830">1830</date> when another proponent, <name type="pname">George Watson Brimmer</name>, sold to the <name type="place">Massachusetts</name> Horticultural Society a particularly beautiful piece of property consisting of 72 acres of heavily wooded, hilly terrain, the characteristic <name type="place">New England</name> landscape of drumlins&#x2014; ridges deposited by successive epochs of glaciation &#x2014;and bogs, and ponds left in the wake of the retreating ice. Poetically inclined Harvard students, who liked to frequent this naturally picturesque spot of bosky dells, grassy knolls, and an abandoned colonial farmstead, called it Sweet Auburn after a vanished English hamlet destroyed by the enclosure movement, which Oliver Goldsmith had lamented in his poem "The Deserted Village" (<date when="1770">1770</date>). Like P&#x00E8;re Lachaise, it had a high point or mount from which a panoramic prospect unfolded&#x2014;hence Mount Auburn&#x2014;but unlike the French cemetery where there was no stream or pond, it had a deep enfolding small valley into which water gushed and pooled. The tide of sentiment ran high as Joseph Story, associate justice of the United States Supreme Court, delivered his consecration oration to an estimated audience of two to three thousand Bostonians gathered in this natural amphitheater on <date when="1831-09-24">September 24, 1831</date>.</p><p>For the next three years, the society's president, Dearborn, masterminded the project, serving as the cemetery's landscape designer. Like others of his generation, Dearborn was a man of multiple talents and capable of practicing them at a professional level. To ready himself for the task at hand, he sent to <name type="place">London</name> and <name type="place">Paris</name> for books and engravings dealing with landscape theory and design, including an account of the creation of P&#x00E8;re-Lachaise, which he translated for the benefit of his fellow citizens. He also steeped himself in the works of Repton and Price as he thought about<pb n="335"/><pb n="335" type="orig"/>how to turn the naturally Picturesque cemetery site into both a commemorative landscape and an experimental garden. This horticultural component was integral to his broad vision, as was the notion of creating a studio school on the premises for the instruction of professional landscape designers.</p><p>The author of a two-volume treatise on Greek architecture, Dearborn now sought to develop siting opportunities for the monuments that would make Mount Auburn an American version of Stowe or Stourhead (see Chapter Seven). His plan provided a circulation system that looped around the hilly topography in parabolic curves, providing efficient access for hearses to all parts of the grounds and, supplemented by additional paths, a means of strolling through the delectable scenery (fig. 9.27).</p><p>Although the two men never admitted a breach, a rift between Dearborn's and Bigelow's supporters was soon apparent. The horticultural faction sided with Dearborn's more inclusive vision of Mount Auburn as a broad-based landscape institution, with an active program of practical instruction like that of the <name type="place">London</name> Horticultural Society where Paxton had apprenticed, while others supported Bigelow's more focused one of a cemetery alone. This resulted in an official separation in <date when="1834">1834</date>, with the reincorporation of the Cemetery Proprietors of Mount Auburn as an independent entity.<ref target="#CH9-n20"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref> As head of the trustees of the ten-member board governing Mount Auburn, Bigelow exerted a strong influence on the rules and regulations governing the cemetery's administration and visitation policies, at the same time exercising his considerable talents as an architect by designing several of its monuments.</p><p>Policy forbade slab tombstones like those found in the old <name type="place">New England</name> churchyards where the forebears of the Mount Auburn trustees were buried. Bigelow and others looked to Classical Greece and ancient <name type="place">Egypt</name> for a symbolism that reflected the liberal Unitarian and Universalist spirit preaching salvation for all and the heavenly reunion of families, which now prevailed over the stern philosophy of Calvinist predestination whereby only a tiny minority&#x2014;the elect&#x2014;were deemed eligible for reward after death. The obelisk, appropriated by ancient <name type="place">Rome</name> as a trophy of conquest and converted by Renaissance city planners and garden builders into a widely copied landscape feature, connoted both timelessness and the death-embracing culture of ancient <name type="place">Egypt</name>. Somewhat miniaturized, obelisks were frequently employed in eighteenth-century English gardens as memorials to cultural and political heroes. Just as an obelisk memorialized George <name type="place">Washington</name>, now scaled-down versions in white marble marked the resting place of prominent <name type="place">Boston</name> families who purchased plots in Mount Auburn. In addition, Bigelow used a pair of obelisks decoratively to frame the imposing neoEgyptian style gate he designed for entrance to Mount Auburn, which bore the inscription: "Then shall the Dust return to the Earth as it was, and the Spirit shall return unto God who gave it"<ref target="#CH9-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">21</hi></hi></ref> (fig. 9.28). Pillars and pedestals surmounted by urns and sarcophagi resembling Rousseau's tomb were also popular among the first proprietors (fig. 9.29).</p><figure xml:id="fig-399"><graphic url="CH9_027.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.27. Plan of Mount Auburn Cemetery, <name type="place">Cambridge</name>, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>, designed by Jacob Bigelow. <date when="1831">1831</date>. Engraving by <name type="pname">James Smillie</name>, from <name type="pname">J.</name> and <name type="pname">C. Smillie</name>, <hi rend="italic">Mount Auburn Illustrated,</hi><date when="1851">1851</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-400"><graphic url="CH9_028.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.28. Entrance to Mount Auburn Cemetery. Engraving by <name type="pname">James Smillie</name>. from <name type="pname">J.</name> and <name type="pname">C. Smillie</name>, <hi rend="italic">Mount Auburn Illustrated,</hi> <date when="1851">1851</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>In James Smillie's <date when="1847">1847</date> engravings, the white marble monuments that had superseded the Puritans' gray slate tombstones gleam brightly against the dark foliage in the still heavily forested cemetery (fig. 9.30). Within the romantically Picturesque landscape, they act as poetic accents. The atmosphere of<pb n="336"/><pb n="336" type="orig"/>a forest glen is intentional. In the early years of the cemetery's existence, in keeping with the founders desires to retain as much as possible the inherent charms of the site, maintenance was limited to keeping gravel paths accessible; only in the second half of the nineteenth century did the cemetery assume a parklike aspect. Also evident is Mount Auburn's intended function as a didactic landscape, a place of moral instruction, for the engravings show parents with young children in tow as well as solitary figures meditating in its sweetly melancholy gloom. The cemetery's purpose as a contemplative landscape was underlined by the publication of visitors' guides with brief, inspiring biographies of the distinguished dead. In spite of its role in expressing community values and community pride, the plots were private property, and the proprietors not only erected monuments&#x2014;often in anticipation of their deaths&#x2014;to function as future genealogies in stone, but they also fenced their places of perpetual rest with handsome cast-iron fences.</p><figure xml:id="fig-401"><graphic url="CH9_029.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.29. View of Harvard Hill, Mount Auburn Cemetery. Engraving by <name type="pname">James Smillie</name>, from <name type="pname">J.</name> and <name type="pname">C. Smillie</name>, <hi rend="italic">Mount Auburn Illustrated,</hi> <date when="1851">1851</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-402"><graphic url="CH9_030.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 9.30. Loring Monument, Mount Auburn Cemetery. Engraving by <name type="pname">James Smillie</name>, from <name type="pname">J.</name> and <name type="pname">C. Smillie</name>, <hi rend="italic">Mount Auburn Illustrated,</hi> <date when="1851">1851</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-403"><graphic url="CH9_031.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.31. Hillside chamber tombs with granite faades, Mount Auburn Cemetery</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Although Bigelow promoted interment directly in the ground, many plot owners constructed chamber tombs similar to those at P&#x00E8;re-Lachaise. Some chamber tombs were nestled into hillsides and faced with granite after stonecutters perfected techniques for carving and incising this durable material (fig. 9.31). As the cemetery began to acquire more burial plots, memorial sculpture, and works of architecture, notably Bigelow's Gothic Revival chapel and his George <name type="place">Washington</name> Tower, it also acquired a greater degree of horticultural ornamentation. New trustees exercised keen fiduciary oversight and were careful to set aside funds from the proceeds of lot sales for landscape maintenance. Gradually Mount Auburn became, as it remains today, a memorial garden enriched by the mixture of many exotic and native plant species.</p><p>Bigelow designed and donated the cemetery's last major embellishment, a monumental female Sphinx, dedicated in <date when="1871">1871</date> to the Union dead (fig. 9.32). By this time, mnemonic devices and landscapes evoking the past were less compelling to a new generation of Americans more interested in progress than in the past. Idealization of republican virtue and the domestication of death seemed less important after the Civil War than materialistic success and optimistic faith in the future. The notion of history as continuous linear improvement that many Americans came to identify with their nation's peculiar destiny fostered an attitude of denial toward death and an aversion to reminders of human mortality and the decline of civilizations. By contrast, the founders of Mount Auburn held that history was cyclical, believing that the young republic they were shaping would one day, like <name type="place">Rome</name>, fall into ruin. Their elegiac monuments were meant for future generations to read as a testament to the greatness of the republican experiment in <name type="place">America</name>, the solidarity of families, and the virtue and industry of the men and women commemorated within its idyllic precincts.</p><p>Mount Auburn served as the progenitor of rural cemeteries in other cities: Laurel Hill in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> (<date when="1836">1836</date>), Green Wood in <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> (<date when="1838">1838</date>), Spring Grove in Cincinnati (<date when="1845">1845</date>), and Cave Hill in Louisville (<date when="1848">1848</date>). In addition, it exerted an influence over the old barren burial grounds in cities, and these, now no longer in active use, were given iron fences, grass, trees, and shrubs, becoming the pleasant green urban oases they are today.</p><p>Although there were plenty who left written records demonstrating that the didacticism of Mount<pb n="337"/><pb n="337" type="orig"/>Auburn effectively touched them much as Bigelow and the other founders had hoped, even in the early years of its existence, people did not necessarily go there for moral uplift. From its inception, the cemetery was an immensely popular place for an outing, so much so that superintendents issued admittance passes and enforced rules restricting certain types of recreation. The same was true at Green-Wood, the <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> cemetery where Manhattan residents flocked on Sundays for a holiday in scenic surroundings. Their evident enjoyment of this form of recreation caused some civic-minded New Yorkers to ask the question: why not a people's park devoid of reminders of mortality?</p><figure xml:id="fig-404"><graphic url="CH9_032.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.32. Sphinx, Mount Auburn Cemetery, designed by Jacob Bigelow and sculpted by <name type="pname">Martin Milmore</name>. <date when="1871">1871</date></hi></figDesc></figure></div></div><div type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">IV. <hi rend="smallcaps">The New Metropolis: Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux as Park Builders and City Planners</hi></hi></head><p>When Mount Auburn and Green-Wood were created, the country had not yet developed any public parks, museums, or other large-scale cultural institutions. Soon, however, voluntary associations of citizens began to found these, diminishing the cemetery's role as moral landscape and repository for monuments. Not surprisingly, Andrew Jackson Downing saw the rural cemetery as a transitional institution. In <date when="1849">1849</date>, he editorialized in <hi rend="italic">The Horticulturist:</hi> "The great attraction of these cemeteries ... lies in the natural beauty of the sites, and in the tasteful and harmonious embellishment of these sites by art. . . . Does not this general interest, manifested in these cemeteries, prove that public gardens, established in a liberal and suitable manner, near our large cities, would be equally successful?"<ref target="#CH9-n22"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref>His tragic death three years later prevented him from advancing the park cause. But by this time, politicians had embraced it thanks to the well-reasoned passion with which he and others, such as the poet William Cullen Bryant, who served as editor of the <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">New York</name> Evening Post</hi> from <date when="1829">1829</date> to <date when="1878">1878</date>, had advocated establishing public parks for the people. Calvert Vaux (<date when="1824">1824</date>&#x2013;<date when="1895">1895</date>) stood ready to put his talent and training with Downing into the creation of <name type="place">America</name>'s first large-scale public park, Central Park, and luckily he found in Frederick Law Olmsted (<date when="1822">1822</date>&#x2013;<date when="1903">1903</date>), erstwhile farmer, journalist, and editor, a collaborator capable of helping him found both the parks movement and the profession of landscape architecture in <name type="place">America</name>.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">New York's Campaign for a Park</hi></hi></head><p>Vaux left Newburgh and moved to <name type="place">New York</name> in <date when="1856">1856</date> at a time when the city was beginning to develop a lively artistic culture. In addition to theaters and music halls, department stores had opened their doors on Broadway, and shopping and promenading to enjoy both the commercial and the social spectacle had become a pleasurable routine for many New Yorkers. At the same time, the city's thriving port and commercial enterprises attracted a swelling volume of immigrants, particularly after the potato famine of the <date when="1840">1840</date>s in <name type="place">Ireland</name> and political turbulence in the wake of several failed revolutionary movements in Europe in <date when="1848">1848</date> stimulated mass exodus from countries abroad. <name type="place">New York</name> reformers organized societies to minister to the needy, and although public health had been greatly improved after the Croton Aqueduct brought pure drinking water to the city in <date when="1842">1842</date>, crowding now fostered both disease and vice. With few exceptions, <name type="place">New York</name> had little to offer in the way of publicly accessible greenery. There was the Battery, the city's historic waterfront promenade at the foot of Manhattan Island; City Hall Park; Jones's Wood, an informal 160-acre picnic grove beside the East River between Sixty-sixth and Seventy-fifth Streets; and Green-Wood, the immensely popular rural cemetery in <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>. The city's residential squares&#x2014;St.John's Park, Gramercy Park, Union Square, <name type="place">Washington</name> Square&#x2014;were mostly fenced, with access restricted to neighboring property holders. Well-to-do <name type="place">New York</name> businessmen&#x2014;the city's civic leaders&#x2014;traveling abroad noticed the parks in <name type="place">England</name>, <name type="place">France</name>, and <name type="place">Germany</name>, which had been opened to the general populace as a matter of royal favor or <hi rend="italic">noblesse oblige.</hi> It was obvious to them that to satisfy their recreational needs and especially those of their wives and children, as well as to establish their city competitively as a pleasant and civilized urban center of international importance, they should take responsible action to<pb n="338"/><pb n="338" type="orig"/>improve it by constructing a public park. In this they were urged forward by women whose work in various charitable associations made them conscious of the importance of this type of environmental and humanitarian improvement for the poor and whose burgeoning cosmopolitanism made them long as well for an American version of Hyde Park or the ChampsElys&#x00E9;es where they could readily socialize in public. Uptown landowners stood to gain from the improvement a park would bring to surrounding real estate, so they were natural proponents in bringing the plan forward.</p><p>After much contentious debate, the state legislature passed a bill in <date when="1853">1853</date>, authorizing the acquisition of land below the existing Croton Reservoir in the center of the island between Seventy-ninth and Eighty-sixth Streets and north of it where the large New Reservoir was being built between Eighty-sixth and Ninety-sixth Streets. <name type="pname">Fernando Wood</name> (<date when="1812">1812</date>&#x2013;<date when="1881">1881</date>), <name type="place">New York</name>'s Democratic mayor after <date when="1854">1854</date>, saw that a large public works project could assist immigrant laborers and, incidentally, his own bank account, inasmuch as he was heavily invested in parkside real estate. In what later historians would cite as his single heroic act, he exerted his leadership in favor of proceeding with the construction of Central Park between Fifth and Eighth Avenues and 59th and 106th Streets.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Design and Building of Central Park</hi></hi></head><p>It was now necessary to acquire the land. Beginning in the fall of <date when="1853">1853</date>, a commission surveyed and estimated the value of the building lots and improvements on the site of the future park, meeting numerous futile complaints, particularly from landowners within the park who felt they had invested more capital and labor in improving their holdings than the price they were being awarded. Even so, the $5 million land acquisition cost far exceeded the cost that had been projected for the <hi rend="italic">built</hi> park. As the parkland was exempted from the market, the surrounding property automatically went up in value. Regulations to curb certain activities considered to be nuisances such as piggeries and bone-boiling works were enacted, making the area surrounding the park desirable for the future as a place of fashionable residence. By <date when="1857-10-01">October 1, 1857</date>, with considerable hardship on the part of many former residents, including those clustered in an active African-American community known as Seneca Village on the west side of the park, the park site was cleared of inhabitants.</p><p>Anxious to wrest power from Mayor Wood, the legislature in <name type="place">Albany</name>, which was dominated by the newly formed Republican Party, removed authority over Central Park from the city and placed it under a state-appointed, eleven-member commission. Egbert Viele (<date when="1825">1825</date>&#x2013;<date when="1902">1902</date>), the engineer Wood had appointed to survey the park, was reappointed by the newly formed Board of Commissioners. Vaux had seen the plan Viele had prepared in <date when="1856">1856</date> for the park, which Wood had approved, and he realized how inferior it was with respect to the opportunity at hand. Vaux had recently acted as a founding member of the American Institute of Architects, and he now organized a successful lobbying effort for a design competition in order to achieve a plan that, according to him, would not disgrace the city or the memory of Downing. On <date when="1857-10-13">October 13, 1857</date>, the commission announced the terms of the public competition, and Vaux now became instrumental on the first of two significant occasions in directing the talents of Frederick Law Olmsted into the service of landscape design.</p><p>Olmsted had previously met Vaux once when he called upon Downing in Newburgh. But at that time he had no idea that he would pursue landscape as a career. Having first established himself with his father's financial help on Staten Island as a gentleman farmer employing the scientific principles similar to those pioneered by Loudon, he had felt impelled to travel abroad in <date when="1850">1850</date> to study English agricultural practices at firsthand, recording his observations in a book, <hi rend="italic">Walks and Talks of an American Farmer in <name type="place">England</name>.</hi> Its critical success led him to pursue further journalistic endeavors based upon travel. Choosing the pen name "Yeoman," he dispatched a series of letters to the newly formed <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">New York</name> Daily Times,</hi> from various points along the routes he took through the American South and the frontier states as far west as <name type="place">Texas</name>. His constant theme was the superiority of free labor over slave agriculture, but interwoven into his text were passionately vivid descriptions of the countryside. Self-taught in his uncle's library where he may<figure xml:id="fig-405"><graphic url="CH9_033.jpg"/></figure><pb n="339"/><pb n="339" type="orig"/>have first encountered the writings of Price and Gilpin, he was, like his father who had taken him on carriage rides as a boy in search of the Picturesque, a discriminating connoisseur of natural scenery. Now, however, the Panic of <date when="1857">1857</date> had forced the publishing house for which he worked to close. Being prevented from pursuing his literary career as a publisher and the editor of <hi rend="italic">Putnam's Monthly Magazine,</hi> Olmsted was grateful to receive the job of superintendent of the clearing operations for Central Park under the supervision of Viele, the engineer-in-chief.</p><p>Vaux had learned a good deal about landscape design as he worked with Downing on the improvement of the public grounds in <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, as well as on the private estates where they collaborated, but he realized that Olmsted's daily familiarity with the park landscape and his stature as an author and person of moral influence would make him an ideal partner in the design competition. Thus began the friendship of the architect and literary-man-turnedadministrator as they paced together over the park's terrain and formed the vision embodied in the competition entry they labeled the Greensward Plan (fig. 9.33). By judiciously clearing away here and planting there, by moving earth to rearrange the land into gently rolling contours, by laying drains and converting swamps into ponds, there would emerge a landscape that was both pastoral and Picturesque.</p><p>To understand the Greensward Plan and the subsequent work of the two men after they became professional partners, one must attempt to enter the mind of Olmsted as fully as possible, for however much intelligence and design ability Vaux contributed, Olmsted's brand of nineteenth-century spirituality and democratic humanitarianism supplied something fundamentally philosophic to their common vision of the designed landscape. This vision was akin to Downing's in that it was rooted in a belief that parks in cities and the domesticated middle landscape of freestanding homes set in parklike surroundings away from the crowded urban workplace would act as a civilizing force in society. But Olmsted's more comprehensive view of landscape was not derived from Downing or from Loudon, Downing's preceptor.</p><p>Downing had recast Loudon's concepts to suit the conditions of American society and the country's natural landscape, recommending a Picturesque and sometimes rustic architectural vocabulary to harmonize with and accent picturesque scenery. But, like Loudon, he was a horticulturist who valued plant display for its own sake. Olmsted&#x2014;"Yeoman"&#x2014;found the Gardenesque style a fussy distraction from the park's real purpose, which was the creation of rural scenery that evoked a poetic mood lifting one out of everyday care and ennobling the spirit with intimations of the divine. This kind of scenic contemplation was therapy for the overworked paterfamilias, a healthful occupation for women, a positive educational influence upon children, and a means of acculturation for the masses. Olmsted never presented himself as having botanical expertise, preferring plants arranged for their overall artistic effect to those presented as individual scientific specimens.<ref target="#CH9-n23"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">23</hi></hi></ref>The task of incorporating the recently enriched botanical palette into garden compositions in which specimen trees or beds of flowers were objects of attention was for him irrelevant to the business of park making.</p><figure xml:id="fig-406"><graphic url="CH9_034.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.33. Greensward Plan, Central Park design competition entry of Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux. <date when="1857">1857</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>For the same reason, Olmsted held that architecture and sculpture should be subservient to landscape. Utilitarian and decorative elements should be placed within an overall impression of tranquilly beautiful and ruggedly Picturesque rural scenery. In later years, when he served as mentor to aspiring young landscape architects, he did not direct them to the works of the prominent nineteenth-century authors, Loudon and Downing, but rather to those of Price<pb n="340"/><pb n="340" type="orig"/>and Repton. Like these eighteenth-century writers, he saw landscape not as a collection of features artistically arranged for display, but rather as a shifting panorama, a sequence of views and vistas that opened up harmoniously as one moved through the countryside or city park. His own deepest religious experiences were, like those of his father, Wordsworthian and transcendentalist&#x2014;rapt responses to the beautiful and sublime in nature. He also loved the rich, picturesque mystery of things half-concealed by overhanging vines. His keen emotional response to lush tropical effects caused him to attempt to simulate the scenery he had seen in the Louisiana bayous and on the Isthmus of Panama in an Americaninflected version of the eighteenth-century English Picturesque. By exploiting such optical characteristics as the play of light and shade in the shadows cast by trees across a sunlit meadow, the atmospheric haze of a distant umbrageous horizon line, and the mystery suggested by an intricate fringe of vines screening a shadowy entrance to a grotto, he created a design idiom that was both naturalistic and Romantic.</p><figure xml:id="fig-407"><graphic url="CH9_035.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.34. Sheep Meadow, Central Park, <name type="place">New York</name> City</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-408"><graphic url="CH9_036.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.35. Sheep Meadow, Central Park, contemporary view. In keeping with the pastoral ideal embodied in this landscape, the sight of the surrounding city was screened from view by the park's topographic modeling and umbrageous border plantings. Olmsted and Vaux wanted to imply the nonexistence of the park's rectangular boundaries and the indefinite continuation of pastoral scenery, a successful strategy before the age of skyscrapers, which now loom dramatically along its borders, providing perhaps a new scenic category: the urban sublime.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>His immersion as a young man in the "green, dripping, glistening, gorgeous!" landscape of rural <name type="place">England</name>&#x2014;"enchantment indeed, we gazed upon it and breathed it&#x2014;never to be forgotten"<ref target="#CH9-n24"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">24</hi></hi></ref>&#x2014;had imprinted his mind with an imagery of pastoral beauty that served him as lasting inspiration, but the English class system that achieved this beauty for the advantage of a few aristocrats through the enclosure movement and the hard labor of the poor offended his sense of social responsibility. The sight in <name type="place">England</name> that had impressed him most happily from a democratic standpoint was Paxton's Birkenhead Park: "Five minutes of admiration, and a few more spent in studying the manner in which art had been employed to obtain from nature so much beauty, and I was ready to admit that in democratic <name type="place">America</name>, there was nothing to be thought of as comparable with this People's Garden."<ref target="#CH9-n25"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">25</hi></hi></ref>Now, thanks to Vaux's invitation to join him in the design competition for Central Park, he had the chance to work on a far grander scale to create a "People's Garden" in <name type="place">New York</name>.</p><p>Because of Olmsted's daytime duties as superintendent and the many interruptions by an incessant stream of job seekers, he and Vaux did much of their collaboration on moonlit nights as they paced the future park, appreciating the scenic potential of its bold outcroppings of Manhattan schist, proposing certain topographical alterations in order to deepen swamps into lakes and mound soil into rolling meadows. They studied where to place drainage lines and discussed the configuration of carriage drives and the<pb n="341"/><pb n="341" type="orig"/>best vantage points for vistas. Friends gathered in the evenings at Vaux's house on Eighteenth Street to assist in the preparation of the pen-and-ink drawing. On <date when="1858-03-31">March 31, 1858</date>, the deadline for the competition, Olmsted and Vaux submitted their Greensward Plan, which now hangs in the Arsenal, the <name type="place">New York</name> City Department of Parks headquarters in Central Park. On <date when="--04-28">April 28</date>, the commissioners announced their decision to award first prize and the announced premium of $2,000 to the Vaux-Olmsted team.</p><p>The element that more than any other defines an Olmsted-Vaux landscape is a spacious meadow with gentle rises and scattered clumps of trees arranged about its periphery so as to lead the eye beyond its indeterminate boundaries into an illusionistic distance of seemingly unending rural scenery. It was difficult to achieve in Central Park because of its broken topography and narrow rectangular shape. Above Ninety-eighth Street, however, there was a piece of tableland that lent itself to becoming the North and East Meadows, while below the Sixty-Fifth Street Transverse Road the designers proposed blasting away bedrock in order to fill and level the surface for a Ball Ground. Because the transverse road's below-grade level made it inconspicuous, the Ball Ground was visually united with the 14-acre Sheep Meadow immediately north of it (figs. 9.34, 9.35). Together these two green areas served to portray as best possible the designers' scenic desideratum in the park's south end. To nourish a thick mat of turf for the grazing flock that would enhance the park's pastoral appearance they covered the Sheep Meadow with 2 feet (.6 meters) of topsoil. Grading the park's borders into low berms and planting trees "to insure an umbrageous horizon line"<ref target="#CH9-n26"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">26</hi></hi></ref>was another feat of landscape legerdemain the designers employed in order to screen from view the future four-story houses that would rise along the suddenly valuable frontage lots.</p><figure xml:id="fig-409"><graphic url="CH9_037.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Left top:</hi> 9.36. Archway carrying the carriage over a transverse road, Central Park, c. <date when="1860">1860</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-410"><graphic url="CH9_038.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Left middle:</hi> 9.37. Pedestrians crossing beneath Carriage Drive, Central Park. Lithograph by Sarony, Major &amp; Knapp, c.<date when="1860">1860</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-411"><graphic url="CH9_039.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Left bottom:</hi> 9.38. Pedestrians separated from horseback riders by means of a stone bridge, Central Park. Lithograph by George Hayward, ca. <date when="1860">1860</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-412"><graphic url="CH9_040.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.39. Bow Bridge, Central Park</hi></figDesc></figure><p>The most ingenious aspect of the Greensward Plan was the engineering of four east-west crossings to carry workaday city traffic through the park along below-grade transverse roads (fig. 9.36). Here, too, low berms with plantings screened from park visitors' sight the carts and draft animals moving on these roads. In executing the Greensward Plan, Olmsted and Vaux carried the principle of grade separation of traffic one step further by segregating pedestrians from carriage traffic and riders on horseback. This gave Vaux, often in association with Jacob Wrey Mould, the opportunity to design a number of stone arches for paths and bridle trails carrying pedestrians and horseback riders beneath carriage drives as well as a handful of ornamental cast-iron bridges for paths spanning bridle trails (figs. 9.37,9.38). Bow Bridge, at the narrow neck between the two lobes of the Lake, allowed pedestrians to cross from the foot of Cherry Hill to the Ramble, an intricately designed woodland for strolling. It constitutes Vaux's masterwork in this mid-nineteenth-century building material (fig. 9.39).</p><pb n="342"/><pb n="342" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-413"><graphic url="CH9_041.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.40. Bethesda Terrace, Central Park. The carved panels encasing the grand double stairs descending to the Bethesda Fountain and the lakeshore depict a rich profusion of animal and vegetal forms symbolizing the seasons of the year. Ornamentation like this, using images depicting natures abundance in a manner similar to that of medieval stonecarvers, owes a debt to the writings of John Ruskin, an important influence on the intellectual and artistic culture of Victorian <name type="place">England</name> and its counterpart in nineteenth-century <name type="place">America</name>.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Today Olmsted and Vaux are sometimes criticized as being the carriers of patrician values and the agents of elitist objectives because they created a park for scenic viewing by carriage and on horseback&#x2014;as well as on foot&#x2014;and did not cater to a greater degree to more populist pastimes involving games and sports. This viewpoint imposes a later value system on their objectives and ignores the fact that, at the time they designed Central Park, the physical recreational movement still lay in the future. For their romantically inclined generation, scenic strolling was a healthful pastime much enjoyed by all classes. They were sincere in their belief that this pleasure, which Olmsted deemed to be akin to being moved by poetry, would soften the lives of the less fortunate members of society, which included many newcomers from other countries. They were convinced that the park's pastoral and Picturesque scenery would serve as an informal public school, instructing immigrants through an unconscious process of scenic enjoyment in the shared values, which were still predominantly agrarian, of the new democratic society-in-formation.</p><p>It is undeniable that there were certain prospective users who felt few transcendental stirrings in the presence of scenery and who saw the park merely as a social arena, a place to parade their wealth and marriageable daughters, often exercising ill-disguised class prejudice. But this did not mean that the idealism expressed in the vision of Olmsted and Vaux was not genuine. They did not discourage such immediately popular activities as ice-skating and boating on the Lake, and the rules Olmsted promulgated as superintendent were designed to protect the park from overuse and abuse rather than to discriminate against a class of users. Most important, the Greensward Plan was supple in its ability to absorb new uses over the years. Unlike many of the landscapes presented to the public by the twentieth-century park builder <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name>, which typically consist of single-purpose recreation facilities, the spaces Olmsted and Vaux created are able to serve a variety of purposes. In his writings, Olmsted divided the park's landscape into two kinds of space: "neighborly" and "gregarious," the former being for small groups consisting of families and friends who came to the park to picnic and enjoy scenery, while the latter was designed to serve the parade of strangers who congregated in the manner of Parisians on boulevards to enjoy the spectacle of one another. The park was thus intended as a place in which to delight in both nature and one's common humanity.</p><p>Absent from the Greensward Plan were Downing's proposed "noble works of art, statues, monuments and buildings," although in <date when="1880">1880</date> Vaux built the first structure housing the Metropolitan Museum inside the park near Fifth Avenue and East Eighty-second Street. In addition, a conservatory originally planned near Fifth Avenue and East Seventy-fourth Street was constructed in <date when="1899">1899</date> in the north end of the park near Fifth Avenue and East 105th Street on the site where Olmsted had set up a temporary nursery and botanic garden. Throughout the park, the rural motif ruled in the predominant interest of "neighborly" recreation, but an important area was reserved for "gregarious" purposes: the elm-arcaded Mall, a straight concourse extending from Sixty-fifth to Seventy-second Street, which was set on a diagonal axis<pb n="343"/><pb n="343" type="orig"/>to detract attention from the park's rectilinear boundaries. Focused upon Vista Rock in the distance, which Vaux later crowned with the neo-Gothic, castlelike Belvedere, this grand promenade, designed for sociable congregation, leads strollers to a broad stairway and through the Arcade beneath the Seventy-second Street Cross Drive to the lakeside Terrace, Vaux's architectural masterpiece (fig. 9.40).</p><p>Here, with his collaborator Mould, Vaux designed a pair of monumental staircases carved with ornamental panels, profuse with motifs of vegetation and wildlife representing the four seasons. These grand stairs provided an alternative means of reaching the Terrace, useful for those alighting from carriages parked on the Cross Drive rather than passing on foot from the Mall through the Arcade. In the center of the circular Terrace, a jet sent a plume of water into the air until it was replaced in the <date when="1870">1870</date>s by a fountain surmounted by a sculpture representing the angel that bestowed healing power upon the pool of Bethesda in Jerusalem.<ref target="#CH9-n27"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">27</hi></hi></ref>This work by Emma Stebbins (<date when="1815">1815</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>) celebrated the public health benefits brought to the city a generation earlier by the Croton Aqueduct, and the figures at the fountain's base symbolize the blessings of Temperance, Purity, Health, and Peace. Two tall poles with ornamental bases and crossbars for long vertical fishtail banners stand next to the Lake where the designers effected a seemingly effortless transition from modest grandeur to Picturesque simplicity. This achievement is evident also in the way the designers made the geometric lines of the Mall and Terrace merge gracefully with the curving paths and naturalistic scenery alongside them.</p><p>In the south end of the park, the designers paid particular attention to the needs of women and children, visitors who might not wish to wander far from its principal entrance at Fifty-ninth Street and Fifth Avenue. Immediately south of the Sixty-fifth Street Transverse Road and serviceable from it, Vaux constructed the Dairy, a small building of rusticated stone with an ample wooden loggia providing shelter from the sun and inclement weather. Here children could play with toys furnished by a park attendant or drink fresh cow's milk. The designers christened a large nearby outcrop of Manhattan schist the Kinderberg. Polished by glacial scouring to form a natural slide, it had broad steps carved into its base and a rustic shelter crowning its top. The fenced playgrounds that are popular attractions in today's park were added after <date when="1934">1934</date> by <name type="pname">Moses</name>, but in the nineteenth century, park workers set up portable swings and seesaws in season.</p><p>In the original Greensward Plan, the northern border of the park is at 106th Street where an arboretum was specified but never built on the east side, while on the west side there was nothing beyond the Great Hill, which Olmsted and Vaux encircled with an appendage to the West Drive to afford carriage riders panoramic prospects from this high point in the park. The commissioners soon realized that the topography between 106th and 110th Streets would not readily permit urban development because it was both too elevated by bedrock protrusions and too swampy where the resistant Manhattan schist gives way to the easily erodible Inwood marble that underlies the Harlem plain. They wisely acquired this additional land in <date when="1863">1863</date>, increasing the park's size from 750 acres to 843 acres. This allowed Olmsted and Vaux to save the sites of several fortifications left from the Revolution and the War of <date when="1812">1812</date>, to promote as a forest of native American trees an already wooded area, and to create the Harlem Meer in the park's new northeast corner, a much larger water body than the Pond in the southeast (fig. 9.41).</p><p>An army of a thousand workers, directed at first by Olmsted, moved nearly 5 million cubic yards, or approximately 10 million one-horse cartloads of stone, earth, and topsoil out of or into the park between <date when="1858">1858</date> and <date when="1873">1873</date>. In addition, Olmsted supervised chief landscape gardener Ignaz Anton Pilat in planting a rich variety of trees, shrubs, and vines. Moreover, he promulgated park rules and oversaw the training of a cadre of park keepers responsible for maintaining order and educating the public to respect the landscape. All the while, to his intense irritation, he was subjected to the oversight and penny-pinching curtailments imposed by the park commission's comptroller, Andrew Haswell Green.</p><figure xml:id="fig-414"><graphic url="CH9_042.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.41. Harlem Meer and the <name type="pname">Charles A. Dana</name> Center, Central Park</hi></figDesc></figure><p>In <date when="1861">1861</date>, the Civil War interrupted the partners' collaboration on the ongoing creation of Central Park. Olmsted, who prided himself on his administrative abilities more than his landscape artistry, accepted a position as the executive secretary of the U.S. Sanitary Commission, the forerunner of the</p><pb n="344"/><pb n="344" type="orig"/><p>American Red Cross. He desired to serve the Union cause, and reasoning that moving nurses and supplies to the front was a managerial task similar to moving men and materials in the park, he departed for <name type="place">Washington</name>, leaving Vaux in charge of the work in the park, which continued throughout the war.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Olmsted in Transition</hi></hi></head><p>Until <date when="1863">1863</date>, when he accepted a position as the resident manager of the Mariposa Mines in <name type="place">California</name>, Olmsted helped reorganize the Army's Medical Bureau, took charge of distributing food and goods collected from branches of the Sanitary Commission in the North, and oversaw the evacuation of wounded Union soldiers on hospital transport ships. In <name type="place">California</name>, while supervising the Mariposa operations, he served as the head of a commission to make recommendations on the management of the Yosemite Valley as a public preserve. Although Anglo-Americans had discovered its spectacular scenery only sixteen years before, Yosemite was already a tourist attraction. Congress had the previous year withdrawn it from the public domain and deeded it to the state of <name type="place">California</name> "for public use, resort, and recreation," the first area in the nation to be set aside for this purpose. Olmsted's preliminary report on <hi rend="italic">The Yosemite Valley and the Mariposa Big Trees</hi> is a landmark enunciating the individual's right to enjoy public scenery and the government's obligation to protect citizens' exercise of that right.</p><figure xml:id="fig-415"><graphic url="CH9_043.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.42. Long Meadow, Prospect Park, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>. The Long Meadow illustrates the kind of scenic unfolding of pastoral landscape that constitutes the essence of Olmsted and Vaux's park ideal. The eye threads a passage through clumps of trees, passing over a series of gentle undulations to a hazy horizon line that appears to extend beyond the park's confines.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>At this period in his life, Olmsted still considered landscape design merely as a sideline. As the fortunes of the Mariposa mining venture sank, he considered returning to a career in journalism. At the same time, Vaux, who had been forced by political pressure to resign his Central Park position, wrote Olmsted saying that they had been offered reappointment as landscape architects&#x2014;the title they chose for their profession&#x2014;in Central Park and that there was another important commission awaiting collaboration: Prospect Park in <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, named for the elevation known as Mount Prospect.</p><p>Olmsted, loath to subject himself again to the kind of "squabbles with the Commission and the politicians" he had experienced in Central Park, was reluctant to accept Vaux's second entreaty to enter into collaboration. Vaux, however, urged him as persuasively as possible: "I am perhaps deficient in personal ambition&#x2014;but I can feel for it in others. If you do not see that you are honored by developing this fitness for art work of course&#x2014;don't come. It must be the art of landscape architecture and the art of administration combined. Think this over. We are neither of us old men you know. To me it seems &amp; always has seemed a magnificent opening. Possible together, impossible to either alone."<ref target="#CH9-n28"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">28</hi></hi></ref>Olmsted was still reluctant to consider himself an artist but thought that he could "do anything with proper assistants, or money enough&#x2014;anything any man can do. I can combine means to ends better than most, and I love beautiful landscapes and rural recreations and people in rural recreations&#x2014;better than anybody else I know."<ref target="#CH9-n29"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">29</hi></hi></ref>Still uncertain that he could make a living in this line of work, he nevertheless decided to return to <name type="place">New York</name> and join Vaux in the continuing construction of Central Park and the design of the park that <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>'s civic leaders wanted to build in emulation of it.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Creating Prospect Park</hi></hi></head><p>Vaux had already convinced James Stranahan, the president of the park board, that the original site authorized by the state legislature&#x2014;350 acres straddling Flatbush Avenue&#x2014;was less desirable than the western portion of this site plus a large tract of adjoining farmland where there existed the opportunity to create an illusion of infinitely extensive rural space and a large lake. The popularity of ice-skating in Central Park made an even larger Prospect Park lake competitively attractive, and the park commissioners agreed to divest themselves of the portion of their original site east of Flatbush Avenue&#x2014;land now occupied by the <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> Museum of Art and <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> Botanic Garden&#x2014;and to purchase the site recommended by Vaux, bringing the park's total acreage to 526.</p><p>The park did not have prominent, ice-polished rock outcrops like the ones that picturesquely accented the scenery in Central Park, but it was situated on a glacial moraine. This provided a naturally rich soil and a gently rolling terrain as well as glacial erratics&#x2014;large boulders left after the ice melted. The designers artfully employed these as compositional elements when they built the Ravine between the Long Meadow and the Lake (figs. 9.42, 9.43). In creating the 75-acre Long Meadow, they were not constrained by the disposition of the park's boundaries<pb n="345"/><pb n="345" type="orig"/>as they had been in Central Park where they were hampered by the firmly rectilinear shape dictated by the <date when="1811">1811</date> grid plan for Manhattan. Also, in Prospect Park they were free of the necessity of providing transverse roads for nonpark traffic. Thus they were able "to connect a series of dissevered and isolated patches of comparatively level ground, into one sweep of grass-land that is extensive enough, to make a really permanent impression on the mind."<ref target="#CH9-n30"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">30</hi></hi></ref>On the perimeter of the Long Meadow&#x2014;considered by many as the quintessential Olmstedian landscape&#x2014; they mounded earth into berms and then created spacious vaulted tunnels, a design master stroke that orchestrates the passage of visitors in a manner that induces surprise and heightens sensory awareness and appreciation of the long vista of gently undulating rural scenery. The pleasure of the experience is heightened by the park's urban context.<ref target="#CH9-n31"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">31</hi></hi></ref></p><figure xml:id="fig-416"><graphic url="CH9_044.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.43. Plan of Prospect Park, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux. <date when="1871">1871</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-417"><graphic url="CH9_045.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.44. The Ravine, Prospect Park, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>. c. <date when="1870">1870</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>As in Central Park, the designers created a space for "gregarious" recreation in the elegant concert grove with ornamental stonework by Vaux similar to that which distinguished Bethesda Terrace in Central Park. The concert grove is flanked by an upper and a lower carriage concourse accessible from the park's sinuous circuit drive, and the whole ensemble constituted an informal amphitheater oriented to face the small Music Pavilion located on an island in Prospect Lake, now covered over by the Wollman Rink. The Ravine's stream with waterfalls spilling over rocks and profusely planted slopes, which has recently been restored, simulated the rugged picturesqueness one might find on an outing in the Catskill Mountains (fig. 9.44).</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Exploding Metropolis</hi></hi></head><p>As walled cities became things of the past after the formation of nation-states and as industrial technology provided means of transportation that effectively shrank distance, making it possible to commute between widely separated places of work and home, the spatial envelope of cities became greatly enlarged. In spite of a lingering Jeffersonian bias in favor of a predominantly agrarian destiny for <name type="place">America</name>, manufacturing and commerce were breeding increasingly large urban populations, and this fostered an unprecedented growth in the size of cities. Public sanitation victories through the kind of engineering technology represented by <name type="place">New York</name>'s Croton Aqueduct system and other Industrial-Age improvements such as smooth macadam roadbeds instead of cobblestone paving made large cities more livable than before.</p><p>But they still presented many difficulties for their inhabitants, the most notable being deprivation of contact with nature as the countryside became<pb n="346"/><pb n="346" type="orig"/>increasingly distant from the city. Olmsted and Vaux felt that a single park's role as a civilizing influence, ameliorating the noise and hectic pace of the metropolis, was still somewhat limited. They envisioned the carriage drives within parks being extended to become parkways, tree-canopied transportation corridors connected to other parks, the whole forming a new framework superimposed over the grid, a green skeleton guiding the city's expansion. They saw, moreover, that roadway layout necessarily dictated the pattern and nature of urban growth, with residential development of a more elegant nature being spawned by a circulation system that segregated private estates from commercial through traffic. In their grasp of the city as an evolving regional organism they were the country's first urban planners.</p><figure xml:id="fig-418"><graphic url="CH9_046.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.45. Plan of a portion of Eastern Parkway, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, <name type="place">New York</name>. <date when="1868">1868</date>. Six rows of trees were to be planted along the length of the parkway, dividing the 260-foot (79-meter) right-ofway into a center drive for carriages, with two lanes on each side, one of which was designated a pedestrian walk, while the other served as a side road for the approach of vehicles to the adjoining house lots. These were to be 100 feet (30.4 meters) in width, allowing for the construction of freestanding "villa" residences with private gardens. Service lanes where horses could be stabled, goods delivered, and garbage removed were to be located in back of the house lots.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>The parity implied by the <date when="1811">1811</date> grid plan for <name type="place">New York</name> City was congenial to the expressed democratic values of the new republic. Moreover, it was a practical convenience for developers. Nevertheless, Olmsted wrote scathingly about its disadvantages. He felt the <name type="place">New York</name> grid to be especially uncongenial to the needs of people because the block sizes dictated by its street layout forced property to be divided into deep lots, usually no wider than 25 feet (7.6 meters). This resulted in rows of cramped narrow houses with poor light and ventilation. He wished to remedy this condition by carrying the park influence to the level of a system, with greenery easily accessible throughout the metropolitan area. Where land had not yet been platted, lots for homes could be created that would permit healthful cross ventilation, penetration by sunlight, and a green lawn. Unlike the grid with its straight streets intersecting at right angles and static perspectives, the parkway system would conform to topography and scenic opportunity, which could be captured by the kind of curving alignments that allowed the landscape to unfold from a series of ever-changing vantage points.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The First Parkways</hi></p><p>The creation of the <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> park offered Olmsted and Vaux the opportunity to advocate a more comprehensive vision for the metropolitan landscape. In their preliminary report to the commissioners dated <date when="1866-01-24">January 24, 1866</date>, they articulated under the heading "Suburban Connections" the desirability of a pleasure drive connecting Prospect Park with the beach on the Atlantic Ocean. Imaginatively, they saw how another drive could run east along the beach, then pass through undeveloped countryside, continuing parallel with the East River until it touched the shore at Ravenswood, Queens, where either by ferry or high bridges as yet unbuilt it would connect with one of the wide crosstown Manhattan streets leading to Central Park. Further, they envisioned this extensive greenway dedicated to pleasure driving extending west from Central Park to the Hudson River, where it could run for a distance parallel to that river with views of the Palisades on the opposite shore and, in the distance, the blue outline of the Shawangunk Mountains.</p><p>Two years later after work on the park had begun, Olmsted and Vaux used the report they delivered to the board as an opportunity to expound this metropolitan-scale planning concept. They now proposed a scheme, which went beyond their original one of a recreational parkway linking two major parks with the region's ocean beaches and extensive river waterfront, to encompass the notion of <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>'s destiny as an ideal residential community. Even allowing for shipping and commercial activity equal to that of Manhattan across the river, much of the city&#x2014;although it had not yet become a borough of Greater <name type="place">New York</name>&#x2014;could function as a bedroom suburb. "<name type="place">Brooklyn</name> is <name type="place">New York</name> outside the walls,"<ref target="#CH9-n32"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">32</hi></hi></ref> they wrote, an implied reference to the faubourgs that had earlier sprung up outside the walls of <name type="place">Paris</name> and other walled cities in Europe.</p><p>In their report Olmsted and Vaux detailed the history of urban street plans from medieval times to the present, citing the missed opportunity when Wren's plan was ignored in the rebuilding of <name type="place">London</name> after the Great Fire of <date when="1666">1666</date>. They proposed for <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> the first elements of a major arterial system that took into account the need for smooth roadbeds for the increasingly numerous light spring-suspension carriages, which were "quite unfit to be used in streets adapted to the heavy wagons employed in commercial traffic."<ref target="#CH9-n33"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">33</hi></hi></ref>At the same time, they realized that<pb n="347"/><pb n="347" type="orig"/>delivery carts and other kinds of commercial traffic could not be banned from abutting residential property altogether.</p><p>Taking inspiration from the new avenue de l'Imp&#x00E9;ratrice (now avenue Foch), which Olmsted had seen on a trip to <name type="place">Paris</name> in <date when="1859">1859</date>, and <name type="place">Berlin</name>'s great treelined avenue, Unter den Linden, each of which was connected to a large park while simultaneously serving as "an intermediate pleasure-ground [rather] than a part of the general street system,"<ref target="#CH9-n34"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">34</hi></hi></ref>the designers sketched the route of Ocean Parkway leading from Prospect Park to the beach at Coney Island and that of Eastern Parkway running from the park toward the Williamsburg section of <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> (fig. 9.45). A third parkway was proposed to link the park with Fort Hamilton and the site of the future Marine Park overlooking the Verrazano Narrows to the south.</p><p>The designers further remarked that new public transportation improvements made possible the occupation of a much larger urban area at lower densities than heretofore. Separation of residence and workplace was a corollary of this enlargement of towns. <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, "set apart and guarded by nature as a place for the tranquil habitation of those whom the business of the world requires should reside within convenient access of the waters of <name type="place">New York</name> harbor"<ref target="#CH9-n35"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">35</hi></hi></ref> was ideally situated to become a pleasant residential suburb. Olmsted and Vaux hoped that with its domestic character established by the parkway and street system recommended in their report, the kind of energetic self-made young men who had left their leafy country towns for the commercial opportunities of the city would be drawn to purchase property in <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>'s new middle landscape. It was a model that could be replicated as <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> and other cities grew, extending themselves to encompass their surrounding rural countryside. The loss of that countryside to urbanization was compensated for by the abundant greenery of the now more loosely woven fabric of the metropolitan landscape with its parkways connecting city dwellers to the generously scaled new urban parks filled with rural scenery.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Buffalo's Park System</hi></hi></head><p>The firm that Olmsted and Vaux had formed was now called upon to consult in other cities. Even as they were writing their report to the <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> commissioners outlining their parkway concept, they were advising the city of <name type="place">Newark</name>, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, that large cultural institutions such as museums were extraneous to rural parks and should be built outside them and that, in considering the acquisition of land for a public park, the town fathers should also consider purchasing strips of land for future construction of pleasure drives and walks. They gave similar advice to clients in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> and <name type="place">Albany</name>. It was in Buffalo, however, that the partners got to implement an entire park-and-parkway system. There, in <date when="1804">1804</date>, <name type="pname">Joseph Ellicott</name>, brother of <name type="pname">Andrew Ellicott</name>, <name type="pname">Pierre L'Enfant</name>'s chief surveyor for <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, had laid out a city where a radial street plan was focused upon a central square.</p><figure xml:id="fig-419"><graphic url="CH9_047.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.46.<date when="1868">1868</date> Plan of Buffalo Park System, <date when="1876">1876</date> map</hi></figDesc></figure><p>A group of citizens in Buffalo, <name type="place">New York</name>, summoned Olmsted in the fall of <date when="1868">1868</date> to examine three sites under consideration for a park. He traveled to the city for a site meeting and admired its departure from the grid in its layout. He then proceeded to sketch a plan that grafted onto this street pattern a system of parkway-linked parks. The new plan thus consisted of not one, but all three park sites with parkways connecting them to one another (fig. 9.46). The 350-acre Delaware Park gave the designers an opportunity to create a large meadow and a 46-acre lake and to provide an extensive circuit drive with grade separation of intersecting pedestrian paths as in Central and Prospect Parks. A second park, the Front, occupied 36 acres overlooking the Niagara River near its entry into Lake Erie and was designed as a viewing terrace, which could also accommodate large gatherings. The Parade, a 56-acre tract on elevated land near the eastern edge of the city, where military functions took place, included children's play equipment and Vaux's large refectory. The parkways, 200-foot-wide (61-meter-wide) landscaped boulevards, now lined with handsome residences, remain a much<pb n="348"/><pb n="348" type="orig"/>appreciated Buffalo amenity. In <date when="1874">1874</date>, on land contiguous to Delaware Park, Olmsted prepared a plan for "Parkside," the city's first residential suburb, which had curving streets lined with trees and large lots for fine homes with landscaped grounds.</p><figure xml:id="fig-420"><graphic url="CH9_048.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.47. Plan for Riverside, <name type="place">Illinois</name>, <date when="1869">1869</date></hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Riverside, Illinois</hi></hi></head><p>Almost simultaneously, in Riverside, <name type="place">Illinois</name>, on the Des Plaines River 9 miles (14.5 kilometers) west of <name type="place">Chicago</name> and accessible to commuters by train, Olmsted and Vaux had the chance to employ their principles for laying out residential communities (fig. 9.47). Here was an opportunity to demonstrate on 1,600 acres of farmland the truly metropolitan character of their vision, which was far different from Downing's merely suburban ideal. In doing so, they went beyond the explicit commission of the Riverside Improvement Company to design a parkway connecting city and suburb. They wanted to create a transportation alternative to the railroad, providing a recreational amenity not only for Riverside families, but also for carriage-owning <name type="place">Chicago</name> residents who wanted a pleasant outing in the countryside. Like the <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> parkways, the <name type="place">Chicago</name> parkway&#x2014;several miles of which were constructed&#x2014;had segregated lanes, with pedestrians and horseback riders occupying the lane next to the central roadway and carts and wagons the outside utility lane.</p><p>For the circulation system within the community, the designers created curving, well-drained, treelined roads with sidewalks bordering lawns, which they specified to be 30 feet (9.1 meters) deep and planted with at least two trees. Like a <name type="place">New England</name> town, Riverside had its common. There were, moreover, because of the configuration of the road system, many triangular pieces of land that were intentionally exempted from the process of parceling house lots, and these served as additional public green space. But the largest reservation of land for common recreational enjoyment was the 160-acre stretch of land paralleling the Des Plaines River, envisioned as a waterfront park.</p><p>Management difficulties and financial problems made the partners resign their commission in <date when="1870">1870</date>. A thousand acres east of the river and a small piece of land to the west were eventually developed according to their plan, but many half-acre lots were divided into two lots, and the large park remained unbuilt. Today, however, this leafy suburb, which is now surrounded by ordinary grid-style urbanization, stands out as an example of the intelligent approach to the design of the new American metropolitan landscape in the middle of the nineteenth century when Olmsted and Vaux infused the process of real-estate development with social and recreational considerations of lasting consequence.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Chicago Parks</hi></hi></head><p>At the same time that the partners were working on Riverside, <name type="place">Chicago</name> was becoming a commercial dynamo vigorously seeking the civic symbolism that would assert its supremacy within the Union. The state legislature had recently passed a bill authorizing the creation of three large parks, two of which had received approval in a voters' referendum. Separate commissions were created to oversee each park, a fact that served to prevent the comprehensive urban planning approach taken in Buffalo.</p><p><name type="pname">William LeBaron Jenny</name>, a French-trained architect, was chosen to design the western recreational complex consisting of Douglas Park and Garfield (originally Central) Park, while Olmsted and Vaux were hired to design the united <name type="place">Washington</name> Park and Jackson Park for the South Park Commission (fig. 9.48). Unfortunately, the fire of <date when="1871">1871</date>, which destroyed much of <name type="place">Chicago</name>, prevented the construction of these parks from moving forward at the time. Even if begun, the parks on the South Park Commission's flat, unpromising site adjacent to Lake Michigan offered little opportunity for realizing Olmsted and Vaux's ideal scenery of rolling meadowland. In addition, because <name type="place">Chicago</name> had a district-based rather than a city-wide park system, the designers were called upon to fit more elements into their plan for the two parks than would have been the case had they been able to adopt an integrated metropolitan approach,<pb n="349"/><pb n="349" type="orig"/>assigning different recreational functions more broadly to a greater number of parks.</p><p>But Lake Michigan itself in their opinion compensated "for the absence of sublime or picturesque elevations of the land."<ref target="#CH9-n36"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">36</hi></hi></ref>To extend its scenic influence and also to provide good drainage of the Midway and <name type="place">Washington</name> Park, they planned a 165-acre lagoon in Jackson Park. Because the designers thought that most park visitors would arrive by boat on the lakeside, an inlet and adjacent 200-foot (61-meter) pier formed the principal entrance to South Park. In inland <name type="place">Washington</name> Park, they found an opportunity for the creation of a large open meadow, which they called Southopen Green. The two parks were united by the Midway Plaisance,<ref target="#CH9-n37">37</ref>a linear band of lawns and shrubbery with a central canal that connected the water from the "mere" in <name type="place">Washington</name> Park with that of the Lagoon in Jackson Park. Defying the harsh lakefront climate, Olmsted saw the Lagoon as an opportunity to create an approximation of the tropical scenery he had admired on his travels in Louisana, thus combining "the fresh and healthy nature of the North with the restful, dreamy nature of the South."<ref target="#CH9-n38"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">38</hi></hi></ref>Not until twenty years later, when he was summoned to be the landscape design member of the planning team for the <name type="place">Chicago</name> World's Fair of <date when="1893">1893</date> on the site of Jackson and <name type="place">Washington</name> parks, did he have a chance to implement this and other elements of the design he had produced with Vaux.</p><p>This project was the last the two men designed together, for in <date when="1872">1872</date>, for reasons of mutual convenience, they dissolved their partnership. Vaux continued his career as a gifted practitioner of Romantic Ruskinian architecture until the vogue for Beaux-Arts Neoclassicism eclipsed the Picturesque style toward the end of the century. Olmsted, now fully confirmed in his own mind as a landscape architect, created a new firm in which he was joined first by his adopted stepson, John Charles Olmsted, and later by his son, Frederick Law Olmsted, Jr.</p><figure xml:id="fig-421"><graphic url="CH9_049.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.48. Plan for the <name type="place">Chicago</name> South Park Commission, by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux, <date when="1871">1871</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-422"><graphic url="CH9_050.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.49. Park System from the <name type="place">Boston</name> Common to Franklin Park&#x2014;Boston's Emerald Necklace&#x2014;by Frederick Law Olmsted, Olmsted &amp; Eliot, Landscape Architects. <date when="1894">1894</date></hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Boston's Emekald Necklace</hi></hi></head><p>As in other cities, citizen action in <name type="place">Boston</name> stimulated government response, and in <date when="1869">1869</date> the <name type="place">Massachusetts</name> General Court passed an act authorizing one large or several small parks. Some Bostonians spearheading<pb n="350"/><pb n="350" type="orig"/>the parks effort were impressed by comments made by landscape architect <name type="pname">Horace William Shaler <name type="place">Cleveland</name></name> (<date when="1814">1814</date>&#x2013;<date when="1900">1900</date>) of <name type="place">Chicago</name> to the effect that what <name type="place">Boston</name> needed was not a "central" park, but rather a surrounding greenbelt including drives and scenic areas for public use. On <date when="1870-02-25">February 25, 1870</date>, Olmsted lectured at the Lowell Institute on "Public Parks and the Enlargement of Towns," presciently anticipating large-scale urban growth and advocating a similar metropolitan vision. Five years of often heated public debate and several planning proposals ensued. A commission set up in <date when="1875">1875</date> solicited Olmsted's advice on site selection. From this beginning, which led to a series of commissions lasting the rest of his professional life, he was able to project a bold planning vision of parkway-linked parks: a metropolitan-scale "Emerald Necklace" (fig. 9.49).<ref target="#CH9-n39"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">39</hi></hi></ref></p><figure xml:id="fig-423"><graphic url="CH9_051.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.50. Meadow with Schoolmaster Hill, Franklin Park, <name type="place">West Roxbury</name>, c. <date when="1900">1900</date>, an example of the type of gently undulating rural scenery that Olmsted sought to provide as a means of preserving pastoral ideals within rapidly growing nineteenth-century industrial cities</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-424"><graphic url="CH9_052.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 9.51. Ellicott Arch, Franklin Park, <date when="1892">1892</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-425"><graphic url="CH9_053.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.52. Moraine Farm, Beverly, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>, open field, designed by Frederick Law Olmsted</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Working with Charles Sprague Sargent, the director of the Arnold Arboretum, Olmsted was able to effect the transfer and leaseback arrangements between Harvard University, the owner of the Arboretum, and the city, which allowed jointly funded improvements and operations on the 120-acre site, one of the gemstones of the necklace. The two men disagreed about ways to plant the public parkland next to the Arboretum in Brookline. Sargent, the botanist, favored a taxonomic approach and the use of native plants only, while Olmsted, the artist, felt that including exotic plants would enhance the effects of light and shade, gradations of color, contrasts in texture, and compositional arrangement of forms he envisioned. Olmsted, who saw botanical display as a perversion of the principles of park making, which he felt should always be directed toward creating broad stretches of naturalistic scenery, ironically found himself advocating a more diverse botanical palette than that of the professional botanist.</p> <p>In 500-acre Franklin Park, considered by Olmsted to be the principal jewel, where the natural terrain of West Roxbury gave him the opportunity to create a broad rolling meadow and a grade-separated circulation system that allowed pedestrians to approach it through handsome rustic arches, he achieved a good approximation of his scenic park ideal (figs. 9.50, 9.51). Now, in <date when="1884">1884</date>, with Vaux no longer at his side, he built these of natural stone boulders instead of the dressed and carved stone that made his former partner's arches in Central Park and Prospect Park works of ornamental architecture. Here the meadow was also conceived as a baseball field, with boulders for bleachers and a rustic changing area nearby. This is an early instance of sports permitted on an Olmsted park meadow, a harbinger of the future transformation by others in much less sensitive design terms of many existing Olmsted lawns and meadows into spaces for organized recreation.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Olmsted, Richardson, and Eliot</hi></hi></head><p>While Olmsted still nominally held the title of consulting landscape architect to the Parks Department, he was thoroughly disgusted by <name type="place">New York</name>'s political milieu, so in <date when="1881">1881</date>, he transferred his office and home to Brookline, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>. His friend and neighbor there was the noted architect Henry Hobson Richardson (<date when="1838">1838</date>&#x2013;<date when="1886">1886</date>), and during the five years before Richardson's death, the two had several opportunities for intensely sympathetic collaboration, in which Richardson's neo-Romanesque yet original style encouraged Olmsted's increasing boldness in the use of boulders and rough fieldstone. Olmsted still harbored a penchant for trailing vines and found the combination of these and massive rustic stone walls pleasing.</p><pb n="351"/><pb n="351" type="orig"/><p>At Moraine Farm, the estate of John C. Phillips in Beverly, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>, on the banks of Wenham Great Pond, he had the opportunity to design a 275acre American version of a <hi rend="italic">ferme orn&#x00E9;e</hi> where a beautiful hayfield with clumps of deciduous and evergreen trees at the edges performed the same aesthetic function as the Long Meadow in Prospect Park (fig. 9.52). Here, on the east side of the house designed by the Bostonian architects Peabody and Stearns and overlooking the pond, he built a long sinuous terrace banked by a retaining wall of natural boulders, beneath which masses of laurel and rhododendron cascade down to the edge of the water (fig. 9.53).</p><p>Olmsted was now the undisputed leader in the profession of landscape architecture in <name type="place">America</name>. His services were heavily in demand, and he found himself traveling back and forth across the country by train to serve a wide clientele, designing park systems for Rochester, <name type="place">New York</name>, and Louisville, Kentucky In <date when="1879">1879</date>, he assisted in preparing the report that led in <date when="1885">1885</date> to the scenic preservation of Niagara and of the abundant botanical diversity of Goat Island between the American and Canadian Falls. He and Vaux teamed up again to develop an environmentally sensitive plan that would allow visitors to fully appreciate this scenic wonder without the distraction of tawdry commercial development.</p><p>With his young partner, Charles Eliot, Olmsted was able to extend the concept of <name type="place">Boston</name>'s municipal park system to a broad metropolitan scale. Eliot, the son of the president of Harvard, was instrumental in forming the Trustees of Public Reservations (now known as the Trustees of Reservations), an early example of a conservation organization dedicated to preserving wilderness areas in <name type="place">New England</name>. In addition to small publicly accessible properties held by the Trustees, Eliot envisioned large reservations in the public domain, for which a metropolitan commission was needed. He worked tirelessly with Sylvester Baxter, a writer turned regional planner, to develop political consensus among the communities within and the jurisdictions outside the boundaries of the municipality of <name type="place">Boston</name> for a Metropolitan District to acquire and improve parkland within a 10-mile (16.1-kilometer) radius of the city. Their survey of the area took in the islands in the harbor, beaches, forests, three river basins, several hills, five ponds, and other sites they found desirable as nature preserves or suitable for public recreation.</p><figure xml:id="fig-426"><graphic url="CH9_054.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.53. East Terrace, Moraine Farm, Beverly, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>, estate of <name type="pname">John C. Phillips</name>, designed by Frederick Law Olmsted. c. <date when="1880">1880</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>The Board of Metropolitan Park Commissioners appointed under the <date when="1892">1892</date> act was created to a large degree as a result of their work. This Board read the Eliot-Baxter report and plan, which was published the following year. In it, Baxter outlined their recommendations for restoring tree cover, guiding real-estate development, reducing water pollution, making transportation accessible, and designing small local community playgrounds. Eliot's report, with accompanying maps and diagrams, summarized the area's physical and historical geography and described the opportunities awaiting the commission's subsequent actions in the well-watered and hilly glaciated terrain of metropolitan <name type="place">Boston</name>. Thus, as he neared the end of his active professional career, Olmsted was able to rejoice in the success of his young prot&#x00E9;g&#x00E9; in carrying forward his own peculiarly American mission of promoting civilization through landscape preservation. Tragically, Eliot's life was cut short by death only four years later. In addition, there were new forces at work in American society, seeking to promote civilization in more conspicuous ways.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Olmsted in a Neoclassical Context</hi></hi></head><p>The movement to shape cities according to the monumental model provided by <name type="place">Paris</name> and other European capitals emerged from the generation of architects after Vaux, who trained abroad in a variety of Neoclassical styles derived from the French Renaissance and its Italian models. These younger men converted some of the nation's growing industrial wealth into mansions for the wealthy and civic grandeur for the public at large. Among these was Richard Morris Hunt (<date when="1828">1828</date>&#x2013;<date when="1895">1895</date>), the first American of renown to design in the style called Beaux-Arts after the &#x00C9;cole des Beaux-Arts in <name type="place">Paris</name> where a number of aspiring architects from the United States went to study in the second half of the nineteenth century. Olmsted and Vaux were not happy when a newly formed Committee on Statuary, Fountains and Architectural Structures invited Hunt to propose alterations to the Arsenal in Central Park in <date when="1860">1860</date>; the Civil War caused these plans to be shelved for the duration. More upsetting was Hunt's proposal, drawn up at the committee's request, for a series of monumental Neoclassical gateways at the park's four southern entrances. Vaux's<pb n="352"/><pb n="352" type="orig"/>opposition persuaded the park commissioners not to construct these monumental entrances.</p><figure xml:id="fig-427"><graphic url="CH9_055.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.54. U.S. Capitol, Terrace on the west front, designed by Frederick Law Olmsted. <date when="1873">1873</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Olmsted felt that statuary in the park should be confined to the Mall and Bethesda Terrace, and he expressed his fear of other monumental Beaux-Arts architectural encroachments by Hunt on the park's pastoral landscape. Nevertheless, Olmsted was able to work within the context of a Neoclassical design vocabulary when necessary. In <date when="1873">1873</date>, he accepted the commission of the Senate Committee on Buildings and Grounds to design the 46 acres around the United States Capitol in <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name> In this case, it was obviously necessary to ignore his precept of fitting buildings inconspicuously into the landscape, as the chief purpose of the project was to heighten the monumentality and dignity of the nation's most important public building. In addition to banning Gardenesque effects, which he considered fussy distractions from this principal object, he built the massive terrace that forms a podium along the Capitol's north, south, and west sides and unifies the building with its surroundings (fig. 9.54).</p><p>In the two final commissions of his career, Olmsted worked directly with Beaux-Arts architects. In <date when="1888">1888</date>, twenty-five-year-old George <name type="place">Washington</name> Vanderbilt commissioned him to design the grounds at Biltmore, his estate near Asheville, North Carolina. Here Hunt was the architect of a palatial mansion resembling a French Renaissance <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau.</hi> Olmsted's plan encompassed 2,000 acres of mountainous landscape. Inasmuch as the site did not lend itself to becoming a park in the pastoral and Picturesque tradition, Olmsted recommended that Vanderbilt should devote most of it to scientific forestry. The millionaire eventually increased his holdings to 120,000 acres and hired America's first professional forester, Gifford Pinchot, who later became the founding head of the United States Forest Service. Olmsted also convinced Vanderbilt to create an arboretum.</p><p>At Biltmore, Olmsted's particular genius as a landscape designer expressed itself in the estate's road system: a 3-mile (4.8-kilometer) approach road, the borders of which he enhanced with "varied forms of vegetation... all consistent with the sensation of passing through the remote depths of a natural forest."<ref target="#CH9-n40"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">40</hi></hi></ref>Here, as in Central Park and elsewhere, he wanted to plant lush masses of many species of rhododendron and a rich variety of other woodland shrubs in order to create the "sense of the superabundant creative power, infinite resource, and liberality of Nature"<ref target="#CH9-n41"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">41</hi></hi></ref>that tropical scenery had always evoked in him. The long approach road at last brings the visitor, who has had no anticipatory view of what lies ahead, to a rectangular grassy esplanade, beyond which Hunt's immense <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> of Indiana limestone looms suddenly into view. At Moraine Farm, the view of the lake was not revealed until one passed through the house onto the terrace overlooking it; so, too, at Biltmore, Olmsted withheld the panoramic scenery of the Great Smokies with Mount Pisgah in the distance until one had passed through the house onto the terrace there. Thus, although more architecturally elaborate than the rustic terrace built earlier in <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>, the terrace at Biltmore serves the same purpose as a viewing platform for a heretofore concealed spectacle of nature at its most glorious.</p><p>At the same time that he worked at Biltmore, Olmsted became a member of the design team, headed by the architect <name type="pname">Daniel H. Burnham</name>, that was planning the World's Columbian Exposition of <date when="1893">1893</date> for <name type="place">Chicago</name>. This World's Fair, like the expositions organized first in <name type="place">England</name> and then in <name type="place">Paris</name> in the second half of the nineteenth century, was intended as an international showcase of the products of industry. But unlike the earlier fairs, which had produced technologically innovative structures&#x2014;notably the Crystal Palace and the Eiffel Tower&#x2014;Burnham and his Beaux-Arts-trained colleagues wished to put the architectural stamp of Neoclassical grandeur, rather than of modernity, upon this one. Olmsted was consulted on site selection and, with the assistance of his talented young prot&#x00E9;g&#x00E9; and partner Henry Sargent Codman, chose the still-unimproved site of Jackson Park. This gave him an opportunity to revisit the <date when="1871">1871</date> design he had prepared in partnership with Vaux. Now, however, it was necessary to adopt a much more pronounced orientation toward "gregarious" recreation, with the further understanding that, as at the United States Capitol, the grounds would showcase the buildings. The large lagoon he had planned twenty years earlier was still possible and desirable if<pb n="353"/><pb n="353" type="orig"/>it were treated as a series of waterbodies, some of which were to be given a geometric architectural treatment to complement the buildings. With their uniform cornice lines and white color, the largest of these made an impressive grouping around Olmsted's most conspicuous water feature, a long central basin with a canal leading to other parts of the lagoon system, each of which served as a watery foreground for another composition of fair buildings (fig. 9.55).</p><p>Still, Olmsted found an opportunity to provide relief from the noisy crowds and architectural grandiloquence of the fair in the wooded island in the center of the lagoon. There he tried within the short growing period before opening day to create an air of poetic mystery and the appearance of a natural bayou by establishing a rich aquatic vegetation and dense shoreline growth (fig. 9.56). Here, fair visitors could find a ramble of sinuous paths and the illusion of nature in the midst of the hubbub and excitement of the fair. Olmsted wished to keep the island free of structures, protesting when a music hall was contemplated in that location. Praising the achievement of the <name type="place">Chicago</name> World's Fair as the grounds were being completed, the writer on architecture, gardens, and landscape design, Mariana Griswold Van Rensselaer, told future visitors, "You will already know that much of the ground immediately beneath you was not even solid, ugly prairie, but treacherous marsh. And looking over this ground now&#x2014;here with its straight, stately, wide canals and architectonic terraces, and there with its irregularly-shaped lagoons and islands&#x2014;you will understand how a great artist like <name type="pname">Mr. Olmsted</name> can absolutely create in a way which almost equals Nature's own."<ref target="#CH9-n42"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">42</hi></hi></ref></p><figure xml:id="fig-428"><graphic url="CH9_056.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.55. Central Basin (Court of Honor), World's Columbian Exposition, <name type="place">Chicago</name>, designed by Frederick Law Olmsted in collaboration with Daniel Burnham. <date when="1893">1893</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-429"><graphic url="CH9_057.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 9.56. Lagoon and Island, World's Columbian Exposition, <name type="place">Chicago</name>, designed by Frederick Law Olmsted. <date when="1893">1893</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Olmsted, overworked and ailing, was now called upon to add his influential voice to those opposing a speedway in Central Park, one of many proposed encroachments over the years. A six-month holiday abroad with his daughter and son for the purpose of regaining his health gave him the opportunity to revisit with renewed delight the English countryside he had first admired as a young man. At the same time, he deplored the contemporary Victorian obsession with horticulture. As we shall read in Chapter Eleven, a controversy was raging between Sir Reginald Blomfield, author of <hi rend="italic">The Formal Garden in <name type="place">England</name></hi> and proponent of a return to geometrical<pb n="354"/><pb n="354" type="orig"/>planning principles, and William Robinson, the ardent foe of topiary and ornamental floral bedding-out and prolific author of <hi rend="italic">The English Flower Garden, The Wild Garden,</hi> and other books and articles championing herbaceous borders artfully composed of casually intermingled perennial plants. Although the trailing vines recommended by Robinson exactly suited Olmsted's taste and he found <hi rend="italic">The Wild Garden</hi> useful in selecting plants for such places as the Ramble in Central Park, he was now more convinced than ever that he had been right to take what was useful from the writings of Gilpin and Price and to have developed an American landscape style emphasizing broad, overarching scenic themes. He even made a pilgrimage to the church at Boldre where Gilpin had been vicar, and he traveled along the route beside the river Wye that Gilpin had described in one of his books. Visiting <name type="place">Paris</name>, where he examined the grounds of the exposition of <date when="1889">1889</date>, he hoped that in <name type="place">Chicago</name> the "petty effects and frippery" of ornamental floral display would be avoided. He admired, however, the "fitness for their purposes" of the buildings left in the wake of the <name type="place">Paris</name> fair and expressed reservation about those of the White City, as people called the collection of temporary buildings made of staff&#x2014;plaster and fiber laid over timber forms&#x2014;then rising on the shores of Lake Michigan. He hoped that the <name type="place">Chicago</name> buildings were "not going to look too assuming of architectural stateliness and to be overloaded with sculptural and other efforts for grandeur and grandiloquentpomp."<ref target="#CH9-n43"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">43</hi></hi></ref></p><figure xml:id="fig-430"><graphic url="CH9_058.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.57. Boathouse, Prospect Park, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, <name type="place">New York</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Stanford White</name> and <name type="pname">Frank J. Helmie</name>. <date when="1905">1905</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>But for now, thanks to the influence of the <name type="place">Chicago</name> World's Fair, the field belonged to Daniel Burnham and other Beaux-Arts practitioners. The achievements of Calvert Vaux were overshadowed by these architects, and the former partners' belief in the overriding therapeutic and spiritual values of naturalistic landscapes in an urban setting was denied by the Gilded Age's desire for monumental grandeur. While he still held the position of landscape architect to the board in charge of <name type="place">New York</name> City parks, Vaux had protested against the design of a speedway planned now for the edge of the Harlem River, but his objections were high-handedly brushed aside, and he died under mysterious circumstances in <date when="1895">1895</date>. Olmsted fell victim to dementia, retired from public life, and was confined during the five years preceding his death in <date when="1903">1903</date> in the McLean Hospital at Waverly, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>, where he had designed the grounds. But before his intellectual powers were eclipsed, he had seen clearly that the Beaux-Arts architects' appetite for monumentality was antithetical to the older ideal of a republican <name type="place">America</name> that he and Vaux had tried to embody in their parks.</p><p>In <date when="1894">1894</date>, Stanford White (<date when="1853">1853</date>&#x2013;<date when="1906">1906</date>), the most fashionable Beaux Arts architect in the generation after Hunt, was approached to build a tennis house in Prospect Park. It was not constructed until <date when="1909">1909</date> by his former associate, <name type="pname">Frank J. Helmle</name> (<date when="1868">1868</date>&#x2013;<date when="1939">1939</date>), also the architect in <date when="1905">1905</date> of the Prospect Park Boathouse (fig. 9.57). Designed after the Library of St. Mark in <name type="place">Venice</name> by Jacopo d'Antonio Tatti, called Sansovino (<date when="1486">1486</date>&#x2013;<date when="1570">1570</date>), the Boathouse, though handsome in its own right like the Tennis House, is alien to the spirit<pb n="355"/><pb n="355" type="orig"/>of the park's rustic and rural-seeming landscape. Further aggrandizing what was intended to be a pastoral refuge from city life, the firm of McKim, Mead and White carried out in Prospect Park what Hunt had failed to do in Central Park. Here they erected three monumental Neoclassical entrances (fig. 9.58). Not unreasonably, Olmsted felt that White and his Beaux Arts colleagues were "trying to establish the rule of motives that are at war with those that ruled in the original laying out of <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> Park."<ref target="#CH9-n44"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">44</hi></hi></ref>All the same, instructed by <name type="place">France</name>, American tastemakers of the time were committed to the values of opulence expressed by the later term denoting the period as the Gilded Age, and the emulation of Europen urban grandeur was well established as a dominant motive underlying civic beautification. Instructed by <name type="place">France</name> in another regard as well, they were also embarked on a course of Industrial Age urban modernity.</p><figure xml:id="fig-431"><graphic url="CH9_059.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">9.58. The Soldiers' and Sailors' Memorial Arch, Grand Army Plaza, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, <name type="place">New York</name>, designed by <name type="pname">John H. Duncan</name>, architect, with architectural embellishment by <name type="pname">McKim</name>, <name type="pname">Mead</name> and <name type="pname">White</name> and sculpture by <name type="pname">Frederick MacMonnies</name>, <name type="pname">Thomas Eakins</name>, and <name type="pname">William O'Donovan</name>. <date when="1889">1889</date>&#x2013;<date when="1901">1901</date></hi></figDesc></figure></div></div><div type="section"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes foR Chapter Nine</hi></hi></head><note xml:id="CH09-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p> The term <hi rend="italic">ecological</hi> as used to describe the relationship between organisms and their respective environments was coined in <date when="1866">1866</date> by Ernst Haeckel, a German zoologist, in <hi rend="italic">Generelle Morphologie der Organismen.</hi> See David Lowenthal, <hi rend="italic">George Perkins Marsh: Prophet of Conservation</hi> (Seattle: University of <name type="place">Washington</name> Press, <date when="2000">2000</date>), ch. 13, p. 283, and footnote 41.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p> I am indebted to Melanie Louise Simo for her good analysis of Loudon's career and influence. See Melanie Simo, <hi rend="italic">Loudon and the Landscape: From Country Seat to Metropolis</hi> (<name type="place">New Haven</name>: Yale University Press, <date when="1988">1988</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Bernard de Jussieu</name> (<date when="1699">1699</date>&#x2013;<date when="1777">1777</date>) and his nephew Antoine-Laurent de Jussieu (<date when="1748">1748</date>&#x2014;<date when="1836">1836</date>), the principal competitors of Linnaeus, based their system of plant classification on the physical forms of plants rather than on their reproductive structures.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p> <hi rend="italic">Gardener's Magazine,</hi> vol. XVI (<date when="1840">1840</date>), p. 620. As discussed in Chapter Thirteen, Christopher Tunnard, champion of the modern garden, developed a similar theory whereby elements were to be composed asymmetrically along an invisible axis so as to achieve "occult balance." See Christopher Tunnard, <hi rend="italic">Gardens in the Modern Landscape</hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: The Architectural Press, <date when="1938">1938</date>), p.92.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p> See <name type="pname">Hazel Conway</name>, <hi rend="italic">People's Parks: The Design and Development of Victorian Parks in Britain</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>: <name type="place">Cambridge</name> University Press, <date when="1991">1991</date>), p. 229. I am indebted to this excellent source for this and much other valuable information regarding the early public parks movement in Great Britain.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 48.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">David Schuyler</name>, <hi rend="italic">Apostle of Taste: <name type="pname">Andrew Jackson Downing</name> <date when="1815">1815</date>&#x2013;<date when="1852">1852</date></hi>(<name type="place">Baltimore</name>: The Johns Hopkins Press, <date when="1996">1996</date>). I am indebted to this historian's intimate knowledge of nineteenth-century landscape design and designers in the following discussion of Downing and the development of the "middle landscape," the extension of the metropolis into rural areas with the creation of the first suburbs, and a new architectural vocabulary of suburban villa design. See also <name type="pname">Judith K. Major</name>, <hi rend="italic">To Live in the New World: <name type="pname">A. J. Downing</name> and American Landscape Gardening</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: The MIT Press, <date when="1997">1997</date>) for a good discussion of how Downing adapted contemporary English design principles and horticultural practices to the conditions of American society and the character of its natural landscape in the first half of the nineteenth century.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Andrew Jackson Downing</name>, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on the Theory and Practice of Landscape Gardening,</hi> 6th ed. (<name type="place">New York</name>: A. 0. Moore &amp; Co., <date when="1859">1859</date>), p. 25.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p> <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Theory and Practice of Landscape Gardening,</hi> p. 65.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 59.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 60.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 120.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p> <hi rend="italic">Rural Essays</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Levitt</name> and <name type="pname">Allen</name>, <date when="1856">1856</date>), pp. 147&#x2013;53 <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi></p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p> As quoted in Schuyler, <hi rend="italic">Apostle of Taste,</hi> p. 192.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p> As the garden historian John Dixon Hunt points out, <name type="pname">John Claudius Loudon</name> was the first to apply the term <hi rend="italic">landscape architecture</hi> to the work of landscape designers. In <date when="1840">1840</date>, Loudon republished Repton's <hi rend="italic">Observations on the Theory and Practice of Landscape Gardening</hi> (<date when="1803">1803</date>) under the title <hi rend="italic">The Landscape Gardening and Landscape Architecture of the Late Humphrey Repton.</hi> See Hunt, <hi rend="italic">Greater Perfections</hi> (<name type="place">Philadelphia</name>: University of Pennsylvania Press, <date when="1999">1999</date>), p. 217. But neither Repton nor Loudon after him seems to have employed the term in presenting themselves to clients. Repton had christened himself "Landscape Gardener" upon entering professional practice, and Loudon considered himself to be primarily an agronomist, botanist, horticulturalist, and author. Olmsted and Vaux wished to distinguish between their kind of work&#x2014; which often involved extensive engineering and significant reformation of the land to produce a naturalistic effect akin to that of rural scenery&#x2014;and Loudon's kind of ornamental horticulture and that of Repton late in his career when he deemed appropriate a Gardenesque treatment in areas adjacent to the house. Nevertheless, the notion that they were <hi rend="italic">artists,</hi> not simply engineers or administrators, was important to them. In discussing the use of the title with Olmsted, who apparently objected to it as being too vague, Vaux said as they were about to reenter partnership in <date when="1865">1865</date>, "I have always liked the title Landscape Architect because&#x2014;the specialty was fairly embodied. A title that could as easily be transferred to an inartistic public work is not as satisfactory.... The term Landscape Architect does not suit you, well I am sorry for it. I think it is <hi rend="italic">the</hi> title. We want to set art ahead and make it <hi rend="italic">command</hi> its position, administration, management, funds, commission, popularity and everything else&#x2014;then we have a tangible something to stand on." (See <name type="pname">Charles C. McLaughlin</name> <hi rend="italic">et al. The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted,</hi> vol. V, pp.<pb n="356"/><pb n="356" type="orig"/>363,373&#x2013;74.) The earliest instance of their use of <hi rend="italic">landscape architect</hi> as a professional title came in <date when="1860">1860</date> when they were so described in their appointment to advise on laying out streets in northern Manhattan. <hi rend="italic">(See The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted,</hi> vol. Ill, p. 267, note 1.) Olmsted deferred to Vaux's preference for the term when they reestablished their partnership in <date when="1865">1865</date> as Olmsted, Vaux, &amp; Company, Landscape Architects. At this time, they were reappointed by the Executive Committee of Central Park to serve as "Landscape Architects to the Board."</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p> For the following discussion of landscapes of memory, those containing monuments and memorial grave sites, and of the movement from burying ground to rural cemetery I am particularly indebted to Blanche Linden-Ward, <hi rend="italic">Silent City on a Hill: Landscapes of Memory and <name type="place">Boston</name>'s Mount Auburn Cemetery</hi> (Columbus: <name type="place">Ohio</name> State University Press, <date when="1989">1989</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p> Circular letter, <date when="1823-07">July 1823</date>, as quoted in Linden-Ward, <hi rend="italic">Silent City on a Hill,</hi> p. 124.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p> The developer of the Quincy granite quarries, Gridley Bryant, was instrumental in building the first railway in <name type="place">America</name> in <date when="1827">1827</date> in order to transport the blocks of stone to the shore for transport to the monument site in Charlestown near <name type="place">Boston</name></p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">William Wordsworth</name>, "Essay upon Epitaphs." <hi rend="italic">Friend</hi> 25(Feb. <date when="1810">1810</date>): 408. Reprinted in <hi rend="italic">The Excursion: A Poem</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">C. S. Francis</name>, <date when="1850">1850</date>). Quoted in Linden-Ward, <hi rend="italic">Silent City on a Hill,</hi> p. 61.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">20.</hi></seg><p> Dearborn, who had no further direct involvement at Mount Auburn, went on to help found and design in <date when="1846">1846</date> another rural burial ground in the <name type="place">Boston</name> area, the Forest Hills Cemetery in Roxbury.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">21.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">James Smillie</name>, drawings, and <name type="pname">Cornelia W. Walter</name>, description, <hi rend="italic">Mount Auburn</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">R. Martin</name>, <date when="1851">1851</date>), p. 18.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">22.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Andrew Jackson Downing</name>, "Public Cemeteries and Public Gardens" (<date when="1848-07">July 1848</date>) in <hi rend="italic">Rural Essays,</hi> p. 157.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n23" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">23.</hi></seg><p> When Olmsted visited <name type="place">England</name> for the second time in <date when="1859">1859</date>, he corresponded with <name type="pname">William Jackson Hooker</name> (<date when="1785">1785</date>&#x2013;<date when="1865">1865</date>), botanist and director of the Royal Botanical Gardens at Kew, deploring how "the old simple formal fashion of gardening... [and] the peculiar landscape beauty of old English places... is sacrificed to botanic beauty and variety and the interest of frequent contrasts &amp; surprises." (Letter, c. <date when="1859-11-29">November 29, 1859</date>, in <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted,</hi> vol. Ill, ed.) <name type="pname">Charles C. McLaughlin</name>, <name type="pname">Charles E. Beveridge</name> and <name type="pname">David Schuyler</name> (<name type="place">Baltimore</name>: The Johns Hopkins University Press, <date when="1983">1983</date>, p. 232). In the essay "The Spoils of the Park," written in <date when="1882-02">February, 1882</date>, after he had left <name type="place">New York</name>, Olmsted expressed in even stronger terms his aversion to the Gardenesque: "During the last twenty years Europe has been swept by a mania for sacrificing natural scenery to coarse manufactures of brilliant and gaudy decoration under the name of specimen gardening: bedding, carpet, embroider, and ribbon gardening, or other terms suitable to the housefurnishing and millinery trades. It was a far madder contagion than the tulip-mania, or the morus-multicaulis fever of our youth." In <hi rend="italic">Forty Years of Landscape Architecture: Being the Professional Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted, Senior,</hi> ed. <name type="pname">Frederick Law Olmsted</name>, Jr., and <name type="pname">Theodora Kimball</name> (<date when="1922">1922</date>; reissued <date when="1970">1970</date>, <name type="place">Bronx</name>, <name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Benjamin Blom</name>, Inc.), p. 143.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n24" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">24.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Frederick Law Olmsted</name>, <hi rend="italic">Walks and Talks of an American Farmer in <name type="place">England</name></hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">George P. Putnam</name>, <date when="1852">1852</date>), p. 87. As an Anglo-American experiencing a sense almost of homecoming, Olmsted is rhapsodic about his first encounter with the English landscape. He continues, with details of sensory appreciation, describing a scene that might have been a painting by Constable: "We stood dumb-stricken by its loveliness, as, from the bleak April and bare boughs we had left at home, broke upon us that English May&#x2014;sunny, leafy, blooming May&#x2014;in an English lane; with hedges, English hedges, hawthorn hedges, all in blossom; homely old farm-houses, quaint stables, and haystacks; the old church spire over the distant trees; the mild sun beaming through the watery atmosphere, and all so quiet&#x2014;the only sounds the hum of bees and the crisp grass-tearing of a silkenskinned, real (unimported) Herford cow over the hedge."</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n25" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">25.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 79.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n26" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">26.</hi></seg><p> Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux, <hi rend="italic">Description of a Plan for the Improvement of the Central Park: "Greensward" in Landscape into Cityscape: Frederick Law Olmsted's Plans for a Greater <name type="place">New York</name> City,</hi> ed. Albert Fein (Ithaca, <name type="place">New York</name>: Cornell University Press, <date when="1967">1967</date>), p. 71.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n27" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">27.</hi></seg><p> According to Scripture, "Now there is at Jerusalem by the sheep market a pool, which is called in the Hebrew tongue Bethesda, having five porches. In these lay a great multitude of impotent folk of blind, halt, withered, waiting for the moving of the water. For an angel went down at a certain season into the pool, and troubled the water: whosoever then first after the troubling of the water stepped in was made whole of whatsoever disease he had." John 5:2&#x2013;4, <hi rend="italic">The Holy Bible,</hi> Authorized (King James) Version.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n28" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">28.</hi></seg><p> Letter from Calvert Vaux to Frederick Law Olmsted, <date when="1865-05-12">May 12, 1865</date>, in <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted,</hi> vol. V, ed. <name type="pname">Charles C. McLaughlin</name>, <name type="pname">Victoria Post Ranney</name> (<name type="place">Baltimore</name>: The Johns Hopkins Press, <date when="1990">1990</date>), p. 364.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n29" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">29.</hi></seg><p> Letter from Frederick Law Olmsted to Calvert Vaux, <date when="1865-06-08">June 8, 1865</date>, in <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted,</hi> vol. V, p. 390.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n30" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">30.</hi></seg><p> "Report of the Landscape Architects and Superintendents" (<date when="1870-01">January 1870</date>), <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted:</hi> vol. VI, ed. <name type="pname">Charles C. McLaughlin</name>, <name type="pname">David Schuyler</name> and <name type="pname">Jane Turner Censer</name>, p. 357.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n31" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">31.</hi></seg><p> For a detailed description of the sensory experience of entering the Long Meadow through the Endale Arch, see Tony Hiss, <hi rend="italic">The Experience of Place</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Alfred A. Knopf</name>, <date when="1990">1990</date>), pp. 28&#x2013;36.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n32" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">32.</hi></seg><p> Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux, "Report of the Landscape Architects and Superintendents to the President of the Board of Commissioners of Prospect Park, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> (<date when="1868">1868</date>)" in Fein, <hi rend="italic">Landscape into Cityscape,</hi> p. 153.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n33" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">33.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 151.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n34" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">34.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 158.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n35" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">35.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 155.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n36" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">36.</hi></seg><p> Quoted without citation in Victoria Post Ranney, "Olmsted in <name type="place">Chicago</name>" (<name type="place">Chicago</name>: The Open Lands Project, <date when="1972">1972</date>), p. 27.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n37" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">37.</hi></seg><p> The term <hi rend="italic">plaisance</hi> was used by Olmsted to denote a landscape with paths and grassy areas defined by shrub-planted borders, a part of a park intended for picnicking and strolling during daylight hours but one that, because of security issues posed by its dense plantings, was fenced and closed at night See <hi rend="italic">Frederick Law Olmsted Papers, Supplementary Series,</hi> vol. 1, p. 218.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n38" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">38.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 28</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n39" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">39.</hi></seg><p> Cynthia Zaitzevsky is the author of the definitive study of Olmsted's creation of the <name type="place">Boston</name> park system. See Cynthia Zaitzevsky, <hi rend="italic">Frederick Law Olmsted and the <name type="place">Boston</name> Park System</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, <date when="1982">1982</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n40" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">40.</hi></seg><p> Frederick Law Olmsted to <name type="pname">George W. Vanderbilt</name>, <date when="1889-07-12">July 12, 1889</date>, as quoted in <name type="pname">Charles E. Beveridge</name> and <name type="pname">Paul Rocheleau</name>, <hi rend="italic">Frederick Law Olmsted: Designing the American Landscape</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Rizzoli, <date when="1995">1995</date>), p. 226.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n41" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">41.</hi></seg><p> Letter to Ignaz Anton Pilat (<date when="1820">1820</date>&#x2013;<date when="1870">1870</date>), head gardener of Central Park, <date when="1863-09-26">September 26, 1863</date>, in McLaughlin <hi rend="italic">et al. The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted,</hi> vol. V, p. 85.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n42" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">42.</hi></seg><p> Mariana Griswold Van Rensselaer, "The Artistic Triumph of the Fair-Builders" in <hi rend="italic">Accents as Well as Broad Effects: Writings on Architecture, Landscape, and the Environment, <date when="1876">1876</date>&#x2013;<date when="1925">1925</date>,</hi> ed. <name type="pname">David Gebhard</name> (<name type="place">Berkeley</name>: University of <name type="place">California</name> Press, <date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 71.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n43" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">43.</hi></seg><p> According to <name type="pname">Charles E. Beveridge</name>, editor of Olmsted's papers, this quotation comes from a "letter with no salutation or date, but internal evidence indicates that Olmsted wrote it to his partners John Charles Olmsted and Henry Sargent Codman in April of <date when="1892">1892</date>." Letter to the author, <date when="2000-01-17">January 17, 2000</date>.</p></note><note xml:id="CH09-n44" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">44.</hi></seg><p> Letter from Frederick Law Olmsted to <name type="pname">William A. Stiles</name>, <date when="1895-03-10">March 10, 1895</date>. Citation courtesy of <name type="pname">Charles E. Beveridge</name>, letter to the author, <date when="2000-01-17">January 17, 2000</date>.</p></note></div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>