<div type="chapter">
<pb n="357"/>
<pb n="357" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER TEN INDUSTRIAL AGE CIVILIZATION: BIRTH OF THE MODERN CITY, BEAUX-ARTS AMERICA, AND NATIONAL PARKS</hi></head>
<figure xml:id="fig-432">
<graphic url="CH10_001.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p>The force that has driven modernism and postmodernism as much as the cultural currents and countercurrents running through them&#x2014;the force that has informed all philosophy, politics, eco-<lb/>
nomics, sociology, and art since the last half of the nineteenth cen-<lb/>
tury&#x2014;is machine technology.<ref target="#CH10-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref>It has injected into human culture unprecedented elements of power and speed, which have greatly accelerated the pace of change as well as the pace of life. Machine technology has offered innumerable benefits, and it has also focused attention on the processes of production rather than on its ends.</p>
<p>In examining designed landscapes of the past 150 years, we must continually reckon with their technological infrastructures and the extent to which they are informed by a machine-age men-<lb/>
tality. This is true even when they were created to express opposi-<lb/>
tion to the Industrial Age. Machine technology and human attitudes toward the machine&#x2014;whether celebratory, ambivalent, or con-<lb/>
demnatory&#x2014;provide an ineluctable cultural context that has pow-<lb/>
erfully shaped landscape design in modern times.</p>
<p>The nineteenth century was, generally speaking, an optimistic age. It is true that the enormous stresses associated with acceler-<lb/>
ating scientific discovery, which increasingly undermined religious conviction, and even faith, in the purpose of the rationalist scien-<lb/>
tific enterprise itself, created a sense of unease. Emerson may have darkly intuited the consequences of runaway technology when he complained that "things are in the saddle and ride mankind," but his transcendentalist philosophy nevertheless envisioned nature as a positive, spiritually nourishing force, and he shared with other early witnesses to the Industrial Age the sanguine hope that moder-<lb/>
nity would prove beneficial to humankind.</p>
<p>In our discussion of Goethe's important insights into the dynamics of Romantic culture in the eighteenth century, we saw his attempt to reconcile its tenets with those of classicism as well as his conviction, caustically expressed by Mephistopheles, that pan-<lb/>
theistic worship of nature and spiritual seduction by its idyllic charms deflected human potential from its full expression. In <hi rend="italic">Faust: Part II,</hi> written between <date when="1825">1825</date> and <date when="1831">1831</date>, Goethe sensed the new sources of physical and human energy that were being released by the Industrial Revolution. Ties with history, both personal and soci-<lb/>
etal, had to be severed if <hi rend="italic">progress</hi>&#x2014;the watchword of industrial cap-<lb/>
italism&#x2014;was to occur. Faust, having destroyed his love, Gretchen, in Part I because he could no longer inhabit the traditional society she represents, is offered in Part II an intoxicant more potent than sex or even love: power. This is not the power of kings, but rather the power of industrial progress. It implies the right to challenge nature and alter culture for socially beneficial ends.</p>
<p>In Part II, Faust assumes the role of Nietzsche's Superman, becoming a developer capable of confronting mighty natural forces and traditional folkways and settlement patterns in the act of build-<lb/>
ing and destroying. His vision is that of the engineer; he will har-<lb/>
ness capital and labor for a giant coastal reclamation project, erecting dams and digging canals, "To hold the lordly ocean from the shore/To set the watery waste new boundary lines," in order to create a dynamic new economy for the ultimate benefit of humankind. As in the American myth of Paul Bunyan, the intrepid pioneers who assist Faust in this mighty work are emigrants from Gretchen's Old World of familiar and constrained village life. In the process of their labor, they are enlarged; they become bold actors in the heroic drama of conquering and subduing nature.</p>
<p>Goethe foresaw the Industrial Age and the social freedom it would engender, but he also saw the tragic implications of its often inhuman disregard of people's lives. There was a price to be paid for economic efficiency in terms of physical and emotional disloca-<lb/>
tion. Not only did human life become less laborious with the advent of industrialization, it also became more impersonal. The rural round gave way to urbanism and a culture based on new concepts
<pb n="358"/>
<pb n="358" type="orig"/>
of time and space. People were no longer tied to the pastoral rhythms of the seasons or boundaries of daily movement circum-<lb/>
scribed by wind-filled sails, the stamina of horses, and human walk-<lb/>
ing distances. Movement is one of the imperatives of power. Machine-facilitated personal mobility and speed are among mod-<lb/>
ernism's premier values. There is a hurried character to modern times that distinguishes them from any other age.</p>
<p>Rapid change is another hallmark of modernity. Faust can no longer go back to the wellspring of childhood but is doomed to rest-<lb/>
less forward motion, forever set upon the course of modernity with its unending cycles of change in which only novelty and invention hold meaning. The paradox of power is that everything is provi-<lb/>
sional, in flux; progress depends upon the willing and unsentimen-<lb/>
tal sacrifice of what has gone before, for each new development will inevitably be discredited.</p>
<p>Cities, especially, became increasingly machinelike in appear-<lb/>
ance, and the nature of everyday life was irreversibly altered as eas-<lb/>
ily purchased, mass-produced commodities and new building technologies made it possible to discard, replace, and improve the old or obsolete. No longer was the built environment the result of the muscular labor of humans and animals, and no longer were the articles of daily life&#x2014;pots and pans, tools and utensils, carriages and wagons, clothing and furniture&#x2014; crafted by hand. More peo-<lb/>
ple now lived in structures erected with the aid of machinery and consisting of many machine-made parts, cooked with factory-built appliances, ate their meals on factory wares, dressed in industrially produced clothing, and purchased inexpensive mass-produced clocks to help them fit their daily routine to industrial work hours and transportation schedules. A new temporal commodity, leisure, one of the outcomes of the regimented industrial work week, made possible new forms of recreation with important consequences for landscape design.</p>
<p>To accommodate large-scale population growth in the second half of the nineteenth century, major cities&#x2014;notably, <name type="place">Paris</name>, <name type="place">Lon-<lb/>
don</name>, and Vienna&#x2014;began to alter urban form through industrial technology, creating new transportation arteries to accelerate vehic-<lb/>
ular movement and employing new kinds of materials and engi-<lb/>
neering solutions to increase building scale and extend the range of construction possibilities. Old royal parks were opened to the pub-<lb/>
lic, and new people's parks were created as recreational leisure became for middle and working classes alike an antidote to machine-<lb/>
age urban stress and as increased leisure became one of the fruits of mechanization. Because military tactics now rendered such urban defenses completely obsolete, ancient walls continued to be torn down and the land they had occupied turned into wide boulevards. Thus ungirdled, the growing city also became more porous; dense old neighborhoods were now penetrated by the straight new thor-<lb/>
oughfares designed to facilitate movement and commerce.</p>
<p>The changes revealed different classes of people to one another as enigmatic, but interesting, strangers. The curious tried to imagine these others' lives. Baudelaire, the poet supremely aware of <name type="place">Paris</name> in transition, writes of the "ant-seething city, city full of dreams," affirming a new and terrible kind of beauty found "in sin-<lb/>
uous folds of cities old and grim, where all things, even horror, turn to grace" as he observed the perplexed valor of the denizens of Old <name type="place">Paris</name> in the face of so much tremendous change. The epitome of the <hi rend="italic">fl&#x00E2;neur,</hi> he wrote poems about crones and coquettes, the soul-<lb/>
penetrating glances of strangers, the lives hitherto hidden from view and now exposed, all simultaneously occurring as rich and poor moved and mingled anonymously in the new urban milieu. There was something both frightening and thrilling in the possi-<lb/>
bility of these fleeting encounters.</p>
<p>Cosmopolitan urbanism implied a rejection of tradition. Like Faust, one was prepared to sacrifice past attachments and even moral scruples for technique, expediency, and efficiency as well as for intellectual adventure, sensory experience, and artistic self-<lb/>
expression. Personal experience came to be seen as a form of wealth, encouraging people to push to the limits of their abilities, energy, capital resources, and available time as they attempted to turn the material world to increasing advantage. Thus had the forces of Romanticism, nurtured by Rousseau's philosophy, proclaimed new moral autonomy for the individual.</p>
<p>The philosopher Immanuel Kant (<date when="1724">1724</date>&#x2013;<date when="1804">1804</date>), though cer-<lb/>
tainly no Romantic of the <hi rend="italic">Sturm und Drang</hi> school, had above his desk a picture of Rousseau. Kant believed passionately in the unfet-<lb/>
tered human will and the individual's right to choose a personal course of moral action. He was therefore sympathetic to the tenets of the American and French Revolutions&#x2014;at least before the Reign of Terror repressively stifled diversity of political opinion in France&#x2014;because these great public manifestations of Romanti-<lb/>
cism vested authority not in a monarch, however benevolent, but in the people. Human beings, in Kant's view, were not to be con-<lb/>
sidered as passive creatures in a world where everything was pre-<lb/>
ordained by God, natural science, and inherited systems of government. Kant took the position that the human mind bestows upon the universe a sense of order. This was quite different from the attitude of earlier philosophers such as Descartes or Aristotle, who thought of the mind as an instrument for discerning the estab-<lb/>
lished order of the universe by empirical means. The powerful intel-<lb/>
lectual and moral freedom granted individuals by Kantian philosophy was paralleled by the rising tide of democratization among nation-states and the attempt to create human environ-<lb/>
ments through political processes involving governmental machin-<lb/>
ery designed for collective decision making.</p>
<p>In this light we may observe how, beginning in the eighteenth century and accelerating with the French Revolution, cities became increasingly the domain of the people, their form no longer dic-<lb/>
tated by royal policy and aristocratic privilege even when, as in the case of Second Empire <name type="place">Paris</name>, their transformation was accom-<lb/>
plished by imperial fiat and state authority. As old cities were being torn apart and their social contents rendered visible, there arose a new political awareness, which was nourished by broad readership of daily newspapers sold on the street. The streets that were designed as a deterrent to revolutionary mobs and as parade routes where marching bands elicited emotions of patriotic pride were also upon occasion the arenas of violent social protest. Ordinarily, however, they served as the lively theater of daily life as increasing numbers of people perambulated and an ever-growing segment of society was able to purchase the growing quantities of factory-pro-<lb/>
duced merchandise appearing in shop windows.</p>
<pb n="359"/>
<pb n="359" type="orig"/>
<p><name type="place">Paris</name>, the first avowedly modern city, not only stimulated a great surge of strolling in its new boulevards but also pro-<lb/>
vided parks as special places where leisure could be spent. In the works of the Impressionists when the city is their subject we may observe the pleased wonder with which Parisians embraced the transformations that were occurring (fig. 10.1). Intimate emotions were no longer veiled from view; in the industrial city personal and public life had become fused into one. The con-<lb/>
stant movement in the streets, with the opportunities for peo-<lb/>
ple-watching and serendipitous sociability thus provided, and the display of commodities and luxury goods in sidewalk stalls and behind plate glass windows made them intensely interesting. Sud-<lb/>
denly all was in motion, and all had become a source of spectacle and excitement. Everything, even&#x2014;or perhaps especially&#x2014;one-<lb/>
self, was on display.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-433">
<graphic url="CH10_002.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.1. Jean B&#x00E9;raud, <hi rend="italic">Outside the Vaudeville Theater, <name type="place">Paris</name>.</hi> c. <date when="1885">1885</date>. Private collection. Here the raised sidewalk is the domain of the boulevardier, the <hi rend="italic">flaneur</hi> the shopper, and the theater goer. New features of the <name type="place">Paris</name> urban scene are the columnar kiosks for posters advertising cultural attractions, the numerous street and building lights, and the plate-glass windows.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The notion of the city as an object of formal presentation and symbolical representation, an architectural artifact enjoying the pres-<lb/>
tige formerly accorded the court, an urban organism to be concep-<lb/>
tualized in its entirety and ornamented proudly was an eighteenth-century phenomenon. The St. Petersburg of Peter the Great and <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, the federal capital Pierre L'Enfant planned for the new United States, were monumental cities built according to these intentions (see figs. 6.44,6.54). The intentions of founders, however, are often disregarded by subsequent generations and most cities in any case are conceived pragmatically rather than grandly, as serviceable places for conducting business and meeting the needs of daily life. Nevertheless, prosperity breeds philanthropy, civic pride, and the desire to emulate what is deemed best. Such was the case in Gilded Age <name type="place">America</name>, the period following the Civil War when most cities built their major cultural institutions and parks. The "White City" that rose on the banks of Lake Michigan in <date when="1893">1893</date> set the course of architecture and urban planning firmly in the direc-<lb/>
tion of monumental grandeur. Like Haussmann's <name type="place">Paris</name>, which cov-<lb/>
ered its new Industrial Age infrastructure with a neoclassical architectural veneer, the American city with which it was contem-<lb/>
porary now sought to cloak itself with monumental dignity. Not surprisingly, the model for this effort was <name type="place">Paris</name> itself. Architects and landscape architects trained at the &#x00C9;cole des Beaux-Arts carried for-<lb/>
ward the tenets of the City Beautiful Movement, a two-decade cam-<lb/>
paign to aggrandize American cities with heroic sculpture, noble architecture, spacious boulevards, and handsome public spaces. Without the backing of a monarchical regime like that of Napoleon III or a powerful public servant such as Haussmann to finance and forcefully administer a large array of coordinated capital construc-<lb/>
tion projects, most City Beautiful plans were only fragmentarily real-<lb/>
ized. In <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, which enjoyed special status as the nation's capital, however, a congressional commission was formed to oversee a comprehen-<lb/>
sive plan, resulting in the clearance of obstructions from the Mall and its realignment and extension, the construction of the Lincoln and Jefferson Memorials, and the building, after much debate, of a scenic parkway for motorists in the Rock Creek valley.</p>
<p>Machine mobility, which first made cities such as <name type="place">Paris</name> tourist meccas, created new accessibility to sparsely tenanted wild landscapes as well. In <name type="place">Amer-<lb/>
ica</name>, where transcendentalism had been an important philoso-<lb/>
phy in the nineteenth century, the concept of the nation as an Arca-<lb/>
dia persisted even as it continued to be mechanically divided according to the Jeffersonian grid. This ideal was promoted by the United States Congress when, beginning in <date when="1872">1872</date>, it created national parks in areas where there was spectacular natural scenery. These were soon equated in the eyes of many Americans with the cathe-<lb/>
drals and other important historic monuments of Europe as icons of national identity. First railroads and later interstate highways brought vacationers in increasing numbers to these natural sites, now legislatively certified as sacrosanct. Railroad interests were, in fact, deeply and profitably involved in promoting the creation of national parks. Without Industrial Age modes of transportation as a stimulus to mass tourism, there would have been little reason to create the parks in the first place. If the scenic lands encompassed by the parks had remained inaccessible, there would have been no need to protect them from industrial or commercial exploitation, and without means of transportation, their acquisition with tax dollars could not have been justified by a corresponding benefit to the citizenry of the United States. During the first half of the twen-<lb/>
tieth century, when driving for pleasure was perceived as an impor-<lb/>
tant form of recreation, additional public dollars were spent on the creation of parkways and state park systems that permitted urban dwellers to spend a day in the country and enjoy the trip as well.</p>
<p>To understand how the revolution in transportation made the landscape at large accessible and how the modern city became a completely ungirdled entity&#x2014;a phenomenon of motion, an arena of pleasure, and the nexus of a much larger region made accessible both for recreation and residential settlement&#x2014;we must go back 150 years in time to examine the transformation of <name type="place">Paris</name> during the Second Empire of Napoleon III. Haussmann's <name type="place">Paris</name>, however authoritarian in concept and harsh in displacing the poor, was progressive in its attention to middle-class needs. With its con-<lb/>
sideration of transportation, recreation, and sanitation, and the atmosphere of widely shared urban pleasure it produced&#x2014;as glimpsed in the paintings of the Impressionists and through the eyes of the novelist Marcel Proust (<date when="1871">1871</date>&#x2013;<date when="1922">1922</date>)&#x2014;it ushered in the era of modern urbanism.</p>
<div type="section">
<pb n="360"/>
<pb n="360" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Haussmann's Paris: Birth of the Modern CiTY</hi></hi></head>
<p>Elected president of the Second Republic in the wake of the defeat of the republican revolutionaries of <date when="1848">1848</date>, Napoleon Bonaparte's nephew, Louis-Napoleon Bonaparte&#x2014;known as Napoleon III after he became emperor by a coup d'&#x00E9;tat in <date when="1851">1851</date>&#x2014;returned from exile in <name type="place">England</name> to assume the reins of government. To forestall further revolutionary uprisings, he wanted to tear apart the dense fabric of <name type="place">Paris</name> by creating new avenues. These would divide the city into sectors and isolate the potentially treacherous neighborhoods, making it more difficult for a mob to erect barricades and seize control of the capital in the future. But to think of his twenty-year transformation of <name type="place">Paris</name> sim-<lb/>
ply in political and tactical terms is a mistake. It was primarily a skillful reinvention of the urban form itself through comprehensive city planning and the appli-<lb/>
cation of Industrial Age technology to solving the problems of several types of circulation: water, sewage, trains, carriages, and pedestrians. By this time mass societies had come into existence, and the notion had become prevalent that government bore a fun-<lb/>
damental responsibility for public sanitation, trans-<lb/>
portation routes, and the physical form and condition of the urban framework in general. <hi rend="italic">Urbanisme,</hi> "city planning" in French, was a term coined in the second half of the nineteenth century to denote a techno-<lb/>
cratic approach to shaping cities by regularizing their form and ministering to the needs of their popula-<lb/>
tions through the provision and maintenance of such basic infrastructure systems as streets and street lights, aqueducts, drainage lines, and sewers. The term also encompasses the concept of regulatory administra-<lb/>
tion, that is, planning by means of building codes and land use regulations governing the safety and welfare of the city's inhabitants as well as the aesthetics of the urban ensemble. Because facilitation of movement is a primary objective of the modern city, the measure-<lb/>
ment of transportation volumes and flows and the development of terminals, roadbeds, and tracks to accommodate interurban and intraurban modes of travel are central to the planning process.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris:</hi> <date when="1850">1850</date>&#x2013;<date when="1870">1870</date></hi></head>
<p>The accomplishment of rebuilding <name type="place">Paris</name>, which occurred despite deep misgivings and suffering on the part of many, must be measured in terms of the prob-<lb/>
lems faced by the old urban order. Nineteen thousand residents had died in the cholera epidemic of <date when="1848">1848</date>&#x2013;49. In <date when="1850">1850</date>, the population had grown to 1.3 million; over the next twenty years it continued climbing another 25 percent to reach 1.65 million. There was rampant unemployment and extreme overcrowding. Most of the city was a dense tangle of residential and manu-<lb/>
facturing quarters, unfathomable except to those with long familiarity with its narrow, tortuous medieval streets. Historically redolent and venerably pictur-<lb/>
esque, Old <name type="place">Paris</name> nonetheless glowed in the memo-<lb/>
ries of many Parisians and tourists who continued to mourn, long after they had disappeared, cherished bits and pieces of its vanished cityscape.</p>
<p>The real impetus for reordering the street pat-<lb/>
tern came not from military motives so much as from the impulse of the rapidly expanding industrial capi-<lb/>
talist society to have the mobility it needed to con-<lb/>
duct business. Specifically, the premier machine of the Industrial Age, the steam-powered railroad train, pro-<lb/>
pelled <name type="place">Paris</name> and other cities into the modern age. Tracks penetrated several quarters along the city's urban periphery, large shedlike industrial buildings of iron and glass were built as terminals, and the volume of traffic generated by travelers coming and going necessitated replacing some of the city's welter of crooked streets with broad, straight thoroughfares to connect with destinations in the center.</p>
<p>During the years of his exile in <name type="place">England</name>, Louis-<lb/>
Napoleon had seen some of the developments in transportation, sanitation, and parks that made <name type="place">Lon-<lb/>
don</name> the leader in modernization among European cities. Fortunately for him, he was able to find in <name type="place">France</name> a state administrator precisely suited to carry out an ambitious agenda of public improvements in <name type="place">Paris</name>. Baron Georges-Eug&#x00E8;ne Haussmann (<date when="1809">1809</date>&#x2014; <date when="1891">1891</date>), whom he appointed prefect of the Department of the Seine, was a government official skilled at manipulating tools that were new at the time, but which are common today: laws enabling the con-<lb/>
demnation and appropriation of private property and debt financing. To justify their actions, the emperor and Haussmann reasoned that improvements in the city's infrastructure and the creation of new and improved public spaces would raise real-estate values and bring higher tax returns with which to pay off the debts incurred. Although Haussmann's financing schemes ran into trouble, leading to his downfall in <date when="1870">1870</date>, the city's course of modernization was by then irrevocably set in the direction in which it continued until World War I.</p>
<p>Haussmann was able to conceptualize the entire city in technological, mechanistic terms as an entity, and although the Second Empire architecture that lined his new boulevards borrowed such time-hon-<lb/>
ored motifs as mansard roofs and sculptural details derived from Baroque classicism, these were merely the decorative trappings of a resolutely technologi-<lb/>
cal approach to construction. Bourgeois financiers provided the money that built the buildings and many
<pb n="361"/>
<pb n="361" type="orig"/>
of the public improvements, and Haussmann's radi-<lb/>
cal transformation of <name type="place">Paris</name> was aimed at making the city not only efficient but also agreeable for this mid-<lb/>
dle class. Before, there had been large <hi rend="italic">h么tels</hi> for aris-<lb/>
tocrats and crowded lodgings for artisans and shopkeepers. Now, with regulations creating uniform cornice lines and roof heights, there were blocks of buildings with spacious apartments for bankers, mer-<lb/>
chants, manufacturers, lawyers, physicians, politicians, and other members of the bourgeoisie. There were also grand new hotels serving a new and transient segment of the population, the tourists who came in increasing numbers. Haussmann's urban framework, moreover, accommodated another invention of cap-<lb/>
italist-consumer society: the department store, an airy palace with an interior skylighted courtyard con-<lb/>
structed of cast iron and glass like the huge sheds built as train depots and like the new wholesale meat and produce market, Les Halles Centrales.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Circulation</hi> is the operative word in understand-<lb/>
ing Haussmann's program for rebuilding <name type="place">Paris</name>. Not only did the growing commercial city need to move people and goods in and out by rail, but it also had to accommodate the many carriages owned by its pros-<lb/>
perous bourgeoisie. In addition, omnibuses began operation in <date when="1855">1855</date>, preceding the <hi rend="italic">M&#x00E9;tro,</hi> built in <date when="1900">1900</date>, as a means of mass transit. Furthermore, if it was to remain healthy, the city needed to transport wastes more efficiently. The recent invention of ferrocon-<lb/>
crete&#x2014;concrete reinforced with metal&#x2014;facilitated the construction of large collector tunnels that were part of a network of sewers planned by Haussmann. These carried the city's drainage northwest away from the built-up urban area to Asni&#x00E8;res, where it was released into the Seine. Because of population growth and pollution of the Seine, Parisians' traditional source of potable water, Haussmann's engineers designed aqueducts to draw copious amounts from the Yonne, Vanne, and Dhuis River valleys.</p>
<p>The character of the city was changed in pro-<lb/>
found ways. Houses formerly faced interior court-<lb/>
yards, but now new block and building plans allowed tall windows to open onto the street. From their bal-<lb/>
conies residents gazed upon the spectacle of carriages and people moving below (fig. 10.2). Large shop win-<lb/>
dows of plate glass created a thin membrane between interior and exterior space; the display of merchan-<lb/>
dise stimulated pedestrian traffic as browsing and buy-<lb/>
ing became popular pastimes, giving birth to the consumer society with its endless dreams of material goods as a basis of the good life. Caf&#x00E9;s catered to the increased movement of people in the new streets, serving as outdoor living rooms where social life became a daily ritual in a city increasingly attracted to pleasure. Gaslight&#x2014;soon to be replaced by elec-<lb/>
tric lighting&#x2014;illuminated streets and the inside of shops and caf&#x00E9;s, while increasing nighttime security and extending the hours people moved abroad in pub-<lb/>
lic. The <hi rend="italic">promeneur</hi> walked the new boulevards for pleasure, while the <hi rend="italic">flaneur</hi> idled away the hours, observing the quotidian dramas that often served as fodder for journalism.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-434">
<graphic url="CH10_003.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.2. Gustave Caillebotte, <hi rend="italic">The Man at the Window.</hi> <date when="1876">1876</date>. Private collection. From the window of the artist's family's apartment on the third floor of an outward-facing building of the <date when="1860">1860</date>s on the rue de Lisbonne, the figure in the painting (the artists brother Ren&#x00E9;) is gazing down the rue Miromesnil toward its inter-<lb/>
section with George-Eug&#x00E8;ne Haussmann's tree-lined boule-<lb/>
vard Malesherbes, where the figure of a woman stands upon a raised sidewalk, ready to cross the street.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The channels Haussmann cut through the city&#x2014;his <hi rend="italic">percements</hi>&#x2014;and the public buildings erected by the talented architects employed by his Ser-<lb/>
vice des B&#x00E2;timents Civils became the <hi rend="italic">mise-en-sc&#x00E8;ne</hi> for a new kind of public pageantry. The caf&#x00E9;s he planned for every major boulevard intersection were eddies in the current of humanity that flowed through them. The Op&#x00E9;ra, the cultural institution claimed by bour-<lb/>
geois society more completely than any other, assumed the role of social stage played by Versailles two hundred years before. In <date when="1860">1860</date>, <name type="pname">Jean-Louis-Charles Garnier</name> (<date when="1825">1825</date>&#x2013;<date when="1898">1898</date>) won the competition to design a magnificent new opera house. The architect con-<lb/>
ceived its grand staircase as a spreading fan of steps to display the train of the Empress Eug&#x00E9;nie's gown, but its real function, as it turned out when the build-<lb/>
ing was completed in <date when="1875">1875</date> during the Third Repub-<lb/>
lic (four years after the fall of Napoleon III), was to display the members of the fashionable world to one another against a backdrop of ruby and gold neo-<lb/>
Baroque splendor. Borrowing here as elsewhere the design vocabulary Le N么tre had developed for the seventeenth-century French garden, Haussmann placed this opulent landmark as the focal point of one
<pb n="362"/>
<pb n="362" type="orig"/>
of his arrow-straight avenues lined with uniform blocks of new buildings. The whole architectural ensemble served as an ordered and stable counter-<lb/>
point to the surge of movement along the grand, wide thoroughfare. The flow of traffic and the lively character of public life in this new urban space were evident even on a rainy day in <date when="1898">1898</date> when the scene was painted by the Impressionist artist Camille Pis-<lb/>
sarro (fig. 10.3).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-435">
<graphic url="CH10_004.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.3. <name type="pname">Camille Pissarro</name>, <hi rend="italic">Place du Theatre Fran&#x00E7;ais, <name type="place">Paris</name>, in the Rain (Avenue de i'Op&#x00E9;ra).</hi> <date when="1898">1898</date>. The Min-<lb/>
neapolis Institute of Arts</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-436">
<graphic url="CH10_005.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 10.4. <name type="place">Paris</name>, Artists' Plan. <date when="1793">1793</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Movement in, around, and through architec-<lb/>
tural space was Haussmann's primary goal, and the sculptural facades, bell towers, spires, domes, tri-<lb/>
umphal arches, and statues of an earlier age, as well as those of his own, were merely the ornamental and symbolically necessary props for the much grander spectacle of his resolutely modern city. This involved the eradication of much ad hoc urbanization in the vicinity of important buildings, such as the city's palaces and Notre-Dame. Haussmann wished to make these monuments more visible and to create open spaces for public celebrations, while also making the city more defensible in times of riot. To contem-<lb/>
porary Parisians, it seemed that Haussmann's urban surgery had suddenly revealed hidden areas of their city as obscure, unvisited side streets were made busy and prosperous by their proximity to new boulevards. Although thousands of people were evicted and dem-<lb/>
olition sites sold to developers, the commercial and real-estate boom of the period drowned out the voices of protest against this wholesale destruction.</p>
<p>In addition to creating the great boulevards, Haussmann realigned many ordinary streets, regu-<lb/>
lated the appearance of building facades, planted miles of street trees, landscaped new public squares at important intersections, installed lights, benches, and other sidewalk amenities, and enlisted the sup-<lb/>
port of building owners in public-space cleaning pro-<lb/>
cedures that made the city a cynosure of municipal housekeeping.</p>
<p>To assign the emperor and Haussmann entire credit for the transformation of <name type="place">Paris</name> in the nine-<lb/>
teenth century is erroneous. The sovereign provided the conceptual support and the technocrat the finan-<lb/>
cial acumen and administrative zeal to achieve amaz-<lb/>
ingly speedy results, but neither projected an entirely original vision. Together they effected a canny mar-<lb/>
riage of French monumentalism and industrial capi-<lb/>
talism by energizing a planning process that had already begun.</p>
<p>Planning and historic preservation were born in <name type="place">Paris</name> in the wake of the French Revolution, when the state confiscated Church property and evaluated monuments of the <hi rend="italic">ancien r&#x00E9;gime</hi> for conservation pur-<lb/>
poses. The Convention of <date when="1793">1793</date> commissioned a group of artists to prepare the so-called Artists' Plan in which individual districts were studied with a view toward the development of appropriated land and with the idea of displaying within a nexus of radiat-<lb/>
ing avenues buildings deemed of particular architec-<lb/>
tural importance (fig. 10.4). The Artists' Plan projected the creation and extension of long straight axes, notably in the densely clotted eastern part of the city, and it forecast one of the fundamental planning strategies of Haussmann's New <name type="place">Paris</name>: that based on an analysis of the city as stagecraft, with historic mon-<lb/>
uments and landmark buildings as well as important edifices of state symbolically embodying the new French polity displayed like set pieces. But this plan did not comprehend <name type="place">Paris</name>, as Haussmann's would, as an integer in which the city, not the sector, was the planning unit.</p>
<p>At the beginning of the nineteenth century,
<pb n="363"/>
<pb n="363" type="orig"/>
Napoleon I had pledged to make <name type="place">Paris</name> the most beau-<lb/>
tiful city in Europe. He was also aware of the need to modernize the city with projects that would improve public health, outdoor food markets, and traffic flow. Although his reign was too brief and the shortage of development capital too severe to initiate the kind of large-scale transformations that his nephew under-<lb/>
took a half century later, he effectively set the Neo-<lb/>
classical tone for most subsequent city planning. Renaming the place Louis XV the place de la Con-<lb/>
corde, he created an important cross axis running through it, emphasized by the construction of cer-<lb/>
tain iconic monuments. A mile distant along the tree-<lb/>
lined axis of the Champs-&#x00C9;lys&#x00E9;es at the summit of Chaillot Hill, he constructed the largest triumphal arch ever built, the Arc de Triomphe (<date when="1806">1806</date>&#x2013;36), a potent symbol and grandiose climax to one of the world's most important urban perspectives.</p>
<p>With the help of his favorite Neoclassical archi-<lb/>
tects, Charles Percier (<date when="1764">1764</date>&#x2013;<date when="1838">1838</date>) and Pierre-Fran&#x00E7;ois-<lb/>
L&#x00E9;onard Fontaine (<date when="1762">1762</date>&#x2013;<date when="1853">1853</date>), Napoleon established the beginning of an axis into the densely built quar-<lb/>
ters of eastern <name type="place">Paris</name> by transforming the northern edge of the Tuileries Gardens into the rue de Rivoli (fig. 10.5). Employing the traditional formula of the sidewalk arcade that we have observed in Henri IV's place Royale (place des Vosges), they built the first segment of massive buildings with horizontal bands of uniform balconies and stringcourses reinforcing the perspective line of the axis (see fig. 4.48). The con-<lb/>
tinuous balconies on the <hi rend="italic">piano nobile,</hi> third, and attic floors opened the spectacle of the street to those inside, suggesting its function as a parade route, while the extended ground-floor arcade made an elegant shoppers' promenade.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-437">
<graphic url="CH10_006.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.5. <name type="pname">Rue de Rivoli</name>, <name type="place">Paris</name>, begun in <date when="1806">1806</date> under Napoleon I. Photograph by Adolphe Braun. c. <date when="1855">1855</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-438">
<graphic url="CH10_007.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 10.6. July Column, place de la Bastille, <name type="place">Paris</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Louis-Philippe (ruled <date when="1830">1830</date>&#x2013;<date when="1848">1848</date>) as a constitu-<lb/>
tional monarch lacked the resources for large-scale urban embellishment available to earlier kings, but he nevertheless continued the concept set forth in the Artists' Plan of emphasizing individual public spaces by erecting the July Column on the place de la Bastille and the Egyptian obelisk at the place de la Concorde (fig. 10.6; see fig. 6.38). In the <date when="1840">1840</date>s, he built the first railroad stations, including the Gare de l'Est, which was linked to the center of the city by the wide boule-<lb/>
vard de Strasbourg.</p>
<p>An especially important development that affected the future of city planning was the establish-<lb/>
ment in <date when="1819">1819</date> of the &#x00C9;cole des Beaux-Arts with its rig-<lb/>
orously Neoclassical program of architectural education. As mentioned in Chapter Nine, it was here that the American architects responsible for the City Beautiful movement received their training beginning in the second half of the nineteenth century. The French winners of its prestigious Prix de <name type="place">Rome</name> almost invariably received important government building commissions when they returned from their advanced classical studies in <name type="place">Italy</name> as <hi rend="italic">pensionnaires</hi> at the French Academy, which is housed in the Villa Medici on the Pincian Hill in <name type="place">Rome</name>. Thus, from the ranks of the &#x00C9;cole des Beaux-Arts came the architects who designed the monuments and blocks of new
<pb n="364"/>
<pb n="364" type="orig"/>
apartment buildings in Haussmann's New <name type="place">Paris</name>. Their Neoclassical vocabulary and its application as a masonry and sculptural veneer over industrial mate-<lb/>
rials in many of these structures help explain the sty-<lb/>
listic consistency and apparent continuity with tradition of the rapidly modernizing city.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-439">
<graphic url="CH10_008.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.7. <name type="place">Paris</name> map showing Haussmann's new boulevards, engraving from <name type="pname">Jean-Charles-<lb/>
Adolphe Alphand</name>, <hi rend="italic">Les Prome-<lb/>
nades de <name type="place">Paris</name>.</hi> <date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;73</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-440">
<graphic url="CH10_009.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 10.8. <name type="place">Paris</name> street furni-<lb/>
ture, engraving from <name type="pname">Jean-<lb/>
Charles-Adolphe Alphand</name>, <hi rend="italic">Les Promenades de <name type="place">Paris</name>.</hi> <date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;73</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Napoleon III, having lived in <name type="place">London</name>, where architects and engineers were applying new forms of industrial technology to construction and urban prob-<lb/>
lem solving, desired to bring an even greater degree of modernity to the French capital. Even before appointing Haussmann prefect of the Department of the Seine, Napoleon III began extending the Rue de Rivoli east toward the H么tel de Ville; refashioning Louis XIV's old hunting park, the Bois de Boulogne, into an English-style public pleasure ground; remov-<lb/>
ing the slum that had grown up between the Tuileries and the Louvre; restoring the cathedral of Notre-<lb/>
Dame; and planning a new food market, Les Halles Centrales. Napoleon III had, moreover, prepared a map of the city that showed an arterial network of <hi rend="italic">percements</hi> knifing through the older fabric of narrow short streets, and it was this graphic representation of his urban renewal proposals that he handed Hauss-<lb/>
mann upon his appointment. Even though this plan changed, particularly after <date when="1861">1861</date> when the annexation of the <hi rend="italic">outlying faubourgs</hi> created the need for new arterial connections, municipal buildings, and public services, Haussmann always viewed this imperial doc-<lb/>
ument as his charter, considering himself to be merely the emperor's servant and agent in transforming <name type="place">Paris</name>.</p>
<p>Haussmann had been prefect of Bordeaux before becoming prefect of the Department of the Seine in <date when="1853">1853</date>, a position that can be roughly charac-<lb/>
terized as city manager of <name type="place">Paris</name>. He was responsible for overseeing the planning, design, financing, and construction of all capital improvements as well as the daily operations of municipal management. To provide the necessary base maps for their work, Haussmann had thorough planimetric and topo-<lb/>
graphic surveys made of the city and its recently annexed suburbs. The resulting Plan of <name type="place">Paris</name> config-<lb/>
ured the city-in-transformation, plotting the <hi rend="italic">perce-<lb/>
ments,</hi> for which condemnation and demolition of property were necessary, as well as the new building alignments where existing streets were to be widened by the Service de la Voirie, or Bureau of Roads (fig. 10.7). Thoroughly technocratic in his approach to his job, he had as his chief associates engineers such as Eug&#x00E8;ne Belgrand (<date when="1810">1810</date>&#x2013;<date when="1878">1878</date>), who conceived and managed the construction of the vast new aqueduct and sewer systems, and the landscape designer <name type="pname">Jean-<lb/>
Charles-Adolphe Alphand</name> (<date when="1817">1817</date>&#x2013;<date when="1891">1891</date>), whom he put in charge of constructing new parks, promenades, and city squares.</p>
<p>Squares such as the place du Cht&#x00E2;elet sacrificed their status as <hi rend="italic">places,</hi> becoming instead vehicular traf-<lb/>
fic circles and pedestrian traffic islands, a function that distinguished the Parisian squares from the ones in <name type="place">London</name>, which continued to serve as quiet urban oases even after that city's modernization. They were given attractive but standardized street furniture, which in its ubiquity served informally to symbolize the city's distinctive new appearance (fig. 10.8). In developing these nodes of relation, as Haussmann termed them, for the boulevard systems, Le N么tre's paradigm of avenues radiating from <hi rend="italic">rond-points</hi> served him well, allowing the city both fluidity of motion and monumental axiality.</p>
<p>The Champs-&#x00C9;lys&#x00E9;es was redefined with new <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> of trees and lined with gaslights designed by Jakob Ignaz (Jacques-Ignace) Hittorff (<date when="1792">1792</date>&#x2013;<date when="1867">1867</date>),
<pb n="365"/>
<pb n="365" type="orig"/>
the city architect. In the eastern sector of the city, the southern part of the Canal Saint-Martin was decked over to become the boulevard Richard-Lenoir in <date when="1861">1861</date>. The same kinds of trees, flowers, news kiosks, con-<lb/>
cession stands, and gaslights that made western <name type="place">Paris</name> attractive to the rich also appeared in this less affluent part of the city.</p>
<p>Just beyond the outer ring of boulevards, which had replaced the customs wall of <date when="1786">1786</date>&#x2013;88, lay two large royal hunting parks: the Bois de Boulogne in the west was approached by Haussmann's new, wide avenue de l'Tmp&#x00E9;ratrice (avenue Foch), and the Bois de Vincennes was situated in the east to the south of the porte de Vincennes and the existing ceremonial thoroughfare, the cours de Vincennes. To serve the recreational needs of high society in <hi rend="italic">le West End,</hi> Alp-<lb/>
hand was charged with continuing the conversion of the Bois de Boulogne into an elegant pleasure ground with passages of Picturesque scenery interspersed with a race track and restaurants (figs. 10.9a, 10.9b).</p>
<p>Because it is a collection of unrelated facilities as well as a palimpsest inscribed with traces of past uses, the Bois de Boulogne park complex does not have the unified planning vision characteristic of Olmsted's parks in <name type="place">America</name>, with which it is con-<lb/>
temporary. While developed in the English style with undulating paths replacing all but two of the former straight <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> and an irregular-shaped lake reminis-<lb/>
cent of the Serpentine in <name type="place">London</name>'s Hyde Park, it is more a collection of heterogeneous amusements. Lovely as it is in some of its parts, particularly the Bagatelle and the Shakespeare Garden, these were not developed as part of a comprehensive landscape design. Nor is there, as in Central Park, an overriding note of moral purpose; the Bois de Boulogne was intended more as a fashionable resort than as a pas-<lb/>
toral antidote to urban stress.</p>
<p>Although intended for the working class, the Bois de Vincennes was treated to a similar degree of Picturesque detail as the Bois de Boulogne. In addi-<lb/>
tion to these two large parks, Haussmann created the Parc Montsouris along the city's southern edge between the Porte d'Orl&#x00E9;ans and the Porte d'Italie and refashioned the Parc Monceau, the duc de Chartres's eighteenth-century <hi rend="italic">jardin anglo-chinois</hi> at the northwest-<lb/>
ern edge of the city, into a Picturesque nineteenth-century park containing several of Louis de Carmontelle's remaining <hi rend="italic">follies.</hi> In the northeastern quadrant of the city, between <date when="1864">1864</date> and <date when="1867">1867</date>, he transformed the vermin-infested Buttes-Chaumont, an abandoned rock quarry where squatters lived, into a romantically Picturesque 55-acre park (fig. 10.10).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-441">
<graphic url="CH10_010.jpg"/>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-442">
<graphic url="CH10_011.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.9a and 10.9b. Bois de Boulogne, before and after its transformation by <name type="pname">Jean-Charles-Adolphe Alphand</name>. Engraving from Alphand, <hi rend="italic">Les Promenades de <name type="place">Paris</name>.</hi> <date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;73</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-443">
<graphic url="CH10_012.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 10.10. Plan of Parc des Buttes-Chaumont, designed by <name type="pname">Jean-Charles-Adolphe Alphand</name>. Engraving from Alphand, <hi rend="italic">Les Promenades de <name type="place">Paris</name>.</hi> <date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;73</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The spirit that informs all of these Parisian parks is highly theatrical. Resembling elaborate stage sets, many passages of their scenery are composed of rock-<lb/>
<pb n="366"/>
<pb n="366" type="orig"/>
work combining natural and simulated stones. At the Parc des Buttes-Chaumont, Alphand's Picturesque genius was given full rein, and at <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> the cost of redesigning the much larger Bois de Boulogne, he added huge quantities of artificial rockwork to the existing old quarry faces, thereby creating a romantic pseudomountainous landscape rising out of an artificial lake.<ref target="#CH10-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref>Two streams, one containing a waterfall that spilled into a grotto with artificial sta-<lb/>
lactites and stalagmites, are fed by water from one of the canals of <name type="place">Paris</name>. Crowning the promontory that forms the park's central feature, a small replica of the Temple of Vesta at Tivoli serves as a belvedere from which to view the panorama of <name type="place">Paris</name>. Leading to the temple is a high suspended bridge called, melodra-<lb/>
matically, the Bridge of Suicides; an alternative, longer route provides sinuously curving paths to the top. This scene was meant to induce a <hi rend="italic">grand frisson,</hi> or thrill of amazement, a sensation different from the tranquil mood of poetic reverie Olmsted attempted to produce in viewers of his scenery (fig. 10.11).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-444">
<graphic url="CH10_013.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.11. Pont des Suicides, Parc des Buttes-Chaumont, designed by <name type="pname">Jean-Charles-<lb/>
Adolphe Alphand</name>. Engraving from Alphand, <hi rend="italic">Les Prome-<lb/>
nades de <name type="place">Paris</name>.</hi> <date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;73</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-445">
<graphic url="CH10_014.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 10.12. Square des Innocents, designed by <name type="pname">Jean-<lb/>
Charles-Adolphe Alphand</name>. Engraving from Alphand, <hi rend="italic">Les Promenades de <name type="place">Paris</name>.</hi> <date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;73</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Haussmann's parks are not, like those of Olm-<lb/>
sted and Vaux, a reaction to the industrial city, a rural vision of pastoral peace offered to counteract urban stress; rather they present themselves as additional pleasures in a city of many pleasures, a city already comfortable in its progressive modernity. Although these French parks partake of the same Picturesque style as the American parks, they are not naturalistic in the way Olmsted's parks are. The French parks incorporate plantings of lush, high-maintenance, sub-<lb/>
tropical vegetation, and their path systems do not con-<lb/>
form to the dictates of topography, but assume the lines of the French curve, a drafting instrument with scroll-shaped cutouts. Regarding the latter, the gar-<lb/>
den writer and editor William Robinson penned these caustic words: "In the plans of the best French land-<lb/>
scape-gardeners it is quite ridiculous to see the way the walks wind about in symmetrical twirlings, and, when they have entwined themselves through every sweep of turf in the place, seem to long for more spaces to writhe about in."<ref target="#CH10-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref>The sinuosity that was an end in itself as well as the concentration on effects that the French term <hi rend="italic">f&#x00E9;erique,</hi> enchanting and fairy-<lb/>
like, bespeak an underlying cultural attitude that has more in common with Disney's Magic Kingdom than with the pastoral simplicity of Central Park where all adornment&#x2014;botanical, sculptural, or architectural&#x2014; was clearly subservient to a landscape composition designed to carry the visitor through a chain of scenes in which the experience is primarily <hi rend="italic">spatial.</hi></p>
<p>Several illustrations in Alphand's book, <hi rend="italic">Les Promenades de <name type="place">Paris</name></hi> (<date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;73), an important record of Haussmann's transformation of the city, depict the characteristic treatment of the new streets and their related green spaces (fig. 10.12). Maintenance codes governed the appearance of private frontages, ensuring the cleanliness of facades and their scrap-<lb/>
ing and painting or whitewashing at intervals of ten years or less.</p>
<p>In making <name type="place">Paris</name> both progressive and pleasura-<lb/>
ble, Haussmann also changed its scale. The city grew in size by one half with the addition of the new <hi rend="italic">arrondissements.</hi> The unprecedented length of Hauss-<lb/>
mann's wide, straight boulevards&#x2014;their perspectival views emphasized by even building walls with uni-<lb/>
form roof, cornice, and balcony lines&#x2014;made the extent of the urban mass more readily apparent. In addition, wider streets made taller buildings possible and even desirable as a matter of proportionate rela-<lb/>
tionship, a fact recognized in the <date when="1859">1859</date> building code, which decreed that on streets 65 feet (20 meters) or more wide, buildings could gain 8 feet (2.5 meters)&#x2014; amounting to an additional story&#x2014;in height.</p>
<p>Haussmann's boulevard openings were the
<pb n="367"/>
<pb n="367" type="orig"/>
occasions for triumphal public celebration presided over by the emperor. With their Venetian banners and gold curtains decorated with stars and garlands, these unveilings memorialized not only the grandeur of the remade city, but also the power of government, municipal and state. Perhaps the emperor risked too much politically in allowing Haussmann to lavish resources to such an extent upon the capital and, at least during the first decade of his administration, to publicize them so conspicuously. Eventually, opposi-<lb/>
tion within the Chamber of Deputies caused an inves-<lb/>
tigation into the prefect's methods of financing, and the discovery of certain irregularities brought about his dismissal in <date when="1870">1870</date>.</p>
<p>That same year Napoleon III capitulated to the Germans at Sedan during the Franco-Prussian War. A republic was proclaimed, bringing about the fall of the Second Empire and the end of Napoleon's reign. The war continued as <name type="place">Paris</name> underwent a four months' seige and then German occupation before surren-<lb/>
dering. Within weeks, revolutionary forces were elected to the <name type="place">Paris</name> municipal council, and these rad-<lb/>
ical members of the Commune seized control of the city. Their revolt against the national government, however, was quickly crushed by the troops of the new republic.</p>
<p>These events did not put an end to <name type="place">Paris</name>'s con-<lb/>
tinued modernization in the Haussmannian manner. The Communards' damage to the city was severe, but after their brief time in power, the Third Repub-<lb/>
lic set about repairing the destruction, extending more avenues, and refurbishing the Luxembourg Gardens. Gabriel-Jean-Antoine Davioud, a park designer in the Haussmann administration, designed the grandiose Trocad&#x00E9;ro Palace in a pseudo-Spanish Moorish style as <name type="place">Paris</name> prepared to host the International Exhibition of <date when="1878">1878</date>, an opportunity to reassert its industrial modernity and cultural advancement.</p>
<p><name type="place">Paris</name> had already hosted two international fairs to showcase industrial technology in <date when="1855">1855</date> and <date when="1867">1867</date>. Beginning in <date when="1867">1867</date>, the Champs-de-Mars, which had been laid out as a parade ground in <date when="1765">1765</date> between the &#x00C9;cole Militaire and the Seine, became the site of these expositions. The huge vaulted spaces of the <name type="place">Paris</name> exhi-<lb/>
bition halls experimentally employed the new build-<lb/>
ing materials of iron and glass, the engineering potential of which was first demonstrated by Loudon's greenhouse constructions and then by Pax-<lb/>
ton's Crystal Palace in <name type="place">London</name>. Just as the city was being opened up and made porous, so these new Industrial Age structures, which seemed startlingly light and lacking in <hi rend="italic">gravitas</hi> at the time, posited an architectural idiom that no longer walled in volu-<lb/>
metric space but dematerialized mass, transforming buildings into airy cages in which the interpenetra-<lb/>
tion of indoors and outdoors became the dominant theme. The structure containing the exhibition halls for the <date when="1867">1867</date> fair was an enormous ellipse of seven concentric galleries featuring a garden with statues and palm trees in the center oval.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Gustave Eiffel</name> (<date when="1832">1832</date>&#x2013;<date when="1923">1923</date>) was at the time of the <date when="1867">1867</date> exposition a young engineer who had founded a factory capable of producing the iron skeleton of the vast gallery on the outer edge of the ellipse, the Galerie des Machines, which had a height of 82 feet (25 meters) and a span of 115 feet (35 meters). Eiffel was also responsible for the hydraulic lifts that introduced the public to a new means of vertical movement.</p>
<p>The Centennial Exposition of <date when="1889">1889</date>, which fol-<lb/>
lowed the International Exhibition that had been staged in <date when="1878">1878</date> to prove that <name type="place">Paris</name> had recovered from the effects of the Communard rebellion and the Franco-Prussian War, pushed French technological experimentation and search for new building forms to new heights, both figuratively and literally. The structure that most impressed visitors to the <date when="1889">1889</date> fair was Eiffel's 984-foot (300-meter) tower of open-lat-<lb/>
tice wrought iron. Eiffel, who had also distinguished himself as a bridge builder, designed it as a demon-<lb/>
stration in structural aerodynamics and load-bearing engineering. Twice as high as the dome of St. Peter's or the Great Pyramid of Khufu at Giza and, unlike these monuments, a labor of mere months, not decades, this icon of early modernity has remained, above all other features within that heavily orna-<lb/>
mented city, the instantly recognizable symbol of <name type="place">Paris</name>.<ref target="#CH10-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref>It was the tallest structure in the world until the Chrysler Building in <name type="place">New York</name> was built in <date when="1930">1930</date>.</p>
<p>Elevators manufactured by the Otis Elevator Company ascend on a curve, carrying visitors to the successive platforms. Suddenly, it was possible to have a panoramic vision not merely of landscape, such as Alpinists could experience by ascending high peaks, but of urban form and history The Eiffel Tower made available to millions of visitors the city's structure as concrete abstraction, giving each the ability to deci-<lb/>
pher in a single reading all known landmarks, topo-<lb/>
graphical and structural, and to discern in this act the story of the city's earliest formation and growth through the centuries. Thus equipped with panoramic vision, one could also profoundly imagine the human dimension of the metropolis, the multitude of indi-<lb/>
vidual lives of the teeming population below. Yet, in the vertiginous descent, structure seems to fragment, and the scenery of the city below appears to spin in kaleidoscopic fashion. The ebullient Cubism of Robert Delaunay (<date when="1885">1885</date>&#x2013;<date when="1941">1941</date>), who painted many ver-<lb/>
sions of the Eiffel Tower beginning in <date when="1910">1910</date>, captures the exhilaration of this quintessentially modern expe-<lb/>
rience of space and landscape (fig. 10.13).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-446">
<graphic url="CH10_015.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.13. <name type="pname">Robert Delaunay</name>, <hi rend="italic">Eiffel Tower.</hi> <date when="1911">1911</date>. The Guggenheim Museum, <name type="place">New York</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="368"/>
<pb n="368" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">II. <hi rend="smallcaps">The City Beautiful: Monumental Urbanism in Beaux-Arts America</hi></hi></head>
<p>It would be difficult to exaggerate the effect of Hauss-<lb/>
mann's <name type="place">Paris</name> on other cities of the world. It is fair to say that, even within the context of modernism and postmodernism, designers have continued to employ some of the devices of monumental urban planning, of which mid-nineteenth-century <name type="place">Paris</name> remains the primary example, especially in capital cities where the building program has called for a symbolical display of government power through architecture and land-<lb/>
scape. Even without such an agenda, modernism's imperative to enable vehicular movement and to assist the forces of capitalist industry and commerce was strong, and practically everywhere old streets were widened, fortifications gave way to new boulevards, and rail transportation systems were built as city after city was opened up both to new possibilities of urban life and to a radically new urban form.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-447">
<graphic url="CH10_016.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.14. Plan for <name type="place">Chicago</name>, <name type="place">Illinois</name>, proposed by <name type="pname">Daniel Burnham</name>. <date when="1909">1909</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Ironically, in democratic <name type="place">America</name> the desire for civic monumentality was such that Gilded Age mag-<lb/>
nates and political leaders overlooked the authoritar-<lb/>
ianism implicit in this style of city planning, adopting its forms to express the lofty ideals of the republic rather than the power of monarchy. It was a time when newly made American millionaires looked to Europe for role models in the mores of aristocracy. It was a time when Americans sought to emulate Europe's impressive legacy of heritage buildings and monuments in the mansions of the rich and in the public art and architecture that proclaimed the pros-<lb/>
perity and dignity of their cities. In this they were helped by the training undertaken by design profes-<lb/>
sionals. The aesthetics of several generations of American architects and landscape architects was forged in Haussman's <name type="place">Paris</name> under the influence of the &#x00C9;cole des Beaux-Arts where they studied beginning in the last third of the nineteenth century.</p>
<p>By the beginning of the twentieth century, in the wake of the <date when="1893">1893</date> <name type="place">Chicago</name> World's Fair, the neo-<lb/>
classicism they imbibed there was being vigorously promoted by Charles Mulford Robinson, a Rochester, <name type="place">New York</name>, journalist and the author of <hi rend="italic">The Improve-<lb/>
ment of Towns and Cities, or the Practical Basis of Civic Aesthetics</hi> (<date when="1901">1901</date>) and <hi rend="italic">Modern Civic Art, or The City Made Beautiful</hi> (<date when="1903">1903</date>). The City Beautiful movement aimed at ennobling American cities and European colonial capitals through monumental planning, and Daniel Burnham, fresh from his triumph as principal plan-<lb/>
ner of the <date when="1893">1893</date> World's Columbian Fair in <name type="place">Chicago</name>, was commissioned to develop new layouts for <name type="place">Cleveland</name>, <name type="place">San Francisco</name>, <name type="place">Manila</name>, and <name type="place">Chicago</name> (fig. 10.14). Where there were existing gridiron street patterns, these plans attempted to impose upon them grand diagonal boulevards whose intersections formed mag-<lb/>
nificent plazas and whose vistas terminated in mon-<lb/>
umental public works.</p>
<p>Frederick Law Olmsted had spent a good deal of time during his last productive years mentoring his son and namesake who became his professional heir and the future head of the firm. It is ironic in light of Olmsted, Sr.'s, antipathy toward the heroic style of the Gilded Age that one of the first commissions <name type="pname">Olmsted</name>, Jr., assumed upon entering practice was in collaboration with Burnham. Following the <name type="place">Chicago</name> World's Fair, Senator James McMillan's Committee on the District of Columbia appointed him landscape architect on the team under Burnham's leadership to carry L'Enfant's original plan for the nation's capital to a new level of monumental grandeur. The other members were Stanford White's partner, <name type="pname">Charles McKim</name> (<date when="1847">1847</date>&#x2013;<date when="1909">1909</date>), and the Beaux-Arts sculptor Augustus Saint-Gaudens (<date when="1848">1848</date>&#x2013;<date when="1907">1907</date>).</p>
<p>In order to prepare themselves for this chal-<lb/>
<pb n="369"/>
<pb n="369" type="orig"/>
lenging assignment to give <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, an image that not only glorified the founders of the republic and the president who saved the Union but also one that suited America's newly assumed iden-<lb/>
tity as a world power, Burnham, McKim, Olmsted, and the secretary to Senator McMillan, Charles Moore, sailed for Europe in the summer of <date when="1901">1901</date> to study architecture, parks, and urban design in several cities. For seven weeks they sketched and discussed ideas stimulated by their travels to <name type="place">Paris</name>, <name type="place">Rome</name>, <name type="place">Venice</name>, <name type="place">Budapest</name>, <name type="place">Frankfurt</name>, <name type="place">Berlin</name>, and <name type="place">London</name>.</p>
<p>Washington's layout had become muddled by later nonconforming elements, such as a train station athwart the Mall, but the outlines of its grand plan, derived from that of Versailles, were partially realized and called for further development. Not surprisingly, the members of the team returned on the first of August determined to clarify, reinforce, and extend L'Enfant's axial plan (fig. 10.15). Within the con-<lb/>
tentious atmosphere of <name type="place">Washington</name> politics, they were fortunate to win critical support from President Theodore Roosevelt and, after his election in <date when="1909">1909</date>, from President William Howard Taft. Thus, con-<lb/>
gressional opponents did not manage to derail the McMillan team's intentions, and the head of the Penn-<lb/>
sylvania Railroad acceded to its recommendation that Union Station be placed north of the Capitol. Con-<lb/>
struction of a new station according to Burnham's plans was completed in <date when="1907">1907</date>, and the old train tracks were removed from the Mall once it was made oper-<lb/>
ational. Adjacent to the station on the northwest a similarly monumental new Post Office, also designed by Burnham, was built. The proposal to realign the Mall on axis with the <name type="place">Washington</name> Monument and plant the remainder as a simple grass <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> bordered by quadruple rows of elms was also carried out after much debate and furor in the press.</p>
<p>As his final act of office before leaving the pres-<lb/>
idency, Theodore Roosevelt appointed a Council of Fine Arts composed of architects, painters, sculptors, and a landscape architect&#x2014;Frederick Law Olmsted, Jr. Approved in a bill passed by the House of Repre-<lb/>
sentatives and Senate in <date when="1910">1910</date>, the seven-member com-<lb/>
mission appointed by Taft continued to include Olmsted. The Mall axis was extended according to the McMillan Plan beyond L'Enfant's original plan, and a canal-like reflecting basin was built between the <name type="place">Washington</name> Monument and Henry Bacon's new Gre-<lb/>
cian-style temple housing the monumental statue of President Abraham Lincoln by Daniel Chester French in Potomac Park. This impressive memorial to the nation's sixteenth president, the subject of contro-<lb/>
versy like other elements of the plan, was not com-<lb/>
pleted until <date when="1922">1922</date>.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-448">
<graphic url="CH10_017.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.15. McMillan Plan for <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name> <date when="1901">1901</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The McMillan plan had called for a national cemetery on the opposite bank of the Potomac with "white stones, inconspicuous in themselves, covering the gentle, wooded slopes, and producing the desired effect of a vast army in its last resting place."<ref target="#CH10-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref>In <date when="1925">1925</date>, Congress authorized construction of the <name type="place">Arlington</name> Memorial Bridge according to designs prepared by the firm of McKim, Mead, and White. The bridge, a bridge plaza, and Water Gate between the bridge and the parkway proposed along the edge of Rock Creek were completed by <date when="1932">1932</date>. Another important monu-<lb/>
ment, one honoring the third president, Thomas Jef-<lb/>
ferson, was located at the end of the plan's great cross axis extending from Lafayette Square in front of the White House to a terminus in the Tidal Basin of the Potomac River. Plans inspired by the Pantheon in <name type="place">Rome</name> were prepared for the Jefferson Memorial Com-<lb/>
mission by John Russell Pope, also the architect of the National Gallery of Art, and submitted shortly before his death in <date when="1937">1937</date>. These were subjected to much wrangling, but after they had been somewhat modi-<lb/>
fied, reduced in scale, and approved by the Senate in spite of objections from the Fine Arts Commission, the monument was put into construction in <date when="1938">1938</date>. The
<pb n="370"/>
<pb n="370" type="orig"/>
McMillan Plan's proposal for a dignified treatment of the grounds immediately surrounding the <name type="place">Washing-<lb/>
ton</name> Monument, the linchpin of the entire National Capital redevelopment plan, was never carried out.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-449">
<graphic url="CH10_018.jpg"/>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-450">
<graphic url="CH10_019.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.16a and 10.16b. Senate Park Commission renderings of alternative closed and open valley plans for Rock Creek and Potomac Parkway, <name type="place">Wash-<lb/>
ington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name> <date when="1902">1902</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-451">
<graphic url="CH10_020.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 10.17. Plan for Rock Creek and Potomac Parkway, prepared by <name type="pname">James G. Lang-<lb/>
don</name>, Office of Public Buildings and Grounds, <date when="1916">1916</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>As with other elements of the plan, politics and professional rivalries plagued the development of Rock Creek and Potomac Parkway, a 2-and-陆-mile (4-kilo-<lb/>
meter) scenic road connecting the Potomac waterfront near the Lincoln Memorial with Rock Creek Park north of the National Zoo at the northern boundary of the District of Columbia.<ref target="#CH10-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref>It is sometimes forgot-<lb/>
ten that the City Beautiful movement, while advocat-<lb/>
ing neoclassical monuments, axial planning, and geometrical landscape design, also propounded the need for park systems in which naturalistic landscap-<lb/>
ing complemented Beaux-Arts architectural grandeur. While Senator James McMillan chaired the Senate Committee on the District of Columbia, the official name of the <date when="1901">1901</date> McMillan Commission charged with detailing the plan for monumental <name type="place">Washington</name> was the Senate Park Commission, and its <date when="1902">1902</date> report is titled <hi rend="italic">The Improvement of the Park System of the District of Columbia.</hi> Frederick Law Olmsted, Jr., the author of the park and parkway sections of the report, sought to furnish the nation's capital with the same type of parks and park-connecting parkways that had recently been created in <name type="place">New York</name>, <name type="place">Boston</name>, and Buffalo and were being developed for Cincinnati, Milwaukee, Min-<lb/>
neapolis, and other American cities.</p>
<p>Seen as a means of curing an environmental problem and an eyesore (industrial wastes were dumped along the lower portions of Rock Creek), as well as a way to eliminate the topographical barrier between Georgetown and <name type="place">Washington</name> proper, the project was delayed by debate, continuing for several years, over whether it should be an open-valley scenic parkway or a boulevard-type "closed" parkway cov-<lb/>
ering a conduit (figs. 10.16a, 10.16b). Finally, on <date when="1913-03-14">March 14, 1913</date>, Congress passed a bill authorizing the open-<lb/>
valley concept. Olmsted continued to maintain his involvement as a consultant to the project and was dis-<lb/>
appointed when aspects of his advice, such as the perimeter roadways and some of the Picturesque effects seen in the <date when="1916">1916</date> plan, were ignored (fig. 10.17). Other aesthetically desirable elements were eliminated in the interests of economy and traffic engineering, but finally, in <date when="1923">1923</date>, ten years after its authorization, the parkway was under construction. With the impetus gained from federal work programs in the <date when="1930">1930</date>s, it was almost completed by the end of that decade.</p>
<p>The fulfillment of many of the objectives of the McMillan report remained the most realized achieve-<lb/>
ment of the City Beautiful movement in America. Nowhere except in <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, were the results of this effort accomplished on an urban scale, but several civic centers and many banks, libraries, museums, train stations, bridges, and monuments were added to the American cityscape as a result of this impulse (see fig. 9.59). Typically, municipal gov-<lb/>
ernment followed, rather than led, the efforts that were organized by groups of public-spirited citizens and journalists as city after city in the United States followed the lead of Burnham and Robinson, seek-<lb/>
ing to counteract the ugliness of their earlier rapid commercial and industrial growth with Neoclassical urban monumentalism.</p>
<p>As we shall see in the next chapter, the rich vocabulary of forms inherited from <name type="place">France</name> and <name type="place">Italy</name> furnished British and American garden designers with many motifs, which they borrowed freely. The stu-<lb/>
<pb n="371"/>
<pb n="371" type="orig"/>
dents at the &#x00C9;cole des Beaux-Arts and the <name type="place">Rome</name> Prize winners at the American Academy did not ponder deeply the humanist iconography informing these now agreeably mellow garden landscapes, but sought instead to appropriate their aura of venerability along with their undeniably fine compositional elements. They looked to these antique landscapes for inspira-<lb/>
tion because, like the characters in the novels of Henry James, they were subject to a peculiarly Amer-<lb/>
ican sense of cultural inferiority. Regular transatlantic travel by steamship, another Industrial Age trans-<lb/>
portation advancement, made them acutely aware of their own country's narrow history and thin civiliza-<lb/>
tion when compared with the many centuries of human artistic endeavor recorded in the stones of Europe's ancient ruins, medieval cathedrals, and Renaissance villas and ch&#x00E2;teaux. Others of their coun-<lb/>
trymen saw American civilization in somewhat dif-<lb/>
ferent terms, as an opportunity to forge a new kind of national identity, one that celebrated the country's uniqueness in occupying almost an entire continent that was by nature endowed with scenery in all three traditional categories&#x2014;beautiful, picturesque, and sublime. Surely, they reasoned with transcendental-<lb/>
ist conviction, that very scenery, particularly in its sub-<lb/>
lime dimension, was a natural resource even more fundamental to the ethos of their freshly evolving civ-<lb/>
ilization than any replication of European monu-<lb/>
mental grandeur on native soil could ever be. By conserving significant lands within the public domain through the creation of a national park system, they would vouchsafe for future generations this wonder-<lb/>
ful patrimony, which also constituted a newly avail-<lb/>
able stimulus to tourism and recreation.</p>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">III. <name type="place">America</name> the Beautiful: The National Park System</hi></hi></head>
<p>In <date when="1851">1851</date>, a U.S. Army party known as the Mari-<lb/>
posa Battalion pursued a band of Miwok-Paiute Indians into the Yosemite Valley of <name type="place">California</name>. Although prospectors had come upon it earlier, it was the Mariposa Battalion's report of Yosemite's stunning scenery that aroused the interest of entrepreneurs eager to exploit natural wonders as tourist attractions. We may recall that journalists had played an important role in the creation of Central Park. Similarly, writers and publishers took up the Yosemite cause. In this they were aided by the emerging art of photography. Stere-<lb/>
ographs for the armchair traveler spread the fame of the sheer granite walls rising 3,000 feet (914 meters) from the valley floor, but the real power and majesty of the scenery was better conveyed by the prints made from large glass plate negatives by Carleton E. Watkins (<date when="1829">1829</date>&#x2013;<date when="1916">1916</date>) and other photographers.</p>
<p>Wordsworthian Romanticism and the desire to celebrate an American equivalent to the Alps&#x2014;which John Ruskin had brought into focus as scenery of the sublime category capable of inspiring emotion in cul-<lb/>
tivated breasts&#x2014;as well as the delight American chau-<lb/>
vinists found in appropriating a "sacred place" that was equivalent to a Gothic cathedral or a Greek tem-<lb/>
ple soon led to the proposal to set aside the Yosemite and the nearby Mariposa Grove of giant sequoia trees <hi rend="italic">(Sequoia gigantea</hi>) as an inalienable part of the public domain. A bill was introduced in the United States Senate in <date when="1864">1864</date> to cede these lands to the state of <name type="place">Cal-<lb/>
ifornia</name> "for public use, resort and recreation," and when it was passed and signed into law by President Abraham Lincoln, the first step had been taken toward preserving portions of the national scenic pat-<lb/>
rimony for popular enjoyment. At this time, envi-<lb/>
ronmentalism and preserving wilderness to protect select ecosystems was not part of the public con-<lb/>
sciousness; the new park was regarded rather as a tourist commodity to be appreciated for its sublime scenery in the same manner as one would admire a noble work of art.</p>
<p>As discussed in Chapter Nine, at the time of Yosemite's acquisition by the state of <name type="place">California</name> (it would later become part of the national park system), Frederick Law Olm-<lb/>
sted, Sr., was in <name type="place">California</name> as the director of the Mariposa Mines, and because of his reputation as a park administrator, was appointed by the governor to oversee the development of design and management policies for Yosemite Park and the Mariposa Big Tree Grove. In a letter to his wife, Olmsted shared his first impression of this fine stand of <name type="place">California</name> giant sequoia trees: "You recognize them as soon as your eye falls on them, far away, not merely from the unusual size of the trunk but its remarkable color&#x2014;a cinnamon color, very elegant. You feel that they are distinguished strangers [who] have come down to us from another world, &#x2014;but the whole for-<lb/>
est is wonderful."<ref target="#CH10-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Olmsted, like almost everyone else at the time, realized the opportunity Yosemite presented for the burgeoning tourist industry and remarked in the report that he wrote in <date when="1865">1865</date> that Yosemite should "prove an attraction of simi-<lb/>
lar character and a similar source of wealth to the whole community, not only of <name type="place">California</name> but of the United States"<ref target="#CH10-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref>as the natural scenery of Switzerland. The nineteenth-cen-<lb/>
tury appetite for scenic wonders was tremendous, as the popularity of Niagara Falls had proved. Here, on an even grander scale than Niagara, was an example
<pb n="372"/>
<pb n="372" type="orig"/>
of scenery that could be characterized as sublime. Already painters and lithographers as well as pho-<lb/>
tographers and writers were making a living depict-<lb/>
ing it, and hotel developers and souvenir vendors were busy with schemes to exploit it.</p>
<p>The first object of any plan for Yosemite would necessarily be to protect its scenic integrity and to pre-<lb/>
vent the kind of commercial exploitation that marred the landscape around Niagara in the nineteenth cen-<lb/>
tury. Fortunately nature had accomplished at Yosemite what extensive grading and planting had done in Central Park: the visual exclusion of the rest of the world from an idyllic landscape. Lofty walls enclosed the valley and helped the visitor experience the exhilarating sense of spatial completeness and sanctity as in a majestic cathedral. For Olmsted, Yosemite represented "the union of the deepest sub-<lb/>
limity with the deepest beauty of nature, not in one feature or another, not in one part or one scene or another, not any landscape that can be framed by itself, but all around and wherever the visitor goes."<ref target="#CH10-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref> It had taken him some months to appreciate the beauty of <name type="place">California</name>'s dry-climate vegetation, but now in his Yosemite report, he could rhapsodize: "Cliffs of awful height and rocks of vast magnitude . . . are banked and fringed and draped and shadowed by the tender foliage of noble and lovely trees and bushes, reflected from the most placid pools, and associated with the most tranquil meadows, the most playful streams, and every variety of soft and peaceful pas-<lb/>
toral beauty."<ref target="#CH10-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref>The plan that he proposed was one with as few "artificial constructions" as possible and a circular carriage drive with turnouts placed to pres-<lb/>
ent the best opportunities for scenic viewing.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-452">
<graphic url="CH10_021.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.18. <name type="pname">Carleton E. Watkins</name>, <hi rend="italic">Cathedral Rock, 2,600 Feet, Yosemite.</hi> c. <date when="1866">1866</date>. The Metro-<lb/>
politan Museum of Art, <name type="place">New York</name>. Elisha Whittelsey Collection</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Today we think of Yosemite as simply one park within a magnificent system of national parks, and we therefore perhaps underestimate the powerful place it occupied in the nineteenth-century imagina-<lb/>
tion. The geologist Clarence King must have felt, like Olmsted, that Yosemite presented a synthesis of the sublime and the beautiful when he spoke of "a soft aerial depth of purple tone ... hiding details, veiling with its soft amethystine obscurity all that hard, bro-<lb/>
ken roughness of the Sentinel cliffs."<ref target="#CH10-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref>The inclina-<lb/>
tion toward the reverential was greatly enhanced by the atmospheric qualities of Albert Bierstadt's large and immensely popular paintings that cast religious light and color over the scene rather than emphasiz-<lb/>
ing Yosemite's sculptural qualities as Carleton Watkins's photographs did (fig. 10.18).</p>
<p>Perhaps the Sierra <name type="place">Nevada</name> and Yosemite found their true prophet in the naturalist John Muir (<date when="1838">1838</date>&#x2013;<date when="1914">1914</date>). What Ruskin had been to the Alps, Muir was to the Sierra. Ruskin saw the mountains as the "schools and cathedrals" of the human race, "full of treasures of illuminated manuscript for the scholar, kindly in simple lessons to the worker, quiet in pale cloisters for the thinker, glorious in holiness for the worshipper."<ref target="#CH10-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref>Muir found holy inspiration in trying to fathom the geologic history of the mountains that had been shaped by almost unimaginably powerful forces, including the passage of mighty glaciers.</p>
<p>The poet Wordsworth, whose lasting influence pervaded, however unconsciously, the attitude of wilderness lovers such as Muir, had conceived of "spots in time," vivid scenes of nature that became imprinted on the mind. Like funds in the bank avail-<lb/>
able for withdrawal at a later date, these scenes pro-<lb/>
vided capital for recollection and contemplation in the future. Muir's impressions perhaps went further; he believed that the sights of nature reveal the majesty of God and leave a permanent mark upon our souls. To Ralph Waldo Emerson, he extended an invitation to experience the exaltation of a journey with him in the high Sierras. The transcendentalist and author of the famous essay "On Nature" answered the call and, in <date when="1871">1871</date>, at the age of sixty-seven, made the arduous and rewarding journey.</p>
<p>Unknown except to Native Americans, trappers, and a few intrepid frontiersmen whose accounts of its seemingly fantastic, cosmically disordered scenery of spluttering mud volcanoes, shooting geysers, and boiling sulfur springs was often discounted, Yellow-<lb/>
stone did not enter the public consciousness until around <date when="1870">1870</date>. Again, it was journalists, artists, and pho-<lb/>
tographers who stimulated appreciation of this col-<lb/>
lection of natural wonders. Ferdinand V. Hayden, director of the U.S. Geological Survey, sought funds for a scientific exploration of the area, and his expe-<lb/>
dition party included the photographer William H. Jackson (<date when="1843">1843</date>&#x2013;<date when="1942">1942</date>) and the painter Thomas Moran
<pb n="373"/>
<pb n="373" type="orig"/>
(<date when="1837">1837</date>&#x2013;<date when="1926">1926</date>). Not only were the national parks to be objects of national pride and cultural icons them-<lb/>
selves, but also the depiction of them set new stan-<lb/>
dards of taste in landscape art and scenic appreciation. The work of Moran and Jackson was instrumental in the campaign that resulted in the passage in <date when="1872">1872</date> of a bill in Congress to establish Yellowstone as the coun-<lb/>
try's first national park (fig. 10.19).</p>
<p>Proponents, many of whom were railroad magnates and businessmen, deemed the benefits of the proposed park to be considerable: It would stim-<lb/>
ulate tourism and passenger railroads. For many tourists, of course, it was not the sublimity of the Yel-<lb/>
lowstone Canyon that attracted them as much as the weird, infernal performances of the mud pots, hot springs, and geysers. They came primarily to be enter-<lb/>
tained by these phenomenal features. John Muir, how-<lb/>
ever, could be depended on to read into the phantasmagorical Yellowstone landscape lessons both divine and Darwinian as he reminded his readers of the creative power of geologic forces embodying "cre-<lb/>
ation, progress in the march of beauty through death."<ref target="#CH10-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref>To his spiritual passion Muir wedded a prac-<lb/>
tical sense, and through his efforts the Sierra Club was founded as an organization advocating public own-<lb/>
ership of wilderness lands and, later, environmental protection in more general ways.</p>
<p>In <date when="1890">1890</date>, the Yosemite area (minus the Yosemite Valley) was transferred from the state of <name type="place">California</name> to the national government, and, in <date when="1899">1899</date>, Mount Rainier National Park was created. Other parks were acquired not only for scenic, but also for scientific and histori-<lb/>
cal reasons, especially after Theodore Roosevelt, encouraged through his association with <name type="pname">John Muir</name>, became an early proponent of conservation. The administration of these parks was haphazard, for there was as yet no National Park Service. Then, in <date when="1914">1914</date>, Stephen Mather (<date when="1867">1867</date>&#x2013;<date when="1930">1930</date>), an industrialist in <name type="place">Chicago</name> and an ardent hiker and member of the Sierra Club, wrote to Secretary of the Interior Franklin K. Lane, complaining of the condition of the parks. Lane, well aware of the problem, had already employed a young lawyer in <name type="place">California</name>, <name type="pname">Horace M. Albright</name>, to study ways to improve the administra-<lb/>
tion of the national parks. Recognizing that, as a businessman, Mather possessed considerable organi-<lb/>
zational and administrative talents, Lane promptly invited him to come to <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, and take charge of the situation. Mather accepted the chal-<lb/>
lenge, and he and Albright became a formidable team. Their combination of idealism and pragmatism forged the National Parks Act, creating the National Park Service, which President Woodrow Wilson signed into law in <date when="1916">1916</date>. The national park system that was forged in the ensuing years&#x2014;as many more national parks were created, historic sites designated, and large tracts of unspoiled coastline legislated into national seashores&#x2014;is a proud achievement of the American people and has been a potent instrument in shaping the nation's image of itself.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-453">
<graphic url="CH10_022.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">10.19. <name type="pname">Thomas Moran</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Grand Canyon of the Yellow-<lb/>
stone.</hi> <date when="1872">1872</date>. National Museum of American Art. Lent by the U. S. Department of the Inte-<lb/>
rior, National Park Service</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="374"/>
<pb n="374" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Ten</hi></hi></head>
<note xml:id="CH10-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p> <hi rend="italic">Modernism</hi> is the movement that responded optimistically to machine tec-<lb/>
hnology and the speeded-up tempo of twen-<lb/>
tieth-century machine-age civilization. It is expressed in several arts: in painting and sculpture as Cubism, Futurism, and other styles that fragment form and generally value its abstract character more than any remaining narrative content; in music as jazz, a fluid, improvisational medium that captures the syncopated tempo and erotic energy pulsing through urban life; in archi-<lb/>
tecture as design that honors industrial technology and materials by divesting itself of the proportions and ornament of classi-<lb/>
cal humanism and the structural means and decorative vocabulary inherited from the medieval and Renaissance past; in lit-<lb/>
erature as poems and novels that portray the transactions between the human soul and societies in which the security of com-<lb/>
munity has been superseded by personal anonymity and an intoxicating sense of possibility derived from new means of physical mobility and a new sense of social freedom. Modernism is fundamentally a state of culture that romanticizes reason, believing that rational application of sci-<lb/>
ence and technology combined with egal-<lb/>
itarian politics will create a better world. <hi rend="italic">Postmodernism</hi> questions modernism's attempted radical break with history and, because many modernist ideals have been discredited, sees its utopian articles of faith as naive. Being reactive, it is stylistically reiterative, re-presenting historical styles in quotation form, as echoes of earlier forms within a contemporary culture that is philosophically groundless and therefore without a special formal vocabulary of its own. Ironically, postmodern culture is vastly more machine-driven than the culture of modernism that preceded it.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p> During his visit to <name type="place">Paris</name> in <date when="1859">1859</date>, Olmsted noted the essential character of this aspect of French park construction, remarking that "The principal rock-work is much more like an operatic fairy scene than any thing in nature; and as its great size prevents it from being regarded as puerile or grotesque, like Chinese garden scenes, it may be consid-<lb/>
ered to have been conceived in an original style to which the term romantic may be rightly applied." Essay on "Parks at Home and Abroad" (<date when="1861">1861</date>); see Charles Capen McLaughlin, ed.-in-chief, <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted, Volume III: Creat-<lb/>
ing Central Park,</hi> ed. Charles E. Beveridge and David Schuyler (<name type="place">Baltimore</name>: The Johns Hopkins University Press, <date when="1983">1983</date>), p. 349.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">William Robinson</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Parks, Prome-<lb/>
nades &amp; Gardens of <name type="place">Paris</name></hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: <name type="pname">John Murray</name>, <date when="1869">1869</date>), p. 64.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p> For a brilliant meditation upon the mean-<lb/>
ing of the Eiffel Tower, see Roland Barthes, <hi rend="italic">The Eiffel Tower and Other Mythologies,</hi> trans. <name type="pname">Richard Howard</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, Inc., <date when="1979">1979</date>). Here Barthes writes, "The Tower attracts meaning, the way a lightning rod attracts thunderbolts; for all lovers of signification, it plays a glam-<lb/>
orous part, that of pure signifier, i.e., of a form in which men unceasingly put <hi rend="italic">mean-<lb/>
ing</hi> (which they extract at will from their knowledge, their dreams, their history), without this meaning thereby ever being finite and fixed: who can say what the Tower will be for humanity tomorrow? But there can be no doubt it will always be something other and something much more than the Eiffel Tower" (University of <name type="place">Cali-<lb/>
fornia</name> Press ed., <date when="1997">1997</date>, p. 5).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p> Report of the Senate Committee on the District of Columbia on the Improvement of the Park System of the District of Columbia, <hi rend="italic">The Improvement of the Park System of the District of Columbia</hi> (<name type="place">Washington</name>: <date when="1902">1902</date>) as quoted in <name type="pname">John W. Reps</name>, <hi rend="italic">Monumental <name type="place">Washington</name>: The Planning and Develop-<lb/>
ment of the Capital Center</hi> (<name type="place">Princeton</name>: Princeton University Press), p. 131.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p> I am indebted to Timothy Davis, "Rock Creek and Potomac Parkway, <name type="place">Washington</name>, DC: The Evolution of a contested urban landscape," <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History of Gar-<lb/>
dens &amp; Designed Landscapes</hi> 19:2 (April&#x2014;June <date when="1999">1999</date>) for the excellent research upon which the following narrative is drawn.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p> "Letter to Mary Perkins Olmsted, Bear Valley, <date when="1863-11-20">November 20, 1863</date>," in <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Fred-<lb/>
erick Law Olmsted, Volume V,</hi> ed. Victoria Post Ranney (<name type="place">Baltimore</name>: The Johns Hopkins University Press, <date when="1990">1990</date>), pp. 136&#x2013;37.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p> "Preliminary Report upon the Yosemite and Big Tree Grove," in <hi rend="italic">The Papers of Frederick Law Olmsted, Volume V,</hi> ed. Victoria Post Ranney, p. 501.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 500.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p> Ibid.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">John Muir</name>, <hi rend="italic">Mountaineering in the Sierra <name type="place">Nevada</name>,</hi> as quoted in Sears, <hi rend="italic">Sacred Places: American Tourist Attractions in the Nine-<lb/>
teenth Century</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Oxford</name> Univer-<lb/>
sity Press, <date when="1989">1989</date>), p. 134.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">John Ruskin</name>, <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters</hi> (<name type="place">Boston</name>: Dana Estes, <date when="1880">1880</date>), vol. IV, p. 217.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH10-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p> "The Yellowstone National Park," <hi rend="italic">Our National Parks</hi> (<date when="1901">1901</date>), as quoted in Sears, op. cit., p. 177.</p></note>
</div>
</div>
