<div type="chapter">
<pb n="470"/>
<pb n="470" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER FIFTEEN HOLDING ON AND LETTING GROW: LANDSCAPE AS PRESERVATION, CONSERVATION, ART, SPORT, AND THEORY</hi></head>
<figure xml:id="fig-578">
<graphic url="CH15_001.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p>The rapidity of change in the designed landscape is an important by-product of modernity. The accelerating powers of the Late Machine Age and the new Information Age have gained tremendous force as the fast-paced and continually evolving alliance of science and technology has assumed a position of extraordinary cultural dominance in contemporary society. This has caused the meaning of space and time to simultaneously expand and contract. Even as we contemplate travel to the outer reaches of our universe, contempo-<lb/>
rary cosmology offers only the most contingent explanation of our place within its framework. Because of these things, everything appears to be mutable. Increasingly, place appears to be in flux.</p>
<p>Just as modern physics has unseated old cosmological veri-<lb/>
ties, proving that outer space is an indeterminate galactic sprawl, so too have the centrifugal forces that once constellated suburbs within the orbit of major urban centers been superseded by newer technologies that make even so-called Edge Cities edgeless, part of a patterning of amorphous human settlement never before seen. Like a mutating organism, this kind of sprawling urbanism is part of the unending process of landscape transformation.</p>
<p>Industrial technology has created within the span of a single century an entirely new landscape of electric power grids, conti-<lb/>
nent-spanning highways, and skyscraper cities that would seem unbelievable to a visitor from the not-too-distant past. The mod-<lb/>
ern regional city&#x2014;a loose-knit urban agglomerate containing air-<lb/>
ports, expressways, a vast network of streets and corresponding pattern of lights and neon signs, and air-conditioned high-rise commercial buildings set in a sea of suburban homes and shopping centers&#x2014;is still a recent phenomenon. The passenger elevator, water mains, and pipes for the delivery of hot and cold running water, the flush toilet&#x2014;all these developments that we now take for granted are minor when compared with the way technology has revolutionized agriculture and gathered up entire populations from the land and enfolded them into the city Urbanism has so pervaded the rural landscape that the metaphor of "the machine in the gar-<lb/>
den," as analyzed by Leo Marx from a literary perspective in his book of that title, can now be inverted; the quintessential <hi rend="italic">rus in urbe,</hi> Central Park, could be called "the garden in the machine" that is <name type="place">New York</name> City, the heart of the Atlantic seaboard megalopolis, which extends from <name type="place">Boston</name> to <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name></p>
<p>Even where suburbanization has not occurred, farming as an economic mainstay and means of individual family livelihood has all but disappeared as industrial technology has transformed food production and efficient transportation systems have enabled national and global shipments of perishable commodities. Rural land, much of it reverting to second growth, is valued more as scenery than as cropland or pasture. Local farming, where it still exists, has become either marginal or a specialized enterprise cater-<lb/>
ing to an upscale market. A rural residence no longer implies an agrarian occupation or outlook as increasingly for many people res-<lb/>
idential location is becoming a matter of personal choice.</p>
<p>Corporate franchises have assisted suburban developers in the colonization of regional space. Everywhere the forces of global capitalism are at work. Powered by mass marketing and advertis-<lb/>
ing, they are creating a universal culture, making national and regional identities less distinctive even as growing numbers of tourists travel to remote places in search of <hi rend="italic">local</hi> color.</p>
<p>Centripetal as well as centrifugal forces are at work. As cities in <name type="place">America</name> and elsewhere begin to reverse their recent decades of decline with renewed capital investment in their core areas and the residential return of retirement couples and young professionals, their attractiveness as places to live as well as their role as tourist destinations and entertainment centers is increasing. Thus we see at the beginning of the twenty-first century a transformation of the city not by governmental planning, such as was sought by
<pb n="471"/>
<pb n="471" type="orig"/>
visionaries at the beginning of the previous century, but rather by free enterprise. No longer centers of manufacturing and trade, some cities are promoting themselves in terms of the service economy and a more vibrant lifestyle than can be found in the suburbs. Many are reconfiguring industrial waterfronts as promenades lined with restaurants, sports facilities, and outdoor festival spaces; retrofitting commercial real estate with mall-style stores and theaters; turning industrial buildings into loft apartments, shops, artists' studios and galleries; and reclaiming abandoned rail and canal rights-of-way as jogging and bike trails. Cultural centers, entertainment complexes, and arenas for spectator sports are high on almost every contempo-<lb/>
rary urban agenda. These things, together with electronic-game arcades, health clubs, tennis centers, and other fitness and recreational facilities, are making cities places that are increasingly dedicated to personal gratification.</p>
<p>In addition, with a sense of entitlement to recreational ben-<lb/>
efits implicit in the democratic values of Western industrial coun-<lb/>
tries and <name type="place">Japan</name>, leisure continues to give rise to new land uses and landscape designs, as evidenced by the construction of golf courses in many countries and climates, even desert ones, because of the phenomenal latter-day popularity of an obscure sport that origi-<lb/>
nated on the links lands of estuarial <name type="place">Scotland</name> in the fifteenth cen-<lb/>
tury. Thus, ironically in accommodating new forms of pleasure, the metropolis, which has so urbanized its surrounding rural landscape that its natural environs have all but disappeared, is itself becoming more parklike in character.</p>
<p>Photography's relationship to landscape, discussed in the pre-<lb/>
vious chapter, grows apace. As a genre, landscape photography stimulates an appreciation of the poetics of place and builds archives that register the appearance and uses of places through time. Today historical photographs of landscapes and cityscapes provide a valu-<lb/>
able record of their former appearance, assisting preservationists and educating the public. Aerial photography is an important tool for the cultural geographer's reading of the vernacular landscape. It has made commonplace the <hi rend="italic">synoptic</hi> vision that Patrick Geddes advocated from his Outlook Tower&#x2014;that is, seeing cities and their regional landscapes entire in a single panoramic bird's-eye view that reveals overall structure while eliminating from sight close-range detail and disorder. Further, photography is the indispensable means whereby artists of Earthworks or Conceptual pieces of a tempo-<lb/>
rary nature document and gain recognition of their work.</p>
<p>In addition, photography has altered the way in which we read the city. Film has made us comfortable with <hi rend="italic">montage,</hi> choosing relevant fragments from a plethora of visual stimuli and reassem-<lb/>
bling them into a coherent personal imagery and narrative that is both sensory and symbolic. Urbanites are all film editors to a degree; understanding the metropolis and feeling at home in its impersonal immensity would be difficult without this strategy of composite conceptualization. An important means of distraction from everyday life, film has become a contemporary form of <hi rend="italic">fl&#x00E2;nerie,</hi> the voyeuristic pursuit of the everyday dramas of the metropolis. Mental mapping of the city is, as urban design analyst Kevin Lynch taught, a means of parsing it through a process of per-<lb/>
sonal landmarking.<ref target="#CH15-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref>Notable architecture and important public places&#x2014;as well as the locations of establishments that cater to our personal needs&#x2014;become geographies of the mind. As cities grow increasingly vast and diffuse, this imagistic form of perception is the only way in which we are able to make sense of our sur-<lb/>
roundings. Urban public space has, like films and photomontage, become for deconstructivist philosophers such as Jacques Derrida (b. <date when="1930">1930</date>) an impersonal vessel for multiple, simultaneous, and sequential personal meanings.</p>
<p>The incomprehensibility of the modern city and its suburbs is mitigated by networks of communication and transportation&#x2014; newspapers, radio and television broadcasting, bus and subway routes. We grasp the city in terms of these lines of movement and channels of information, media for a miscellany of messages as well as the means of navigating the metropolis. Photography in the form of advertising saturates these networks just as it domi-<lb/>
nates prominent public spaces where there is a large flow of traf-<lb/>
fic. We have become comfortable with our dichotomous existence, at home physically in front of the television set and at the same time mentally in Bangladesh where disaster has struck or at the scene of a crime in another part of our own city, courtesy of the news services' roving video crews.<ref target="#CH15-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref>We swim in a sea of visual stim-<lb/>
uli, and increasingly what we focus upon most intently is not our visible surroundings but the mental images evoked by representa-<lb/>
tions of another reality elsewhere.</p>
<p>With the commodification of urban life and culture, pho-<lb/>
tography has played a significant role in eroticizing the public envi-<lb/>
ronment. Libidinal stimuli proliferate as ads on bus shelters, billboards, and movie marquees. With its rivers of rippling neon and moving car lights, the spatially ambiguous nocturnal city can assume a fantastic, surreal aspect catering to the dreams and desires that photography has projected so alluringly on the movie screen and on the street. By both night and day, shop windows proclaim the sexualization of the urban environment as well as the increas-<lb/>
ingly public face of pornography. Former cityscapes of stone and brick and steel and glass are being transformed into the scenery of signs as virtuality overwhelms reality.</p>
<p>The city as an arena of human endeavor, community, and pleasure persists in spite of ugliness, suburban sprawl, and the rav-<lb/>
aging effect of the automobile upon its physical fabric and the expe-<lb/>
rience of place within it. Shopping as a form of entertainment is a hallmark of the consumer society, and even in the face of electronic commerce and catalogue merchandising, people still gravitate to Fifth Avenue, Wilshire Boulevard, and Michigan Avenue as well as the mall. Today the city of smokestack factories has given way to the city of commingled commerce and recreation.</p>
<p>And yet there is a sense of malaise and loss. The commodifi-<lb/>
cation of space and the ease with which nature and the built envi-<lb/>
ronment can be altered with heavy earthmoving and construction equipment have made the human bond with nature appear tenu-<lb/>
ous and the tie with the past seem fragile. Just as many of the mighty monuments intended for the ages now lie in ruins, so, too, are the architectural wonders of one generation torn down by the next. The commitment to create public places that express the val-<lb/>
ues of society has waned. Municipal governments in the United States are no longer able to sustain the parks they built only a cen-<lb/>
tury ago and must depend upon varying degrees of private citizen
<pb n="472"/>
<pb n="472" type="orig"/>
initiative to restore and help maintain them. Clearly, the notion that buildings and landscapes have any real permanence other than what we provide through repeated acts of maintenance and preserva-<lb/>
tion is wishful thinking.</p>
<p>Many people fear that the Faustian forces that have propelled modernity may be careening out of control. Humanity's relationship with nature has been thoroughly inverted. Having gained the tech-<lb/>
nological power Goethe foretold in <hi rend="italic">Faust, Part II</hi> and behaving no longer as nature's subjects, humans have acted ruthlessly, poisoned air and water, destroyed forests and wetlands, and caused many wild species to decline or become extinct. Because of this, contemporary society can now look back with a degree of horror on the nine-<lb/>
teenth- and twentieth-century belief in environmental engineering solely for human ends. Gone is the optimism and belief in technol-<lb/>
ogy as a worthy partner of nature as expressed by proponents of modernism such as <name type="pname">Benton MacKaye</name>, <name type="pname">Christopher Tunnard</name>, and <name type="pname">Garrett Eckbo</name> (see Chapters Twelve and Thirteen). Instead, the envi-<lb/>
ronmental movement, with its wide-ranging and sometimes intently focused mission of of planetary damage control, has gathered broad support within industrial nations since the <date when="1970">1970</date>s.</p>
<p>Like wilderness, historic landscapes exist on sufferance; some are protected by legislation but remain vulnerable to encroachment and destruction by economic and political forces. Especially in Amer-<lb/>
ica, where the citizenry has profligately exploited land and a mobile road culture has been a forceful determinant of land use, many once-<lb/>
handsome towns are both rammed through and rimmed by high-<lb/>
ways fringed with gas stations, fast-food franchise establishments, and other commercial operations with signs aggressively sized and illuminated to catch the eye of the rapidly moving motorist.</p>
<p>This willful eradication of much historic fabric in the twen-<lb/>
tieth century by transportation engineers and "urban renewal" plan-<lb/>
ners has brutalized cities to a far greater degree than Haussmann did nineteenth-century <name type="place">Paris</name>. Modernism's radical, intentional dis-<lb/>
regard for history created a palpable discontinuity with the past. In reaction, there arose a well-supported belief that traditional forms of architecture and urbanism are endangered. This helps account for the high regard in which landmark designation and preserva-<lb/>
tion are held today.</p>
<p>But just as environmental stewardship inevitably turns nature into the worthy ward of humanity, preservation of the built envi-<lb/>
ronment, an entirely laudable and overdue effort, has come to a sim-<lb/>
ilarly patronizing position. Formerly, we created monuments as symbols honoring a moral contract that present and future gener-<lb/>
ations hold with the values represented by past heroes. This has suc-<lb/>
cumbed to a fascination with history as a means of experiencing through architecture and artifacts the social and economic practices and lost craft skills of pretechnological times. While dependent upon automobile transportation and the modern technological service infrastructure that makes tourism possible, Colonial Williamsburg and its counterparts ably serve this purpose. Guides provide inter-<lb/>
pretive narratives that satisfy people's desire to sample vicariously a comfortable facsimile of life in bygone days. Theme parks also sim-<lb/>
ulate past environments for the same reasons, and today some his-<lb/>
toric small towns and urban centers are distinguished from these only by virtue of occupying an authentically historic site.</p>
<p>Reaction to the architecturally bland, commercially ingrati-<lb/>
ating, diffuse, and chaotic landscape of late-twentieth-century <name type="place">America</name>, coupled with a profound questioning of the established order of society and the discrediting of the symbolical value of tra-<lb/>
ditional monuments, provided the context for a Conceptual art that engaged viewers in considerations of entropy. Unlike theme-park developers who create a familiar product aimed at the mass con-<lb/>
sumer, the artists who create a novel poetics of place with large-<lb/>
scale transformations of the landscape do so in reaction to the values of the consumer society and what they perceive as the commodification of art. Implicit in their art is an attitude toward time in which "both past and future are placed into an objective pres-<lb/>
ent."<ref target="#CH15-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref>The Earthworks movement pioneered by Robert Smithson and a group of fellow artists, who positioned themselves in oppo-<lb/>
sition to traditional modes of artistic expression and the institu-<lb/>
tional framework for displaying art, created a new kind of anti-<lb/>
monumental, monumental art that was "not built for the ages, but rather against the ages."<ref target="#CH15-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref>Within the context of a consumer soci-<lb/>
ety surfeited with banal products, Smithson and other Earthworks artists, like an earlier generation of Surrealist artists, saw denatured and dehumanized emptiness&#x2014;"a ‘City of the Future' made of null structures and surfaces, [which] performs no natural function [but] simply exists between mind and matter, detached from both, rep-<lb/>
resenting neither"<ref target="#CH15-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref>&#x2014;as a metaphorically appropriate expression. In their work they fostered the spirit found in the literature of Latin American Magic Realists such as Jorge Luis Borges. They often sought sites for their projects in desert environments where, using heavy earthmoving equipment, they constructed, on a similar scale and often with the same cosmological relationship between earth and sky, forms like the mounds and other earthworks found in pre-<lb/>
historic ritual centers.</p>
<p>Today, we find an orientation toward the psychological and the empirical in contemporary Western thought and life. Intellec-<lb/>
tual focus is upon exegesis and fact collection. Contemporary West-<lb/>
ern culture, lacking an overarching, society-embracing religious or ideological construct, is obsessed with history and historical revi-<lb/>
sionism. It places emphasis upon personal experience, individual rights, and the self. Along with diaspora populations attempting to replicate old folkways and familiar environments, indigenous groups threatened by the rapid transformation of the familiar into the strange cling to traditional forms as a means of maintaining self-recognition and personal esteem. As cultural geographer David Lowenthal posits, because the contemporary world is beset with many ills and uncertainties, people "revert to ancestral legacies. As hopes of progress fade, heritage consoles us with tradition."<ref target="#CH15-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref> Our challenge today is to safeguard the future by turning our under-<lb/>
standing of the ephemeral nature of place to positive account, mak-<lb/>
ing good new spaces by preserving some good old places while daring to trust our capacity to create anew Our success will depend upon our skill and luck in achieving environments that incorpo-<lb/>
rate in their design a more perfect understanding of ecological processes and the rightful role of history and nature in human life than is now the case.</p>
<div type="section">
<pb n="473"/>
<pb n="473" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Preserving the Past: Place as Heritage, Identity Tourist Landscape, and New Urbanist Community</hi></head>
<p>Landscape preservation is the process of investing cer-<lb/>
tain portions of environment, both designed spaces and vernacular places, with historical meaning, aes-<lb/>
thetic value, and symbolical intent. Because all built things and created artifacts alter and deteriorate over time, preservation almost invariably implies restora-<lb/>
tion. If what is preserved and restored embodies suf-<lb/>
ficient significance, beauty, and mythic value to serve as cultural heritage in a more universal sense, broad-<lb/>
scale reproduction and replication of the original his-<lb/>
toric forms in other contexts commonly occurs.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Preservation as Cultural Heritage</hi></head>
<p>The <name type="place">Pennsylvania</name> State Building at the World's Columbian Exposition of <date when="1893">1893</date> in <name type="place">Chicago</name> was a fac-<lb/>
simile of Independence Hall in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, or rather an evocation of it, the replica being altered in scale and architectural program. Along with several other state buildings erected at the fair honoring (one year late) the four-hundredth anniversary of Columbus's landfall in <name type="place">America</name> and, by association the Founders of the republic, it helped further the Colonial Revival that had been sparked by the Centennial Exposition of <date when="1876">1876</date> in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>. The Colonial Revival style was subsequently disseminated in tandem with the Neoclassical Beaux-Arts style, which was prominently featured in the monumental white buildings around <name type="pname">Daniel Burnham</name>'s Court of Honor (see fig. 9.56). The iconic and narrative value of landmark reproductions of Independence Hall and the entire design vocabu-<lb/>
lary of the <name type="pname">Colonial Revival</name> is obvious; the relatively brief history of the United States is attractively grounded in the myth it embodies of the simple refinement of an industrious, freedom-loving people. It is not surprising therefore to find many echoes of Independence Hall, Mount Vernon, and other shrines of liberty and national foundation in the pseudohis-<lb/>
toric architecture of the present. It is abundantly clear, too, why in Disney's Magic Kingdom, where the ener-<lb/>
getic wholesomeness of <name type="place">America</name> and its people is the paramount message of the entire theme park, that there should be a mint-condition reproduction of Independence Hall (fig. 15.1).</p>
<p>Historic preservation's role in signaling present values helps account for the persistence of "the styles" in spite of Modernism's polemic against them. Like the view into an endlessly self-reflecting set of mir-<lb/>
rors, these imitations of the past are often imitations of other earlier imitations of the past, and so on, a chainlike process in which old forms are continually reinvested with new meaning as present ideals are associated with past eras. Purged of political rancor and ordinary misery, the landscapes that project the mystique of former ages&#x2014;whether ancient Greece or colonial <name type="place">America</name>&#x2014;retain their hold on the human imagination, becoming totems of both status and ide-<lb/>
ology.</p>
<p>But heritage icons do not tap the more personal reservoirs of memory. <name type="pname">Kevin Lynch</name> (<date when="1918">1918</date>&#x2013;<date when="1984">1984</date>), an influential teacher, environmental design theorist, and thoughtful writer on the subject of place has sug-<lb/>
gested that "we might begin to commemorate the histories of ordinary people in ordinary places [inas-<lb/>
much as] local, intimate time has a much more pow-<lb/>
erful meaning for us than the illustrious time of national monuments."<ref target="#CH15-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref>Lynch was interested in tran-<lb/>
scending stasis, the "preserved-in-amber" quality of so much historic preservation. A more dynamic model of preservation that included the evidence of time&#x2014;the ebb and flow of events across a particular space&#x2014;would encode into cherished spaces notations of change; it would commemorate death and demise as well as birth and creation. Lynch's radical-sound-<lb/>
ing idea was "to conserve <hi rend="italic">and</hi> to destroy the physical environment so as to support and to enrich the sense of time held by the very people that use it."<ref target="#CH15-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-579">
<graphic url="CH15_002.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.1. Independence Hall, Magic Kingdom, Walt Disney World, <name type="place">Orlando Florida</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p><name type="pname">Dolores Hayden</name>, professor of Architecture, Urbanism, and American Studies at Yale University, shares Lynch's concern to discover strategies for investing ordinary places with commemorative value as a means of connecting the lives of ordinary peo-<lb/>
ple to their immediate surroundings. Hayden worked
<pb n="474"/>
<pb n="474" type="orig"/>
over a period of eight years "to situate women's his-<lb/>
tory and ethnic history in downtown [<name type="place">Los Angeles</name>], in public places, through experimental, collaborative projects by historians, designers, and artists."<ref target="#CH15-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref> The efforts of Hayden and others have been helped by a changing cultural climate that seeks, however imper-<lb/>
fectly at times, to respect equally the contributions to society of both sexes and to honor the heroines and heroes of many different ethnic backgrounds. The stubborn fact remains that much preservation senti-<lb/>
ment adheres especially to those outstanding indi-<lb/>
vidual buildings, cityscapes, and landscapes where substantial past investment of money and design tal-<lb/>
ent was made by people who were prominent in their time. In addition, despite a contemporary disinclina-<lb/>
tion toward heroic sentiment and religious and patri-<lb/>
otic public monuments, some of the ideals and values of the past that are expressed in historically preserved landscapes often continue to hold important sym-<lb/>
bolical meaning for people today.</p>
<p>Closely allied with preservation as a means of assigning commemorative value to the built envi-<lb/>
ronment, conservation is the protection of natural areas from despoliation by human activity that harms essential qualities of place and the habitats of other species. Both preservation and conservation emerged as important causes in the second part of the nine-<lb/>
teenth century. Since the <date when="1960">1960</date>s&#x2014;a period of wide-<lb/>
spread social and political change fostering populism and democratic empowerment&#x2014;recognition of tremendous population growth and the dire conse-<lb/>
quences of rampant development and unchecked industrial pollution have given impetus to organized movements that continue to advance the related causes of preservation and conservation.</p>
<p>Although conservation groups often have an anti-urban bias and are therefore indifferent to issues regarding the design of cities, both forces&#x2014;preserva-<lb/>
tion and conservation&#x2014;are essential to a landscape ethic that values the environment as a continuum in which nature is rightly perceived as being everywhere, in the densest urban neighborhoods as well as in the wilderness. To achieve a viable landscape ethic based on this integrated perspective it is also necessary to accept and help shape new industrial development, the mainstay of most modern economies and the means of sustaining decent living standards among the masses. There is hope that the reportorial power of new global information systems and the management capabilities made possible by computer technology and the Internet will assist in creating this necessary ethic of responsible total planetary stewardship. Our task here is to advocate that outcome as we examine how preservation and conservation have affected land-<lb/>
scape as a place-making enterprise.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Preservation as Cultural Identity</hi></head>
<p>Cultures in transition are pulled in two directions, enthusiastically toward the future and nostalgically toward the past. Especially in times of great techno-<lb/>
logical change, economic stress, and social disloca-<lb/>
tion, people entertain fantasies of recovering the past, a time when they imagine that life was simpler and more rewarding, craftskills were honest, people were prosperous, and communities lived in harmony. Although this is a thoroughly edited version of his-<lb/>
tory, the trappings of the past provide useful symbols for the present. The artifacts, architecture, and land-<lb/>
scapes of a bygone era are invested with value and meaning, becoming the delight of historians and con-<lb/>
noisseurs as well as the icons of embattled gentility. There is a moral dimension and educative element to this process, which seeks to make reverence for ances-<lb/>
tral forms and older lifeways a rallying point around which values of nation and community can cohere.</p>
<p>The <name type="place">New England</name> town, whose origins we examined in Chapter Six, reached its apogee between <date when="1780">1780</date> and <date when="1830">1830</date>, during <name type="place">America</name>'s early industrial age.<ref target="#CH15-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref> Nestled in hilly and mountainous terrain, most <name type="place">New England</name> towns were subsequently bypassed by eco-<lb/>
nomic development, becoming depopulated back-<lb/>
waters as railroads sought more accessible routes and extended farther west, causing emigration to larger industrial centers and richer agricultural lands. But by the middle of the nineteenth century, wealthy peo-<lb/>
ple from <name type="place">New York</name> and <name type="place">Boston</name> began to establish themselves in summer colonies in <name type="place">Stockbridge</name>, <name type="place">Mass-<lb/>
achusetts</name>, and other towns of the Berkshires as well as elsewhere. These affluent part-time citizens helped form Village Improvement Societies for the purpose of planting trees along the towns' principal thor-<lb/>
oughfares and transforming into grassy, parklike pic-<lb/>
turesqueness their central commons, which had been pastures in Puritan times and remained mostly bar-<lb/>
ren, utilitarian, workaday spaces until this landscap-<lb/>
ing was undertaken.</p>
<p>During his brief but influential career, <name type="pname">Andrew Jackson</name> Downing was an early proselytizer for the beautification of towns and villages in this way. In Downing's time, the mid-nineteenth century, houses were adorned with brackets and painted in then-fash-<lb/>
ionable russet browns and other earth-tone colors. But following the Centennial of <date when="1876">1876</date>, as the country began its race toward large-scale industrialization, the early preservationists who were tastemakers within these venerable communities&#x2014;an alliance of sum-<lb/>
mer residents and well-to-do natives who shared the same Anglo-Saxon ethnic origins&#x2014;sought to con-<lb/>
nect themselves ideologically and symbolically with the nation's beginnings by adopting a more chaste, though elegant, architecture style harking back to the
<pb n="475"/>
<pb n="475" type="orig"/>
colonial and federal periods. In Litchfield, Connecti-<lb/>
cut, for instance, residents reproduced Colonial-style houses, which they painted white, although the orig-<lb/>
inal models were mostly unpainted, with shutters and trim of handsomely contrasting black or dark green. Outbuildings, barns, and other unprepossessing rural paraphernalia that had once surrounded the actual colonial houses were edited out of the restoration program. To commemorate the nation's Centennial, Litchfield's Village Improvement Society planted reg-<lb/>
ularly spaced elm trees, whose overarching branches soon canopied the main street. In this way, Litchfield, along with <name type="pname">Sharon</name>, <name type="place">Stockbridge</name>, and other early examples of gentrification throughout <name type="place">New England</name> projected a composite image of an earlier <name type="place">America</name>, a place that was gracious, green, white, and steepled.</p>
<p>There was an escapist element in this kind of historic preservation, a flight from the problems of the swelling industrial cities with their diverse immi-<lb/>
grant populations. There was an element of snob-<lb/>
bery, too; the Colonial theme expressed the assertion of primacy on the part of the old guard, a means of securing status and respect within the rapidly chang-<lb/>
ing society. Beneath its veneer of republican virtue and communal decorum, inevitable tensions arose between those mostly well-to-do residents with incomes often derived from industrial enterprises else-<lb/>
where and local townspeople who valued historical ambiance less than economic development.</p>
<p>The re-created <name type="place">New England</name> town assumed iconic status in the imaginations of many Americans, becoming a symbol of the prosperous, homoge-<lb/>
neous, nuclear community of individuals living in a state of friendly symbiosis. Its architectural forms served as a common vocabulary employed by devel-<lb/>
opers of early malls and subdivisions, as we have seen in our discussion of Levittown with its Cape Cod Colonial houses built around a series of "Village Greens." Appropriated by hotel chains and corporate franchises, the Colonial Revival style became a ubiq-<lb/>
uitous language, a means of fostering consumer trust by linking particular commercial corporations with patriotic sentiment.</p>
<p>The same forces that stimulated the preserva-<lb/>
tion movement in <name type="place">New England</name> promoted citizen efforts to save historic landscapes in the Old South and other parts of the country. Often these were led by women, many of whom belonged to genealogi-<lb/>
cally oriented organizations such as the Colonial Dames or the Daughters of the Texas Republic (pre-<lb/>
servers and custodians of the Alamo). In <date when="1931">1931</date>, <name type="place">Charleston</name>, <name type="place">South Carolina</name>, passed the first perma-<lb/>
nent design-review ordinance, mandating that private property owners within the designated historic area submit proposed alteration schemes for approval.</p>
<p>Enthusiasm for colonial heritage extended to other than its Anglo-Saxon Protestant forms. In <name type="place">Cal-<lb/>
ifornia</name>, <name type="place">New Mexico</name>, <name type="place">Texas</name>, and <name type="place">Florida</name>, Anglo-Amer-<lb/>
icans appropriated a Spanish Colonial design idiom, which they romanticized as the Mission Style, while residents in <name type="place">Louisiana</name> looked appreciatively toward the residue of a French Colonial past. By the mid-<lb/>
<date when="1950">1950</date>s, about ten American cities, including <name type="place">Santa Barbara</name> and <name type="place">New Orleans</name>, had historic districts. This kind of preservation, like the yet-to-be-conceived theme park, treated landscape as historical narrative, with emphasis upon those parts of the story that were most attractive and laudable, omitting those, such as slavery, that caused embarrassment.</p>
<p>Restoration along approved lines in historic dis-<lb/>
tricts has led to wide replication of historic forms. In some places, this process has also become an exercise in genteel mythmaking in which restrictive covenants and a stringent building-approval process have codi-<lb/>
fied design, resulting in the wholesale manufacture of regional cultural identity by architects and builders through the creation of a romanticized landscape of the past. Notable in this regard, <name type="pname">Santa Fe</name>, <name type="place">New Mex-<lb/>
ico</name>, is a place where people of Anglo-Saxon stock dwell in adobe houses that are commodious versions of older Hispanic models, which in turn were derived from the architecture and building materials of Native American pueblos.<ref target="#CH15-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref> Few people seem to mind the faux-adobe gas stations and shopping centers on the highway, but some Hispanics and Native Americans understandably resent the hegemonic appropriation of cultural heritage and landscape by non-natives who wear the city's much-transformed design tradition like a colorful shawl while often considering its living representatives to be an underclass. But there is a candy coating, economically speaking, on outsider-<lb/>
financed, highly interpretive historic preservation: Cities such as Santa Fe that have cultivated their his-<lb/>
toric image in this way are tourist magnets. Having denied themselves the opportunity to transform their cultural landscape, they grow prosperous from the trade of visitors.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Preservation as Cultural Tourism</hi></head>
<p>In the same way that Disneyland pioneered the con-<lb/>
cept of the theme park, Colonial Williamsburg pio-<lb/>
neered the historically preserved landscape as tourist attraction. Like <name type="pname">Walt Disney</name>, <name type="pname">John D. Rockefeller</name>, Jr., the philanthropic sponsor of the transformation of Williamsburg, <name type="place">Virginia</name>, from a sleepy southern town into a bustling sightseers' mecca, had a dream that proved extremely popular. Beginning in <date when="1926">1926</date>, he created Colonial Williamsburg by restoring 82 eigh-<lb/>
teenth-century buildings, removing 720 built subse-<lb/>
quently, and reconstructing 341 colonial structures
<pb n="476"/>
<pb n="476" type="orig"/>
according to the best available, but often sketchy, evi-<lb/>
dence. Black residents were relocated, power lines buried, and automobiles banned from the Historic Area. Rockefeller's intention was to make it possible, with the aid of costumed guides, for visitors to Williamsburg to experience another century with the same educational interest a curious tourist might bring to travel in another land.<ref target="#CH15-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-580">
<graphic url="CH15_003.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.3. Celebration, <name type="place">Florida</name>. A pattern book developed by <name type="pname">Robert A. M. Stern</name> and other Disney architects is the source of Celebration's intended southern-accented eclecti-<lb/>
cism.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-581">
<graphic url="CH15_004.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 15.2. Garden of the Governors Mansion, Colonial Williamsburg, designed by Arthur Shurcliff. c. <date when="1930">1930</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>One may remark on the beauty of Williams-<lb/>
burg's gardens with the certainty that none much like them existed when <name type="place">Virginia</name> was still a colony (see fig. 6.50). Garden archaeology here was scarcely rigorous or scientific, and <name type="pname">Arthur A. Shurcliff</name> (<date when="1870">1870</date>&#x2013;<date when="1957">1957</date>), the landscape-architect member of Rockefeller's Colo-<lb/>
nial Williamsburg planning team, developed his restoration designs in a highly interpretive manner.<ref target="#CH15-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref> The wife of Williamsburg's mayor described his vig-<lb/>
orous revision of the local scenery in this diary entry:
<q><date when="1931-05-22">May 22, 1931</date>b. <name type="pname">Mr. Shurcliff</name> came down like a wolf on the fold again today. He rushed in and out several times with charts and plans for all sorts of alarming "landscapes" in our yard. He has boxwood on the brain. . . . <name type="pname">Mr. Shurcliff</name> is hurt and grieved by our lack of appreciation when we declare that we don't want more box-<lb/>
wood mazes and hedges all over our yard!<ref target="#CH15-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref></q></p>
<p>Nevertheless, she found all the transplanting and lay-<lb/>
ing out of trim brick walks a fascinating spectacle. With a substantial budget for maintenance, Colonial Williamsburg's re-created gardens have enjoyed a showcase level of seasonal display and year-round degree of neatness that would have been impossible in the case of the originals (fig. 15.2).<ref target="#CH15-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>The tendency to embellish the physical evidence of the past in the act of preservation and restoration reflects the homage we pay to the memories or myths it embodies. The impulse to suffuse with the golden light of a romantically recalled yesteryear the restored or re-created landscapes of today accounts for the glossy, picture-perfect quality of Disney's theme parks and Colonial Williamsburg. It also accounts for the setlike quality of Celebration, <name type="place">Florida</name>, the new town that was financed, built, and marketed by the Disney Company, a symbolic landscape where every day is yesterday, or rather the same yesteryear of nostalgi-<lb/>
cally recalled time (fig. 15.3). Celebration's neotradi-<lb/>
tional postmodern planners took their cue from the predominant period-and-place theme of Disneyland's Main Street, the imaginary golden-age paradise of the Midwestern small town as it was from the end of the nineteenth century through the first four decades of the twentieth century. As with the impulse toward nostalgia we have observed in the Arts and Crafts Movement, this kind of architectural eclecticism reflects a denial of the powerful prevailing forces of the industrial age and the yearning for an earlier, sim-<lb/>
pler time when, so it is presumed, neighbors were neighborly and people led lives rich in the common-<lb/>
place pleasures of community. Governmentally con-<lb/>
trolled by its parent corporation, Celebration is a well-publicized and highly contested example of the historically flavored lifestyle communities that other developers are also offering to home buyers under the planning rubric of New Urbanism. More than cos-<lb/>
metic in intent, these communities are the most recent experiments in applying to the now vastly dis-<lb/>
tended amorphous metropolitan realm some of the practical principles underlying workable, livable cities that were articulated by <name type="pname">Jane Jacobs</name> and other critics of American planning practice in the late <date when="1950">1950</date>s and early <date when="1960">1960</date>s.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="477"/>
<pb n="477" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Preservation and the New Urbanism</hi></head>
<p>While the urge to validate our present lives by link-<lb/>
ing them to past tradition is necessary to our psy-<lb/>
chological well-being, preservationism is more than architectural appreciation, ancestral piety, or simple nostalgia. The polemic that <name type="pname">Jane Jacobs</name> (b. <date when="1916">1916</date>) hurled against urban renewal in her classic <hi rend="italic">Death and Life of Great American Cities</hi> (<date when="1961">1961</date>) was the cry of a preservationist who prized traditional urbanism not because of aesthetics or any particular regard for his-<lb/>
tory <hi rend="italic">per se.</hi> Her preservationism was not the same as that of the gen-<lb/>
tility-seeking social striver or the gentrifying homeowner in a reviving slum neighborhood.</p>
<p>As we observed in Chapter Twelve, Jacobs pro-<lb/>
moted the street patterns and land use of the old nineteenth-century city, with its sidewalks and ground-floor businesses where people were in con-<lb/>
tinual visual communication. The resulting environ-<lb/>
ment was safer and more socially vibrant than the one of single-use zoning, large-scale superblocks, and superhighways that authoritarian master planners were imposing on the cities of <name type="place">America</name>. The segre-<lb/>
gation of land uses by zoning districts had become common practice after streetcar- and, later, automo-<lb/>
bile-served suburbs made it possible for people to live and work in widely separated locations. By the late <date when="1950">1950</date>s, mass automobile ownership and the federal highway building program had accelerated suburban expansion, and commuting had become common-<lb/>
place in metropolitan <name type="place">America</name>. Middle-class, in-city living virtually disappeared except in a few culturally rich older cities such as <name type="place">New York</name> and <name type="place">Boston</name>.</p>
<p>Jacobs's thesis flew in the face of the conven-<lb/>
tional wisdom that had created these landscapes. With a journalist's keen eye for detail and practical com-<lb/>
mon sense, she concluded that a mix of uses created good neighborhoods such as the one where she and her family lived in Greenwich Village. She held that effectively recycled old housing stock made better homes for the poor than high-rise projects where pub-<lb/>
lic space was green but grim, being generally unsafe. One could learn lessons from the structure of the his-<lb/>
toric tenement street despite the evils of unsanitary crowding in tenement houses.</p>
<p>Jacobs's words, unappreciated in planning cir-<lb/>
cles at the time, have taken on an increasingly reso-<lb/>
nant ring of useful truth. Having fought the battle to save Soho, the warehouse district in Lower Manhat-<lb/>
tan, from destruction by <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name>'s planned Lower Manhattan Expressway, she became the pro-<lb/>
genitor of its renaissance, which sparked the conver-<lb/>
sion of semi-abandoned industrial districts in other cities into zones of yeasty enterprise, filled with art galleries, boutiques, restaurants, and loft apartments.</p>
<p>Today, practitioners of the New Urbanism adhere to planning principles based largely on Jacobs's ideas as they seek to apply pedestrian-oriented, mixed-<lb/>
use planning principles in rectifying the flaws they per-<lb/>
ceive in the current monotonous, sprawling suburban landscape and deteriorated parts of older cities where opportunities exist to recycle real estate and replan neighborhoods. <name type="pname">Andres Duany</name> (b. <date when="1950">1950</date>) and <name type="pname">Eliza-<lb/>
beth Plater-Zyberk</name> (b. <date when="1950">1950</date>), who head the architec-<lb/>
tural firm DPZ, and <name type="pname">Peter Calthorpe</name> (b. <date when="1949">1949</date>) of Calthorpe Associates are prominent apostles of the <name type="place">New Urbanism</name>. Their overriding goal is to re-create lost opportunities for community by disciplining the automobile and establishing the primacy of the pub-<lb/>
lic realm. For New Urbanists, streets are both the communal rooms and the passages of the city. By dethroning "King Car" as the ruler of surburbia and disavowing the conventional approach of trans-<lb/>
portation planners whose primary motive is to move automobile traffic efficiently, they have revalued the street as an important public space for people. To accomplish this, they have revived the street's historic appendage, the sidewalk, a fixture of older cities and their streetcar suburbs. They plan neighborhoods that organize building sites and traffic on a hierarchical network of streets. These are made as narrow as pos-<lb/>
sible as a means of slowing down automobile traffic. Curbside parking replaces large off-site parking lots, and trees shade cars and make them less conspicuous.</p>
<p>New Urbanist plans are compact in scale, with higher densities per acre than conventional suburbs, so that schools and shops are within comfortable walking distances, one-quarter-mile&#x2014;a "five-minute walk"&#x2014;being the radius DPZ considers appropriate for development extension in any direction from the neighborhood center. Families therefore do not have to maintain more than one car, children do not have to be chauffeured or bused to school, and elderly peo-<lb/>
ple who no longer drive do not have to move away but can still lead independent lives.</p>
<p>Public space in New Urbanist communities also takes the form of village greens, the long-lasting lega-<lb/>
cies of the <name type="place">New England</name> town commons. Like sidewalks, these promote face-to-face encounters, thereby stimulating the spirit of community. Unlike traditional modern suburbs where parks, if they exist at all, are randomly sited on residual pieces of land not suitable for residential development, these greens are central elements within the plan, nuclei for surrounding development. They become identifiable town cen-<lb/>
ters, well defined architecturally by their surround-<lb/>
ing buildings. These may consist of the local school, the town hall, the retail center, town houses, apart-<lb/>
ments, and offices, usually in combination since mixed use is a cardinal rule in New Urbanist planning.</p>
<pb n="478"/>
<pb n="478" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-582">
<graphic url="CH15_005.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.4. Plan of Laguna West, Sacramento County, California, designed by Calthorpe Associ-<lb/>
ates. <date when="1990">1990</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Mixed use means that there is more demographic diversity and more mutual interaction among popu-<lb/>
lation groups within a New Urbanist community than in a typical suburb. The pedestrian-oriented town cen-<lb/>
ter is a lively place because its ground-floor shops, restaurants, and services attract patrons from the entire community.</p>
<p>Perimeter parks, or at least natural borders, are also important in the New Urbanist developments. Edges that define and contain districts and the town itself are as important as the town center in over-<lb/>
coming the perception that has caused critics of con-<lb/>
ventional suburbs to echo Gertrude Stein's characterization of Oakland, California, as having "no ‘there,' there." In Calthorpe's thinking especially, a regional planning perspective predominates. It is akin to the perspective of <name type="pname">Benton MacKaye</name>, the Regional Planning Association of <name type="place">America</name>'s advocate of direct-<lb/>
ing metropolitan growth into a series of greenbelt-<lb/>
surrounded new towns modeled on the historic ones of <name type="place">New England</name> (see Chapter Twelve). The Regional Plan Association (RPA), which has sought to guide <name type="place">New York</name>'s metropolitan growth since the <date when="1920">1920</date>s, now subscribes to the New Urbanist notion of nodal urbanism. Calthorpe and the current leadership of RPA see the revival of the light-rail transit systems that were competitively dismantled by the automo-<lb/>
bile and highway interests after World War II as essen-<lb/>
tial to overcoming suburban sprawl and preserving regional nature in any significant way.</p>
<p>New Urbanist planners maintain that design is meant to ensure a public realm, not to revive styles. But older models inspire much of their work, and they demonstrate a strong interest in design detail. Finding the results of Modernist planning bleak and dehumanizing and individualistic works of high-art architecture to be posturing, they seek to reproduce the highly textured building fabric characteristic of older cities, adopting as well the more contextual, con-<lb/>
sensual approach of premodern architects. Duany and Plater-Zyberk label their method "TND," for <hi rend="italic">tra-<lb/>
ditional neighborhood development,</hi> and Calthorpe calls his "TOD," or <hi rend="italic">transit-oriented development,</hi> because of its emphasis on a building density capable of sup-<lb/>
porting capital investment in transit infrastructure. Both produce results that are informed by ideas derived from Beaux-Arts Neoclassicism and the ver-<lb/>
nacular architecture of streetcar suburbs.</p>
<p>This community design for Laguna West, Sacramento County, <name type="place">California</name>, is based on TOD (transit-oriented development) principles (fig. 15.4). Here, planner <name type="place">Peter Calthorpe</name> has applied the <hi rend="italic">patte d'oie,</hi> or goosefoot, pattern of avenue radials derived from seventeenth-century French garden design and subsequently appropriated by eighteenth-, nineteenth-<lb/>
, and early twentieth-century city planners to rein-<lb/>
force the centrality of the hub&#x2014;the 100-acre town center with its cluster of shops, offices, apartments, and cultural and recreational facilities. Although light-<lb/>
-rail transit does not yet exist at Laguna West, Calthorpe's plan presupposes its arrival by creating sufficient urban density to support this kind of trans-<lb/>
portation system. It also caters to the still-existing large market for more traditional suburban-style homes with a broad outer residential band platted according to the pattern of gently curving streets ending in cul-<lb/>
de-sacs, which has been typical of American subdivi-<lb/>
sions built since World War II.</p>
<p>Although it is only a small resort community occupying 80 acres of land on the Gulf Coast of <name type="place">Florida</name>, Seaside, the town planned by <name type="pname">Duany</name> and <name type="pname">Plater-Zyberk</name> and developed by an especially sym-<lb/>
<pb n="479"/>
<pb n="479" type="orig"/>
pathetic client, <name type="pname">Robert Davis</name>, who also participated in its design, has garnered media attention as a lead-<lb/>
ing example of New Urbanism (fig. 15.5). The three observed the beach cottages in Seagrove Beach, <name type="place">Florida</name>, and other Gulf coastal summer colonies and traveled to suburbs in Southern cities where they stud-<lb/>
ied residential architecture types. They sharpened their appreciation of traditional and vernacular styles, noting, for instance, how Charleston's distinctive his-<lb/>
toric house type with its long side porches on two floors is an architecturally pleasing adaptation to cli-<lb/>
mate. The old-fashioned veranda, which had disap-<lb/>
peared with the advent of air-conditioning and newer suburban house types, also drew their admiration. Influential in their revaluation of these past plans and building types was the teaching of <name type="pname">Leon Krier</name> (b. <date when="1946">1946</date>), the Luxembourg-born architect who has led the crusade in <name type="place">London</name> and elsewhere to revive neo-<lb/>
classical and vernacular approaches to community development.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-583">
<graphic url="CH15_006.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.5. Plan of Seaside, Walton County, Florida, designed by Andres Duany and Elizabeth Plater-Zyberk. <date when="1981">1981</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-584">
<graphic url="CH15_007.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 15.6. View of the com-<lb/>
monly accessible beachfront, Seaside, <name type="place">Florida</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The town plan, the Seaside Urban Code, and the Construction Regulations are simultaneously spe-<lb/>
cific and flexible architectural directives that ensure compatibility among neighboring building types by giving guidelines for eight categories of construction and by specifying how structures are positioned on the lot and with regard to the street. Prescribed build-<lb/>
ing types range from arcaded, party-wall, three-to-<lb/>
five-story buildings for stores and apartments in the Downtown Commercial Square to single-family "Classic-Romantic urban villas" on Seaside Avenue to southern bungalows and side-yard single houses on the residential streets elsewhere. The code encour-<lb/>
ages the construction of "carriage houses" &#x2014; free-<lb/>
standing garages with living quarters above &#x2014; as small apartments for elderly relatives, house guests, or rental tenants. The regulations further control specific build-<lb/>
ing materials and practices; they mandate, for instance, metal roofing, wood siding, exposed rafter ends, and operable wood-framed windows.</p>
<p>Seaside's prime real estate, a high dune bluff directly fronting on a magnificent stretch of white sand and the azure water of the Gulf of <name type="place">Mexico</name>, could have been profitably exploited by the developer if he had chosen to sell the entire strip as individual high-<lb/>
priced large lots. Instead, holding the value&#x2014;eco-<lb/>
nomic as well as social&#x2014;of the entire project as paramount, Davis and DPZ made the beachfront property into a shared amenity. On the Gulf side of the highway that runs through Seaside they provided access points, which they marked with gazebos where stepped causeways begin their staged descent across the vegetated dune landscape leading to the beach (fig. 15.6). These have seating, another means of fostering the community's atmosphere of low-key sociability.</p>
<pb n="480"/>
<pb n="480" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-585">
<graphic url="CH15_008.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.7. View of streetscape, with sandy footpath leading to the beach, Seaside, <name type="place">Florida</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Running like a leitmotif throughout Seaside is a unifying vocabulary of white-painted wooden ele-<lb/>
ments&#x2014;picket fences, porch and balcony railings, lattices, gazebos, and window and door frames (fig. 15.7). The ground plane is a well-crafted mix of tex-<lb/>
tures; there are brick-paved principal streets with crushed-shell margins for parked cars and sandy mid-<lb/>
block footpaths leading to the beach. Designed by dif-<lb/>
ferent architects&#x2014;some of whom may bend the rules to express their personal visions&#x2014;and by general con-<lb/>
tractors who simply follow the code and regulations, Seaside's compactly clustered mass of structures, often derided as "cute," are above all congenial. Although neotraditional, their design is the result of a somewhat more flexible approach than is the case at Celebration, where Disney's architects have pro-<lb/>
vided a pattern book for builders to follow in order to achieve the look of pre-World War II suburbs with their mix of Neoclassical and vernacular styles (see fig. 15.3). One of Seaside's most important results in addition to stressing the values of community is its sense of containment. By setting appropriate limits to size and by thinking about centers and edges, <name type="pname">Duany</name> and <name type="pname">Plater-Zyberk</name> have made preservation of traditional community values and preservation of the natural environment complementary. Their critics maintain that the New Urbanism is merely a pallia-<lb/>
tive that has not yet addressed the fundamental and politically complicated issues of reforming the real-<lb/>
estate financing practices and other factors that encourage suburban sprawl and foster urban blight.</p>
<p>It is doubtful that Jane Jacobs envisioned any-<lb/>
thing resembling Seaside when she wrote <hi rend="italic">Death and Life of Great American Cities.</hi> The New Urbanism may be showing middle-class <name type="place">America</name> the way back to the future, but as a movement it is still tentative. <name type="pname">Davis</name>'s bet on community-ori-<lb/>
ented planning is paying off handsomely in terms of Seaside's real estate market, which is geared to the buyers of second homes, but pockets of genteel affluence, however community-oriented in their physical structure, do not create the real social diversity Jacobs observed in cities. New Urban-<lb/>
ist projects are achieving some impressive results in older cities such as Providence, Rhode Island; never-<lb/>
theless, many of the people who need it most&#x2014;for instance, the underfunded community groups who are waging battles to preserve urban fabric and com-<lb/>
munity spirit in <name type="place">New York</name> City's South Bronx&#x2014;are struggling to find the private capital or government support to produce tangible results where they live.</p>
<p>For Jacobs, "projects" and "big money" were antithetical to the ideal community, in which social vibrancy and energetic consensus are achieved because numerous individual investments of time and money define the character of the urban space. "The cities of human beings are as natural, being a prod-<lb/>
uct of one form of nature, as are the colonies of prairie dogs or the beds of oysters."<ref target="#CH15-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> Thus wrote <name type="pname">Jane Jacobs</name> in <date when="1961">1961</date> a year before <name type="pname">Rachel Carson</name> published <hi rend="italic">Silent Spring,</hi> which heralded the environmental movement in the United States. Earth Day, often con-<lb/>
sidered its official beginning, was still nine years away. Most of the national organizations that grew out of grassroots efforts to push government to enact legis-<lb/>
lation and set regulations to save threatened wilder-<lb/>
ness and reform the air- and water-polluting practices of industry did not yet exist. Because of the alarming dimensions of the problems that Industrial Age soci-<lb/>
ety was inflicting upon the planet, when environ-<lb/>
mental organizations came into being in the <date when="1970">1970</date>s it was often with agendas that portrayed humankind as nature's enemy. Feeding this bias was the persistent strain of anti-urbanism that runs deep within Amer-<lb/>
ican culture. Many people still believe the densely built-up older city cherished by <name type="pname">Jacobs</name> and others to be an inimical, inhuman environment that exists apart from nature. But, as Jacobs pointed out, "Human beings are, of course, a part of nature, as much so as grizzly bears or bees."<ref target="#CH15-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref> The suburban movement that spawned the current urban sprawl that she fore-<lb/>
saw is based upon a false premise as well as a false promise: the sentimentalization and domestication of rural and wild nature through the development of a vast, undifferentiated, highway-dominated, ubiqui-<lb/>
tous suburban landscape of tract housing, commer-<lb/>
cial strips, and shopping malls. In this increasingly expansive metropolitan landscape, nature is residual, saved by political action but not promoted or planned through public policy.</p>
<p>By comprehending that the dinosaur of devel-<lb/>
opment will wantonly roam the land as long as there is population growth and economic prosperity and by wanting to guide that growth and prosperity by
<pb n="481"/>
<pb n="481" type="orig"/>
planning more livable suburbs, revitalizing old in-city neighborhoods, and saving natural areas as greenbelts, the New Urbanists appear to understand that the human environment and the natural environment are fundamentally one&#x2014;an inextricable alliance of art, technology, and nature. The question remains: can we in fact build better cities, ones that do not oblit-<lb/>
erate but rather incorporate nature for our sake as well as for its own intrinsic, noneconomic worth? And can we accomplish this within the context of better regional planning, revitalizing historic cities as well as building better suburban towns? This is the true chal-<lb/>
lenge for the New Urbanism or whatever else we may choose to call it.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Conserving Nature: Landscape Design as Environmental Science and Art</hi></head>
<p>The roots of today's environmental consciousness lie in nineteenth-century earth science. In <date when="1863">1863</date>, the British geologist Charles Lyell (<date when="1797">1797</date>&#x2013;<date when="1875">1875</date>) published <hi rend="italic">Geological Evidences of the Antiquity of Man.</hi> <name type="pname">Charles Darwin</name> (<date when="1809">1809</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>) was aware of Lyell's work, which promoted and helped confirm his theory of evolu-<lb/>
tionary biology as in <hi rend="italic">Origin of Species</hi> (<date when="1859">1859</date>). The observations recorded by the German naturalist and explorer <name type="pname">Alexander von Humboldt</name> (<date when="1769">1769</date>&#x2013;<date when="1859">1859</date>) dur-<lb/>
ing his voyages to <name type="place">South America</name>, <name type="place">Cuba</name>, and <name type="place">Mexico</name> advanced the nascent field of ecology. Early geogra-<lb/>
phers such as the <name type="pname">German Karl Ritter</name> (<date when="1779">1779</date>&#x2013;<date when="1859">1859</date>) and the <name type="pname">Swiss-born Arnold Henry Guyot</name> (<date when="1807">1807</date>&#x2013;<date when="1884">1884</date>) studied the earth in relation to human activity. But it was an American, <name type="pname">George Perkins Marsh</name> (<date when="1801">1801</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>), who attempted to show the extent to which human intervention was altering climate, topography, vege-<lb/>
tation patterns, soil, and the habitats of species, often with consequences inimical for future generations. In his landmark book <hi rend="italic">Man and Nature</hi> (<date when="1864">1864</date>) Marsh, who claimed no scientific expertise but a great deal of prac-<lb/>
tical experience as a farmer, industrial investor, and diplomatic traveler, set out to show "that whereas Rit-<lb/>
ter and Guyot think that the earth made man, man in fact made the earth."<ref target="#CH15-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>A native of Vermont, Marsh saw firsthand how clear-cutting of forested slopes had promoted erosion and how these actions had caused the silting of for-<lb/>
mer wetlands and decimated many animal species. In biblical cadences, Marsh described how man the destroyer of nature
<q>has felled forests whose network of fibrous roots bound the mould to the rocky skeleton of the earth,... has broken up the mountain reser-<lb/>
voirs, the percolation of whose waters through unseen channels supplied the fountains that refreshed his cattle and fertilized his fields, . . . has torn the thin glebe which confined the light earth of extensive plains, and has destroyed the fringe of semi-aquatic plants which skirted the coast and checked the drifting of sea sand, . . . has warred on all the tribes of animated nature whose spoil he could not convert to his own uses, and... not protected the birds which prey on the insects most destructive to his own har-<lb/>
vests.<ref target="#CH15-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref></q></p>
<p>Fluent in several foreign languages, both ancient and modern, he read extensively and, as an ambassa-<lb/>
dor first to Turkey and then <name type="place">Italy</name>, he was able to ana-<lb/>
lyze the Mediterranean basin at close range and to surmise why certain areas that had once supported extensive human settlement were now rocky, treeless, arid wastes, inhospitable to human life. By under-<lb/>
standing how the exploitation of the land's resources in the Old World, without any thought of husbandry beyond the immediate term, had reduced such significant portions of the ancient Roman empire to this condition, Marsh hoped to encourage his country-<lb/>
men to reconsider their heedless scramble for wealth at the expense of nature and to develop an ethos of land stewardship. The challenge that he put forth was to take his empirical observations in <hi rend="italic">Man and Nature</hi> as warning signs and to assemble the necessary sci-<lb/>
entific data to understand "the action and reaction between humanity and the material world around it." Only by so doing would humanity be able to deter-<lb/>
mine at last "the great question, whether man is of nature or above her."<ref target="#CH15-n20"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Marsh fully approved of canals, dikes, river embankments, and other means of engineering that channeled the forces of nature toward human ends. But he believed that such controls could be produc-<lb/>
tive in the long term only if nature's regenerative forces were encouraged, not stymied. His book was influential in begetting awareness of the environment as an organic system in which all the parts were inter-<lb/>
dependent. Motives of overweening human greed persisted in his day as they do in ours, and in an aside, he railed against "the decay of commercial morality" and "unprincipled corporations, which not only defy the legislative power, but have, too often, corrupted even the administration of justice."<ref target="#CH15-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">21</hi></hi></ref>Although his urgent message sowed the seeds of forestry and land management practices that eventually became part
<pb n="482"/>
<pb n="482" type="orig"/>
of government, only in recent years have the dire effects that Marsh predicted&#x2014;multiplied by pressures of population growth and forces of industrial mech-<lb/>
anization that he could hardly have imagined&#x2014;prompted political protest and legislative actions leading to pollution controls and some positive steps toward the responsible regeneration of degraded nat-<lb/>
ural environments.</p>
<p>As we have seen, inherent in modernism was a celebratory attitude toward feats of engineering and little regard for their environmental consequences. Although modernist landscape architects following Christopher Tunnard intended and usually inflicted no serious environmental harm, their objectives were essentially aesthetic as they wished to bring their pro-<lb/>
fession in line with the exciting new developments in architecture, painting, and sculpture. In terms of plan-<lb/>
ning, the urban-rural balance that Lewis Mumford preached in opposition to metropolitanism, with greenbelt communities scattered throughout a region, went generally unheeded. Only since the <date when="1970">1970</date>s has a belated awareness of the need to reconcile human objectives with the operation of natural ecosystems become general and influential upon the practice of landscape design. It was at the University of Pennsyl-<lb/>
vania where Mumford taught for a period in the early <date when="1960">1960</date>s that the ground was laid for a landscape archi-<lb/>
tecture that conjoined the regionalism of the <date when="1920">1920</date>s with the emerging environmental consciousness.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Landscape as Environmental Science</hi></head>
<p>"We need nature as much in the city as in the coun-<lb/>
tryside," wrote <name type="pname">Ian L. McHarg</name> (b. <date when="1920">1920</date>) in <date when="1969">1969</date> in his now-classic book, <hi rend="italic">Design with Nature.<ref target="#CH15-n22"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref></hi> In the wake of <name type="pname">Rachel Carson</name>'s eloquent call to environmental con-<lb/>
science in <hi rend="italic">Silent Spring</hi> (<date when="1962">1962</date>), McHarg articulated with similar fervor a conservation strategy that sought to unseat the mind-set condoned by the <name type="pname">Judeo-Chris-<lb/>
tian</name> biblical injunction encouraging humanity to sub-<lb/>
due the earth. He enjoined planners, developers, and landscape architects to view Earth not as an exploitable resource but as the very source of life, the terrestrial miracle in space, an intricate organism of which humanity is an inseparable part. A gifted teacher, as chairman of the Department of Landscape Architecture and Regional Planning at the University of Pennsylvania from <date when="1964">1964</date> until <date when="1986">1986</date>, <name type="pname">McHarg</name> became a leading exponent of an enlightened land-<lb/>
planning strategy that sought to make the constraints and opportunities presented by natural ecosystems an integral part of design and development. Inform-<lb/>
ing his philosophy is his personal experience of the contrast of countryside to industrial city, of wartime landscape devastation to great landscape beauty, and of post-World War II convalescence in both grim and exhilarating environments.</p>
<p>As a landscape architect, McHarg came to feel that it was not enough to simply ameliorate the con-<lb/>
ditions found in the Glasgow slums of his youth. Prac-<lb/>
ticing in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> in the firm he founded in <date when="1963">1963</date>, he recognized that "providing a decorative background for human play"<ref target="#CH15-n23"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">23</hi></hi></ref>did not address the larger environ-<lb/>
mental threat posed by rings of suburbs encroaching upon rural and wild landscapes and the increasing divorce of human beings from wild nature. Further, the environment as a whole was being made toxic with pesticides and industrial wastes, and by then humans had sown the dire seeds of massive planetary devastation by producing the atomic bomb. He believes that urban planners and landscape architects can significantly alter this supremely dangerous course of science and technology and stem the harmful forces within industrial capitalist society.</p>
<p>As we have seen, other landscape architects&#x2014; notably <name type="pname">Charles Eliot</name> and <name type="pname">Jens Jensen</name>&#x2014;had preceded McHarg in advancing the cause of nature preserves in metropolitan areas, in studying native plant ecolo-<lb/>
gies, and in forging a design idiom that expressed the simple beauties of regional locality. Stanley White (<date when="1891">1891</date>&#x2013;<date when="1979">1979</date>) and <name type="pname">Hideo Sasaki</name> (b. <date when="1919">1919</date>), both gifted teachers of landscape architecture, were instrumen-<lb/>
tal in bringing environmental science into the student curriculum. For instance, Sasaki had his Harvard stu-<lb/>
dents study a site in terms of its soil conditions, drainage patterns, and vegetation character and ground-plane coverage. These then became the deter-<lb/>
minants in locating development and assigning preser-<lb/>
vation value. To this analytical approach based on principles of ecological determinism, McHarg added an intuitive methodology incorporating personal val-<lb/>
ues that evinced his affinity for Japanese culture and the metaphysics expressed in the Zen garden as well as his respect for the architecture of Louis Kahn (<date when="1901">1901</date>&#x2013;<date when="1974">1974</date>), who taught architecture at the Univer-<lb/>
sity of <name type="place">Pennsylvania</name> when <name type="pname">McHarg</name> led the landscape architecture program there. <name type="pname">McHarg</name> appreciated Kahn's notion of design as a poetic expression of space and light and of the essential, inherent qualities of material and site.</p>
<p>In an age of scientific rationalism that puts a premium on nonsubjective measures, <name type="pname">McHarg</name> felt compelled to further a science-based approach to designing with nature. He made the natural sciences an essential foundation for his department's curricu-<lb/>
lum at the University of <name type="place">Pennsylvania</name>, with courses in plant ecology and geology. In his geophysical and environmental approach to landscape design, <name type="pname">McHarg</name> developed a coordinated mapping system with overlays to render analyses of ecological, cli-<lb/>
<pb n="483"/>
<pb n="483" type="orig"/>
matic, geological, topographical, hydrological, eco-<lb/>
nomic, natural, scenic, and historical features (fig. 15.8). Assigning categories of social value to these, he has been able to chart optimum development paths and preservation zones according to the carrying capacity of the land and its fitness for specific uses. Put as simply as possible, a <name type="pname">McHarg</name> plan, such as the ones he prepared for the <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> Metropolitan Area, the <name type="place">Baltimore</name> Region, the Potomac River Basin, and for relocating the highway planned through the <name type="place">Staten Island Greenbelt</name>, assigns levels of density and development and categories of land use based upon suitability. Flood and hurricane vulnerability and water conservation are paramount considerations. Overlay analysis shows invariably that valleys with their biologically and hydrologically important river basins and wetlands should be preserved, develop-<lb/>
ment on slopes should be minimized to allow ground-<lb/>
water to drain properly and recharge the subsurface aquifer, and uplands where settlement is least dam-<lb/>
aging allowed to become the zones of most intense occupation. Between <date when="1970">1970</date> and <date when="1974">1974</date>, <name type="pname">McHarg</name>'s firm, <name type="pname">Wallace McHarg Roberts</name> and <name type="pname">Todd</name>, applied this plan-<lb/>
ning methodology to the development of Wood-<lb/>
lands, an 18,000-acre new town built by developer <name type="pname">George Mitchell</name> north of <name type="place">Houston</name>, <name type="place">Texas</name>.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-586">
<graphic url="CH15_009.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.8. Partial plan for the <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> Metropolitan Area, showing land and water features, designed with nature by <name type="pname">Ian McHarg</name>. c. <date when="1960">1960</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sustainability</hi> is a new word in the lexicon of planners and designers. Woodlands, where the homes are clustered in a natural woodland setting rather than on conventionally landscaped lots, demonstrates <name type="pname">McHarg</name>'s synthesis of human ecology and natural ecology in an economically viable plan that measures social and environmental costs together with dollar costs is hardly widespread in <name type="place">America</name>. But to date, the incentives to build similar communities are not widespread. Government's role in terms of environ-<lb/>
mental improvement remains principally regulatory. To plan on a large regional scale in the manner McHarg and others have suggested requires govern-<lb/>
mental effectiveness and creativity backed by elected officials and policy makers at all levels.</p>
<p>Without such environmental planning, social and economic demands&#x2014;for jobs, for public access, for equity&#x2014;result in higher political value being assigned to individual and class interests than to those of society at large. Yet elsewhere sustainable com-<lb/>
munities are being promoted however imperfectly, particularly in northern European countries such as the Netherlands, Sweden, and <name type="place">Germany</name> where there is a stronger ethic and more ingrained politics of responsible land use and urban husbandry than in <name type="place">America</name>.<ref target="#CH15-n24"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">24</hi></hi></ref>Directing the policies of contemporary industrial capitalism and the consumer society toward this end in all countries is one of the most important challenges of the twenty-first century.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Landscape Design as Environmental Art</hi></head>
<p><name type="pname">McHarg</name> has been the most eloquent academic expo-<lb/>
nent of ecological landscape design in <name type="place">America</name>, and <name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name> (b. <date when="1916">1916</date>) has been one of its most active. Whereas <name type="pname">McHarg</name> has felt the need to put envi-<lb/>
ronmental planning within a rational natural-science framework, Halprin has honored the values of envi-<lb/>
ronment more in the manner of an artist, celebrat-<lb/>
ing human creativity and community life within the context of nature and using environmental motifs metaphorically in his designs, which include several
<pb n="484"/>
<pb n="484" type="orig"/>
powerful evocations of nature in downtown public places (figs. 15.9,15.10).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-587">
<graphic url="CH15_010.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.10. Freeway Park, Seattle, <name type="place">Washington</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name> &amp; Associ-<lb/>
ates; <name type="pname">Angela Danadijeva</name>, pro-<lb/>
ject designer; <name type="pname">Edward McCleod</name> &amp; Associates, associate land-<lb/>
scape architects. <date when="1970">1970</date>&#x2013;76. Here a dramatically naturalis-<lb/>
tic space evokes the wilder-<lb/>
ness of the Pacific Northwest while masking the sounds of the freeway.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-588">
<graphic url="CH15_011.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Above right:</hi> 15.9. Lovejoy Plaza, <name type="place">Portland</name>, <name type="place">Oregon</name>, designed by Lawrence Halprin &amp; Associates and <name type="pname">Charles Moore</name>, with Moore/Lyndon/ Turnbull/Whitaker, Architects. <date when="1961">1961</date>&#x2013;68</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p><name type="pname">Halprin</name>'s long and productive career has been nourished by degrees in plant sciences and horticul-<lb/>
ture from Cornell and the University of <name type="place">Wisconsin</name>, <name type="place">Madison</name>, study at Harvard with his adopted mentor Christopher Tunnard after discovering Tunnard's <hi rend="italic">Gar-<lb/>
dens in the Modern Landscape,</hi> and employment in the <name type="place">San Francisco</name> office of Thomas Church where he worked on the Donnell Garden (see figs. 13.24, 13.25). Important to Halprin's work has been his under-<lb/>
standing of landscape design as process rather than unchanging product. He calls this process "scoring," a musical metaphor implying his intention to create spatial frameworks that allow for change over time and within which others can play participatory riffs. His legacy includes, besides his landscape designs, books that elucidate his design approach, including <hi rend="italic">The R.S.V.P. Cycles: Creative Processes in the Human Envi-<lb/>
ronment</hi> (<date when="1969">1969</date>).</p>
<p>Between <date when="1962">1962</date> and <date when="1965">1965</date>, <name type="pname">Halprin</name> was responsi-<lb/>
ble for making San <name type="place">Francisco</name>'s Ghiradelli Square, an early effort at urban revitalization, into a vibrant pub-<lb/>
lic space animated by fountains, outdoor lighting, and landscaping, where people come for alfresco eating, shopping, socializing, and participating in perform-<lb/>
ances, which are often impromptu. His "Take Part" design workshops elicit citizen collaboration in shap-<lb/>
ing a project's final program. Even as several other prominent landscape architects such as <name type="pname">Hideo Sasaki</name> and <name type="pname">Peter Walker</name> (b. <date when="1932">1932</date>) have adopted the corpo-<lb/>
rate-management style of successful large architec-<lb/>
tural firms, Halprin&#x2014;like <name type="pname">Roberto Burle Marx</name> or Halprin's former employer, Thomas Church&#x2014;has maintained his practice using an earlier model, that of the studio, because he finds the creative synergy of its collaborative atmosphere especially congenial.</p>
<p>With a strong interest in making landscape architecture transcend the functional and social to attain a spiritual dimension, Halprin has studied Jun-<lb/>
gian psychology in search of symbols and archetypes that hold universal meaning. Echoing Olmsted's notion of the fundamental benefit of parks as an uplifting of the spirit through the senses, Halprin has said, "What we are after is a sense of poetry in the land-<lb/>
scape, a magnificent lift which will enrich the lives of the people who are moving about in the landscape."<ref target="#CH15-n25"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">25</hi></hi></ref> He has nourished his own spiritual roots by maintaining a strong connection over the years with
<pb n="485"/>
<pb n="485" type="orig"/>
Israel, where he spent some time after high school liv-<lb/>
ing on a kibbutz. His most notable project in that country is the Walter and Elise Haas Promenade built in the mid-<date when="1980">1980</date>s in Jerusalem on a hill overlooking the Old City.</p>
<p>In the United States, <name type="pname">Halprin</name> designed the 7.5-<lb/>
acre <name type="pname">Franklin Delano Roosevelt</name> Memorial located in West Potomac Park, a 66-acre peninsula beside the Tidal Basin in <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name> (fig. 15.11). Dedi-<lb/>
cated on <date when="1997-05-02">May 2, 1997</date>, the memorial to the thirty-<lb/>
second president of the United States consists of a richly planted 1,200-foot-long (365.8-meter-long) sequence of four interconnected garden spaces with narrative sculpture and fountains.<ref target="#CH15-n26"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">26</hi></hi></ref>With his strong sense of landscape as theatrical performance and employing the storyboard technique used by film-<lb/>
makers to plot what he called "Roosevelt's journey of life," <name type="pname">Halprin</name> scripted a sequence of 21 quotations, brief texts from famous speeches by Roosevelt, which are incised into the memo-<lb/>
rial's walls of rusticated pink and red granite. He combined these inscriptions with sculptures by <name type="pname">Tom Hardy</name>, <name type="pname">Neil Estern</name>, <name type="pname">Leonard Baskin</name>, <name type="pname">George Segal</name>, and <name type="pname">Robert Graham</name> in a chronological narrative of Roosevelt's presidency and leadership during two of the nation's gravest ordeals, the Great Depression and World War II. The memorial also contains hope for world peace as symbolized by the inclusion of a statue of Eleanor Roosevelt as a delegate to the United Nations.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Halprin</name>'s connection with <name type="pname">McHarg</name>'s approach to environmental planning is perhaps most evident in his "ecoscore" for Sea Ranch, a planned commu-<lb/>
nity of weekend and vacation homes and condo-<lb/>
miniums developed in the mid-<date when="1960">1960</date>s by Oceanic Properties on property occupying a 10-mile stretch of northern California coastline, which was once used for sheep grazing. <name type="pname">Halprin</name> conceived the plan for the first 1,800 acres to be developed of the original 5,300-<lb/>
acre parcel in collaboration with MLTW the archi-<lb/>
tectural firm of Charles Moore, Donlyn Lyndon, William Turnbull, and Richard Whitaker (figs. 15.12, 15.13). As was later true of Seaside's plan, <name type="pname">Halprin</name>'s plan for Sea Ranch put a premium upon communal spaces, and only about 50 percent of the land was sold to private owners.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-589">
<graphic url="CH15_012.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.11. Franklin Delano Roo-<lb/>
sevelt Memorial, <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name>. <date when="1997">1997</date>. sculpture by <name type="pname">Neil Estern</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-590">
<graphic url="CH15_013.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 15.12. Plan of Sea Ranch, <name type="place">California</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name> &amp; Associ-<lb/>
ates, Landscape Architects, Moore/Lyndon/Turnbull/ Whitaker, and <name type="pname">Joseph Esherick</name>, Architects. <date when="1967">1967</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>By clustering the sites for houses and condo-<lb/>
miniums adjacent to existing cypress hedgerows, <name type="pname">Hal-<lb/>
prin</name> was able to leave the former sheep pastures as open meadows with views to the ocean across the
<pb n="486"/>
<pb n="486" type="orig"/>
beach bluffs. Trails throughout enable residents to experience the landscape as a totality. The meadows are held as commons and their maintenance made a community responsibility. Unlike Seaside, where low picket fences manifest an ambience of yard-to-yard neighborliness, at Sea Ranch owners' rules specify that properties be kept unfenced. The clustered houses without visible property lines or landscaping appear to merge with their natural setting. This inten-<lb/>
tion is furthered by Sea Ranch's rustic architectural vocabulary&#x2014;unpainted redwood or cedar siding and eaveless shed roofs of shingle or sod, which are posi-<lb/>
tioned to deflect the Pacific winds.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-591">
<graphic url="CH15_014.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.13. Sea Ranch</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>As an innovative effort in environmentally har-<lb/>
monious place making and an expression of the <date when="1960">1960</date>s idealism that motivated the careers of both <name type="pname">McHarg</name> and <name type="pname">Halprin</name>, Sea Ranch deserves a place in the his-<lb/>
tory of landscape design. Both of these landscape architects have seen city and country as a continuum, and their influence in furthering a new moral imper-<lb/>
ative by bringing ecological considerations to the fore has been influential within their profession.</p>
<p>As much of the aging industrial infrastructure of cities falls into disuse because of new transportation and manufacturing technologies, landscape architects have been engaged in the reclamation of <hi rend="italic">brownfields,</hi> former factory sites and decaying waterfronts. Notable among those who have attempted to poeticize the industrial past through landscape design is Richard Haag (b. <date when="1923">1923</date>), an early Postmodern con-<lb/>
textualist whose Gasworks Park (<date when="1970">1970</date>&#x2013;78) on the shores of Lake Union in Seattle, <name type="place">Washington</name>, and Bloedel Reserve, <name type="place">Bainbridge Island</name>, Puget Sound, <name type="place">Washington</name> (<date when="1985">1985</date>&#x2014;), demonstrate concern for envi-<lb/>
ronmental healing through bioremediation.</p>
<p>Although contemporary landscape architects have not entirely abandoned the principles of the Pic-<lb/>
turesque, Arts and Crafts, Neoclassical, and Mod-<lb/>
ernist design traditions that have constituted their training during the past century, and although they still rely on some of the principles of these design styles as well as upon McHargian environmentalism to inform their work, several are adopting an approach that seeks the same kind of creative free-<lb/>
dom granted to Conceptual artists. Thus, they look to their own imaginative resources as they manipu-<lb/>
late stones, earth, and water to produce land art, forms in and of the landscape. At the same time, Earthworks artists share some of the same concerns as environmentalists, and they work in a similar manner and at the same scale as landscape architects. As they, too, seek to manifest beauty within a brown-<lb/>
fields context, the distinction between art and land-<lb/>
scape design tends to dissolve.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="487"/>
<pb n="487" type="orig"/>
<head>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Earthworks, Golf Courses, Philosophical Models, and Poetic Metaphors: Landscape as Art Form, Sport, Deconstructivism, and Phenomenology</hi></head>
<p>Industrial technology has produced the machines that can manipulate landscapes with an ease previously undreamed of; without it Earthworks, or Land art, would probably not exist. There are certain ironies, both intended and not, in the creation of these mon-<lb/>
umental and often beautiful projects. Many evoke in scale and cosmological intent the primary earthworks of prehistoric peoples, yet they are not expressions of widely shared and deeply held cosmologically ori-<lb/>
ented religious belief as were the great earthworks created at <name type="place">Newark</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>, or <name type="place">Cahokia</name>, <name type="place">Illinois</name>, which we examined in Chapter One. Rather they are the heroic creations of artists who, often through the agency of bulldozers and other earthmoving equip-<lb/>
ment, have accomplished with relatively small work crews and within their own lifetimes landscape transformations on a scale rivaling that of these original earthworks, the building of which employed battal-<lb/>
ions of workers over a period of many decades or even centuries. Frequently placed by choice or neces-<lb/>
sity in remote and inaccessible locations, often the deserts of the American West, modern Earthworks exist primarily for the appreciation of tourists who are willing, usually by means of a four-wheel-drive vehicle, to experience them firsthand and for other followers of contemporary art who are content to view aerial photographs of them.</p>
<p>Indeed, the camera is their handmaiden, for rarely if ever are these sometimes ephemeral proj-<lb/>
ects undocumented. Still and moving images are as important to the artists as the Earthworks them-<lb/>
selves, and some artists such as Andy Goldsworthy (b. <date when="1956">1956</date>), whose delicate and poetic constructions are exceedingly transitory, have become photographers of professional stature in the service of their art (fig. 15.14). Aerial photography, which also allows us to comprehend better the configuration of such pre-<lb/>
historic earthworks as the Nazca lines in Peru (see fig. 1.35) or Serpent Mound in <name type="place">Ohio</name> (see fig. 1.37), is similarly important in making many modern Earth-<lb/>
works legible.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-592">
<graphic url="CH15_015.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.14. <hi rend="italic">Red River,</hi> <name type="place">Jemez</name>, <name type="place">New Mexico</name>, by Andy Goldsworthy. <date when="1999-07-28">July 28, 1999</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The space they occupy makes a territorial claim to the sublime that substitutes for the inherent divin-<lb/>
ity that prehistoric and ancient societies ascribed to their sacred places. Unlike the acts of cosmological centering performed by these early people, however, the creators of contemporary Earthworks must locate them through a necessarily mundane process involving negotiation of property leases or the pur-<lb/>
chase of real estate. In the case of some Earthworks artists, especially Christo (b. <date when="1935">1935</date>), who for this rea-<lb/>
son perhaps chooses important and conspicuous urban areas for some of his projects, the process of obtaining permits is as important as the realization of the art itself.</p>
<p>Being explicitly identified with specific artists, contemporary Earthworks have an importance within the context of our celebrity-conscious culture more often linked to the name of the artist than to the concepts they are intended to manifest. This is
<pb n="488"/>
<pb n="488" type="orig"/>
unfortunate because many were intended as a critique of art-world values as well as of Industrial Age envi-<lb/>
ronmental degradation. Although Earthworks have a materiality that transcends a strict definition of Con-<lb/>
ceptual art, the Earthworks movement is neverthe-<lb/>
less contemporary with, and part of, the Conceptual art movement. Both Land art and Conceptural art are latter-day links in early-twentieth-century Mod-<lb/>
ernism's break with tradition and expansion of the definition of what is art. Both are part of the same late <date when="1960">1960</date>s gestalt of protest against the established norms for viewing and thinking about art. Both eschew style in favor of idea and form.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-593">
<graphic url="CH15_016.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.15. <hi rend="italic">Spiral Jetty,</hi> Great Salt Lake, Utah, designed by Robert Smithson. <date when="1970">1970</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-594">
<graphic url="CH15_017.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 15.16. <hi rend="italic">Observatory,</hi> Oostelijk (East) Flevoland, the Netherlands, designed by Robert Morris. <date when="1971">1971</date>, recon-<lb/>
structed <date when="1977">1977</date>. Influenced by archaeology and by the phe-<lb/>
nomenology of French philoso-<lb/>
pher Maurice Merleau-Ponty, Morris emphasized the experi-<lb/>
ential participation of the viewer who comprehends dif-<lb/>
ferent scales of time through walking in and around this 300-foot-diameter (91.4-meter-<lb/>
diameter) Earthwork of concentric mounds, embank-<lb/>
ments, and canals. These dif-<lb/>
ferent scales of time include the actual time spent on the site, prehistoric time as sym-<lb/>
bolized by its archaeological form, and cosmological time as referenced by Morris's solar solstice sight lines.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Lakh iworks as Art Form and Landscape</hi></head>
<p><name type="pname">Robert Smithson</name> (<date when="1938">1938</date>&#x2013;<date when="1973">1973</date>), <name type="pname">Robert Morris</name> (b. <date when="1931">1931</date>), <name type="pname">Charles Ross</name> (b. <date when="1937">1937</date>), <name type="pname">Nancy Holt</name> (b. <date when="1938">1938</date>), and <name type="pname">James Turrell</name> (b. <date when="1941">1941</date>) are nontraditional Amer-<lb/>
ican artists whose chosen medium is the land itself&#x2014; soil, rocks, water, existing geological and topograph-<lb/>
ical structures&#x2014;as well as light and sky (figs. 15.15&#x2013;15.21). Smithson, a prolific writer and the most articulate champion of the Earthworks movement before his premature death, made it clear that his con-<lb/>
cerns were with cosmic space and time rather than with historical space and time. He aligned his own intentions with those of fellow artists of his genera-<lb/>
tion who were also concerned with "inactive history" that brought "to mind the Ice Age rather than the Golden Age."<ref target="#CH15-n27"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">27</hi></hi></ref>Further, in the late <date when="1960">1960</date>s, Smithson was in the vanguard of artists who wished to aban-<lb/>
don the notion of art as object. Their polemic was directed against the current status of art as a mar-<lb/>
ketable commodity.</p>
<p>Smithson was in a sense an environmentalist, a man acutely aware of the degradation of natural land-<lb/>
scapes by twentieth-century industry. However, with the idea that even industrial wastelands have an intrin-<lb/>
sic beauty that can be given form and expression through art, he actively sought as sites for his work abandoned quarries, strip mines, polluted lakes, and other disfigured portions of the landscape. His brand of environmentalism was devoid of sympathy for pro-<lb/>
testers who thought of industrialization as essentially evil, a catastrosphe humanity had visited upon nature. His perception of time in "Ice Age" or geologic terms gave him the ability to think within the context of
<pb n="489"/>
<pb n="489" type="orig"/>
planetary, rather than human, dialectics. He brought to his art the perspective of earth science gained from frequent trips as a child to the American Museum of Natural History and on car trips with his family to the American West. From his boyhood interest in natu-<lb/>
ral history and his impressions of the immensity and grandeur of Western scenery as contrasted with the densely suburbanized and heavily industrialized land-<lb/>
scape around Passaic, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, where he grew up, Smithson extracted a worldview that considered mod-<lb/>
ern Machine Age humanity as part of nature and environmental remediation through art as an inter-<lb/>
esting opportunity for artists like himself.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-595">
<graphic url="CH15_018.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.17. <hi rend="italic">Star Axis,</hi> located in the desert east of Albuquerque, <name type="place">New Mexico</name>, designed by Charles Ross. Begun <date when="1974">1974</date>. <hi rend="italic">Star Axis</hi> is a monumental demonstration of the relation-<lb/>
ship of Earths axis and Polaris, the North Star.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-596">
<graphic url="CH15_019.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 15.18. <hi rend="italic">Roden Crater Project,</hi> near <name type="place">Flagstaff</name>, <name type="place">Arizona</name>, designed by <name type="pname">James Turrell</name>. Begun <date when="1970">1970</date>s. <name type="pname">Turrell</name>, who sees natural light as his primary medium, has created within the cone of an extinct volcano spaces in which to experience the ambiences created by the sun and moon at various times of day and year.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>His explorations of desolate and deteriorating industrial landscapes resulted in an exhibition of a new kind of sculpture he called Non-Sites. His work as an artist-consultant to an architectural team com-<lb/>
peting for the contract to expand Dallas-Fort Worth Regional Airport helped him to conceptualize how he could independently make Land art on an airport scale. This led him to abandon the symbiotic rela-<lb/>
tionship between artist and gallery, and in <date when="1968">1968</date>, he traveled through the deserts of <name type="place">California</name>, <name type="place">Nevada</name>, and <name type="place">Utah</name> in search of a suitable location for a large Earthwork. He was particularly attracted to the red-<lb/>
dish-violet color of salt lakes, and in <date when="1970">1970</date>, further search in the West led him and fellow artist Nancy Holt, also his wife, to a portion of the Great Salt Lake in <name type="place">Utah</name> "which resembled an impassive faint violet sheet held captive in a stoney matrix, upon which the sun poured down its crushing light."<ref target="#CH15-n28"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">28</hi></hi></ref>In Smithson's eyes, the peculiar beauty of the desolate site was augmented by the industrial wastes and abandoned machinery he found there, rusting derricks that recorded past attempts to extract oil from tar deposits. The color of the water was the result of the presence of a microorganism. According to Smithson, the site "reverberated out to the horizons only to suggest an immobile cyclone while flickering light made the entire landscape appear to quake.... This site was a rotary that enclosed itself in an immense roundness. From that gyrating space emerged the possibility of the Spiral Jetty."<ref target="#CH15-n29"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">29</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Using heavy machinery like that which had scarred the site, Smithson deposited black basalt rocks and earth, creating a spiraling form 1,500-feet (457.2-<lb/>
meters) long in the purplish-pink water. Underlying
<pb n="490"/>
<pb n="490" type="orig"/>
Smithson's dialectical vision of industrialist and artist engaged in exploitation and reclamation of the earth is the concept of the law of thermodynamics, mod-<lb/>
ern physicists' notion of the universe as being in a state of entropy to which the artist grafted his con-<lb/>
temporary perspective of the natural environment as being debased by human activity but capable nonetheless of poetic expressiveness.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-597">
<graphic url="CH15_020.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.19 and 15.20. Interior and exterior views of <hi rend="italic">Up and Under,</hi> <name type="place">Nokia</name>, <name type="place">Finland</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Nancy Holt</name>, <date when="1998">1998</date>. Built in an abandoned quarry, this Earthwork is composed of sand, concrete, grass, and water. © <name type="pname">Nancy Holt</name>/licensed by VAGA, <name type="place">New York</name>, <name type="place">NY</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Shortly after working with Smithson to docu-<lb/>
ment the creation of <hi rend="italic">Spiral Jetty,</hi> <name type="pname">Nancy Holt</name> under-<lb/>
took to create <hi rend="italic">Sun Tunnels,</hi> an earthwork in Lucin, <name type="place">Utah</name> (<date when="1973">1973</date>&#x2013;76). Set within a vast desert landscape, these 9-foot-diameter (2.7-meter-diameter), 18-foot-<lb/>
long (5.9-meter-long) industrial concrete pipes are positioned in alignment with the rising and setting of the sun at the time of the summer and winter sol-<lb/>
stices. Perforations in the pipes admit light in patterns that evoke various star constellations. More attuned to evoking ancient cosmological expressions in the landscape than modern physics, Holt's subsequent Earthworks include <hi rend="italic">30 Below</hi> (<date when="1980">1980</date>) for the Winter Olympics in Lake Placid, <name type="place">New York</name>; <hi rend="italic">Star Crossed</hi> (<date when="1980">1980</date>) at Miami University, <name type="place">Oxford</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>; and <hi rend="italic">Dark Star Park</hi> (<date when="1984">1984</date>) in <name type="place">Arlington</name>, <name type="place">Virginia</name>. Her most recent Earth-<lb/>
work, <hi rend="italic">Up and Under</hi> (<date when="1998">1998</date>), located in an abandoned sand quarry in the village of Pinsi&#x00F6; near <name type="place">Nokia</name>, <name type="place">Fin-<lb/>
land</name>, consists of seven horizontal concrete tunnels, four of which are aligned on an east-west axis, while three are oriented with Polaris, the North Star (figs. 15.19, 15.20). The tunnels protrude from a 630-foot-<lb/>
long (192-meter-long) snakelike mound ending in a roughly circular mound that is approximately 230 feet (70 meters) in diameter and 26 feet (7.9 meters) high.</p>
<p>Like ancient cosmological landscapes, <hi rend="italic">Up and Under</hi> has an "axis mundi" in the form of a large ver-<lb/>
tical tunnel placed at the crossing of four tunnels beneath the round mound. It brings a circle of sky with clouds, stars, and sometimes the moon into the perception of the viewer within the tunnel. Rein-<lb/>
forcing the cosmological idea of centering space, Holt took samples of soil from villages all over <name type="place">Finland</name> and buried this mixture beneath the vertical tunnel. In addition, she placed three circular sky-reflecting pools, which are fed by an ancient spring, in the quarry floor adjacent to the mounds, whose slopes are covered with grass. The pools, which vary in diameter from 22 feet (6.7 meters) to 30 feet (9.1 meters) to 40 feet (12.2 meters), also mirror the Earthwork. It is meant,
<figure xml:id="fig-598">
<graphic url="CH15_021.jpg"/>
</figure>
<pb n="491"/>
<pb n="491" type="orig"/>
as its title suggests, to be viewed from above, along a path that follows the crescent-shaped cliffs created by the operation of the former quarry, and from under-<lb/>
neath the earth, inside the tunnels. It can also be expe-<lb/>
rienced by following the path at the top of the winding mound or by moving around the forms on the quarry floor. According to Holt, "Each changing visual experience leads to a questioning of perception itself&#x2014;near and far, whole and detail, reflection and reality, aerial and ground."<ref target="#CH15-n30"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">30</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p><name type="pname">Charles Jencks</name> (b. <date when="1939">1939</date>), with his late wife, <name type="pname">Mag-<lb/>
gie Keswick</name> (<date when="1941">1941</date>&#x2013;<date when="1995">1995</date>), a student of the Chinese garden and <hi rend="italic">feng shui</hi> principles of landscape design, created a garden in Dumfriesshire, <name type="place">Scotland</name> (figs. 15.21&#x2013;15.23). Its modeled terrain bears a superficial resemblance to archaeologically inspired Earthworks in the United States. <name type="pname">Jencks</name> and <name type="pname">Keswick</name>, however, were not interested in evoking prehistory. An archi-<lb/>
tectural theorist and popularizer of Postmodernism as well as the author of <hi rend="italic">The Architecture of the Jumping Universe,</hi> Jencks is fascinated with forms that relate to a new theory of cosmogenesis, which claims that the universe continually jumps to new levels of organi-<lb/>
zation. The "garden of cosmic speculation" in <name type="place">Scot-<lb/>
land</name> seeks to represent with elegance and wit Jencks's idea that "the new sciences of complexity, of which chaos is just one of twenty, show the omnipresence of these sudden leaps at all scales."<ref target="#CH15-n31"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">31</hi></hi></ref>Among other things, he wanted the garden to represent the struc-<lb/>
ture of space-time and quantum physics as envisioned by contemporary cosmologists. Different from Ptole-<lb/>
maic and Cartesian space, it portrays, according to Jencks, a universe that is "curved, warped, undulat-<lb/>
ing, jagged, zigzagged and sometimes beautifully crinkly."<ref target="#CH15-n32"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">32</hi></hi></ref> For <name type="pname">Keswick</name>, their garden was a means to express in a twentieth-century Western context <hi rend="italic">qi,</hi> the "breath," or inherent energy, possessed by all phe-<lb/>
nomena, an essential ingredient of Chinese painting and also sought by Chinese garden designers, as we observed in Chapter Eight.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-599">
<graphic url="CH15_022.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.21. Lower Portrack, Dumfriesshire, <name type="place">Scotland</name>. Designed by the owners Charles Jencks and Maggie <name type="pname">Keswick</name>. <date when="1990">1990</date>&#x2013;<date when="2000">2000</date>. Charac-<lb/>
terized by Jencks as "a garden of cosmic speculation," it con-<lb/>
tains a terrace of polished alu-<lb/>
minum and astroturf, which is arranged in a warped pattern suggesting the physical con-<lb/>
figuration of space caused by a "black hole" in the universe.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Within a concave section of the Giant Dragon Ha Ha, lies the Symmetry Break Terrace, which is meant to represent the four basic jumps&#x2014;energy, matter, life, consciousness&#x2014;that have taken place since the creation of our universe. Another terrace designed as a curving recessive checkerboard of Astroturf and polished aluminum is meant to dia-<lb/>
gram the way black holes are thought to warp space-<lb/>
time (fig. 15.21). A Physics Garden (an intended pun upon the Physic Garden for medicinal herbs) displays gatepost finials that are metal spheres representing various models of the universe based upon the Gaia, Ptolemaic, armillary, constellational, and atomic hypotheses.<ref target="#CH15-n33"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">33</hi></hi></ref>The climax of the garden is the 55-foot (16.8-meter) spiral mound and 400-foot (121.9-meter) double-wave Earthwork created with dredged spoil from the marsh that formerly occupied a part of the property (fig. 15.23). Here the designers' intentions were to represent in interlocking sculptural patterns of grass and water the Chinese concept of <hi rend="italic">qi</hi> and the geomantic principles of <hi rend="italic">feng shui</hi> together with the dynamics of complexity science and chaos theory. Thus, Jencks's spiral mound, dubbed the Snail, was created by piling the excavated material from the
<pb n="492"/>
<pb n="492" type="orig"/>
marsh to an angle of repose just preceding that which will cause a landslide&#x2014;"phase transition" as this point is called in the theory of complexity that physicists have developed to explain the creative patterning of matter that occurs on the border between chaos and order. The reversing curve implies the smooth tran-<lb/>
sition observed in the manner in which unlike things are enfolded into a spatial continuum. As a result, <name type="pname">Keswick</name>'s serpentine ponds assume the form of frac-<lb/>
tals, the endlessly recurring paisley shapes observed in nature, while also serving as metaphors for the energy-charged calm that resides in pools through-<lb/>
out the universe.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-600">
<graphic url="CH15_023.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.22. Lower Portrack, kitchen garden with sculpture of pol-<lb/>
ished aluminum representing a double-helix</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-601">
<graphic url="CH15_024.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.23. Lower Portrack, spiral mound and double-wave Earthwork</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Like the creators of Earthworks, golf-course designers are concerned with sculpting the land, although not to express conceptual meaning but
<pb n="493"/>
<pb n="493" type="orig"/>
rather for strategic purposes that are intrinsic to the game. Yet because of the sport's venerable history, its impact on land and water resources, and its impor-<lb/>
tance as an expression of contemporary cultural values, their work deserves discussion here.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Landscape as Sport: The Golf Course</hi></head>
<p>Course architecture is such a basic element of golf that the characteristics of each course account for the degree of challenge it presents to players.<ref target="#CH15-n34"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">34</hi></hi></ref>In a great global family tree of golf courses all the branches can be traced to <name type="place">Scotland</name> where the game grew out of the landscape, the sandy alluvial terrain called links. Natural links are found in estuarine areas where rivers deposit sediment on their way to the sea. Golf origi-<lb/>
nated as a game along the estuaries of the rivers <name type="pname">Eden</name>, <name type="pname">Tay</name>, and <name type="pname">Forth</name>. The first golf course, <name type="pname">St. Andrews</name>, dat-<lb/>
ing from the early fifteenth century was in its earliest form completely natural, a treeless stretch of wind-<lb/>
swept, rolling dunes with soil pockets supporting native bent grasses and some fescue.</p>
<p>The original game involved batting a "featherie," a small leather-bound, feather-stuffed ball, along a route improvised from the grass-covered links, avoiding the natural hazards of the gorse-encrusted dunes and eroded sandy hollows. Tees, clearly defined fairways, and well-manicured putting greens were unknown. Players simply wandered across this hillocky, treeless landscape, aiming their shots at whatever small holes served as cups. Although a series of such holes became institutionalized through repeated play, the number of cups on different Scottish links varied.</p>
<p>In the mid-eighteenth century, golfers' clubs were formed to organize the play. The Society of St. Andrews Golfers instituted turf maintenance for the putting areas, or greens and, in <date when="1764">1764</date>, set eighteen as the official circuit of holes that was later followed else-<lb/>
where. Golf-course architecture had its inception as the members of St. Andrews started to manipulate their natural golfing terrain by cutting double cups into enlarged greens&#x2014;one for matches heading "out," the other for those heading "in," widening the grassy playing strip by substituting turf for heather, and adding artificial hazards. "Penal" design is represented by the Old Course as it originally existed, where it was necessary to clear many natural hazards; the alterna-<lb/>
tive is "strategic" design, which allows the player the option of taking a slightly longer but safer route at the cost of additional strokes. From these basic principles, golf course architecture evolved.</p>
<p>Adopted in <name type="place">England</name> and after <date when="1779">1779</date> in <name type="place">America</name>, golf was played on rudimentary courses often lack-<lb/>
ing the characteristics of linkslands terrain. But the popularity of the game grew, particularly when in <date when="1848">1848</date> the low-cost, durable ball made from the natu-<lb/>
ral latex of the tropical gutta-percha plant was invented. This also made possible the use of revolu-<lb/>
tionary iron-headed golf clubs. As the demand for new courses grew with the gradual spread of the game, the first course designers were Scots and then Englishmen with professional qualifications derived from greenskeeping, not landscape design. They worked almost entirely on the ground, not from drawn plans, paying attention to the practicalities of the game rather than to any picturesque qualities inherent in the landscape. They did little to alter their sites, incorporating existing turf and other features or simply modifying courses, making them safer for the growing population of golfers or extending the length of holes to take into account the longer flight of the new gutta-percha balls.</p>
<p>In the second half of the nineteenth century, innovations in the routing of the course introduced variability in wind direction as a challenge for players. New machinery for mowing and new means of cut-<lb/>
-<lb/>
ting and lining holes with metal cups improved the quality of the greens. Discovery through trial and error proved that the heathlands southwest of <name type="place">London</name> were ideal inland golfing country when cleared of certain vegetation.</p>
<p>By <date when="1900">1900</date>, nearly a thousand courses had been built in the United States. With their distant views across rolling meadowlike greenswards fringed with trees, many of these golf courses offer scenery simi-<lb/>
lar to that found in "Capability" Brown's Grecian Val-<lb/>
ley at Stowe or Olmsted and Vaux's Long Meadow in Prospect Park (see Chapters Seven and Nine). But this is simply coincidence, because on golf courses the designer's primary consideration is not the scenery but rather the lie&#x2014;the position of the golf ball as it ceases rolling and comes to a stop. Bodies of water, however scenic, are intended as hazards for the player, not aesthetic features. Near the putting greens, fair-<lb/>
ways are punctuated with bunkers, shallow sand-filled depressions, also intended as strategically positioned hazards. To provide a final challenge as the player reaches the hole, designers have greens graded with almost imperceptibly undulating surfaces.</p>
<p>The <date when="1920">1920</date>s was a golden era for golf course con-<lb/>
struction in the United States, with an average of six hundred constructed each year between <date when="1923">1923</date> and <date when="1929">1929</date>, boosting the national total from 1,903 to 5,648. Many of these were laid out by local greenskeepers, who were often emigrants from Great Britain, and amateur golfers whose primary intent was to shape the landscape to suit the objectives of the game. Given an extraordinary site on <name type="place">California</name>'s Monterey Penin-<lb/>
sula, two regional tournament champions, <name type="pname">John Francis Neville</name> (<date when="1895">1895</date>&#x2013;<date when="1978">1978</date>) and <name type="pname">Douglas S. Grant</name>
<pb n="494"/>
<pb n="494" type="orig"/>
(<date when="1887">1887</date>&#x2013;<date when="1981">1981</date>), designed the breathtaking Pebble Beach Golf Links in <date when="1918">1918</date>. Built on a high bluff overlooking the Pacific Ocean, Pebble Beach does not occupy true linksland, but its sandy, hummocky, windswept ter-<lb/>
rain and magnificent views of Carmel Bay make it appear to fit its name.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-602">
<graphic url="CH15_025.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.24. Emerald Dunes Golf Course, West Palm Beach, <name type="place">Florida</name>, designed by Thomas Fazio. <date when="1990">1990</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Equally endowed, Cypress Point, adjacent to Pebble Beach, was laid out ten years later by Alister Mackensie (<date when="1870">1870</date>&#x2013;<date when="1934">1934</date>), a British physician turned golf-course designer. Mackensie, who built courses in <name type="place">England</name>, <name type="place">Scotland</name>, <name type="place">Ireland</name>, <name type="place">Canada</name>, <name type="place">Australia</name>, <name type="place">New Zealand</name>, and <name type="place">South America</name> as well as the United States, is considered one of the most eminent course designers in golf history, a reputation bolstered by his publication in <date when="1920">1920</date> of <hi rend="italic">Golf Architecture,</hi> codifying thir-<lb/>
teen key principles guiding course layout. These included&#x2014;in addition to those directed at enhancing the strategic interest of the game, the comfort and convenience of players, and the year-round playabil-<lb/>
ity of the course&#x2014;one that advised blending the course's artificial and natural features so that the two appeared indistinguishable.</p>
<p>By the mid-<date when="1930">1930</date>s, following the worst years of the Great Depression, course construction began to accelerate in the United States with the creation of the federal Works Progress Administration (WPA) to provide work for the unemployed. Municipal golf courses began to appear in cities across the country. The WPA crews moved earth and sculpted terrain using wheelbarrows and hand tools rather than heavy machinery, but after World War II when private golf course construction again boomed and massive unemployment was no longer a problem, modern earthmoving equipment was used. This greatly abbreviated the time it took to build a golf course. In addition, with petroleum no longer scarce, fuel for mowing machinery became readily available, which also stimulated course construction.</p>
<p>During this period <name type="pname">Robert Trent Jones</name> (b. <date when="1906">1906</date>) rose to preeminence as <name type="pname">America</name>'s foremost golf-<lb/>
course architect, and by <date when="1990">1990</date> his firm's portfolio contained 450 courses in forty-two states. Trent blended the "penal" and "strategic" types of design with the creation of a style he called "heroic." His "heroic" courses eschewed the elaborate bunkering of penal-<lb/>
type design, substituting a single, formidable, diago-<lb/>
nally placed hazard such as a pond that the golfer had to clear with a long drive of more than 500 feet (152.4 meters). At the same time, the golfer was allowed to choose an alternative, less risky route to the green. Trent's particular gift as a designer lay in employing penal, strategic, and heroic design techniques accord-<lb/>
ing to the nature of play a course was expected to receive, taking into account whether it was munici-<lb/>
pal operation for the general public, a resort for pay-<lb/>
ing guests, a country club for members, a private layout for an owner and friends, or a tournament venue for professional golfers.</p>
<p>In the <date when="1960">1960</date>s, professional golfers were becoming celebrities, thanks especially to televised sports matches. The popularity of golf, particularly among the growing number of active retired people, was responsible for a new land-planning phenomenon: the residential community built around a golf course. However, by the mid-<date when="1970">1970</date>s, the escalating cost of course construction, the energy crisis, tight money, new environmental regulations in the United States, and land-use restrictions in <name type="place">Japan</name> curtailed the rate of
<pb n="495"/>
<pb n="495" type="orig"/>
golf-course building. Then, during the prosperous <date when="1980">1980</date>s, the pace of course construction revived. <name type="pname">George Fazio</name> (<date when="1912">1912</date>&#x2013;<date when="1986">1986</date>), working with his nephews, <name type="pname">Thomas Joseph Fazio</name> (b. <date when="1945">1945</date>) and <name type="pname">Vincent James Fazio</name> (b. <date when="1942">1942</date>) built and revised courses, including sev-<lb/>
eral for clubs hosting major tournaments. The view from Hole 18, known as Super Dune, on the Emer-<lb/>
ald Dunes Golf Course in West Palm Beach, <name type="place">Florida</name>, shows how, in <date when="1990">1990</date>, Tom Fazio sculpted artificial water bodies, sweeping fairways, and contoured greens to create a scenic panorama out of former scrub land covered with palmetto thickets (fig. 15.24).</p>
<p>In <date when="1974">1974</date>, eminent professional golfer Jack Nick-<lb/>
laus (b. <date when="1940">1940</date>) organized his own firm. In <name type="place">Scottsdale</name>, <name type="place">Arizona</name>, his Desert Highlands <name type="pname">Golf Club</name> (<date when="1984">1984</date>) demonstrated how a grass-demanding sport could be successfully integrated into a naturally arid landscape. Restricted in the amount of irrigation he could use, Nicklaus created wide swaths of playable sand between fairly narrow turfy fairways and the pebbles and coarse rock of the surrounding desert. Never-<lb/>
theless, Nicklaus, who seeks a deluxe finish to his courses, insists upon velvety bent grass for all his greens no matter the climate. In addition, he typically builds cascades for his water hazards, installs elabo-<lb/>
rate irrigation systems, and specifies the use of state-<lb/>
of-the-art mowing equipment.</p>
<p>Perhaps Thorstein Veblen's theory of conspic-<lb/>
uous consumption, or nonproductive leisure as a means of displaying wealth, discussed in Chapter Twelve, is nowhere more manifest than in the game of golf, especially if this assessment takes into account the difficult issue of water rights in dry climates. In spite of conservationists' protests, the popularity of the game is such that it is politically difficult to stem the tide of course construction, even in arid com-<lb/>
munities where water reservoirs run dangerously low and capacity cannot be expanded. The fact that golf-<lb/>
ing has become almost an obligatory ritual among corporate businesspeople who routinely meet clients on the links exacerbates this difficult and continuing ecological and societal problem.</p>
<p>Although contemporary enthusiasm for golf may be capricious, the story we have briefly traced of its evolution from the seaside links of <name type="place">Scotland</name> to the inland desert around <name type="place">Scottsdale</name>, from a sport whose objectives and rules were shaped by landscape to one that employs a high degree of artifice and mecha-<lb/>
nization in manipulating the landscape to create new challenges for players, is an entirely pragmatic one. At the opposite end of the spectrum is the landscape that is highly theoretical in its design intent, one that takes shape not from the land or the requirements of sport or other user demands. Such a landscape is Parc de la Villette in <name type="place">Paris</name>.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Landscape as Deconstructivist Theory: Parc de la Villette</hi></head>
<p>Architect Bernard Tschumi (b. <date when="1944">1944</date>) designed Parc de la Villette on the eastern rim of <name type="place">Paris</name> as a decon-<lb/>
structivist exercise informed by the concepts of dis-<lb/>
sociation developed by philosopher <name type="pname">Jacques Derrida</name> (b. <date when="1930">1930</date>) (figs. 15.25, 15.26). Whereas Earthworks artists such as Smithson sought metaphysical repre-<lb/>
sentation in their work, the deconstructivist Tschumi believes as did Derrida that "in architecture we find something that contradicts the metaphysics of repre-<lb/>
sentation and thus everything linked to representa-<lb/>
tion."<ref target="#CH15-n35"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">35</hi></hi></ref>Like Smithson, Tschumi starts from the same Postmodern position that chaos rules, but instead of creating as did Smithson an art that represents entropy, he subscribes to Derrida's concept of architecture in which "the strongest reference [is] to absence."<ref target="#CH15-n36"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">36</hi></hi></ref></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-603">
<graphic url="CH15_026.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.25. Plan of Parc de la Villette, designed by Bernard Tschumi. <date when="1984">1984</date>&#x2013;89</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Tschumi was one of 471 entrants in the design competition for the new 175-acre park that was to rise between <date when="1984">1984</date> and <date when="1989">1989</date> on the site of the old Parisian cattle market and slaughterhouses. The competition guidelines called for an innovative park that would be superior to the nineteenth-century Picturesque parks designed by Alphand (see Chapter Ten). A prolific the-<lb/>
<pb n="496"/>
<pb n="496" type="orig"/>
orist who practices architecture from a highly intel-<lb/>
lectual perspective, Tschumi saw Parc de la Villette's design as an opportunity to manifest textual decon-<lb/>
structivism in terms of landscape. After his design was selected by a twenty-one-person jury chaired by <name type="pname">Roberto Burle Marx</name>, Tschumi invited architect <name type="pname">Peter Eisenman</name> and <name type="pname">Derrida</name> to participate with him by developing a small area within the park. To the com-<lb/>
mission of designing a space within Parc de la Villette Derrida brought his interest in Plato's <hi rend="italic">Timaeus</hi> and its definition of space as <hi rend="italic">chora,</hi> the virgin receptacle of place, or the spacing that is the condition for every-<lb/>
thing to take place, the necessary means of providing a web for places.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-604">
<graphic url="CH15_027.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.26. Sunday in the Parc de la Villette. The recreational experiences enjoyed by visi-<lb/>
tors within Tschumi's essay in park architecture as decon-<lb/>
structivist philosophy are more diverse and active than the ones Sunday parkgoers have in nineteenth-century Parisian parks.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-605">
<graphic url="CH15_028.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below right:</hi> 15.27. Parc Andr&#x00E9; Citroen, designed by two teams of competition entrants: <name type="pname">Alain Provost</name>, <name type="pname">Jean-Paul Vigu-<lb/>
ier</name>, and <name type="pname">Jean-François Jodry</name> and <name type="pname">Patrick Berger</name> and <name type="pname">Gilles Cl&#x00E9;ment</name>. <date when="1985">1985</date>&#x2013;<date when="1992">1992</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-606">
<graphic url="CH15_029.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 15.28. Parc Andr&#x00E9; Citroen</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Tschumi's self-imposed challenge was to give spatial expression to a philosophical idea that rejects unitary meaning in favor of spontaneous multiple occurrences, or "event-texts" in the language of deconstructivism. His method was to create a fluid, nonspecific, uncentered, unconfined space &#x2014; a the-<lb/>
oretically boundaryless receptacle devoid of any rep-<lb/>
resentational associations, a blank textbook in which anyone can inscribe whatever meaning they choose.</p>
<p>Although in Tschumi's theoretical view it has no boundaries, Parc de la Villette is anchored by a sci-<lb/>
ence museum on its southwest end and by a music conservatory and performance hall on its northeast perimeter. These large cultural institutions, also the result of design competitions, were built at approxi-<lb/>
mately the same time as the park. In addition, the industrial structures that once served as slaughter-<lb/>
houses have been reused as event centers. The park in between and surrounding these buildings is an open grassy plain designed as an imaginary grid punc-<lb/>
tuated by <hi rend="italic">folies,</hi> a series of bright red, cubelike build-<lb/>
ings, which appear as large abstract geometric sculptures set at regular intervals upon the greens-<lb/>
ward. Tschumi intended his green platform with red <hi rend="italic">folies</hi> placed at grid intersections as "a surface of mul-<lb/>
tireferential anchoring points for things or people which leads to a partial coherence."<ref target="#CH15-n37"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">37</hi></hi></ref>Though with-<lb/>
out specified uses at the time of construction, these now function like structures in conventional parks; some are snack bars, one is a children's play structure, another a first-aid station, and so forth. A curvilinear, below-grade Bamboo Garden designed by Alexandre Chemetoff (b. <date when="1950">1950</date>) provides a counterpoint to the strict geometry of Tschumi's theoretically endless spa-<lb/>
tial grid. At grade, a similarly serpentine path also plays against the regularity of the overall plan.</p>
<p>This highly intellectualized approach to land-<lb/>
scape creation is the province of design competitions and the product of an avant-garde cultural establish-<lb/>
ment. The French have historically been especially hospitable to innovation and cerebral forms of artis-<lb/>
tic expression. However, other new Parisian essays in landscape creation, notably the new parks of Bercy and Andr&#x00E9; Citro&#x00EB;n, do not pursue the deconstruc-<lb/>
tivist course charted at Parc de la Villette. These other new parks project the kind of meaning and symbolic structure of older gardens where representation&#x2014; the <hi rend="italic">re-presentation</hi> of ideas, as opposed to the presen-<lb/>
<pb n="497"/>
<pb n="497" type="orig"/>
tation of an implicitly endless grid as an intentionally <hi rend="italic">meaning-less</hi> space in which visitors find whatever "event-text" or momentary significance they may wish&#x2014;aims to create poetical place, not merely value-<lb/>
neutral space (figs. 15.27, 15.28).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-607">
<graphic url="CH15_030.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.29. Prostrate column with the inscription "Arcadia, a Place in <name type="place">Sparta</name>'s Neighbor-<lb/>
hood," Little <name type="place">Sparta</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-608">
<graphic url="CH15_031.jpg"/>
<p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 15.30. Little <name type="place">Sparta</name>, <name type="place">Stonypath</name>, <name type="place">Dunsyre</name>, near <name type="place">Lanark</name>, <name type="place">Scotland</name>, garden designed by Ian Hamilton Fin-<lb/>
lay. Begun <date when="1966">1966</date>. Inscription on rough-hewn stones: "The Pre-<lb/>
sent Order is the Disorder of the Future&#x2014;Saint Just."</hi></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Landscape as Concrete and Metaphysical Poetry</hi></head>
<p>Poet and visual artist <name type="pname">Ian Hamilton Finlay</name> (b. <date when="1925">1925</date>) established his reputation in the <date when="1960">1960</date>s as a pioneer of concrete poetry, the arrangement of individual words on a page, often accompanied by pictorial images, in ways that gives them psychological resonance and heightened meaning. His garden near <name type="place">Lanark</name>, <name type="place">Scot-<lb/>
land</name>, which he calls Little <name type="place">Sparta</name>, with its textual ele-<lb/>
ments&#x2014;graphically beautiful incised stones and wood&#x2014;explores the gap between language and sign, indulging a subtle interplay of word and form, within the context of landscape (figs. 15.29,15.30). As a gar-<lb/>
den of association, Little <name type="place">Sparta</name> is reminiscent of such eighteenth-century creations as <name type="pname">William Shenstone</name>'s Leasowes or <name type="pname">Henry Hoare</name>'s Stourhead, which also abound in evocations of antiquity.<ref target="#CH15-n38"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">38</hi></hi></ref>As we saw in Chapter Seven, the Leasowes was a <hi rend="italic">ferme orn&#x00E9;e,</hi> and Stourhead, with its themes from the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid,</hi> is a highly poetic landscape manifesting Virgil's epic narration of the founding of <name type="place">Rome</name>. Like these eighteenth-<lb/>
century predecessors, Little <name type="place">Sparta</name> consciously recalls the Arcadian paintings of the seventeenth-century artist <name type="pname">Claude Lorrain</name> and the nostalgic echoes of a Golden Age found in Virgil's <hi rend="italic">Eclogues,</hi> the series of pastoral poems composed by the Latin poet between 42 and 37 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Situated in the rolling Pentland Hills of southern <name type="place">Scotland</name> where sheep graze, the garden effectively implies these earlier depictions of a bucolic landscape studded with a few antique ruins. In such Claudian or Virgilian scenes human action occurs within the rhythms of a timeless agrarian round as shepherds and flocks move in sunlit meadows and rest beside shady groves and softly gliding streams. At Lit-<lb/>
tle <name type="place">Sparta</name>, the themes of water and land, waves and hills, boats and huts predominate, although the gar-<lb/>
den also contains references to the French Revolution and warfare, especially World War II, and symboli-<lb/>
cally hints at the shadow of destructive nuclear power under which we live today. With such memorials to our losses of innocence as the fallen "Arcadia" column
<pb n="498"/>
<pb n="498" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-609">
<graphic url="CH15_032.jpg"/>
</figure>
and "Nuclear Sail," a smoothly rounded, silkily fin-<lb/>
ished, matte gray "gravestone," Little <name type="place">Sparta</name>'s improb-<lb/>
able and ironic dialogue with the tranquil Scottish borderland may perhaps be best characterized as an elegant and elegiac meditation on postindustrial as well as postpastoral civilization.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Maya Ying Lin</name> (b. <date when="1959">1959</date>) is an artist who works in the conceptual zone between landscape design and sculpture, and, like Finlay, she understands the com-<lb/>
bined power of words and visual imagery. Often clas-<lb/>
sified with Earthworks artists, she is less concerned with creating large-scale works of cosmological ref-<lb/>
erence in remote locations than with imaging a meta-<lb/>
physical poetry in environments that are readily accessible and where her art gains significance from the opportunities presented by the site. For these rea-<lb/>
sons, Lin's work is not abstractly philosophical. Instead, it is informed by psychology and phenome-<lb/>
nology. Unlike the awesome and somewhat intimi-<lb/>
dating works of some artists, Lin's con- structions are intimate and inviting, while serving an essentially poetic purpose. Water and stone and images of time and movement are important elements in her art, and she employs these in sensory as well as symbolical ways. Psychology is evident in her use of other forms of sensory stimulation besides the visual: her work is tactile and aural, encouraging one to touch, be still, and listen. She is more concerned with investing places with universal human significance than with creating spaces like Parc de la Villette that are intended to serve as abstract architectural demonstrations of philosophical theory.</p>
<p>Lin sprang to prominence in <date when="1981">1981</date> as a Yale undergraduate when she won the design competi-<lb/>
tion for the Vietnam Veterans Memorial (fig. 15.31). A requirement of the Vietnam Veterans Memorial Fund, sponsors of the competition, was that the memorial contain the names of the more than 57,000 servicemen who died or are missing in action in that tragic conflict. Conceived as two retaining walls of black polished granite holding a grassy bank at an angle of 132 degrees, this sober, tactile, meditation upon death and war leads the visitor along an inclined path past the inscribed necrology that begins and ends at the apex of the triangular incision in the earth.</p>
<p>Begun as a studio project in an architecture class, Lin's competition entry drew inspiration indirectly from a memorial that was formally quite different: Sir Edwin Lutyens's monument to the missing soldiers of the World War I Battle of the Somme in Thiepval, <name type="place">France</name>, an immense archway upon which 100,000 names are inscribed. "To walk past those names and realize those lost lives&#x2014;the effect of that is the strength of the design," Lin has written. Her approach was similarly "apolitical, harmonious with the site, and conciliatory" Lin wished to produce a monument
<pb n="499"/>
<pb n="499" type="orig"/>
that was lacking in histrionic content but capable of serving as a necessary cathartic vehicle for mourning the tragedy of the war, a means for veterans and other visitors to come to terms with the soldiers' deaths. About the design, she says, "I imagined taking a knife and cutting into the earth, opening it up, an initial vio-<lb/>
lence and pain that in time would heal. The grass would grow back, but the initial cut would remain a pure flat surface in the earth with a polished, mirrored surface, much like the surface on a geode when you cut it and polish the edge. The need for the names to be on the memorial would become the memorial; there was no need to embellish the design further. The people and their names would allow everyone to respond and remember. ... I always wanted the names to be chronological, to make it so that those who served and returned from the war could find their place in the memorial."<ref target="#CH15-n39"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">39</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>One side of the Vietnam Memorial's wide sunken V points to the <name type="place">Washington</name> Monument, which is reflected in the somber granite's mirror fin-<lb/>
ish; the other is directed toward the Lincoln Memor-<lb/>
ial. The openness, darkness, and below-grade horizontality of the Vietnam Veterans Memorial sub-<lb/>
tly oppose the self-containment, whiteness, and ver-<lb/>
ticality of those structures. "By linking these two strong symbols for the country, I wanted to create a unity between the nation's past and present," says Lin. The mirror finish also reflects the visitors' images and the surrounding park, "creating two worlds, one we are a part of and one we cannot enter."<ref target="#CH15-n40"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">40</hi></hi></ref> The still-<lb/>
ness and emotion are palpable as visitors descend to experience the wide V's sober embrace, some of their fingers tracing over the letters of the names. Few overtly heroic monuments command this degree of respectful attention. Fresh flowers, recently written notes, and other newly deposited tokens of respect and love bespeak the continuing bond between the living and the dead.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-610">
<graphic url="CH15_033.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.31. Vietnam Veterans Memorial, Constitution Gardens, <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, designed by Maya Lin. <date when="1982">1982</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>In enjoining artists "to portray a more interest-<lb/>
ing, beautiful, dynamic, and tragic universe,"<ref target="#CH15-n41"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">41</hi></hi></ref> Charles Jencks is thinking of the deeper cosmological consciousness produced by twentieth-century sci-<lb/>
ence. Along with Jencks, Lin is interested in giving landscape expression to the new concepts of the uni-<lb/>
verse that are emerging through advanced science and technology. By coincidence, she was born and grew up in <name type="pname">Athens</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>, near the Hopewell Mounds, and while these ancient relics probably hold the same fascination for her as for archaeologists and other cos-<lb/>
mologically oriented artists of Earthworks, her pri-<lb/>
mary objective is to discern and express what we are here suggesting as "fourth nature," a state that inte-<lb/>
grates the three preexisting categories of nature&#x2014; wilderness, cultivated land, and the garden&#x2014;with science and technology. This dimension of her work
<pb n="500"/>
<pb n="500" type="orig"/>
derives inspiration from the optical and photographic instruments&#x2014;microscopes, telescopes, and satellite cameras&#x2014;that make us perceive the world and uni-<lb/>
verse in new ways.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-611">
<graphic url="CH15_034.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">15.32. <hi rend="italic">The Wave Field,</hi> François-Xavier Bagnoud Aerospace Engineering Build-<lb/>
ing, University of <name type="place">Michigan</name>, <name type="place">Ann Arbor</name>, <name type="place">Michigan</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Maya Lin</name>. <date when="1995">1995</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>To create <hi rend="italic">The Wave Field</hi> (<date when="1995">1995</date>), a 100-foot-<lb/>
square (30.5-meter-square) earth and grass memorial commissioned for the François-Xavier Bagnoud Aero-<lb/>
space Engineering Building at the University of Michi-<lb/>
gan in Ann Arbor, Lin studied the fluid dynamics associated with the physics of flight (fig. 15.32). The image that gave substance to the fluidity, indetermi-<lb/>
nacy, and unending repetitiousness of the movement of air currents essential to flight was for her a photo-<lb/>
graph of ocean waves in a turbulent sea. Here she evokes both her notion of the indeterminate charac-<lb/>
ter of the endless advancing and receding ocean and the oceanic appearance of the waving prairie that was once the American Midwest. Each of the earthen waves, which vary slightly in breadth and height, is a cozy shell in which students come to sit and read. As Michael Brenson explains:
<q>In <hi rend="italic">The Wave Field,</hi> indeterminacy becomes place. Lin grounds it, makes it available to actual peo-<lb/>
ple. She also gives it a moral purpose, even an urgency, that would be inconceivable in many hymns to indeterminacy. <hi rend="italic">The Wave Field</hi> makes a case for art's ability to encourage people to gather in an environ-<lb/>
ment where they will be comfortable with one another and able to trust what they have not yet recognized and what they cannot measure or control; an environment in which children feel safe and inspired by the pleasure that can come from experiencing the world in terms of discovery, play, intercon-<lb/>
nectedness, and flow.<ref target="#CH15-n42"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">42</hi></hi></ref></q></p>
<p>Place as indeterminacy and experience as dis-<lb/>
covery, play, interconnectedness, and flow are con-<lb/>
cepts of the twentieth and twenty-first centuries. Earthworks and other forms of Conceptual art bear witness to the entropic character of contemporary civilization, engage our imaginations in new cosmo-<lb/>
logical perspectives on the meaning of time and space, and provide metaphorical expression for our otherwise inexpressible sorrows or joys. At the same time, our everyday lives proceed in diurnal time and real space. Our understanding of contemporary place must therefore accommodate the accelerated change, motion, and communication that characterizes the new Postindustrial Age. We must seek to compre-<lb/>
hend a geography that is both temporal and spatial, one of flows, instantaneousness, and virtuality. Place is, in the last analysis, experiential, as much a state of mind as an earthly reality. It is, according to contem-<lb/>
porary thought, grounded within us, within our phys-<lb/>
ical bodies as well as within our psyches. This is true whether we are stationary&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">in place</hi>&#x2014;or traveling. It is important to understand that movement itself is part of the experience of place and that we are all in a sense weavers of landscape. It is with this notion of place-making as weaving and the reading of the world as a loom of landscape, a cultural geography, that we will conclude.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="501"/>
<pb n="501" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Fifteen</hi></head>
<note xml:id="CH15-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p> See Kevin Lynch, <hi rend="italic">The Image of the City,</hi> <name type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: The M.I.T. Press, <date when="1960">1960</date>. Lynch's small influential classic volume on reading the city develops the concept of nodes&#x2014;topographic features, landmark structures, prominent or eccentric build-<lb/>
ings, public open spaces&#x2014;as easily visu-<lb/>
alized reference points in the mental maps that act like circuit boards of place within our brains.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p> These words are being written on <date when="2000-01-01">Janu-<lb/>
ary 1, 2000</date>, after watching the millennial fireworks bursting in the night sky over <name type="place">New York</name> City while also viewing a televi-<lb/>
sion broadcast of filmed New Year's cele-<lb/>
brations in every part of the world. One saw the collapsing of time and space in the present century's intensely globalizing cul-<lb/>
ture and observed iconic structures of place&#x2014;the Eiffel Tower in <name type="place">Paris</name> and many other world monuments&#x2014;now presented as intensely illuminated spectacles, serv-<lb/>
ing as talismans in a time of seemingly momentous transition as well as the foci of mass gatherings of humanity. <name type="place">New York</name> City's Times Square, whose design char-<lb/>
acter is&#x2014;appropriately in an age of media power&#x2014;distinguished more by highly technological visual display of information and photographic imagery than by any eas-<lb/>
ily recognizable architectural character, was the self-proclaimed epicenter of this global party.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p> Robert Smithson, "Entropy and the New Monuments" (<date when="1966">1966</date>), <hi rend="italic">Robert Smithson: The Collected Writings,</hi> ed. <name type="pname">Jack Flam</name> (<name type="place">Berkeley</name>: University of <name type="place">California</name> Press, <date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 11.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p> Ibid. According to Smithson, "The slurbs, urban sprawl, and the infinite number of housing developments of the postwar boom have contributed to the architecture of entropy." op. cit., p. 13.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 14.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p> David Lowenthal, <hi rend="italic">The Heritage Crusade and the Spoils of History</hi>(<name type="place">Cambridge</name>: <name type="place">Cam-<lb/>
bridge</name> University Press, <date when="1998">1998</date>), p. xiii.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p> Kevin Lynch, "Time and Place in Envi-<lb/>
ronmental Design," <hi rend="italic">City Sense and City Design: Writings and Projects of Kevin Lynch,</hi> ed. Tridib Banerjee and Michael Southworth (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: MIT Press, <date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 630.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., pp. 629&#x2013;30.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Delores Hayden</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Power of Place: Urban Landscapes as Public History</hi> (<name type="place">Cam-<lb/>
bridge</name>, Mass.: MIT Press, <date when="1995">1995</date>), p. xi.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p> For a good discussion of the changing meanings assigned the <name type="place">New England</name> town, see William Butler, "Another City upon a Hill: Litchfield, Connecticut, and the Colo-<lb/>
nial Revival," in <hi rend="italic">The Colonial Revival in <name type="place">America</name></hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: W. W. Norton &amp; Com-<lb/>
pany, <date when="1985">1985</date>), pp. 15&#x2013;51.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p> See <name type="pname">Chris Wilson</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Myth of Santa Fe: Creating a Modern Regional Tradition</hi> (Albuquerque: University of <name type="place">New Mexico</name> Press, <date when="1997">1997</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p> For a good interpretation of the motives, often unconscious, underlying the re-<lb/>
creation of historical narratives through landscape preservation and restoration, see David Lowenthal, <hi rend="italic">The Past Is a Foreign Country</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>: <name type="place">Cambridge</name> University Press, <date when="1985">1985</date>). According to Lowenthal, "We are often innocent of conscious intent to change what we mean simply to conserve or celebrate.... We can now see how ped-<lb/>
agogic and patriotic commitments shaped Henry Ford's Greenfield and John D. Rock-<lb/>
efeller's Williamsburg. But we cannot detect our own preconceptions, which warp the past no less than Ford's or Rock-<lb/>
efeller's." See op. cit., pp. 325&#x2013;26.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p> See <name type="pname">Charles B. Hosmer</name>, Jr., "The Colo-<lb/>
nial Revival in the Public Eye: Williamsburg and Early Garden Restoration," <hi rend="italic">The Colo-<lb/>
nial Revival in <name type="place">America</name>,</hi> pp. 52&#x2013;70.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p> Mary Haldane Begg Coleman, "The Reminiscences of Mrs. <name type="pname">George P. Cole-<lb/>
man</name>," transcript of interview, <date when="1956-02-22">February 22, 1956</date> (Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Archives: Oral History Collection), p. 62. As quoted in <name type="pname">Charles B. Hosmer</name>, Jr., "The Colo-<lb/>
nial Revival in the Public Eye: Williamsburg and Early Garden Restoration," <hi rend="italic">The Colo-<lb/>
nial Revival in <name type="place">America</name>,</hi> pp. 61&#x2013;62.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p> The impulse to make Williamsburg's faded past, which may have been "a little bit thin," nevertheless very pretty and in keeping with contemporary aesthetics as influenced by Industrial Age manufactur-<lb/>
ing standards and maintenance practices extends well beyond Shurcliff's gardens. For instance, "In restored Colonial Williams-<lb/>
burg, paints and fabrics brighter than colonists ever had were justified on the ground that eighteenth-century folk would surely have used such colours if they could have found and afforded them." See Lowen-<lb/>
thal, <hi rend="italic">The Past Is a Foreign Country,</hi> p. 329.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Jane Jacobs</name>, <hi rend="italic">Death and Life of Great American Cities (<name type="place">New York</name>:</hi> Random House, <date when="1961">1961</date>), pp. 443&#x2013;44.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p> Ibid.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p> See <name type="pname">David Lowenthal</name>, <hi rend="italic">George Perkins Marsh: Prophet of Conservation</hi> (Seattle: University of <name type="place">Washington</name> Press, <date when="2000">2000</date>), p. 267, note 1.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">George Parkins Marsh</name>, <hi rend="italic">Man and Nature, Or, Physical Geography as Modi-<lb/>
fied by Human Action</hi> (<date when="1864">1864</date>), ed. <name type="pname">David Lowenthal</name> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, <date when="1965">1965</date>), pp. 38&#x2013;9.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">20.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 465.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">21.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 51, note 53.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">22.</hi></seg><p> Ian <name type="pname">McHarg</name>, <hi rend="italic">Design With Nature,</hi> 25th Anniversary edition (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">John Wiley</name> &amp; Sons, Inc., <date when="1992">1992</date>), p. 5.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n23" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">23.</hi></seg><p> Ibid, p. 19.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n24" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">24.</hi></seg><p> See Anne Whiston Spirn, <hi rend="italic">The Granite Garden: Urban Nature and Human Design</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Basic Books, <date when="1984">1984</date>). See also Timothy Beatley, <hi rend="italic">Green Urbanism: Learn-<lb/>
ing from European Cities</hi> (<name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>: <name type="place">Island</name> Press, <date when="2000">2000</date>). For a good discussion of the term <hi rend="italic">urban husbandry</hi> as a means of revitalizing cities as places to live, see <name type="place">Roberta Gratz</name> and <name type="place">Norman Mintz</name>, <hi rend="italic">Cities Back from the Edge: New Life for Down-<lb/>
town</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Preservation Press, <name type="pname">John Wiley</name> &amp; Sons, Inc., <date when="1998">1998</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n25" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">25.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Harlow Whittemore</name>, in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the National Conference on Instruction in Landscape Architecture,</hi> Asilomar, Pacific Grove, <name type="place">California</name>, July 5&#x2013;7, <date when="1957">1957</date>, p. 30. As quoted in <name type="pname">Peter Walker</name> and <name type="pname">Melanie Simo</name>, <hi rend="italic">Invisible Gardens: The Search for Mod-<lb/>
ernism in the American Landscape</hi> (<name type="place">Cam-<lb/>
bridge</name>, Mass.: MIT Press, <date when="1994">1994</date>), pp. 258&#x2013;59.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n26" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">26.</hi></seg><p> For the history of the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial, I am indebted to <name type="pname">Reuben M. Rainey</name>, "The Garden as Narra-<lb/>
tive: <name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name>'s Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial," unpublished manu-<lb/>
script, <date when="1995">1995</date>.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n27" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">27.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Robert Smithson</name>, "Entropy and the New Monuments" (<date when="1966">1966</date>), <hi rend="italic">Robert Smithson: The Collected Writings,</hi> ed. <name type="pname">Jack Flam</name> (<name type="place">Berkeley</name>: University of <name type="place">California</name> Press, <date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 11.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n28" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">28.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Robert Smithson</name>, "Spiral Jetty" (<date when="1972">1972</date>), <hi rend="italic">Robert Smithson: The Collected Writings,</hi> p. 145.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n29" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">29.</hi></seg><p> Ibid, p. 146.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n30" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">30.</hi></seg><p> Interview with the author, <date when="2000-07-27">July 27, 2000</date>.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n31" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">31.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Charles Jencks</name>, as quoted in Cooper and Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Transformed: The Pri-<lb/>
vate Garden for the Twenty-first Century,</hi> p. 67.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n32" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">32.</hi></seg><p> As quoted by <name type="pname">Julie V. lovine</name>, "Sermon on the Mound," <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">New York</name> Times Magazine,</hi> <date when="1996-02-04">February 4, 1996</date>, p. 44.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n33" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">33.</hi></seg><p> See Cooper and Taylor, op. cit., p. 72.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n34" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">34.</hi></seg><p> For my knowledge of the history of golf course design as outlined below I am indebted to <name type="pname">Geoffrey S. Cornish</name> and <name type="pname">Ronald E. Whitten</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Architects of Golf,</hi> rev. ed. (<name type="place">New York</name>: HarperCollins, Publishers, <date when="1993">1993</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n35" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">35.</hi></seg><p> Transcript of meeting in <name type="place">New York</name>, <date when="1985-09-17">Sep-<lb/>
tember 17, 1985</date>, in <hi rend="italic">Chora L Works</hi> by Jacques Derrida and Peter Eisenman, edited by Jeffrey Kipnis and Thomas Leeser <name type="place">New York</name>: The Monacelli Press, <date when="1997">1997</date>), p. 8.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n36" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">36.</hi></seg><p> Ibid.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n37" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">37.</hi></seg><p> Bernard Tschumi, <hi rend="italic">Cin&#x00E9;gramme Folie: Le Parc de la Villette</hi> (Prince-<lb/>
ton, N.J.: Princeton Architectural Press, <date when="1987">1987</date>), p. 24.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n38" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">38.</hi></seg><p> According to <name type="pname">John Dixon Hunt</name>, "Finlay is undoubtedly a special case in modern landscape architecture. He is special not because he is different but because his radical invocation of basic devices from the history of place-making makes more of those traditions than most other designers." See John Dixon Hunt, <hi rend="italic">Greater Perfections</hi> (<name type="place">Philadelphia</name>: University of Pennsylvania Press, <date when="2000">2000</date>), p. 117.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n39" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">39.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Maya Lin</name>, "Making the Memorial," <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place">New York</name> Review of Books:</hi> XLVII:17 (<date when="2000-11-02">November 2, 2000</date>), pp. 33&#x2013;34.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n40" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">40.</hi></seg><p> Ibid.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n41" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">41.</hi></seg><p> "Landscape of Waves," <hi rend="italic">Prospect Mag-<lb/>
azine</hi> (Winter, <date when="1996">1996</date>): 2&#x2013;5, as quoted in Beardsley, <hi rend="italic">Earthworks and Beyond,</hi> p. 197.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH15-n42" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">42.</hi></seg><p> "Maya Lin's Time," in <hi rend="italic">Maya Lin: Topolo-<lb/>
gies (</hi>Winston-Salem: Southeastern Center for Contemporary Art, <date when="1998">1998</date>), p. 41.</p></note>
</div>
</div>
