<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/html/tei.xsl"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY</title>
                <author>ELIZABETH BARLOW ROGERS</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>HARRY N. ABRAMS, INC.,</publisher>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY by ELIZABETH BARLOW
                    ROGERS</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div type="chapter"><pb n="502"/><pb n="502" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER SIXTEEN THE WEAVING OF PLACE AND THE GEOGRAPHY OF FLOWS: LANDSCAPE AS BODILY EXPERIENCE AND VERNACULAR EXPRESSION</hi></head><figure xml:id="fig-612"><graphic url="CH16_001.jpg"/></figure><p>The cultural background shaping contemporary attitudes toward landscape and place can be discerned in philosophy, which toward the end of the nineteenth century found its domain in alliance with psychology. During this period, confidence in Western society's progressive ideology began to erode as science and philosophy split ever further apart, and the restless search for truth became a matter of continually shifting premises. As revolutionary scientific discoveries overthrew former religious belief about the creation of the universe, they substituted no reasonable new cosmology, only the exhilarating yet sometimes disquieting intellectual voyage into the unknown that continues still.</p><p>The implications of evolutionary biology in <hi rend="italic">The Origin of Species,</hi> which <name type="pname">Charles Darwin</name> (<date when="1809">1809</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>) published in <date when="1859">1859</date>, made it clear that humankind could no longer be viewed as separate from the rest of the animal kingdom. Furthermore, the field of scientific geology developed by Sir Charles Lyell (<date when="1797">1797</date>&#x2013;<date when="1875">1875</date>), from whose fossil record Darwin drew many of his conclusions, undermined completely the notion that Earth's topography&#x2014;the context and medium of landscape design&#x2014;could have been modeled by mythological gods or a Divine Craftsman, rather than by the natural forces of crustal upthrust and erosion by wind and water.</p><p>At the same time that geologists learned that the shape of Earth's surface is the product of many eons of flux, physicists unsettled established verities regarding the stability and timelessness of the universe. At the beginning of the twentieth century, the formulation of the second law of thermodynamics, which foretells the disintegration of the universe as it moves toward a state of entropy, undermined the Enlightenment's confident, rational Cartesian-Newtonian cosmology. <name type="pname">Albert Einstein</name> (<date when="1879">1879</date>&#x2013;<date when="1955">1955</date>) further eroded the principles of Enlightenment science with the theory of relativity, and thus the independent and absolute nature of space and time. Quantum mechanics further unseated accepted truths.</p><p>The Enlightenment concept of a heliocentric universe was relegated to the dustbin of science. In recent years, the theory of a Big Bang has gained general acceptance as the generative power behind a multigalactic universe composed of many hundreds of billions of solar masses. Telescopic space probes of heretofore unimaginable depth are revealing ever more remote galaxies. Today universal space is understood to be curved, even malleable, rather than as extending in a straight plane as Ren&#x00E9; Descartes had logically supposed in the seventeenth century.</p><p>Seen thus in the light of biology, geology, and physics, belief in a stable, unchanging, God-created world and belief in the human being's extraordinary, semidivine status within it were severely shaken. Religion thus proved capable of providing personal conviction and moral guidance only for the individual rather than serving as a metaphysical structure of belief for society at large. Friedrich Nietzsche (<date when="1844">1844</date>&#x2013;<date when="1900">1900</date>) laid down the premise for existentialism with his declaration of "the death of God." Nietzsche believed that, liberated from the concept of an objective reality based upon rationality, humans could realize their potential through the heroic enterprise of self-invention&#x2014;the creation of an individual Truth. In Nietzsche's supremely Romantic vision of the unshackled self, art acquired the status formerly accorded religion, and the poet assumed the seat of the philosopher, whose function was now generally confined to the area of linguistics, logical positivism, and other noncosmological subjects.</p><p>Psychology began to preempt the role of philosophy in informing human thought and providing cultural context. Sigmund Freud (<date when="1856">1856</date>&#x2013;<date when="1939">1939</date>) analyzed the human psyche by interpreting the experiences of childhood and the symbolical messages divulged in dreams. He posited that the unconscious mind and powerful bio<pb n="503"/><pb n="503" type="orig"/>logical instincts are the operative forces beneath civilization's veneer of rationality and ethical religion, accounting for its darker, chthonic impulses. To Freud's psychology Carl Jung (<date when="1875">1875</date>&#x2013;<date when="1961">1961</date>) added his concept of the collective unconscious grounded in, and structured by, archetypal principles. Jung's theories provide insight into the universality of psychological experience and the persistence of myth as a cultural phenomenon and metaphorical instrument for shaping intellectual perception and making art.</p><p>The weakening of collective religious belief bolstered by Nietzsche's vision of the autonomous creative self and by psychology's focus on the interior lives of persons promoted individualism belief in the primacy of the individual and the rights of individuals within the larger framework of society. To some extent, statism belief in the supremacy of the state as the provider of a value system and social and economic structures capable of sustaining citizens both spiritually and physically&#x2014;attempted to fill the vacuum left by religion's diminishing role in people's lives. But, as Nietzsche intuited, the liberating notion of humanity's essential freedom and ability to rationally fashion a society of its own choosing has a dark side. People during an increasingly troubled and complex twentieth century came to understand this as divisiveness, enmity, racism, and revolt flourished along with our propensity for exploitation and cruelty. Unpersuaded by the rhetoric of evil demagogues or inept political leaders of the state's supremacy and viability as a substitute for God, many thinking people found themselves in a condition of existential despair. Yet if humankind is its own ultimate resource, then philosophy must necessarily focus upon the individual as an instrument of action as well as cognition.</p><p>Phenomenology and existentialism offered new philosophical perspectives in this regard. The German philosopher Edmund Husserl (<date when="1859">1859</date>&#x2013;<date when="1938">1938</date>) sought to overcome the dualism inherent in Enlightenment philosophy following Descartes's separation of the field of inquiry into an objective material universe and a subjective cognitive self. Husserl gave primacy to the experience of everyday life, <hi rend="italic">Lebenswelt,</hi> or "life-world" as the basis of reality Phenomenology, the investigation of the data of consciousness&#x2014;moods, values, desires&#x2014;and the things of the material world, including mathematics and the concept of space, constituted the philosophical basis for reforming spiritual life. Within this framework, psychology was more than a social science; it validated intuition and subjective awareness as means for understanding the world.</p><p>With the publication of <hi rend="italic">Being and Time</hi> (<date when="1927">1927</date>), <name type="pname">Martin Heidegger</name> (<date when="1889">1889</date>&#x2013;<date when="1976">1976</date>), Husserl's successor as professor of philosophy at the University of Freiburg, extended Husserl's phenomenological investigations and attempt to rescue humanity's understanding of itself from the confines of rational science. Implicit in the philosophical concept he called <hi rend="italic">Dasein</hi>&#x2014;meaning "attunement," or "being <hi rend="italic">there,</hi> inhabiting and dwelling in the world"&#x2014; is the cherishing of place as the intimate infrastructure of everyday experience. As the urban historian <name type="pname">Sam Bass Warner</name>, Jr., reminds us, Heidegger traced the verb to <hi rend="italic">dwell,</hi> which is fundamental to his concept of <hi rend="italic">Dasein</hi> to its original meaning: to build <hi rend="italic">and</hi> to cultivate land.<ref target="#CH16-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref></p><p>In his major work, <hi rend="italic">Ph&#x00E9;nom&#x00E9;nologie de la perception</hi> (Phenomenology of Perception, <date when="1945">1945</date>), the French philosopher Maurice Merleau-Ponty (<date when="1908">1908</date>&#x2013;<date when="1961">1961</date>) also countered the existential angst and the nihilism fostered by the spiritual crisis of modern life by focusing upon "sense experience." For Merleau-Ponty, "Sense experience is that vital communication with the world which makes it present as a familiar setting of our life."<ref target="#CH16-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref> The body anchors the individual in the world, connecting consciousness with the empirical and giving coherent structure to perception and behavior. In this light, we are not passive subjects registering by means of cognition the spectacle of the world but agents of its transformation, projecting significance upon both our personal and collective histories through real and symbolic actions, thereby giving life form.</p><p>In relation to our subject, landscape, Merleau-Ponty's discourse on the phenomenological aspect of space is instructive. He maintains that our need to feel stable, <hi rend="italic">in place,</hi> not vertiginously adrift but anchored <hi rend="italic">somewhere,</hi> proceeds from our bodily constitution, our innate sensation of up and down, which is our primary apprehension of space and of being in the world. The affirmation of this basic truth and Merleau-Ponty's poetic regard for personal experience puts him in league with another French philosopher, Gaston Bachelard (<date when="1884">1884</date>&#x2013;<date when="1962">1962</date>). Bachelard used the combined approach of psychology and phenomenology to articulate in <hi rend="italic">The Poetics of Space</hi> (<date when="1957">1957</date>) a concept of "topoanalysis" in which poetic reverie encourages the individual to spiritually reinhabit the intimate spaces of memory where he finds images "which are all light and shimmer," proving that "houses that were lost forever continue to live on in us."<ref target="#CH16-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref>According to Bachelard, through daydreams time is enfolded into psychic spatiality, as intimate places, particularly the places of childhood, abide in memory and dreams.</p><p>Bachelard's philosophical musing upon the poetics of place constitute an examination of "the quite simple images of <hi rend="italic">felicitous space."</hi><ref target="#CH16-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref>His topophilia, or fond remembrance of place, however, has its counterpart. Instead of examining space, as did <name type="pname">Bachelard</name>, in terms of imaginative poetics and phenomenology resonant with Jungian archetypes and individual psychology, <name type="pname">Michel Foucault</name> (<date when="1926">1926</date>&#x2013;<date when="1984">1984</date>) studied it as a historical, non-absolute, impermanent phenomenon, with widely differing interpretations from era to era and from culture to culture. Foucault posited a "heterotopology" of "countersites" that challenges Bachelard's order of intimate psychical place with an analysis of such politicized, historicized spaces as prisons, cemeteries, and parks.</p><p>In addition, in <hi rend="italic">Les Mots et les choses</hi> (<date when="1966">1966</date>: translated into English as <hi rend="italic">The Order of Things: An Archaeology of the Human Sciences,</hi> <date when="1970">1970</date>) Foucault provides an analysis of the function of representation, which, as landscape historian John Dixon Hunt extrapolates, can be usefully applied to a new and needed historiography of the garden. That account would suppress recitation of a narrative of styles in favor of an analysis (such as has been attempted in this book) of landscape as a combination of nature and art manifesting historically relevant cultural values.<ref target="#CH16-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref> With these intellectual premises in mind, we will conclude our history of landscape design with a meditation on how all of us act as place-making agents as our moving bodies claim space and as we create forms and inscribe patterns upon the landscapes of the world, which are forever part of nature whatever our particular cultural values may be.</p><div type="section"><pb n="504"/><pb n="504" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Body and Space: The Weaving of Place</hi></head><p>Within the span of an individual life, it is especially difficult to grasp the fundamental truth that everything, including the architecture of nature&#x2014;mountains, plains, rivers, seas&#x2014;is forever changing. Imposing order on nature and believing that the spaces we shape have permanence seem to be necessary imperatives for maintaining our bearings psychologically. Even when space is outside of our personal influence in terms of structure, we appropriate it by the movements of our bodies.</p><p>Following Bachelard, we may think of our dwellings as nests of personal space and our craniums as the repositories in which are stored many remembered places, even, or especially, places erased by time. But we should not think of place as stationary. From the window of the moving automobile or, more sensationally, from the windswept, unprotected motorcyclist's perspective, place is fluid, the streaming scenery of the highway.<ref target="#CH16-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref>What is important to understand is that whether we are in fast or slow motion, we are claiming space with the sensations experienced by our moving bodies while internalizing meanings of place through the impressions stored in our minds. Space can be thus likened to a loom, and our shuttling motion as we traverse familiar habitats or explore unknown ones makes us weavers of place as we create a fabric of the mind with which to cloak our naked psyches and attach ourselves to the world.</p><p>We may observe that our feet trace and retrace habitual steps. In this way we weave and reweave the fabric of physical and psychological space, making ourselves at home in the world. Our weaving capability is such that, like birds, some of us can live transient lives and over their course borrow or build many nests that we call home. Thus adaptable, we are like other biological creatures, also weavers of space, place-making animals. To visualize this activity metaphorically we may think of strings with knots, or better, because it is a more maplike and therefore a more placelike image, intersecting lines in a field with dots. The strings or lines represent the routes we traverse and the knots or dots the stationary points where we settle for awhile.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Claiming Space</hi></head><p>The theoretical reweaving of unraveled place constitutes the work of archaeological anthropologists who attempt to understand the role of movement&#x2014;ritual processions, ceremonial dancing, pilgrimage to nature shrines, and so forth&#x2014;in the place-making activities and hence the landscape designs of Paleolithic and Neolithic peoples. The Walbiri people in <name type="place">Australia</name>, a society of contemporary hunter-gatherers, demonstrate how habitual passage over traditional lines of movement invests landscape with significance and mythic content. The Walbiri have imposed on their territory a sacred web of tracks called songlines linking stations that are associated with totemic beings, or dreamings. These dreaming sites are elements in a mnemonic system employed by the nomadic Walbiri, who must memorize the features of an arid locale where the scarcity of rainfall makes knowledge of potential water holes essential.<ref target="#CH16-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref></p><p>Walbiri dreaming sites, the locus of religious ceremonies, serve as landmarks within an otherwise indistinguishable desert landscape.<ref target="#CH16-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref>The totems of the Walbiri consist of various animals, astronomical features, the elements&#x2014;wind, rain, and fire&#x2014;and even some important human artifacts such as spears or digging sticks. Cultural heroes wandered along the established songlines in the mythic period known as dreamtime, which is conceived as both a long-ago and continuing category of existence.<ref target="#CH16-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref> In dreamtime, these creative figures assumed human form, shaped topography, gave the landscape its features, and deposited their totemic essences in the places where they halted in their journeys before transforming themselves into animal or plant form and returning into the earth at a spot, usually of some topographical distinction, that served as their memorial and principal shrine. Dreamtime continues as an alternative to historical time, and the impregnation of the ordinary world with its spiritual essences and the corresponding impregnation of human fetuses with the dreamings of their place of conception shape the identity of individual members of the society and affect their mutual relationships. By performing rituals at the dreaming sites, Walbiri men may enter dreamtime for a brief period, becoming the heroes they impersonate. The care of the dreaming sites and custodial responsibility for the rituals and songs belonging to them are assigned to individual lodges associated with each location. At Ngama Cave, located near Yuendumu in a valley with abundant game and where three songlines converge, one lodge continues to maintain the totemic wall paintings depicting snake, dingo, and wallaby.</p><p>As we saw in Chapter Two, the ancient Greeks wove their colonial cities <hi rend="italic">per stringas,</hi> as bands of north-south and east-west streets forming a Hippodamian grid, and then wove a looser net of territorial claims by extending pilgrimage routes to the shrines located near the limits of the <hi rend="italic">chora.</hi> By moving along processional routes into the countryside to the temple shrines as well as by walking the streets of the <hi rend="italic">polis,</hi> people activated this fabric of space and inter<pb n="505"/><pb n="505" type="orig"/>nalized it as place.<ref target="#CH16-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref> So, too, do we fashion from the patterns of our movement our notions of place. Thus place, which is coterminous with our own selves, is the claim our moving bodies make upon regional space, which, in accommodating our comings and goings, gains familiarity and accrues meaning. As philosophy historian Edward Casey reminds us, <hi rend="italic">"Bodies build places</hi> ... through inhabiting and even by traveling between already built places."<ref target="#CH16-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref>Seen in this way, place is something that is sequenced like the Walbiri songlines by movement along routes that are punctuated with landmarks in which we have invested significance, if only the significance of customary sight. In the highly commercial capitalist societies of the West, the rituals of shopping and eating out are important components in our contemporary concept of <hi rend="italic">chora,</hi> the regional receptacle of place.</p><p>Place is therefore kinetic, a pattern of habitual movements through remembered space. Where our intuitive directional system based upon familiarity and repetition of experience breaks down, as when large numbers of strangers are in transit, passing through airports or train and bus stations, we substitute for our mental maps of place well-developed graphic systems containing conventional international symbols. As highways, automobiles, and trucks have put more and more people on the move and made mass marketing and distribution systems commonplace, society's impulse has been to delocalize place by creating ubiquitous and predictable cultural geographies. Retail and hotel chains and other instantly recognizable commercial franchise operations such as service stations and fast-food restaurants thus become the denominators of the placeless place where anyone can presumably feel at home.</p><p>As we saw in Chapter One, Puebloan people in the Southwest have woven place by establishing a flow of energy that also guides the people's footsteps between the pueblo and the inconspicuously stonemarked mountain shrines that establish the cosmological paradigm within the landscape. Like the <hi rend="italic">agora</hi> of the Greek <hi rend="italic">polis,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">bupingeh,</hi> or central plaza, constitutes the civic and social heart of the pueblo, and the <hi rend="italic">nansipu,</hi> the small stone-encircled depression within the <hi rend="italic">bupingeh,</hi> marks the cosmological axis mundi and the centerpoint of the spatial tapestry that extends from the pueblo in four directions to the encircling mountains that rim the horizon. But although the pueblo sacralizes space, it is not itself considered to be a sacred, immutable form, being simply the temporary center of a people who may move to another location someday, allowing their adobe walls to melt back into the earth. The fixity of the pueblos as we know them today is a product of an Euro-American cultural construct that perceived nature in nonreligious terms as a commodity. The newcomers granted land by law as property or territory with established boundary lines. By contrast, the migration of Pre-Columbian Native Americans is found in the archaeological record, particularly in the ruins of long-abandoned pueblos dotted across the Southwest.</p><p>Ironically, at the same time that post-Columbian Americans began to restrict the movements of Native Americans, they set themselves in motion, weaving a new American <hi rend="italic">chora</hi> of continental dimensions as they moved west to colonize the land. The warp and woof of Jefferson's national grid became a loom of spatial weaving such as the world had never seen before. Within the mile-square, 640-acre sections described by its orthogonal lines, fields and the smaller-scale grids of cities were established. But the actual roads that followed the engineers' surveys that mapped the national grid were not created until much later. Depressions in the prairie grass where the Great Plains end near Fort Union in eastern <name type="place">New Mexico</name> mark the ruts of the wagon wheels that formed the Santa Fe Trail. Frederick Law Olmsted, traveling in the antebellum South, found himself continually slowed down by the miry, rutted roads. With tolls but no federal taxes to support their establishment or upkeep, the roads of <name type="place">America</name> were all local for more than a century and a half of the republic's existence, making each region insular and all long-distance highway travel an arduous adventure.</p><p>In Chapter Twelve we examined how this situation changed as the automobile became a popular and increasingly dominant mode of transportation. The limited-access "townless highway" conceived by Benton MacKaye and the first motor parkways on Long Island and in Westchester County, <name type="place">New York</name>, were thought of as regional arteries and their purpose as primarily recreational, bringing newly mobilized city-dwellers nearer to nature. But following World War II, a powerful congressional lobby supporting motor transportation interests fostered the creation of interstate highways, and the United States became laced with expressways&#x2014;multilane arteries for trucks as well as cars. This national network supplanted the earlier regional one featuring parkways. The journey was no longer its own reward; speed and absence of traffic congestion replaced motorized recreation as the engineer's primary goals. As parkway construction waned, landscape architects were rarely employed on roadway design projects, as was the case in the early twentieth century when the <name type="pname">Bronx River</name>, <name type="pname">Taconic</name>, <name type="pname">Merritt</name>, and other parkways in the <name type="place">New York</name> metropolitan region were built.</p><p>In the global, technology-oriented culture of the twentieth-first century, images of local and historical<pb n="506"/><pb n="506" type="orig"/>place have become universalized through endless replications, and we have become infinitely more mobilized than participants in prior civilizations. Time and space are experienced differently, and the world has become a geography of flows: of people, of goods, and of information (fig. 16.1). The result is a multicultural landscape pastiche, a transcultural scenery of borrowed design motifs and symbols. We may lament the frenetic pace of contemporary life and long to get back to nature, but the journey cannot be accomplished without connection to the technology of transportation flows.</p><figure xml:id="fig-613"><graphic url="CH16_002.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">16.1. A "geography of flows." Freeway, Seattle</hi></figDesc></figure><p><name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name> understood this. In his <date when="1966">1966</date> essay on freeways he wrote:<q>Freeways out in the countryside, with their graceful, sinuous, curvilinear patterns, are like great free-flowing paintings in which, through participation, the sensations of motion through space are experienced. In cities the great overhead concrete structures with their haunches tied to the ground and the vast flowing cantilevers rippling above the local streets stand like enormous sculptures marching through the architectonic caverns. These vast and beautiful works of engineering speak to us in the language of a new scale, a new attitude in which high-speed motion and the qualities of change are not mere abstract conceptions but a vital part of our everyday experiences.<ref target="#CH16-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref></q></p><p>Followers of Jane Jacobs would caution against romanticizing the beauty of engineering and panoramic skyline vistas from freeways. These exhilarating Faustian experiences of human power are all too often at the expense of existing neighborhoods, irremediably disrupting people's lives and social bonds. But that does not mean that all highway construction is inimical, especially were politicians and planners to heed the finest lesson offered by the Disney Company's theme-park planners: a system of multiple, integrated transportation technologies aimed at creating neighborhood-sized, car-free environments. This goal would force careful consideration of exterior access and parking needs along with the interior infrastructure necessary to facilitate pedestrian and light-rail transit flows.</p><p>An ethos of intelligent stewardship of Earth's biological and human environments and good frameworks for political decision-making are fundamental if we are to successfully address with scientific, technical, and artistic means the global challenges that confront us. In Europe especially, regional planners have begun to think of conservation in terms of the transportation costs associated with the environmental footprints of cities&#x2014;that is, the amount of far-flung hinterland necessary to sustain them with food, water, and energy&#x2014;and to mass buildings and preserve green space with stronger regard for the natural channels of air and water flowing through them.</p><p>The flows of images and information via satellite technology and the Internet provide new means of advancing global stewardship and promoting integrated international environmental management systems. To succeed fully, this stewardship must encompass a psychological and phenomenological attachment to place. We must therefore learn to value<pb n="507"/><pb n="507" type="orig"/>the qualities that constitute place and understand what it means to be a body that moves through space, a corporeal self at rest and in motion, a being that is capable of place making within the context of home, nature, and community.</p><p>Because mind and body cannot be divorced and because it is the mind that insists on organizing &#x2014; imposing order on&#x2014;space, place is, in fact, wherever we are physically. By being emplaced in space we ineluctably claim space as place. When the astronaut Neil Armstrong set his foot on the moon in <date when="1969">1969</date>, claiming a giant stride for humankind, the moon became a place as well as a heavenly body.</p><p>Movement is pleasure and often spiritual reward. Curious by nature, we are explorers, claiming place by venturing forth to look and learn, even if we have no intention of settling. Scaling the mountain summit or diving below the ocean's surface imprints us with experience of place. Standing on the mesa or the open plain and watching the sun plunge beneath the horizon or, away from city lights, gazing into the dark immensity of the night sky at the Milky Way and the myriad stars produces in us the same sensation of cosmological awe that prehistoric peoples converted into religious myth and calendrical calculation.</p><p>It is important to distinguish between mindbody space and abstract, intellectualized space. Alone among sentient creatures, human beings are capable of conceptualizing space in both real and abstract terms, as lived experience on the one hand and as cartography, mathematical model, or cosmological diagram on the other. We have imposed a system of spatial coordinates&#x2014;longitude and latitude&#x2014;upon our planet as a universally agreed-upon aid to navigation. Satellites programmed to pinpoint position now beam information that can be captured by computers, giving drivers of automobiles or hikers in the wilderness accurate information about their current location and directions to their destinations. Surveyors have made possible the mapping of virtually the entire surface of the globe with great precision and at a fine scale. To this base of topographical information, geographers and natural scientists, as well as demographers, economists, and political scientists, have added much useful information regarding climate, geology, vegetation, wildlife habitat, the boundaries of cities, states, and nations, and human road systems and settlement patterns. Map reading enables us to picture accurately places we have never seen, and cinematic and still photography at both aerial and ground level increases our ability to visualize remote places. Nevertheless, the <hi rend="italic">experience</hi> of space as place remains personal.</p><figure xml:id="fig-614"><graphic url="CH16_003.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">16.2. Hikers on Crater Lake Trail, Crater Lake National Park, <name type="place">Oregon</name></hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Camping</hi></head><p>To go camping is to internalize spatial experience most vividly and to comprehend human place making in its most elemental form. Through availing themselves of all manner of technical aids, such as warm clothing made of industrially manufactured synthetic fibers, good topographical maps, or perhaps a handheld computer with satellite-beamed compass orientation, exact location, and directional information, the backcountry camper claims wilderness (first<pb n="508"/><pb n="508" type="orig"/>nature) as an experience of place by following trails. Blazed by the original explorers of wilderness, trails are tracks made by the feet of horses, cattle, and humans who have gone ahead (fig. 16.2). Each hiker who threads a way along these paths or bushwhacks with stream courses and sun position for guidance weaves out of spatial distance a personal experience of place. This takes the form of a composite of sensory impressions: the resinous pungency of pine, the low rumble from the thundercloud over the mountain; the darkness and cool of the forest with its carpet of leaf litter, moss, ferns, and mushrooms; the picnic on a sun-warmed rock in the meadow of breeze-blown grasses and nodding wildflowers. If we are journalists, we may make of these experiences a string of words, for narrative is an important adjunct to place making, and even an illiterate camper will have his or her story of the Way.</p><p>Yet no story of a journey is without its caesuras, and no trek is without its pauses, breaks for rest and sleep. The camper, like the wayfarer seeking an inn for the night, must tie a knot in the string of space he or she is weaving, by selecting a temporary nest or den, the spot where a tent makes a home, the place where, cocooned in a sleeping bag and covered by a fragile shell of fabric, one sets forth on a voyage of nocturnal dreams. Or, dispensing with the insubstantial house that the tent represents, the camper joins those prehistoric ancestors who governed their lives through myth and celestial observation, studying the rotational movements of the bright lights overhead, still amazed, if not as wondering as they, about the cosmological meaning of those lights' majestic march across the heavens through the hours of darkness.</p><p>This exhilarating venture into nature, our first home, sharpens our senses, but we must not imagine that, even as campers relearning ancient skills, we can recover in wilderness the perspective of prehistoric humankind. We may only imagine it from our own cultural vantage point. The vapor trail of the jet overhead and the distant roar of its engine as it courses along its prescribed skyway join the flight and cry of the jay, reminding us that we live in a world that is increasingly of our own making. Yet even our technologically derived environments are part of nature and must submit to nature's laws: this is the lesson of camping in those reserves of "first nature" that remain on a crowded planet.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Bodily Place</hi></head><p>Finally, we are place. The axis mundi of cosmology is imbedded in our unconscious because we walk upright. Because we walk upright we traverse space, making place through movement. If we are women, we have wombs, the primordial image of place as medium and matrix. In us abides the cave, prenatal paradise, and protected sanctuary. If we are men, we produce semen, the procreative male seed that fertilizes the female egg residing in the uterus. As men we stand for the potency represented by storm clouds and mountain peaks; as women we symbolize the earth's fertile valleys and hidden recesses, holding, containing, embracing life within our wombs and in our arms. Together women and men shape space and make place by virtue of our movements and our decisions.</p><p>To deconstruct space is to immediately reorganize it intellectually, for the ordering principle of our brain is much stronger than our will to acquiesce to formless, spatial chaos. To feel at sea, uncentered, adrift in undifferentiated, essentially placeless space, is to experience an unbearable sense of disorder and confusion, like the oppressive weight of darkness and silence in a sealed tomb or airless dungeon. Even in these dire circumstances, however, as long as we are aware of our spatial anxiety, experiencing our palpitating heart and dry-mouthed, wet-palmed fear, we are in place, being, so to speak, in body.</p><p>Settlements, especially cities, accrue meaning over time, although this meaning is always changing. Within cities, the more numerous and significant sacred spaces are, the greater the city. Because cities are fabrics of space dense with buildings, sometimes their most sacred spaces are their unbuilt places: the agora, the monumental plaza or square, the public park. These are the amply filled-in blanks within the metropolitan spatial continuum. In fact, parks and parklike open spaces are sometimes the most powerful definers of place, important markers in the mental geography of every resident beyond the age of early childhood when the concept of space is still limited, not yet expanded beyond mother, home, yard, and immediate neighborhood. One senses with special force, and sometimes poignance, the vitality and persistence of the human urge to interact with nature and to create satisfying places in the community garden, a provisional landscape occupying temporarily vacant urban land. The community garden contradicts facile assumptions regarding urban dwellers' indifference to nature and predictions about the death of public space. Within these and other superficially insignificant, often marginal spaces can be found expressions of ethnic identity, spiritual fulfillment, and economic improvement.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Community Gardens</hi></head><p>With the alteration of the social landscape of <name type="place">America</name> following World War II, the inner urban ring became less dense and more racially mixed as both migrants and immigrants took up residence. The drop in real estate values that made rents in these<pb n="509"/><pb n="509" type="orig"/>areas affordable for newcomers also gave landlords less incentive to maintain their properties. With the advent of the civil rights movement in the <date when="1960">1960</date>s and the riots sparked by police confrontation with those demanding racial equality, some of these neighborhoods experienced wanton destruction. In the wake of the rioting, many landlords simply deserted their destroyed properties and already deteriorated buildings. With no utility or maintenance services, these sites were also abandoned by their tenants. Eventually many buildings were torn down and their sites left as rubble-strewn open space. With no remittance of the taxes due on them, municipal real estate departments were forced to claim these properties.</p><p>But still there were people who called the neighborhoods surrounding these lots home, and as <name type="pname">Sam Bass Warner</name>, Jr., points out, "today's American urban community garden is the child of new politics and abandoned city land."<ref target="#CH16-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref>Some of these gardens have become showcases of ornamental horticulture as well as green retreats, recreational centers in which to relax and socialize (fig. 16.3).</p><p>In spite of the community gardens' popularity, many public officials believe that they are not the best use of random parcels of city-owned land when measured against the need for housing and their desire to generate revenues from taxes and land sales to developers. Those who turn open spaces into green places through the investment of their creativity, time, and labor&#x2014;gaining for themselves a sense of place in the process&#x2014;are confronted by those with superior power over land because of ownership and the ability to regulate its use. This power stems from a value system in which land is considered a commodity and place as something fungible. In <name type="pname">Boston</name>, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, <name type="place">Chicago</name>, and Seattle, however, a new ethic that attempts to balance green space with the need for housing and municipal revenues is emerging, and governmentally sponsored redevelopment programs in these American cities are being undertaken within the context of neighborhood-based city planning.</p><p>Whether gardens are urban or suburban, of our own making or ones we create with the help of professional designers, they are personal paradises where we find soul space, our places for dreaming, family life, play, and entertaining friends. But these are not the only cherished landscapes. For some, Central Park or the city of <name type="place">Paris</name> are homes for the heart even more valued than their own abodes, place being as much as anything a state of mind. As our bodies and minds claim space and live place, everywhere can be utopia, which literally means <hi rend="italic">nowhere,</hi> but which we are able by our acts of imagination and will to convert into our own visionary <hi rend="italic">somewhere.</hi> We ourselves <hi rend="italic">are</hi> place, but we are also forever <hi rend="italic">in</hi> place, whether moving or at rest. To feel connected and centered in the world is to know how to find our way, to navigate ourselves spatially and locate ourselves in the small temporary centers we call home. Because we live in communities, not in isolation, our decisions and those of others affect the nature of place both individually and collectively with regard to the societal arrangements we create to structure the allocation and use of space and the examples and standards we set forth with regard to landscape design.</p><figure xml:id="fig-615"><graphic url="CH16_004.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">16.3. Clinton Community Garden, <name type="place">New York</name> City</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Our journey through landscape design history has enabled us to see that populism is ascendant in our time and that, although often vulnerable to superior economic forces, landscapes like community gardens are important expressions of culture and individual aspiration. When we look at the entire built landscape we see that it is a fabric woven by countless individuals. The term <hi rend="italic">vernacular</hi> is often applied to landscapes that manifest place-making by ordinary people. To make generalized observations about this type of human landscape, it is necessary to adopt the analytic approach of the cultural geographer.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb n="510"/><pb n="510" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps">II. Cultural Geography: The Loom of Landscape</hi></head><p>Histories have been written since ancient Greek times, and landscape inevitably figures in the narratives of battle scenes and descriptions of locales of human settlement. But like the landscapes found in Renaissance paintings, landscape description in historical writing most often functions as a backdrop for the tableau in the foreground where human action takes place. Novelists more than historians have proved capable of writing vivid prose descriptions integrating local landscape and human affairs. But even in novels, landscape as protagonist, the central subject of analysis and revelation, is absent. This is the province of the geographer turned cultural anthropologist.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Landscape as a Textbook of Human History and Daily Life</hi></head><p><hi rend="italic">Cultural geography,</hi> the term describing the study of landscape in its broad dimensions as both nature and human artifact, is a recent subject of disciplined inquiry. More philosophical and intuitive than scientific and more eclectic in its approach than traditional geography, it is part of a trend we can trace to the nineteenth century when history, natural history, and art history emerged as fields of professional endeavor. At that time, when the pursuit of knowledge became increasingly specialized, geography evolved from its cartographic origins to become a combination of earth science and social science, with an emphasis upon the economic potential of natural resources. Not until the <date when="1920">1920</date>s, however, did a group of French geographers attempt to project an intimate portrait of the settled regional countryside. As planned by Paul Vidal de la Blache and edited by Pierre Deffontaines, the <hi rend="italic">G&#x00E9;ographie universelle</hi> appeared between <date when="1927">1927</date> and <date when="1948">1948</date> as a series of monographs. As editor of the periodical <hi rend="italic">Revue de g&#x00E9;ographie humaine et d'ethnologie,</hi> Deffontaines continued to relate landscape appearance to culture and the history of human occupation of the land.</p><p><name type="pname">William G. Hoskins</name> (<date when="1908">1908</date>&#x2013;<date when="1992">1992</date>), another pioneer in the field of cultural geography, published <hi rend="italic">The Making of the English Landscape</hi> (<date when="1955">1955</date>), a portrait of his country from the perspective of the historical evolution of its landscape. By roaming the countryside on foot and bicycle and studying its surface features, vegetation patterns, transportation lines, and buildings, Hoskins made his readers aware that landscape could be read as a fascinating document, a morphological record of other times and other lives. Hoskins cherished the vestigial evidence of continuous human occupation over the centuries and the patina of ancient heritage he found in long-settled landscapes, and he was vociferously alarmed by the twentieth century's highly mechanized, capitalist culture that disrupted these historic landscape patterns. Although his work was slow to win a popular audience, by the <date when="1970">1970</date>s his academic post, a television series featuring Hoskins and the English countryside, and paperback republication of his remarkable book sparked considerable interest in landscape analysis from the perspective of cultural history in Great Britain and elsewhere.</p><p><name type="pname">John Brinckerhoff Jackson</name> (<date when="1910">1910</date>&#x2013;<date when="1996">1996</date>) took a related but very different stance from Hoskins.<ref target="#CH16-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref><name type="pname">Jackson</name>'s attention to landscape at a local scale, combined with an artist's eye for visual form and an appreciation of architecture, nurtured his interest in "reading" the landscape. He saw how he could apply the experience he had gained as an intelligence officer in wartime Europe to analyze the landscape of his adopted region, the American Southwest, and how the process of deciphering its cultural meanings could lead to a broader perspective on the relationship between humankind and nature. <hi rend="italic">Landscape,</hi> the magazine that he began publishing three times a year in <date when="1951">1951</date>, was his principal forum for the next seventeen years.</p><p><name type="pname">Like Patrick Geddes</name>, <name type="pname">Jackson</name> was fascinated with aerial perspective as a means of interpreting human settlements, but he did not share Geddes's motives as a city planner. He wanted his readers simply to recognize and appreciate the social, economic, and cultural forces that had shaped "the compact Indian communities, perched on rocks overlooking the fields, the sprawling tree-grown checkerboard of the Anglo-American towns, the Spanish villages strung along a road or a stream; the huddle of filling stations and tourist courts at highway intersections in the desert."<ref target="#CH16-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref> In addition, there was the individual house, which <name type="pname">Jackson</name> viewed as a manifestation of culture as well as an expression of certain spiritual and biological needs.</p><p>The road, emblem of restless movement and the means of continental migration, resides within the American imagination as an important image. Jackson, who traversed the country many times by motorcycle, made the road an important, recurring subject in his work. Unlike the critics of urban and rural visual blight, he never deplored the effect of the automobile on the landscape (fig. 16.4). He saw speed as an exhilarating sensory stimulus, and he would not deny the abstract beauty of "the new landscape, seen at a rapid, sometimes even a terrifying pace."<ref target="#CH16-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> The American highway was for him a collective work of industrial-age folk art, and he applied to the honkytonk roadside strip of motels, gas stations, used-car lots, and fast-food franchises the same dispassionate<pb n="511"/><pb n="511" type="orig"/>perspective that allowed him to view side yards filled with rusting automobiles and other eyesores as evidence of people's means of gaining a livelihood. His article on "The Stranger's Path" describes the tawdry vitality of the route from the bus or train depot on the urban fringe to skid row, the business district, and civic center. He was interested in the ability of people at the bottom rung of society to find accommodation and even a sense of place within the landscape. Thus, landscape was for Jackson never something merely to look at, but to live in. From this attitude stemmed his aversion to modernism in architecture and city planning, even when architects and planners attempted to implement a thoroughly democratic agenda. He doubted that even intelligent suburban landscape design such as Garrett Eckbo's, whose book <hi rend="italic">Landscape for Living</hi> Jackson criticized as too abstract, could serve as effectively as grassroots place-making.</p><figure xml:id="fig-616"><graphic url="CH16_005.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">16.4. Highway commerce, <name type="place">Wichita</name>, <name type="place">Kansas</name></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Besides validating landscape studies as a field that included mobile homes and trailer courts, <name type="pname">Jackson</name> argued against the dichotomous attitude that sees nature and urbanity as polar opposites. In his unified vision, nature was all-pervasive, and he took pains to point out that the same forces of climate, topography, and vegetative growth that appear in the unbuilt countryside operate equally within the built city. Unlike Hoskins, who wished to arrest landscape change and ugly Machine Age incursions that bespoke contemporary people's increasing alienation from nature, Jackson stressed the inevitability of landscape's ever-changing character.</p><p><name type="pname">Jackson</name> honed his iconoclastic perspective as a means of jolting conventional attitudes, especially the Romantic attitude toward nature promulgated by Jean-Jacques Rousseau and later Henry David Thoreau, but he never developed an analytical methodology, nor did he work in any programmatic way to bring about environmental improvement. His principal legacy lies in stimulating a more humanistic approach to looking at landscape.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Conclusion</hi></head><p>As we have seen throughout this book, people have sought at certain times and places a correspondence between abstract, philosophical notions of space and designed manifestations of place. The builders of the cities of Ur, Knossos, and Teotihuac&#x00E1;n centered their constructions in landscape space according to a cosmological diagram. At Vaux-le-Vicomte and Versailles there is a firm relationship between Cartesian cosmology and experiential space. The desire for a correspondence between philosophical and scientific concepts of space and landscape can be seen in our own day, as is evident from some of the Earthworks discussed in the previous chapter.</p><p>But the grounding of spatial abstractions in the landscape is only part of the story of place making. The force of history as inspiration for designing space has only increased during the last two hundred years. The cachet of history and historic places has never been more evident than now as civilization embarks upon its third millennium of the Common Era. The several styles prefaced with "neo&#x2014;" attest to this. Beyond mere stylistic reiteration, history as a salvaging of the past and sometimes a literal replication and re-creation of place has garnered the momentum and resources of an international preservation movement. With the perceived endangerment of place, archaeological sites and landmarks are being protected from alteration. The consumption of history by tourists has become a powerful motive for the current reweaving of place. Old town centers, such as<pb n="512"/><pb n="512" type="orig"/>war-devastated Dresden, are being rebuilt, historic villages are being saved as exquisite corpses, their old functional lives now <hi rend="italic">replaced</hi> by their new role as tourist destinations. Tourist accommodation necessarily alters the thus-valorized space. By way of example, the route leading to the sacred cave of Zeus on Mount Ida (see Chapter One) has been recently surfaced with asphalt paving to facilitate the arrival and parking of buses.</p><figure xml:id="fig-617"><graphic url="CH16_006.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">16.5. Mobile home with garden, Pecos, <name type="place">New Mexico</name>. Contemporary vernacular landscapes created from commercially available products sometimes bespeak their debt to aristocratic tradition, as is evident from the symmetrical planning of this <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> with its Renaissance-style fountain.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>To value the vernacular landscape is to attest to the fundamental implausibility of master planning; no one can predict more than the basic functional needs of others, and human needs are neither universal nor static. While some regulation of land use is in the common interests of all who live together in a society, everyday environments are continually being improvised and reinvented within this spatial framework as the social circumstances of lives change, new economic opportunities arise out of new technologies, and new desires are born (fig. 16.5). And yet, in all the transactions that go on between human beings and nature, there is the impulse to arrest the fluidity of place, to save what is still held dear, and to renew the old as a representation of the desirable values that are believed to reside in certain bygone periods of history, even when the meaning of that period to contemporary people is undergoing change along with everything else.</p><p>Because of its use of industrial technology&#x2014;exemplified by machine guns, fire bombs, gas chambers, rail transport to death camps, and other heinous applications&#x2014;in the brutally efficient <hi rend="italic">displacement</hi> of populations and eradication of spatial structure, the twentieth century witnessed more forced evacuation of place and destruction of spatial meaning than any other. In that century it became apparent that industrial technology is a power that can efficiently destroy the natural environment for short-term economic gain, impoverishing irreplaceable ecosystems, including the human ecosystem, and in some places destroying entire species with ferocious rapidity. But technology is not innately inimical, and it is also being used to improve the conditions and duration of human life, while environmental science is working to restore degraded ecosystems. In this light, place is the planet Earth, a collective human responsibility.</p><p>In our survey of cities, parks, and gardens we have examined landscapes as shaped space and defined place. In bringing our journey to an end, it is important to realize that the making and erasure of place are continuous processes, as is the philosophical conceptualization of space. These transactional activities between human beings and landscape will continue as long as there are minds to inquire about the cosmological meaning of space and to confer collective and personal meaning on place, and as long as there are hands, assisted by machines, to shape space in partnership with nature.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb n="513"/><pb n="513" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Sixteen</hi></head><note xml:id="CH16-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Sam Bass Warner</name>, Jr., <hi rend="italic">To Dwell Is to Garden</hi> (<name type="place">Boston</name>: Northeastern University Press, <date when="1987">1987</date>), p. xii.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Maurice Merleau-Ponty</name>, <hi rend="italic">Phenomenology of Perception, trans.</hi> Colin Smith (<name type="place">New York</name>: Humanities Press, <date when="1962">1962</date>), pp. 52&#x2013;53.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Gaston Bachelard</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Poetics of Space,</hi> trans. <name type="pname">Maria Jolas</name> (<name type="place">Boston</name>: Beacon Press, <date when="1969">1969</date>), p. 33.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Gaston Bachelard</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Poetics of Space,</hi> p. xxxi.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p>Foucault's position is that "the coherence that existed, throughout the Classical age," which he assumes to be the seventeenth century, the period of the dawn of modern science, "between the theory of representation and the theories of language, or the natural orders, and of wealth and value" was shattered beginning in the nineteenth century. With this change, "the theory of representation disappears as the universal foundation of all possible orders; language as the spontaneous <hi rend="italic">tabula,</hi> the primary grid of things, as an indispensable link between representation and things, is eclipsed in its turn; a profound historicity penetrates into the heart of things, isolates and defines them in their own coherence, imposes upon them the forms of order implied by the continuity of time; the analysis of exchange and money gives way to the study of production, that of the organism takes precedence over the search for taxonomic characteristics, and, above all, language loses its privileged position and becomes, in its turn, a historical form coherent with the density of its own past." See Michel Foucault, <hi rend="italic">The Order of Things</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Vintage Books, <date when="1994">1994</date>), p. xxiii.</p><p>For John Dixon Hunt's discussion of Foucault's exegesis on representation, see <hi rend="italic">Greater Perfections</hi> (<name type="place">Philadelphia</name>: University of Pennsylvania Press, <date when="1999">1999</date>), pp. 78&#x2013;80. Hunt's call for a revitalized historiography of landscape design and practice of landscape architecture can be found in <hi rend="italic">Greater Perfections,</hi> chap. 8.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p>As <name type="pname">D. W. Meinig</name> points out, "the key landscape symbol in late twentieth century <name type="place">America</name> is not the home but the highway, and community is not so much a discrete locality as a dispersed social network traced on the landscape by the moving automobile." See <name type="pname">D. W. Meinig</name>, "Symbolic Landscapes: Some Idealizations of American Communities," <hi rend="italic">The Interpretation of Ordinary Landscapes,</hi> ed. <name type="pname">D. W. Meinig</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Oxford</name> University Press, <date when="1979">1979</date>), p. 182.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">John E. Pfeiffer</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Creative Explosion: An Inquiry into the Origins of Art and Religion</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Harper &amp; Row, Publishers, <date when="1982">1982</date>), pp. 153&#x2013;73.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">M. J. Meggitt</name>, <hi rend="italic">Desert People: A Study of the Walbiri Aborigines of Central <name type="place">Australia</name></hi> (<name type="place">Chicago</name>: The University of <name type="place">Chicago</name> Press, <date when="1962">1962</date>), pp. 58&#x2013;71.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p>According to David Abram, "Dreamtime&#x2014;the <hi rend="italic">Jukurrpa,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Alcheringa</hi>&#x2014;that plays such a prominent part in the mythology of Aboriginal <name type="place">Australia</name> ... is a kind of time out of time, a time hidden beyond or even <hi rend="italic">within</hi> the evident, manifest presence of the land, a magical temporality wherein the powers of the surrounding world first took up their current orientation with regard to one another, and hence acquired the evident shapes and forms by which we now know them. It is that time before the world itself was entirely awake (a time that still exists just below the surface of wakeful awareness)&#x2014;that dawn when the totem Ancestors first emerged from their slumber beneath the ground and began to sing their way across the land in search of food, shelter, and companionship." See <hi rend="italic">The Spell of the Sensuous,</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Pantheon Books, <date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 164. See also Bruce Chatwin, <hi rend="italic">The Songlines</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Penguin Books USA, <date when="1987">1987</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p>I am indebted to <name type="pname">Indra Kagis McEwen</name>, author of <hi rend="italic">Socrates' Ancestor: An Essay on Architectural Beginnings</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: MIT Press, <date when="1993">1993</date>) for the description of "Weaving the Polis." See op. cit., pp. 80&#x2013;93.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Edward Casey</name>, <hi rend="italic">Getting Back into Place: Toward a Renewed Understanding of the Place-World</hi> (<name type="place">Bloomington</name>: Indiana University Press, <date when="1993">1993</date>), p. 116. See also Casey's etymological deconstruction of the word <hi rend="italic">dwell,</hi> which in modern usage means to reside or fasten close attention upon. Its Old Norse cognate <hi rend="italic">dvlja</hi> denotes "to linger," "to tarry," or "to delay," while its Old English cognate <hi rend="italic">dwalde</hi> signifies "to go astray," "to wander," or "to err." See op. cit., p. 114.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name>, <hi rend="italic">Freeways</hi>, <name type="place">NewYork</name>: Reinhold Publishing Corporation, <date when="1966">1966</date>), p. 15.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Sam Bass Warner</name>, Jr., <hi rend="italic">To Dwell Is to Garden,</hi> p. 20.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p>For a good comparative discussion of the work of <name type="pname">Hoskins</name> and <name type="pname">Jackson</name>, see <name type="pname">D. W. Meinig</name>, "Reading the Landscape: An Appreciation of <name type="pname">W. G. Hoskins</name> and <name type="pname">J. B. Jackson</name>," <hi rend="italic">The Interpretation of Ordinary Landscapes: Geographical Essays,</hi> ed. <name type="pname">D. W. Meinig</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Oxford</name> University Press, <date when="1979">1979</date>), pp. 195&#x2013;244.</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">J. B. Jackson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Landscape 1,</hi> no. 1 (spring <date when="1951">1951</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH16-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">J. B. Jackson</name>, "The Abstract World of the Hot-Rodder," <hi rend="italic">Landscape</hi> 7 (winter <date when="1957">1957</date>&#x2013;<date when="1958">1958</date>): 22.</p></note></div></div></body><back>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>