<div type="chapter">
<pb n="97"/>
<pb n="97" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER THREE VISIONS OF PARADISE: LANDSCAPE DESIGN AS SYMBOL AND METAPHOR</hi></head>
<figure xml:id="fig-91">
<graphic url="CH3_001.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p>Rooted in human responses to the environment in all his-<lb/>
torical cultures is a deep-seated recognition of the manifold imperfections of this world and a deep longing to re-create a lost place or time where and when life perpetually flourishes, death is unknown, there are no harsh extremes of climate, and no back-<lb/>
breaking toil to grow food and haul water, fear is replaced by law, chaos is vanquished by order, and warfare ceases forever in a perpetual reign of peace. Most of the world's myths&#x2014;biblical, classical, Islamic, early Christian, medieval, Chinese&#x2014;expound this theme.</p>
<p>The word <hi rend="italic">paradise</hi> is derived from the Persian <hi rend="italic">pairi-<lb/>
daeza</hi>, signifying a royal hunting park or orchard enclosed by walls (fig. 3.1).,<ref target="#CH3-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref> Paradise, both as a literary topos and as a realized garden, is ideologically divorced from the world and physically separated from it. It is not outwardly expansive and space-em-<lb/>
bracing, but rather spatially contained and inward-focused. This mythical paradise is, in the Judeo-Christian tradition, a place where humans and animals enjoy a vegetarian bounty and do not prey on one another. The Islamic tradition adds to this benign and secure environment, where the blessed enjoy fruitful ease, such sensory delights as delectable food, wine, music, fragrance, and erotic love.</p>
<p>It is important not to overemphasize the paradise meta-<lb/>
phor at the expense of certain mundane considerations such as topography, climate, or the representation of the beneficent power of a ruler to fructify the local landscape. Nevertheless, the para-<lb/>
dise image&#x2014;a bountiful, geometrically ordered, enclosed space in which water is typically made to flow in four directions, ema-<lb/>
nating from and sometimes returning to a central source&#x2014;is the common paradigm for expressing multiple associations, both religious and secular, in actual Islamic and Western medieval gar-<lb/>
dens. Such gardens can be found in Muslim lands extending from Mughal <name type="place">India</name> to Moorish <name type="place">Spain</name> and elsewhere in <name type="place">Europe</name> as the <hi rend="italic">hortus conclusus</hi>, the enclosed garden, depicted in Christian medieval manuscripts, tapestries, and woodcuts and exemplified in the cloister gardens of monasteries and churches. The visions of paradise as manifested both in actual gardens and in the art of these cultures all imply a reordering of the things of this world to create an idealized and rationally organized environment. Simi-<lb/>
larly, the notion of paradise as a systematic arrangement of all created plant species underlies the layouts of Renaissance botan-<lb/>
ical gardens.</p>
<p>It is difficult now to imagine how harsh and unfriendly the natural world once seemed and equally impossible to con-<lb/>
ceive the fear people once had of wilderness. The impulse to romanticize wild nature as expressed in a more naturalistic approach to garden-making&#x2014;an approach that implies paradox-<lb/>
ically a relatively high level of technological confidence and eco-<lb/>
nomic dominion over nature&#x2014;was completely foreign to the cultural milieus in which true paradise gardens were created. Romanticism as an attitude and the design ideas that flow from it date only from the latter part of the eighteenth century. Although the word "paradise" is often used loosely to denote any garden that is in essence idyllic, the garden symbolizing paradise as it is described in the Quran and the Bible is almost always nature (including human nature) tamed, domesticated, and regulated. According to the Judaeo-Christian view, paradise is a paradigm not only for the garden but also for the just city and the holy man or woman whose well-ordered existence symbolizes obedience to the laws of God. Before examining some actual landscapes that were intended to portray the order, tranquillity, bounty, and free-<lb/>
dom from want and care that two world religions, Islam and Christianity, associate with paradise, we should enrich our under-<lb/>
standing of paradise as a literary topos. This will help us to under-<lb/>
stand the important new role that landscape design came to play as a means of creating representational space, places in which symbols evoked ideas and ideals other than those of a purely paradisiacal nature.</p>
<div type="section">
<pb n="98"/>
<pb n="98" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Paradise as a Literary Topos: Gardens of God and Gardens of Love</hi></hi></head>
<figure xml:id="fig-92">
<graphic url="CH3_002.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.1. Detail of <name type="pname">Bahram Gur Pins</name> the Coupling Onagers, miniature from Shah Tahmasp's <hi rend="italic">Shah-nama (Book of Kings)</hi>, folio 568 recto. Painted by <name type="pname">Mir Sayyid Ali</name>, c. <date when="1533">1533</date>&#x2013;<date when="1535">35</date>. <name type="pname">Tabriz</name>, <name type="place">Persia</name>. Ink, opaque watercolor, and gold on paper. The Metro-politan Museum of Art, <name type="place">New York</name>. Gift of <name type="pname">Arthur A. Houghton, Jr.</name>, <date when="1970">1970</date> (1970.301.62)</figDesc>
</figure>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Garden of <name type="place">Eden</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>The price of disobedience, as readers of Genesis know, is expulsion from paradise. In this account, the newly made Earth was devoid of all vegetation because there was no creature to till it and no rain, but rather a flood rising up out of the ground, irrigating its barren plains.</p>
<q>
<p>Then the <name type="pname">Lord God</name> planted a garden in <name type="place">Eden</name> away to the east, and there he put the man whom he had formed. The <name type="pname">Lord God</name> made trees spring from the ground, all trees pleasant to look at and good for food; and in the middle of the garden he set the tree of life and the tree of good and evil.<ref target="#CH3-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref></p>
</q>
<p>This laconic account gives us very few visual details with which to flesh out this imaginary "first" garden. We are told, however, that "there was a river flowing from <name type="place">Eden</name> to water the garden, and when it left the garden it branched into four streams."<ref target="#CH3-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Of the Hebrew and Christian vision of heaven the Bible gives us even less scenic description, and there have been but few representations in the rich inventory of Western religious art to suggest its physical attri-<lb/>
butes. The idea, however, of a middle place marked by the presence of the Tree of Life and the Tree of Good and Evil, with four streams flowing away from it, pre-<lb/>
sumably in the four cardinal directions, echoes in bib-<lb/>
lical terms the cosmological diagram familiar to us from other prehistoric cultures of a vertical <hi rend="italic">axis mundi</hi> with four horizontal axes extending to the east, west, north, and south points of the horizon. Irrigation run-<lb/>
nels laid out according to a quadripartite pattern such as this must have occurred in some arid parts of the Ancient Near East where agriculture was first prac-<lb/>
ticed.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Classical Paradises</hi></hi></head>
<p>The longevity and the universality of visions signified by the word <hi rend="italic">paradise</hi> are evident from many descrip-<lb/>
tions in classical literature. <name type="pname">Homer</name> created an image of the garden as a paradisiacal reward for valor in his description of the Elysian Fields in the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>. Here <name type="pname">Menelaus</name> receives the news that
<q>
<lg>
<l>the gods intend you for Elysion</l>
<l>with golden Rhadamanthos at the world's end,</l>
<l>where all existence is a dream of ease.</l>
<l>Snowfall is never known there, nor long</l>
<l>frost of winter, nor torrential rain,</l>
<l>but only mild and lulling airs from Ocean</l>
<l>bearing refreshment for the souls of men&#x2014;</l>
<l>the West Wind always blowing.<ref target="#CH3-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref></l>
</lg>
</q></p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> also contains <name type="pname">Homer</name>'s famous descrip-<lb/>
tion of the paradisiacal orchard of Alcinous, which "long-suffering Odysseus stood admiring" before entering the house of his host:
<q>
<lg>
<l>There tall trees grow luxuriantly, pears</l>
<l>and pomegranates, apples bright with fruit,</l>
<l>delicious figs, and flowering olive trees.</l>
<l>Their fruit can never fail nor ever perish,</l>
<l>winter or summer, all year long, for always</l>
<l>Zephyr blows, nurturing some and ripening oth-<lb/>
ers.</l>
<l>Apple on apple, pear on pear matures,</l>
<l>fig upon fig, and grape on clustered grape.</l>
<l>A vineyard rich in fruit is rooted there:</l>
<l>part is spread out on level ground to dry</l>
<l>in sunlight, part is harvested at vintage,</l>
<l>and part they trample. Unripe grapes in front</l>
<l>shed flowers while the others slowly darken.</l>
<l>By the last row, well-ordered garden plots</l>
<pb n="99"/>
<pb n="99" type="orig"/>
<l>grow bountiful fresh greens of every kind.</l>
<l>Two springs flow, one dispersed throughout the garden,</l>
<l>the other gushing from the courtyard, near</l>
<l>the towering house where townsfolk come for water.<ref target="#CH3-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref></l>
</lg>
</q></p>
<p>Myths of Rhadamanthos, Elysion, the Blessed Isles, the distant east (or west), and magical mountain-<lb/>
tops&#x2014;places impossibly remote for ordinary travelers to reach&#x2014;were prevalent until the late fifteenth century, when Europeans discovered and explored vast areas of the planet that had long been <hi rend="italic">terra incognita</hi> in their minds. Before this time the hopeful belief persisted that physical paradise was an actual faraway realm where one might be transported under the right conditions. Along with this ideal of a terrestrial paradise, which might be discovered by far-voyaging mariners, was the notion in classical literature, paralleling the story of the Fall of Man in Genesis, of the lost paradise of a vanished Golden Age.</p>
<p>The Greek poet <name type="pname">Hesiod</name>'s eighth-century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> masterpiece, <hi rend="italic">Works and Days</hi>, articulates both concepts. His version of the Prometheus and Pandora myths helps explain the hard lot of humankind, condemned to wres-<lb/>
tle with the obdurate earth to grow the crops that sustain life, after having first known freedom from want. <hi rend="italic">Works and Days</hi> also gave Greeks a sense of their descent from a race of heroes. It elaborates a series of ages of dimin-<lb/>
ishing ease, physical accomplishment, and nobility of heart and mind: a Golden Age, a Silver Age, a Bronze Age, and a current Age of Iron, an age of warfare and unremitting labor. Other cultures have mythologized similar epochs of regressive human well-being. <name type="pname">Hesiod</name>, however, hon-<lb/>
ors the remembrance of Mycenaean glory and the epic tradition of the Dark Age immortalized by <name type="pname">Homer</name> and inserts, between his Bronze Age and the present diffi-<lb/>
cult Iron Age, an Age of Heroes, those legendary war-<lb/>
rior kings who consorted with the gods in the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>.</p>
<q>
<lg>
<l>War and carnage propelled many of these heroes to their doom,</l>
<l>Yet others of them father <name type="pname">Zeus</name>, son of <name type="pname">Kronos</name>, set-<lb/>
tled at earth's ends,</l>
<l>apart from men, and gave them shelter and food.</l>
<l>They lived there with hearts unburdened by cares</l>
<l>in the islands of the blessed, near stormy Okeanos,</l>
<l>these blissful heroes for whom three times a year</l>
<l>the barley-giving land brings forth full grain sweet as honey.<ref target="#CH3-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref></l>
</lg>
</q>
<p>The Greek lyric poet <name type="pname">Pindar</name> (c. 522&#x2013;c. 443 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) later developed the theme of a vanished epoch when people lived in innocence and knew no hardship or sor-<lb/>
row. Among the Roman poets, <name type="pname">Virgil</name> (70&#x2013;19 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) offered a prophetic vision of a new Golden Age under Emperor <name type="pname">Augustus</name>, while <name type="pname">Ovid</name> (43 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>&#x2013;17 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) looked back nostalgically on a bygone time of simple rustic happiness.</p>
<p>In addition to their temporal images of a previous era of peace and plenty, the spatial concepts of faraway Elysian Fields and Blessed Isles provided consoling visions of an afterlife for the deserving. These two visions, one of an ancient time of bounteousness and tranquillity, the other of a just reward after death, are akin to the two Christian usages of the term <hi rend="italic">paradise</hi> to sig-<lb/>
nify a prelapsarian Garden of <name type="place">Eden</name> and a post-Resurrec-<lb/>
tion home for the faithful in heaven.</p>
<p>By the fifth century, the Christian vision of paradise had been appropriated by the late classical <name type="pname">Carthaginian</name> poet <name type="pname">Blossius Aemilius Dracontius</name> who described it thus:
<q>
<lg>
<l>A place there is from which four rivers flow,</l>
<l>painted with jeweled turf and deathless flowers,</l>
<l>full of sweet-scented, never-fading herbs,</l>
<l>happiest garden in God's universe.<ref target="#CH3-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref></l>
</lg>
</q></p>
<p><name type="pname">Alcimus Ecdicius Av&#x00ED;tus</name>, bishop of <name type="place">Vienna</name> from c. 490 to 518, draws on well-established tradition in his <hi rend="italic">De Spiritalis Historiae Gestis</hi>, locating paradise
<q>
<lg>
<l>East of the Indies, where the world begins,</l>
<l>where earth and sky are said to meet together.</l>
</lg>
</q></p>
<p>Paradise for <name type="pname">Av&#x00ED;tus</name> is a place where
<q>
<lg>
<l>temperate climes preserve eternal spring;</l>
<l>rough winds are absent, under sunny skies</l>
<l>clouds yield to unremittingly clear weather.</l>
<l>The nature of the place requires no rain,</l>
<l>for grasses thrive contentedly on dew.</l>
<l>The ground is always green, earth's smiling face</l>
<l>radiates warmth; plants grow on hills forever,</l>
<l>and leaves on trees: for though they burst in flower</l>
<l>often, swift sap invigorates their buds.<ref target="#CH3-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref></l>
</lg>
</q></p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Muslim Paradise</hi></hi></head>
<p>The Quran, the book of divine wisdom derived from the Hebrew Bible and revealed to <name type="pname">Muhammad</name> by God in the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, has four rivers emanating from para-<lb/>
dise as in Genesis. Here, however, the rivers are more metaphorical than geographical, eternally flowing streams of milk and purified honey. The Quran dwells on
<pb n="100"/>
<pb n="100" type="orig"/>
the luxury and opulence of paradise, the prize for the godly. There the blessed, dressed in robes of silk, will be rewarded:
<q>
<p>Reclining upon soft couches, they shall feel neither the scorching heat nor the biting cold. Trees will spread their shade around them, and fruits will hang in clusters over them.</p>
<p>They shall be served with silver dishes, and beakers as large as goblets; silver goblets which they themselves shall measure: the cups brim-full with ginger-flavored water from the Fount of Sel-<lb/>
sabil. They shall be attended by boys graced with eternal youth, who to the beholder's eyes will seem like sprinkled pearls. When you gaze upon that scene you will behold a kingdom blissful and glori-<lb/>
ous.<ref target="#CH3-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref></p>
</q></p>
<p>There is an understandable emphasis upon cooling shade, clear running water, and refreshing beverages in a desert culture. The elite and affluent imagery of the Qura-<lb/>
nic paradise&#x2014;a luxurious desert oasis with four water-<lb/>
courses streaming from it&#x2014;has been metaphorically linked with the designs for Islamic royal gardens. Like the gardens of the Christian West, these invest the primal cosmological diagram with a specific symbolism and reli-<lb/>
gious authority. This is evident in their spatial organiza-<lb/>
tion, with a central raised platform serving as the dais for an important structure, often a monarch's pavilion or tomb, and four water channels marking the principal compass directions. But, unlike the garden in the Chris-<lb/>
tian West, the Islamic garden was a place where erotic love was given appropriate license.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Islamic Gardens of Delight</hi></hi></head>
<p>In the literature of Islam, the garden does double duty in a metaphorical sense, its attributes being assigned to God by the mystics and to the human lover by the poets. God's grace could be read in the springtime, which briefly col-<lb/>
ored and brightened the parched landscapes that consti-<lb/>
tute much of the Muslim world; there are paeans of praise to the coming of spring in Islamic writing. In all seasons, the oasislike paradise garden reflects the heavenly glory. There one finds the faithful personified as the gatekeeper of Paradise, and abundance in the form of a heavenly fountain. There in the Garden of <name type="place">Eden</name> (the primordial garden and the eternal garden are synonymous in the Quran) stands the Tuba tree, furnishing a double image as it symbolizes both a state of blessedness and the slender grace of the beloved.</p>
<p>The opposition between divine and human love that permeates Christian texts is absent in Quranic mystical thought. <name type="pname">Ruzbihan Baqli</name> in the twelfth century advised spiritual recreation in the contemplation of three things: water, greenery, and a lovely face. All of the garden's flowers existed for the purpose of praising God, and each was assigned one or more divine attributes. Simultane-<lb/>
ously, these same flowers stood for the beauty of various human body parts. Thus the tulip, which symbolizes the martyr, also represents the cheek (as do the hyacinth and the pomegranate flower), and the narcissus, whose white "blind" eye symbolizes the unenlightened, also furnishes an appropriate compliment to the real eyes of the lover. In describing a lovely woman in his <hi rend="italic">Shah-nama</hi> ("Book of Kings"), the Persian national epic, the eleventh-cen-<lb/>
tury poet <name type="pname">Firdawsi</name>, compiled a rich collection of gar-<lb/>
den-derived metaphors and similes:
<q>
<p>She was like ivory from head to toe, with a face like Paradise and a figure as graceful as a tree. Her cheeks were as red as pomegranate blossoms and her lips its seeds, while two pomegranates grew from her silver breast. Her eyes were like the narcis-<lb/>
sus in the garden, and her eyebrows stole the black-<lb/>
ness from the crow's feathers. She is Paradise to look upon.<ref target="#CH3-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref></p>
</q></p>
<p>The flower <hi rend="italic">par excellence</hi>_in the Islamic garden is the <hi rend="italic">gul</hi>, or rose. So revered and admired is it that the very name of the garden, <hi rend="italic">gulshan</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">gulzar</hi>) embodies its name. According to Muslim mystics, the rose was created from a drop of perspiration that fell from <name type="pname">Muhammad</name>'s forehead. The rose, which also provided the conventional analogy for the face of the Beloved, sometimes repre-<lb/>
sented the beautiful <hi rend="italic">houri</hi> who inhabited Paradise. In the mystic tradition, the rose also stands for the soul at peace, its evocative fragrance lingering after it has died. In addi-<lb/>
tion, its many petals folded into one graceful flower sym-<lb/>
bolize union and harmony among humankind. These associations furnished the symbolic substance of the Islamic garden.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Christian Allegorical Exegesis of The Song of Songs</hi></hi></head>
<p>The most lyrically erotic book of the Old Testament is the biblical love poem known as The Song of Songs. Written as a dialogue between the bride and bridegroom (identi-<lb/>
fied with <name type="pname">Solomon</name>), with a chorus of companions provid-<lb/>
ing commentary, The Song of Songs is filled with erotic energy, as the bridal couple extol each other in the lan-<lb/>
guage of landscape with image after image of fragrance, fruit, gem, tree, monument, mountaintop, and comely animal. Nature, both wild and cultivated, is summoned forth in all its processes of dynamic change to evoke the alternating presence and absence of the loved one. Pome-<lb/>
granates, gazelles, asphodels, and lilies are pressed into literary service as similes to describe the beloved.</p>
<p>The interpretation put forward by <name type="pname">Saint Bernard</name>,
<pb n="101"/>
<pb n="101" type="orig"/>
abbot of <name type="pname">Clairvaux</name> (1090&#x2013;1153), transformed these images of the Garden of Love into symbols of divine communion by means of an elaborate exegesis in which the poem became an expression of the <name type="pname">Virgin Mary</name>'s election as the Bride of God and Christ's mys-<lb/>
tical union with his Church. Given the extremely sen-<lb/>
suous nature of the poem, it illustrates not only Christianity's ability to square Scripture with its strong bias in favor of chastity but also its tendency to see allegorical meaning in worldly phenomena.</p>
<p>The bridegroom's declaration,
<q>
<p>My sister, my bride, is a garden close-locked, a garden close-locked, a fountain sealed,<ref target="#CH3-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref></p>
</q>
is converted into a specific symbol of <name type="pname">Mary</name>'s virginity, her womb being a metaphorical garden where the Christ, the Tree of Life, was planted by God.</p>
<p>The Christian interpretation of The Song of Songs as an allegory led to the depiction of the <name type="pname">Virgin Mary</name> in the <hi rend="italic">hortus conclusus</hi>, or enclosed garden, conventionally shown as a flowery meadow inside high walls or encircled by a low wattle fence of the kind familiar all over <name type="place">Europe</name> during the Middle Ages (fig. 3.2). Such fences were constructed to keep wild animals out of cultivated garden plots. One mythical beast, however, was permitted entrance: the unicorn. With its tireless speed and single invincible horn, this imaginary animal symbolizes Christ, who allows Himself to be caught in order to lie down in the Vir-<lb/>
gin's lap&#x2014;that is, he allows himself to be born on Earth. The Marian garden that we most often see in medieval tapestries, miniatures, and prints is a flow-<lb/>
er-studded greensward in which the flowers all have allegorical attributes. The budding rose represents the Virgin's modesty and the lily her purity, while the iris, (the <hi rend="italic">fleur de lys</hi>) stands both for the Kings of <name type="place">France</name> and, by inference, for the line of <name type="pname">David</name> and <name type="pname">Jesus</name>. The garden's straight paths symbolize divine order, and its fountains refer to the sealed fountain in The Song of Songs. Wild landscape and wild animals (except for the mythical unicorn) are firmly excluded from the Marian <hi rend="italic">hortus conclusus</hi> by a wattle fence, hedge of thorns, or high wall.</p>
<p>For some devout early Christians, the wilderness was emphatically not a place for Thoreau-like obser-<lb/>
vation and self-knowledge, but rather a hostile and unfriendly locale, its scenery a metaphor for the rigor with which the saintly penitent must subdue the evil forces within his own breast. By making wild, uncul-<lb/>
tivated nature the domain of demons, Christian thought devalued nature and robbed it of its previous sanctity. Caves became the cells of hermits instead of the homes of oracles, and mountaintops were no lon-<lb/>
ger the abodes of gods as they had been in antiquity, but rather the setting for Christian trial and temptation. Because an apocalyptic ending of human history was predicted and all hope fastened on the afterlife, the beauty of Earth was devalued. Further, denial of the real world gave license to the exploitation of nature and its subjugation to human will. Humans, however, could not remain sensually indifferent to the world or their own sexuality. As will become apparent, the gar-<lb/>
den&#x2014;controlled nature&#x2014;would remain, as it was for the author of The Song of Songs the locus of an ideal-<lb/>
ized approach to love.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-93">
<graphic url="CH3_003.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.2. <hi rend="italic">The Madonna in a Closed Garden</hi>, a hand-colored woodcut by an anonymous <name type="pname">Swabian</name> or <name type="pname">Franconian</name> master. <date when="1450">1450</date>&#x2013;<date when="1470">70</date>. National Gallery of Art, <name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>, Rosenwald Collection</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Garden of Love</hi></hi></head>
<p>For classical writers like the late-fourth-century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> Latin poet <name type="pname">Claudian</name>, who moved to <name type="place">Rome</name> from <name type="place">Alex-<lb/>
andria</name> in 395 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, the garden was the obvious domain of <name type="pname">Venus</name>. The last major poet writing in the classical tradition, <name type="pname">Claudian</name> developed the imagery of the land-<lb/>
scape of pleasure in his version of the familiar classi-<lb/>
cal myth of <name type="pname">Persephone</name>'s abduction by <name type="pname">Hades</name>, <hi rend="italic">De raptu Proserpinae</hi>. In another poem, <hi rend="italic">Epithalamium de Nuptiis Honorii Augusti</hi>, he painted a picture of a pre-<lb/>
cinct sacred to <name type="pname">Venus</name> high on a mountaintop above the Ionian Sea. It overlooks a garden encircled by a golden hedge and filled with birdsong and aromatic plants. This is a garden of fantasy and allegory, a place of delectation and dalliance wherein are found such per-<lb/>
sonifications as
<q>
<p>License bound by no fetters, easily moved Anger, Wakes dripping with wine, inexperienced Fears,
<pb n="102"/>
<pb n="102" type="orig"/>
<name type="pname">Pallor</name> that lovers ever prize, Boldness trembling at his first thefts, happy fears, unstable Pleasure, and lovers' Oaths, the sport of every lightest breeze. Amid them all wanton Youth with haughty neck shuts out Age from the grove.<ref target="#CH3-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref></p>
</q></p>
<figure xml:id="fig-94">
<graphic url="CH3_004.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.3. <hi rend="italic">The Lover and Dame Oyeuse</hi>, a garden scene from an illuminated manuscript, <hi rend="italic">Roman de la Rose</hi>. <name type="pname">Ms. Harl</name>. 4425 folio 12 verso. c. <date when="1485">1485</date>, Flanders. The British Library, <name type="place">London</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Although Christianity firmly revoked the license that ancient peoples, such as the Hebrews, Persians, Greeks, and Romans, had accorded erotic love and con-<lb/>
demned contemporary Islamic mores as sybaritic, the association between gardens and human love remained rooted in the Western imagination. The garden's func-<lb/>
tion as an arena of allegory dealing with the trials and triumphs of young love was perpetuated in medieval and Renaissance literature. Around 1230, the French poet <name type="pname">Guillaume de Lorris</name> narrated his dream of romantic love in an epic poem, <hi rend="italic">The Romance of the Rose</hi>, a work that was carried forward some forty years later by <name type="pname">Jean de Meung</name>, who provided it with an ending that is entirely different in meaning from that intended by its first author (fig. 3.3).</p>
<p>Drawing on the style of the troubadours, <name type="pname">Guil-<lb/>
laume de Lorris</name> invests his portion of the poem with a delicate psychology that goes beyond the troubadours' usual one-sided treatment of love into an exploration of the heart and mind of the lady who is symbolized by the Rose. His part ends with the rejected Lover's realization that he cannot simply overcome all the barriers sur-<lb/>
rounding the object of his desire. In order for him to possess the love of the Rose, she must also have her heart pierced by love's arrow.</p>
<p>In <name type="pname">Jean de Meung</name>'s conclusion&#x2014;a brief for the importance of procreation&#x2014;the Lover persists in his quest and is encouraged to ravish the Rose. <name type="pname">Venus</name> leads the charge, and the Rose's guardian is persuaded to give her to the Lover who joyously proceeds to deflower her. However, the tone here is moral, not lewd. The Lover is not only rewarded with his time love but also with the prize of paradise. To achieve this happy ending, the author of the second part of the poem effectively exposes the earthly garden of courtly, romantic love as false, while building his case for the fruitful garden of procre-<lb/>
ation as the Christian pasture of the Good Shepherd.</p>
<p>In the hundred life-affirming stories of the <hi rend="italic">Decam-<lb/>
eron</hi> by <name type="pname">Giovanni Boccaccio</name> (<date when="1313">1313</date>&#x2013;<date when="1375">1375</date>), written in the middle of the fourteenth century when the Black Death ravaged the population, flesh and spirit are compatible; both are a natural, joyous part of existence. Choosing as a model the Villa Palmieri near <name type="place">Florence</name>, <name type="pname">Boccaccio</name> describes an enclosed garden with its crisscross of wide rose-and jasmine-bordered paths "all straight as arrows and overhung by pergolas of vines," its orange and lemon trees and white marble fountain "covered with marvelous bas-reliefs." Here men and women could enjoy one another's company and praise the garden as a the very model of paradise:
<q>
<p>The sight of this garden, and the perfection of its arrangement, with its shrubs, its streamlets, and the fountain from which they originated, gave so much pleasure to each of the ladies and the three young men that they all began to maintain that if Paradise were constructed on earth, it was inconceivable that it could take any other form.<ref target="#CH3-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref></p>
</q></p>
<p>The notion of the garden as an enclosed space, set apart, and infused with metaphorical meaning&#x2014;a rep-<lb/>
resentation of nature perfected through human art in the service of an ideal&#x2014;is fundamental to our understand-<lb/>
ing of the history of landscape design.<ref target="#CH3-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref> The literature of paradise gave rise to the notion of the garden as a sym-<lb/>
bolical space, and thus the written word helped land-<lb/>
scape design assume a role beyond the one of prehistoric and classical times in which humans accorded divinity to actual sites in nature, shaping space and arranging architectural forms in relationship to the sky and certain features of Earth such as mountains and caves. The con-<lb/>
cept of landscape as symbolically divine, rather than actually divine space, derived particular strength from Islamic and Christian religious ideology as is evident in the way in which these world cultures translated the par-<lb/>
adise ideal into the form of actual gardens.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="103"/>
<pb n="103" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">II. Paradise on Earth: The Islamic Garden</hi></hi></head>
<p>In desert lands, the oasis is typically viewed as a kind of paradise, a respite from the parched land and withering sun. Through conquest and a tolerant religion, the nation of Islam spread westward across <name type="place">North Africa</name> to south-<lb/>
ern <name type="place">Spain</name> and eastward into <name type="place">Central Asia</name> and <name type="place">India</name>, a territory composed principally of vast dry zones with extremes of heat and cold within which scattered green oases furnished a most precious element, water. In their migrations, Islamic peoples absorbed elements bor-<lb/>
rowed from other design traditions, which they synthe-<lb/>
sized into a distinctive style. In desert climates and also where water flowed seasonally, the four heavenly rivers of paradise described in the Quran and the refreshing fountains, as well as the shade and fruit trees to be found there, provided apt symbols for paradise in the oasislike Islamic garden.</p>
<p>Unlike Japanese or English gardens, Persian gar-<lb/>
dens and their Islamic successors were not constructed as spatial itineraries, places of sequential discovery; rather they were designed to serve the purposes of lux-<lb/>
urious ease and sensory delight or, in the case of Mughal tomb gardens, as settings for monuments of commemoration. Water's soothing sound and mesmer-<lb/>
izing reflectivity were essential to their ephemeral atmosphere and paradisiacal character. Built mostly in warm climates, they were exterior living spaces, often sumptuous, yet airy. The porticoed palace, the garden pavilion, and the kiosk opened up to the out-of-doors, and often their walls were pierced by grills to admit a filigree of fragmented light, dematerializing interior space. In these spaces, the distinction between inside and out, between architecture and landscape, between the material world and poetry, seems almost to dissolve.</p>
<p>Fruit trees and flowers, birds and animals, shim-<lb/>
mering tiles, and the gleam and murmur of running water&#x2014;these are the vibrant and delicate substances from which, like a beautiful carpet, the Islamic garden is woven. Indeed, Islamic carpet design and garden lay-<lb/>
out go hand in hand. Garden carpets depict in a stylized manner the <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">chahar bagh</hi></name>, or fourfold garden with its intersecting axial watercourses surmounted by a central fountain (fig. 3.4). In addition, they depict symbolically the vegetation planted in actual gardens: the shade-giv-<lb/>
ing plane tree, identified with the Tuba tree in the Quran; the cypress representing death and eternity; and fruit trees standing for life and fertility. The central cartouche can be interpreted as a platform, which in real gardens was often surmounted by a pavilion. These form the basic and timeless design formula of the Islamic gar-<lb/>
den&#x2014;one or more quadripartite sections defined by narrow watercourses&#x2014;which has its roots in ancient <name type="place">Persia</name> where the archaeological remains of <name type="place">Achaemenid</name> palaces trace the outlines of pavilions overlooking carved stone channels.</p>
<p>The paradigm of quadripartite landscape space with a defined center, from which energy flows out-<lb/>
ward in four directions and to which energy returns from the four corners of the cosmos, is a place-making practice rooted, as we have seen, in prehistoric tradi-<lb/>
tion. But there is a distinction to be made between Islamic and prehistoric cosmological design. Prehis-<lb/>
toric societies viewed landscape space in terms that charged <hi rend="italic">specific</hi> local landscapes with intense religious meaning; their organization of space into quadripar-<lb/>
tite-center configurations was a declaration of the <hi rend="italic">actual</hi> residence of divinity within a given landscape. Islamic garden design was rooted in a religion that was also impregnated with cosmological meaning, but because holy literature had begun to supplement and supplant oral tradition, thereby disse-minating religion more broadly, a universal cosmological <hi rend="italic">symbolism</hi>_of sacred space, rather than the designation of certain spaces as cosmologically sacred, was now an operative cultural principle guiding landscape design. This obser-<lb/>
vation is true for Hebrew-derived, Christian landscape design as well.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-95">
<graphic url="CH3_005.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.4. Garden carpet, 12&#x2032;4&#x2033; &#x00D7; 8&#x2032;8&#x2033; Persian. 18th century. Victoria &amp; Albert Museum, <name type="place">London</name>. The carpet is designed with a pattern that is intended to portray a <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">chahar bagh</hi></name>.</figDesc>
</figure>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Early Persian Gardens</hi></hi></head>
<p>It will be recalled that the word <hi rend="italic">paradise</hi> was originally used to denote a hunting park. <name type="pname">Xenophon</name> (c. 431&#x2013;c. 352 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), the soldier and writer who was a disciple of <name type="pname">Socrates</name>, reports on the beauty of the hunting park, the <hi rend="italic">pairidaeza</hi> at <name type="pname">Sardis</name>, of the <name type="place">Achaemenid</name> king <name type="pname">Cyrus</name> the
<pb n="104"/>
<pb n="104" type="orig"/>
Great (died c. 529 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>). From <name type="pname">Xenophon</name>'s descrip-<lb/>
tion we learn that this royal park was both a hunting park and a geometrically planted orchard. At <name type="place">Pasarga-<lb/>
dae</name>, <name type="pname">Cyrus</name> the Great constructed a palace, a separate audience hall, and a garden pavilion overlooking a stone watercourse with square pools at regular inter-<lb/>
vals.</p>
<p>The shady porticoes of the palace and audience hall at <name type="place">Pasargadae</name>, as well as the garden pavilion itself, overlooked the thin ribbon of water and the orchard-garden that surrounded it. Thus we find in the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> the two indispensable elements of Persian garden design: a straight, geometrically elabo-<lb/>
rated watercourse and a raised platform for garden viewing.</p>
<p>To supply such gardens as this with water, <name type="place">Ach-<lb/>
aemenid</name> engineers constructed underground tunnels called <hi rend="italic">qanats</hi>_using a method developed as early as the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi> and still in use today. These were laboriously dug by hand from the point of delivery to the base of a snow-capped mountain in a gentle ever-ascending grade. Shafts for debris removal and air supply created openings at intervals of approxi-<lb/>
mately 50 feet, and these apertures still dot the vast Iranian plain.</p>
<p>After the conquest of <name type="place">Persia</name> by <name type="pname">Alexander</name> the Great (356&#x2013;323 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), a century of Hellenizing influ-<lb/>
ence preceded the re-establishment of a Persian empire and Persian design traditions under the Parthi-<lb/>
ans (c. 240 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>&#x2013;226 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>). Their capital was Ctes-ip-<lb/>
hon. Between the third and seventh centuries <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, the Sassanians, successors to Parthian rule, who also made Ctesiphon their capital, continued to express Persian influence in their gardens. As inferred from the design of a legendary Persian carpet measuring 450 feet by 90 feet, which was woven for <name type="pname">King Khos-<lb/>
row I Anushirvan</name> (ruled 531&#x2013;579 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>), the imagery of the fourfold garden, divided by channels of running water, with a platform overlooking these water-<lb/>
courses, was an established idiom for actual garden construction. This Persian legacy accorded well with the Quranic concept of paradise, providing a readily accessible model for the Islamic garden.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Islamic Origins</hi></hi></head>
<p>In 610 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, the prophet <name type="pname">Muhammed</name> initiated the Mus-<lb/>
lim religion. It quickly spread through the Arabian peninsula and into the Middle East and <name type="place">Persia</name>. In 766 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, the <name type="pname">Abbasid</name> caliphs, having asserted their politi-<lb/>
cal dominance, founded their capital of <name type="place">Baghdad</name> on the <name type="place">Tigris River</name>. During their rule between the eighth and the thirteenth century, horticulture and technology advanced rapidly. By the early tenth century, the city could boast twenty-three palaces with opulent gar-<lb/>
dens. One of these fabled, long-vanished palaces was known as the House of the Tree. An artificial tree stood in the middle of a large round pond and had eighteen boughs made of gold and silver hung with precious gems in the form of fruits. This ingenious automata had gold and silver birds perched on its branches, and these emitted musical notes when stirred by the passing breeze.</p>
<p>Simultaneously, beginning in the eighth century, Islamic warriors carried their culture west to <name type="place">Spain</name>. Here Muslim rulers synthesized Hellenistic, Roman, Early Christian, and Persian influences. As the power of the <name type="pname">Abbasid</name> caliphs declined, their role shifted from one of political power to one of religious leadership. <name type="place">Baghdad</name> fell to <name type="place">Mongol</name> invaders in <date when="1258">1258</date>, following the campaigns of <name type="pname">Genghis Khan</name> and his heirs, but Islamic culture nonetheless remained a unifying force throughout much of <name type="place">Asia</name>, <name type="place">North Africa</name>, and <name type="place">Spain</name>. Within this culture, the essential garden formula of a watercourse and raised platform for sedentary view-<lb/>
ing was further developed as a quadripartite space in which the divisions were articulated by narrow water channels that could be thought of as symbolizing the four rivers of paradise.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Islamic Gardens of <name type="place">Spain</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>The leaders of the Muslim army that invaded <name type="place">Spain</name> in 711 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> were inspired by the hope of plunder as much as by religious enthusiasm. After defeating the Visig-<lb/>
oths, the western Goths who had in the fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> claimed the parts of the Roman Empire now occu-<lb/>
pied by <name type="place">France</name> and <name type="place">Spain</name>, the Arabs established them-<lb/>
selves within the remains of their enemies' settlements and the extensive ruins of former Roman colonies. Then, in 750, after a palace revolution, a surviving member of the <name type="pname">Umayyad</name> caliphate, the first dynasty of Arab caliphs (661&#x2013;750), fled <name type="pname">Damascus</name> to found the independent emirate of al-Andalus in the southern Spanish region that is known today as <name type="place">Andalusia</name>. Geographically distant, therefore, from Islamic cul-<lb/>
ture in the Middle East, the Arabs in <name type="place">Spain</name> formed their own brilliant and erudite society. Here in <name type="place">Spain</name>, Muslim, Christian, and Jewish communities coexisted under Arab rule. The Arabs had brought with them Persian artistic concepts along with Arabic science, and they married these with Greek philosophy. In this way, <name type="pname">C&#x00F3;rdoba</name> became in the Middle Ages a center of learning, renowned for such philosophers as <name type="pname">Ibn Rushd</name>, known in the West as <name type="pname">Averro&#x00EB;s</name> (<date when="1126">1126</date>&#x2013;<date when="1198">1198</date>), a rationalist who translated <name type="pname">Aristotle</name> and anticipated <name type="pname">Thomas Aquinas</name>.</p>
<p>While southern <name type="place">Spain</name> has the same hot climate as many other parts of the Islamic geographical sphere, its topography is for the most part more rug-<lb/>
ged and its land well watered and more fertile. Moor-<lb/>
ish engineers, rebuilding and extending the remains of
<pb n="105"/>
<pb n="105" type="orig"/>
Roman aqueducts all around them, created intricate irrigation systems by introducing the <hi rend="italic">noria</hi>, a buck-<lb/>
et-scoop waterwheel that raised water into elevated canals. This greatly increased the amount of arable land and facilitated the construction of numerous gar-<lb/>
dens. Agriculture prospered, and famous treatises on the subject were written, such as the one by <name type="pname">Abu Zakariya</name>, a thirteenth-century agronomist and botanist in <name type="place">Seville</name>. Farmers introduced sugarcane and brought into cultivation rice, cotton, flax, silkworms, and many kinds of fruit. Both the valley of the Guadalaquivir and the plain of <name type="place">Granada</name> became densely settled zones with a rich tapestry of agriculture and gardening, their air fragrant with the scent of orange, lemon, and citron trees.<ref target="#CH3-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Topography and contact with the abundant remains of <name type="pname">Iberian Rome</name> served to modify the con-<lb/>
querors' Syrian architectural heritage with its previ-<lb/>
ously assimilated Roman and Persian forms. But Spanish Muslim architecture never aspired to the monumental three-dimensionality of architecture in the West. Instead, its aim was atmospheric, and its highest achievement lay in the interweaving of indoor and outdoor spaces in sensuous and sophisticated ways. Thus, in a typical Moorish house and garden, the patio and the structural spaces surrounding it inter-<lb/>
penetrate one another in a casual yet studied congress of architecture and nature. Ceramic tiles, with their brightly glazed, reflective surfaces, produced an effect of cool airiness.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-96">
<graphic url="CH3_006.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.5. Carmen, Albaic&#x00ED;n district, <name type="place">Granada</name>. 16th century</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-97">
<graphic url="CH3_007.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 3.6. Patio de los Naranjos (Court of the Oranges), Great Mosque, <name type="pname">C&#x00F3;rdoba</name>. c. 9th century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The spatial interpenetration of indoors and out-<lb/>
doors was not confined to fortress palaces or homes such as are found today in the Albaic&#x00ED;n district of <name type="place">Granada</name>, where the durable plan of the Roman peri-<lb/>
style was appropriated and reinterpreted as the <hi rend="italic">car-<lb/>
men</hi>, the inward-focused house and garden of Arabic <name type="place">Spain</name> (fig. 3.5). The same planning principle can be seen in the design of the Great Mosque at <name type="pname">C&#x00F3;rdoba</name>, begun in 785&#x2013;6. The mosque (now a cathedral), has a hypostyle interior in which the columns supporting a vast number of horseshoe-shaped double arches are evenly placed throughout like rows of trees in an orchard. Originally the wall on this side of the mosque opened via a fa&#x00E7;ade of arches to a 3-acre courtyard planted in avenues of orange trees, which were aligned with the columns of the mosque's interior. An under-<lb/>
ground cistern supplied the fountains and irrigation channels in this court, called the Patio de los Naranjos, or Court of the Oranges (fig. 3.6). Unfortunately, the underground cistern has long since been converted into an ossuary, and Christian chapels have filled in the arches that once opened onto this patio.</p>
<p>The Alc&#x00E1;zar<ref target="#CH3-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> in <name type="place">Seville</name>, which dates from about a hundred years after the Christian conquest of that city in <date when="1248">1248</date>, exemplifies the extensive Islamic influ-<lb/>
ence upon subsequent Spanish architecture (fig. 3.7). Using the considerable resources of Islamic crafts-<lb/>
manship, the king of <name type="place">Castile</name>, Pedro the Cruel (ruled <date when="1334">1334</date>&#x2013;<date when="1369">1369</date>), built his fortified palace on the ruins of the former Islamic citadel. The Alc&#x00E1;zar gardens con-<lb/>
sist of a series of enclosed patios. Though altered in
<pb n="106"/>
<pb n="106" type="orig"/>
subsequent centuries, the Moorish origins of these gar-<lb/>
dens are evident in their high enclosing walls, geomet-<lb/>
rical layout, raised paths, numerous fountains, brightly glazed tiles, and plantings of cypress, palm, orange, and lemon trees.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-98">
<graphic url="CH3_008.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.7. Garden of the Alc&#x00E1;zar, the Mud&#x00E9;jar residence of Spanish royalty, <name type="place">Seville</name>. Restored and rebuilt by Pedro the Cruel, beginning in <date when="1366">1366</date>, but substantially altered in subsequent periods</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-99">
<graphic url="CH3_009.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 3.8. The Court of the Lions, <name type="place">Alhambra</name>, <name type="place">Granada</name>. <date when="1370">1370</date>&#x2013;<date when="1390">90</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<p><name type="place">Granada</name> was the last Arabic city recaptured by Christian monarchs, falling to <name type="pname">Ferdinand</name> and <name type="pname">Isabel</name> <date when="1492">1492</date>. Its remaining Arabic gardens&#x2014;the <name type="place">Alhambra</name> and the Generalife&#x2014;which date from the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries, are among the oldest gardens in the world and enjoy legendary status. Sometime around <date when="1250">1250</date>, <name type="pname">Muhammad Ibn Ben Ahmar</name>, the founder of the <name type="place">Nasrid dynasty</name>, who took possession of <name type="place">Granada</name> in <date when="1238">1238</date>, climbed to the top of a bare red escarpment above the valley of the <name type="place">Darro</name> with the spectacular <name type="pname">Sierra Nevada</name> rising behind it and laid claim to a site for his palace where there was already standing a build-<lb/>
ing that probably served as a fortress in the late elev-<lb/>
enth century. Here he ordered the construction of an aqueduct, the water from which has made possible the gardens of the <name type="place">Alhambra</name> and the Generalife ever since. Built over a period of 250 years, principally during the reigns of <name type="pname">Yusuf I</name> (<date when="1333">1333</date>&#x2013;<date when="1354">1354</date>) and <name type="pname">Muhammad V</name> (<date when="1354">1354</date>&#x2013;<date when="1359">1359</date>; <date when="1362">1362</date>&#x2013;<date when="1391">1391</date>), the <name type="place">Alhambra</name>, like the Alc&#x00E1;zar in <name type="place">Seville</name>, is an accretion of enclosed garden spaces, some of which were torn away in the sixteenth century when <name type="pname">Charles V</name> built a vast square palace with a huge circular interior court.</p>
<p>At the <name type="place">Alhambra</name>, the planted areas of several of the enclosed gardens are defined by cross-axial paths. Soil beds were originally sunken well below these walkways and not as we see them today at almost the same grade. Planted with flowers, these garden courts would have been read by viewers sitting on carpets and low cushions placed in the surrounding porticoes as brightly colored tapestries. The fragrance of their orange trees, a unique garden design feature of Moor-<lb/>
ish <name type="place">Spain</name>, would have also perfumed the air. Because one rarely enters directly from the outside into a Span-<lb/>
ish-Moorish patio, but rather through a vestibule or twisting corridor, the sight of a beautiful interior gar-<lb/>
den is unexpected and therefore the impression it makes is powerful, relying as it does on one of the chief tricks of garden art: surprise. For instance, an undistin-<lb/>
guished opening off the Court of the Myrtles turns into a small dark corridor leading to the most famous and complex space within the <name type="place">Alhambra</name>, the Court of the Lions (fig. 3.8).</p>
<p>Here one finds a central fountain and a cruciform pattern of water channels. The fountain is supported by stylized lions with water flowing from their mouths into the basin below, which contemporaries may have linked symbolically with <name type="pname">Solomon</name>, or at least with the notion of wise royal rule associated with the Hebrew
<pb n="107"/>
<pb n="107" type="orig"/>
king.<ref target="#CH3-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref> The basin is also fed by water that runs in a silver thread through the narrow white marble canals from the surrounding porticoed spaces. The most magnificent of these pavilionlike structures is the Hall of the Two Sisters flanking the Court of the Lions on the north. Its cupola of stucco blocks set over an octa-<lb/>
gon is formed into a honeycombed, stalactitelike ceil-<lb/>
ing of mesmerizing intricacy ascending as a symbolical representation of various levels of the heavens. Adding to the ethereal quality of the archi-<lb/>
tecture are slender alabaster columns, brilliant gild-<lb/>
ing, and polychrome tiles designed in a rich array of abstract patterns. Here one finds the familiar avoid-<lb/>
ance of figural imagery and Islamic preference for geometrical forms, believed to embody the mathe-<lb/>
matical order underlying all creation. For the same reason, topiary was scrupulously avoided and plants in this and other Islamic gardens were allowed to assume their natural forms.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-100">
<graphic url="CH3_010.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.9. Acequia,_Generalife, <name type="place">Granada</name>. Original layout from <date when="1319">1319</date>, with subsequent alterations</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>On a nearby hillside is the Generalife, or <name type="pname">Jinnah al-'Arif</name>, as the summer palace of the Spanish Arabic kings was known when it was begun in <date when="1319">1319</date>. In addi-<lb/>
tion to the quiet beauty of its secluded interior garden courts, with their lush vegetation and clear pools of water, the Generalife captures within its scenic embrace the magnificent snow-capped <name type="pname">Sierra Nevada</name> as well as the picturesque towers of the <name type="place">Alhambra</name> silhouetted against the fertile valley of <name type="place">Granada</name> below. As in other Islamic gardens, the designers here used the musicality, reflectivity, and cooling charac-<lb/>
teristics of water to enhance sensory experience. The most prominent of the gardens of the Generalife, the Patio de Acequia, or Patio of the Canal, has, instead of the usual water cross-axis dividing it into four quadrants, a long narrow pool, bridged in the center, into which jets of water fall in arcs (fig. 3.9). These water jets, like the floral borders lining the edges of the marble pavement beside this pool, were probably
<pb n="108"/>
<pb n="108" type="orig"/>
sixteenth-century additions and appear somewhat flamboyant in the context of an Islamic garden. At its northern end, the Patio de Acequia_terminates in a pavilion, the delicacy of which has been compromised by the two stories added during the reign of <name type="pname">Isabella I</name> as queen of <name type="place">Castile</name>, <date when="1474">1474</date>&#x2013;<date when="1504">1504</date>; with <name type="pname">Ferdinand</name>, joint sovereign of <name type="place">Aragon</name> and <name type="place">Castile</name>, <date when="1479">1479</date>&#x2013;<date when="1504">1504</date>).</p>
<p>There were no kitchens or residential quarters at the Generalife. Used overnight only in summer, sleep-<lb/>
ers found rest cushions or couches in alcoves off the porticoes. Cooking was done on braziers in the galler-<lb/>
ies of pavilions or out-of-doors. In spirit then, if not exactly in plan, this garden was, like the Timu-rid gar-<lb/>
dens far to the east at the other end of the Islamic world, a paradisiacal campground for a people whose way of life was as closely related to landscape as to buildings.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Timurid Empire</hi></hi></head>
<p>From the <date when="1360">1360</date>s until his death in <date when="1405">1405</date>, the Turkish military genius <name type="pname">Timur</name>, or <name type="pname">Tamerlane</name> as he is known by Westerners, extended his conquests from the Mediter-<lb/>
ranean on the west to <name type="place">India</name> on the east and far into <name type="place">Russia</name>. He soon filled his Central Asian capital at <name type="place">Samarkand</name> in what is now modern <name type="place">Uzbekistan</name> with huge tile-decorated mosques and other buildings crammed with the plunder of his conquests. He espe-<lb/>
cially delighted in the creation of numerous pleasure gardens in the fertile valley around <name type="place">Samarkand</name>. Irri-<lb/>
gated by large water tanks, planted with fruit trees, sometimes furnished with dazzling tiled palace pavil-<lb/>
ions, and occupied by summer tent encampments, they were not so much tranquil refuges as magnificent places of pomp in which royal visitors were received and day-to-day business was conducted. Carpets and pillows were spread beneath embroidered silk cano-<lb/>
pies. At festivals, servants passed great leather trays heaped with roasted horsemeat, boiled mutton, spicy rice dishes, and fresh fruit among hundreds of richly dressed, bejeweled courtiers.<ref target="#CH3-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>The Timurid conquest of <name type="place">Central Asia</name> was the foundation from which the Mughal Empire sprang. The high-walled gardens of <name type="place">Samarkand</name>, filled with fruit trees and wild game, inspired <name type="pname">Timur</name>'s descendant <name type="pname">Babur</name> (<date when="1483">1483</date>&#x2013;<date when="1530">1530</date>), the founder of the Mughal dynasty, to build similar gardens at <name type="place">Kabul</name> in what is now modern <name type="place">Afghanistan</name> and at <name type="place">Agra</name> in northern <name type="place">India</name>. Also inspirational for <name type="pname">Babur</name> were the gardens at Herat in <name type="place">Afghanistan</name>, which he visited in the autumn of <date when="1506">1506</date>. There he experienced firsthand the pleasures of sophis-<lb/>
ticated courtly life in a garden setting. Recollecting Herat and the loveliness of the garden city of <name type="place">Samar-<lb/>
kand</name>, and understanding, too, the garden's political significance as a way of claiming territory, asserting legitimacy, and maintaining power, he laid out numer-<lb/>
ous gardens high in the mountains at <name type="place">Kabul</name>. There, well-watered hillsides were covered with bunch grasses and spotted with masses of wild native tulips in the spring. In this choice natural setting, <name type="pname">Babur</name> chan-<lb/>
neled natural springs into stone-lined reservoirs sur-<lb/>
mounted by platforms, and then planted many fruit trees. A typical Mughal garden can thus be envisioned in plan as an enclosed space divided into quarters, with a central water axis, a water-<lb/>
surrounded platform for one or more structures (pal-<lb/>
aces or pavilions) located in the center, and a mixture of vineyard, orchard, and flowers.</p>
<p>In the gardens of <name type="place">Kabul</name>, <name type="pname">Babur</name> entertained his warrior-nobles, planned military campaigns, cele-<lb/>
brated important events, held public audiences, com-<lb/>
posed music, and wrote poetry. The garden, in effect, became the royal court, not an adjunct to it. Although <name type="pname">Babur</name>'s successors later built fortified palaces in vari-<lb/>
ous urban centers, the festive tents and light, airy pavil-<lb/>
ions that stood upon the geometrically designed, water-laced terraces of <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">chahar baghs</hi></name>, as these quadri-<lb/>
partite compartmentalized Timurid gardens were called, remained important venues of court life.<ref target="#CH3-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p><name type="pname">Babur</name> built the Bagh-i-Vafa, or Garden of Fidelity, on an elevated site overlooking the Sorkhrud river. This garden is depicted at a greatly compressed scale in the <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">Babur-Nama</hi></name>, the illustrated manuscript of <name type="pname">Babur</name>'s memoirs commissioned by his grandson, the emperor <name type="pname">Akbar</name> (ruled <date when="1556">1556</date>&#x2013;<date when="1605">1605</date>). These paintings show run-<lb/>
nels carrying water from canals to irrigate fruit trees. Here <name type="pname">Babur</name> and his followers could walk among the flowering branches or sit beneath a silken tent or pavil-<lb/>
ion raised upon a <hi rend="italic">chabutra</hi>, a central square stone plat-<lb/>
form, above the four symbolical "rivers" that flowed beneath it (fig. 3.10). <name type="pname">Babur</name> is known to have stopped and camped here frequently with his retinue, sometimes in autumn when the pomegranates ripened.</p>
<p>As <name type="pname">Babur</name> visited the various villages in the coun-<lb/>
tryside around <name type="place">Kabul</name> and the cities en route to it, such as <name type="place">Jalalabad</name>, he frequently directed that his stopping places be laid out as gardens. Garden building and his constant movement from one garden encampment to another were important politically. His appearance in force with his armed retainers and the garden entertain-<lb/>
ments he organized helped him to assert his dominance as <hi rend="italic">Padshah</hi>, or protecting overlord, among rebellious clans.</p>
<p>It was not an easy task. <name type="pname">Babur</name> was confronted by the growing power of the Uzbeks to the north. On the east he was hemmed in by the <name type="place">Himalayas</name> and on the west by the emergent power of the Safavid dynasty in <name type="place">Persia</name>. As Timurid refugees crowded into <name type="place">Kabul</name> fol-<lb/>
lowing the capture of <name type="place">Samarkand</name> by the Uzbeks, there was only one direction in which <name type="pname">Babur</name> could turn: to the south and Hindustan, or northern <name type="place">India</name>.</p>
<pb n="109"/>
<pb n="109" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-101">
<graphic url="CH3_011.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.10. <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Babur</name> Giving Instruction for the Layout of the Bagh-i-<lb/>
Vafa</hi>, from a Mughal miniature, one side of a double page from the <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">Babur Nama</hi></name>, c. <date when="1590">1590</date>, Ms. I.M. <date when="1913">1913</date>.276A, 276 Victoria &amp; Albert Museum, <name type="place">London</name>. Here the Mughal emperor is superintending the building of a garden at <name type="place">Kabul</name>.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>In <date when="1526">1526</date>, after the Battle of <name type="place">Panipat</name>, where he defeated the <name type="place">Delhi</name> sultanate representing a collection of earlier Muslim dynasties that had consolidated power in northern <name type="place">India</name>, he was able to proclaim him-<lb/>
self <hi rend="italic">Padshah</hi> there. To solidify his triumph, he claimed for his court the former capital of the <name type="place">Delhi</name> sultanate at <name type="place">Agra</name> on the Yamuna River. In spite&#x2014;or perhaps because&#x2014;of its dry climate and harsh scenery, which filled him with disgust, he immediately set about rep-<lb/>
licating the gardens he had left behind in <name type="place">Kabul</name>. Indeed, the riverside gardens he built at <name type="place">Agra</name> were referred to as "<name type="place">Kabul</name>." And it was from this garden setting, rather than from the fortress across the river, that <name type="pname">Babur</name> ruled, once more establishing the <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">chahar bagh</hi></name> as a place of state.</p>
<p>Wherever possible, garden designers employed water in highly imaginative ways. On the plains of <name type="place">India</name>, where there were fewer mountain cascades than in <name type="place">Kabul</name>, they had to develop elaborate hydrological measures in order to furnish water channels and irrigate
<pb n="110"/>
<pb n="110" type="orig"/>
vegetation. Early Mughal gardens were supplied by ox-driven <hi rend="italic">norias</hi>. A basin, often octagonal in shape, received water from the tank and distributed it into the channels of the garden as well as into cisterns and baths. Later, engineers were able to provide water more copi-<lb/>
ously by constructing canals that tapped major rivers. Then it was possible to widen narrow channels into true watercourses and install fountains and <hi rend="italic">chadars</hi>&#x2014;masonry ramps carved in a faceted pattern in order to enliven the movement of water and increase the sparkle of refracted light.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-102">
<graphic url="CH3_012.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.11. Shalamar (Abode of Love), overlooking <name type="place">Lake Dal, Kashmir</name>, <name type="place">India</name>. Garden layout from <date when="1620">1620</date>. <hi rend="italic">Shalamar</hi> is the name of an earlier garden in this location. The present garden, which was begun by <name type="pname">Jahangir</name> <date when="1605">1605</date>&#x2013;<date when="1627">1627</date>) and continued by his son, <name type="pname">Shah Jahan</name> (ruled <date when="1627">1627</date>&#x2013;<date when="1658">1658</date>), was called <name type="pname">Farah-Baksh</name> (Bestower of Joy). <hi rend="bold">A</hi> Black Pavillion <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Twin pavillions at Entrance to Harem Garden <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Site of Diwan-i-Khas (Hall of Private Audience) <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Diwan-i-Am (Hall of Public Audience)</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Gardens of <name type="place">Kashmir</name></hi></hi></head>
<p>After <date when="1586">1586</date>, when <name type="pname">Babur</name>'s grandson <name type="pname">Akbar</name> conquered <name type="place">Kashmir</name> in the well-watered foothills of the Hima-layas, Mughal garden builders were able to freely exploit the sensuosity of water. To this favored locale of summer retreat, <name type="pname">Akbar</name> and his successors <name type="pname">Jahangir</name> (ruled <date when="1605">1605</date>&#x2013;<date when="1627">1627</date>) and <name type="pname">Shah Jahan</name> (ruled 1627&#x2013;<date when="1658">1658</date>), with their vast retinues of soldiers, horses, mules, and royal ladies borne in litters on the backs of elephants, made epic journeys from the hot, dry northern plains of <name type="place">India</name>. They traveled through hazardous mountain passes in late winter in order to arrive in time to enjoy the wildflower meadows of spring.</p>
<p>At least three of <name type="pname">Jahangir</name>'s gardens in <name type="place">Kashmir</name> still exist, the most important of which is Shalamar (the Abode of Love), a terraced garden he began laying out in <date when="1619">1619</date> in the foothills of the mountains overlooking Lake Dal (fig. 3.11). Here <name type="pname">Jahangir</name>'s engineers diverted a stream and directed the water into a broad central canal running the length of the entire garden. Shalamar originally com-<lb/>
prised three square terraces, each with a <hi rend="italic">baradari</hi>, or open-sided pavilion placed on a stone platform set in the water at the point where the canal widens to form a square pool. In passing over the garden's succession of low ter-<lb/>
race retaining walls before emptying in the lake, the canal forms a series of cascades. A line of water jets reinforces the principal axis of the canal, and in each pool more jets animate its surface. Regularly planted plane trees further emphasize Shalamar's geometrical <hi rend="italic">char-bagh</hi> layout while providing welcome shade.</p>
<p>The lowest terrace (now truncated by a modern road) is a public space dominated by the <hi rend="italic">Diwan-i-Am</hi>, or Hall of Public Audience, where the emperor received peti-<lb/>
tioners. Above it stands the emperor's garden; its central pavilion was the <hi rend="italic">Diwan-i-Khas</hi>, or Hall of Private Audi-<lb/>
ence (now vanished except for the low black marble
<pb n="111"/>
<pb n="111" type="orig"/>
throne), where members of the court were admitted (fig. 3.12). Above this is the harem garden. It is deeply shaded by two rows of plane trees, and its entrance is guarded by two small symmetrical pavilions. Where the harem garden meets the emperor's garden, horizon-<lb/>
tal slits in the stonework allow the water to flow into side pools and from these, through further slits, down into the canal in a shimmering veil over the side walls of the twin platforms flanking the cascade. In the center of a large square pool with fountain sprays, accessible only by two causeways, stands the open-sided Black Pavilion, believed to have been used as a banqueting hall (fig. 3.13). Here lateral canals create the cruciform plan of a true paradise garden, confirming the inscrip-<lb/>
tion on the pavilion: "If there is a paradise on the face of the earth, it is here, it is here, it is here."</p>
<p>Mughal garden designers were ingenious in devising ways to enhance the garden's paradisiacal atmosphere through the sensuous manipulation of water. For instance, where the water in the central canal at Shalamar drops over the retaining walls of the ter-<lb/>
races, its force projects it beyond the coping; here in the face of the wall beneath the coping, stone carvers cut small niches resembling pigeonholes, and in these ser-<lb/>
vants placed flowers on important occasions. Called <hi rend="italic">chini kanas</hi>, they also contained oil lamps to illuminate the flowing water at night.</p>
<p>In other Kashmiri gardens such as Achbal and Nishat Bagh, also on Lake Dal, <hi rend="italic">chadars</hi> enliven the passage of water wherever grade changes occur (fig. 3.14). Contrasting with the sparkle and roar of <hi rend="italic">chadars</hi>, there are serene pools. At <name type="place">Vernag</name>, located near the Banihal Pass to the Indian plain, the beauty of the site was such that only a spring-fed octagonal basin was added. From its outfall, a 1,000-foot-long canal stretches through a meadow to empty in a mountain stream beside a cedar-clad slope.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-103">
<graphic url="CH3_013.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.12. View of pool and canal from the site of the vanished <hi rend="italic">Diwan-i-Khas</hi>, Shalamar. In the distance is the <hi rend="italic">Diwan-i-Am</hi>, beyond which lies Lake Dal.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-104">
<graphic url="CH3_014.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Far left:</hi> 3.13. Black Pavilion, Shalamar. Visible at the left, the pavilion is surrounded by a square pool filled with water jets.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-105">
<graphic url="CH3_015.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 3.14. Nishat Bagh. First quarter of 17th century, period of <name type="pname">Jahangir</name>. To accommodate the abrupt grade as well as mystical numerology, twelve terraces symbolizing the twelve signs of the zodiac were built. Here the water of the principal canal is carried down successive changes of level via tall <hi rend="italic">chadars</hi>. Their patterned surfaces animate the water, making it glisten and sparkle as it falls. These carved ramps also create a pleasing pattern of light and shade when dry. Stone thrones straddle the canal above the cascades, and pairs of stairways flank them.</figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="112"/>
<pb n="112" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Mughal Tomb Gardens</hi></hi></head>
<p>The fourfold garden, elaborated by a grid of canals with <hi rend="italic">chabutras</hi> at their intersections, remained a constant form during 150 years of Mughal garden development. In the great imperial tomb gardens of the sixteenth cen-<lb/>
tury the <hi rend="italic">chabutra</hi> at the principal intersection was transformed from a mere platform into the base of a magnificent monument. Unlike the royal pleasure gar-<lb/>
dens at <name type="place">Kashmir</name>, which were terraced, with social func-<lb/>
tions assigned to each ascending level, the tomb gardens are essentially flat with only the mildest grade change to permit the gravitational flow of water throughout a grid of narrow watercourses. Water col-<lb/>
lects in the square pools and octagonal basins placed at intersections within the subdivided square grid that surrounds a central square platform. This platform&#x2014;or large-scale <hi rend="italic">chabutra</hi>&#x2014;serves as the base for an impres-<lb/>
sive mausoleum, which is often decorated with a col-<lb/>
orful inlay of semiprecious stones.</p>
<p>The first departure from the relatively modest tombs of Islamic rulers, begun in <date when="1564">1564</date>, was that of <name type="pname">Babur</name>'s successor, his aesthetically sensitive, supersti-<lb/>
tious, and pleasure-loving eldest son <name type="pname">Humayun</name>, who assumed the throne at the age of twenty-two following the great emperor's death in <date when="1530">1530</date>. The Islamic garden historian <name type="pname">James L. Wescoat</name> sums up his role as an urbanist:
<q>
<p>When <name type="pname">Humayun</name> built his palace in <name type="place">Agra Fort</name> and his city in <name type="place">Delhi</name>, he initiated a process of urban-<lb/>
ization which radically altered the meaning and function of gardens in Mughal culture. <name type="pname">Babur</name> had shunned the citadels he conquered. For reasons unknown but perhaps harkening back to the Timurid ideal of Samarquand in the 14th century, <name type="pname">Humayun</name> began to recenter Mughal social life within citadels, ornamenting and surrounding them with gardens.<ref target="#CH3-n20"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref></p>
</q></p>
<p>His widow, <name type="pname">Haji Begum</name>, commissioned the construc-<lb/>
tion of his mausoleum, which is characterized by another Mughal garden scholar, <name type="pname">Elizabeth Moynihan</name>, as being like a cosmic mountain above the four rivers of paradise represented by the garden's four water channels.<ref target="#CH3-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">21</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Inlaid stone and marble were the materials with which <name type="pname">Shah Jahan</name> built the Taj Mahal in honor of his adored wife <name type="pname">Mumtaz-i-Mahal</name> (Chosen One of the Pal-<lb/>
ace), who died in <date when="1631">1631</date> as she was bearing their four-<lb/>
teenth child (figs. 3.15, 3.16). Begun on the banks of the Jamuna in <name type="place">Agra</name> the following year, construction continued for the next sixteen. Like other monumental Mughal mausoleums, the Taj Mahal is set within a <hi rend="italic">char bagh;</hi> however, instead of occupying the traditional space at the intersection of the garden's four principal canals, the extended <hi rend="italic">chabutra</hi> supporting the mauso-<lb/>
leum was placed at the far end following the pattern to be seen at other riverfront gardens at <name type="place">Agra</name>, which has the effect of ensuring that the unforgettable lines of the remarkable structure are always seen against the sky. The tall minarets have been pulled away from the cor-<lb/>
ners of the building and set at the edge of the terrace upon which the building rests, and this ingeniously enlarges the space occupied by the building, while at the same time lightening its apparent mass. Its sky-catching dome and minarets and the well-propor-<lb/>
tioned central canal mirroring it in the water demateri-<lb/>
alize its obvious mass.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-106">
<graphic url="CH3_016.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p>Considered by many as the apotheosis of Mughal culture, the Taj Mahal is also its last important creative achievement. <name type="pname">Shah Jahan</name>, who had killed his brother to secure the throne, was deposed in <date when="1658">1658</date> by his son <name type="pname">Aurangzeb</name>, who in turn had already killed his three brothers. <name type="pname">Aurangzeb</name> had his father imprisoned in the <name type="place">Red Fort</name> on the other side of the river within sight of the
<pb n="113"/>
<pb n="113" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-107">
<graphic url="CH3_017.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.15. Taj Mahal, <name type="place">Agra</name>, <name type="place">India</name>. <date when="1632">1632</date>&#x2013;<date when="1648">48</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-108">
<graphic url="CH3_018.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 3.16. Taj Mahal</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="114"/>
<pb n="114" type="orig"/>
Taj Mahal where, after his death in <date when="1666">1666</date>, he was laid to rest beside his wife. Although the Mughal dynasty, which had been founded by <name type="pname">Babur</name> and secured in power by <name type="pname">Akbar</name>, continued to exist until overthrown by British rule in the nineteenth century, <name type="pname">Aurangzeb</name>'s religious fanati-<lb/>
cism and subsequent wars of succession depleted the resources of empire beyond recovery. The great period of Mughal architecture and garden building was over. Islamic culture, however, continued to flourish else-<lb/>
where, notably in and around <name type="pname">Constantinople</name> after the conquest of the <name type="place">Byzantine Empire</name> by the <name type="pname">Ottoman Turks</name>, and in <name type="place">Persia</name> after the restoration of its autonomy in the sixteenth century.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Turkish Gardens</hi></hi></head>
<p>The <name type="pname">Ottoman Turks</name>, a tribal people of <name type="place">Central Asia</name>, adopted Islam in the ninth century. They were used as mercenaries by both the <name type="pname">Abbasid</name> caliphs and the <name type="pname">Saljuq Turks</name>. One of the <name type="pname">Ottoman</name> warrior tribes that served the <name type="pname">Saljuqs</name> migrated into <name type="place">Asia Minor</name> in the thirteenth cen-<lb/>
tury. As <name type="place">Mongol</name> invaders undermined <name type="pname">Saljuq</name> authority in <date when="1253">1253</date>, the <name type="pname">Ottomans</name> established autonomy and initi-<lb/>
ated their own program of conquest, eventually captur-<lb/>
ing <name type="pname">Constantinople</name> in <date when="1453">1453</date>. Their victorious leader, <name type="pname">Mehmed II</name> (ruled <date when="1444">1444</date>&#x2013;<date when="1446">1446</date>; <date when="1451">1451</date>&#x2013;<date when="1481">1481</date>), renamed it <name type="place">Istanbul</name>.</p>
<p>On the ancient <name type="place">Byzantine</name> acropolis overlooking the <name type="pname">Bosporus</name> to the north and the <name type="place">Sea of Marmara</name> to the south, <name type="pname">Mehmed II</name> built the Topkapi Saray, a vast palace and garden complex, the design of which expressed an elaborate code of <name type="pname">Ottoman</name> courtly ritual and protocol. Removed from the crowded center of the city and sur-<lb/>
rounded by water on two sides and a high wall on the third, it furnished the sultan with the necessary condition of seclusion within a sanctified paradisiacal enclosure.</p>
<p>Because the sultan's orbit was strictly limited by the mystique of his inaccessibility, he depended more than other rulers did on his palace and grounds for visual stimulation and entertainment. Most of his life was spent within an inner court in sumptuously furnished apart-<lb/>
ments, library, and delightful gardens. An outer garden was planned both as an important personal statement in which the themes of power, pleasure, and paradise were interwoven and to serve as a great amusement park con-<lb/>
taining multiple stratagems to combat the boredom of a circumscribed existence.</p>
<p>Life at Topkapi centered around courtyards and gardens, pools and fountains, orchards and vineyards, harem, mosques, baths, kitchens, stables, offices, bar-<lb/>
racks, schools, and armory. Within its precincts, which were divided into men's and women's quarters, a strictly organized social hierarchy prevailed. At the top, power-<lb/>
ful viziers, representing the omnipresent but secluded sultan, conducted affairs of state and meted out justice in the name of the powerful ruler.</p>
<p>The Topkapi Saray, as it evolved in the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries, consisted of three large contig-<lb/>
uous, but not axially arranged, courts outlined by func-<lb/>
tional groupings of buildings. In addition, there were appended to the third court a private hanging garden, sometimes referred to as a fourth court, and a large exte-<lb/>
rior garden with terraces spreading to the <name type="pname">Bosporus</name> and the <name type="place">Sea of Marmara</name>. Within the exterior garden, various areas were set aside for such recreational pursuits as jav-<lb/>
elin throwing, polo, archery, hunting, and other royal pastimes. Here, too, were several kiosks for scenic view-<lb/>
ing and other pastimes.</p>
<p>The first court at Topkapi Saray was known as the Court of Processions after the processional thoroughfare leading from the <name type="pname">Hagia Sophia</name> through its imposing arched Imperial Gate. It was an open, uncluttered cere-<lb/>
monial space, less distinguished by its loosely organized surrounding architecture than by the bejeweled pomp of finely decorated horses and cavalry and the spectacle of exotic animals exhibited there on occasion. At the sec-<lb/>
ond monumental gate, which stood at the far end of the first court, those mounted on horses, with the exception of the sultan, were forced to dismount, and protocol demanded silence upon passing through its vestibule into the second court.</p>
<p>Inside, the second court proved to be an idyllic gar-<lb/>
den surrounded by a stately marble colonnade. Birds sang in the tall cypresses and other trees, and ostriches, pea-<lb/>
cocks, deer, and gazelles wandered on lawns behind red-<lb/>
painted wooden fences. Paths fanned out to the gates of various functional quarters&#x2014;commissary, kitchens, con-<lb/>
fectionery&#x2014;as well as to a range of administrative cham-<lb/>
bers&#x2014;Council Hall, chancery, archives, and treasury. At the far end of this court rose its architectural focus, the third gate, called the Gate of Felicity. Its domed canopy denoted the presence of the sultan just beyond within the third court, the private sanctum of the usually invisible ruler.</p>
<p>The third court, reserved for the royal family and inner household, as well as for the students who were being trained as the future <name type="pname">Ottoman</name> administrative elite, was sumptuously decorated. Ranging along its south-<lb/>
western side was the harem where the sultan's female family members and children lived, as well as their women attendants, servants, and the distaff administra-<lb/>
tors of these quarters. Here, as elsewhere in the vast sprawling complex, there were gardens. These included a large pool overlooking a boxwood garden and another extensive garden for the exclusive use of the women and the sultan.</p>
<p>In the sultan's private garden the Islamic genius for interweaving architecture and garden space was given full play. Here, freed from the rules of ceremony and the
<pb n="115"/>
<pb n="115" type="orig"/>
protocol of aloof reserve demanded of him, the sultan could indulge the emotional side of his nature, writing poetry, enjoying music, reading, dining with male or female companions, or watching the sporting contests below in the outer garden.</p>
<p>There were alcoves furnished with low pillowed sofas in the large, airy, luxuriously decorated <name type="pname">Revan</name> and <name type="pname">Baghdad kiosks</name> (fig. 3.17). Placed under the domes of these pavilions and within window recesses, foun-<lb/>
tains added their agreeable murmur and sparkle to the luminous interiors. Bronze fireplaces provided comfort in winter, and canvas shades lowered by pulleys pro-<lb/>
vided privacy as well as shade from the summer sun. Set upon a marble platform beside a large reflecting pool, such fantastical structures appeared to hover in space.</p>
<p>In such an environment it is not surprising that the most sensuously appealing flowers and fruits were planted. <name type="pname">Sultan S&#x00FC;leyman</name>'s account book of <date when="1564">1564</date>&#x2013;<date when="1565">65</date> refers to an orange grove, potted jasmine, and a field of carnations, while a later record speaks of renewing the jasmine pergolas near the terrace of the House of Felic-<lb/>
ity. Fruit trees of several varieties abounded, and according to the report of one foreign visitor, grapes were grown throughout the year.</p>
<p>Greco-Roman ruins were turned to good account. Many antique sarcophagi had been converted by <name type="pname">Mehmed II</name> into fountain basins, and the large Goth's Column commemorating a Roman victory against their ancient northern foes was left standing in the parklike outer garden a short distance from the gate that con-<lb/>
nected it with the hanging garden, or fourth court.</p>
<p>Extending to the shores of the triangular promon-<lb/>
tory, the outer garden consisted of a series of stepped terraces built over vaulted substructures, some of which incorporated the ruins of the <name type="place">Byzantine</name> acropolis. With its flowing fountains, fertile vineyards, beds of flowers, domed pavilions, sparkling pools, comely pages, and beautiful concubines, it must have appeared as a phys-<lb/>
ical manifestation of paradise as described in the Quran. In addition to serving as a botanical garden for a multitude of rare and delightful plants, the large outer garden also acted as a game preserve and zoological garden for many wild and domesticated animals, water-<lb/>
fowl, and songbirds.</p>
<p>Stretching outward from the medieval <name type="place">Byzantine</name> seawall, four seaside kiosks embraced the extraordi-<lb/>
nary view and provided delightful haunts wherein suc-<lb/>
cessive sultans could indulge in courtly pastimes in the company of pages, dwarfs, concubines, and an occa-<lb/>
sional visiting scholar or potentate. There were other garden kiosks beside the <name type="pname">Bosporus</name> in addition to those of Topkapi. Much admired by travelers to <name type="place">Turkey</name> in the eighteenth century for its curved dome, patterned tiles, and inlay work of marble, granite, and porphyry, the <name type="pname">Ottoman</name> kiosk was often replicated, using less opulent materials, in later Western gardens.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-109">
<graphic url="CH3_019.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.17. <name type="pname">Baghdad Kiosk</name>, in the sultan's private quarters. <date when="1639">1639</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Turkish gardens were also renowned for their extensive use of fountains. Some fountains were upright and meant to imitate the Fountain of Salsabil in the Quran, with water dripping as gently as tears from one scalloped cup into another in a series projecting from a carved marble slab. Others were noisier and provided a screen for confidential conversation. There were also, wherever necessary, ablution pools, which were usually square or rectangular basins. Thus was <name type="pname">Ottoman</name> wealth lavished upon garden art and the ideal of paradise made real.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="place">Isfahan</name>, A City of Gardens</hi></hi></head>
<p>In the century following the establishment of the <name type="pname">Otto-<lb/>
man Empire</name> at <name type="place">Istanbul</name>, <name type="pname">Shah Abbas</name> (ruled <date when="1587">1587</date>&#x2013;<date when="1629">1629</date>) of the Safavid dynasty defeated the Central Asian war-<lb/>
lords. Ten years after ascending the throne, he began to manifest <name type="place">Persia</name>'s re-established autonomy and wealth with the building of a new capital, <name type="place">Isfahan</name>, adjacent to the site of an ancient <name type="place">Achaemenid</name> city and elev-<lb/>
enth-century capital of the <name type="pname">Saljuq Turks</name>. In <date when="1598-03">March 1598</date>, <name type="pname">Shah Abbas</name> traveled from his capital at Qazvin to his palace in the ancient city of <name type="place">Isfahan</name> for the spring celebration of the Persian New Year when wildflowers briefly bloom on the high Iranian plain. With its views of lavender-colored mountains and green fields, gar-<lb/>
dens, and orchards running down to the Zaindeh River, <name type="place">Isfahan</name> furnished a spectacular site in which <name type="pname">Shah Abbas</name> could create an imperial garden city. Construc-<lb/>
tion began immediately to the south of the old town, and garden pavilions, shops, and caravansaries were erected along with public baths, schools, and mosques. An intricate terraced irrigation system was built to carry a canal the length of the 150-foot-wide (45.7-meter-wide) <name type="pname">Chahar Bagh Avenue</name>, so named because it served as the connecting spine and water
<pb n="116"/>
<pb n="116" type="orig"/>
distribution channel for the spectacular now-vanished gardens flanking this linear urban design project (fig. 3.18).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-110">
<graphic url="CH3_020.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.18. <name type="place">Isfahan</name>, <name type="place">Iran</name>. Built first quarter of the 17th century <hi rend="bold">A</hi> <name type="pname">Hezar Jarib</name> <hi rend="bold">B</hi> <name type="pname">Chahar Bagh Avenue</name> <hi rend="bold">C</hi> <name type="pname">Ali Qapu</name> <hi rend="bold">D</hi> <name type="pname">Maydan-e-Shah</name> <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Mosque</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>By the second half of the seventeenth century, <name type="place">Isfa-<lb/>
han</name> was at the height of its splendor, with a population numbering 600,000. Its plan from that period shows, to the south of the tangle of streets and welter of buildings in the old town, three main axial arrangements: the <name type="pname">May-<lb/>
dan-e-Shah</name>, or Imperial Square with its surrounding shops and royal palace on the west, the <name type="pname">Chahar Bagh Avenue</name>, and the mosques aligned to face <name type="place">Mecca</name> in con-<lb/>
formity with universal Islamic practice.</p>
<p>The chief public ground was the <name type="pname">Maydan-e-Shah</name>. Measuring approximately 1664 feet by 517 feet (507 meters by 158 meters), it served as a versatile recre-<lb/>
ational field and a place of pomp, pageantry, and public executions. This great Imperial Square was enclosed by a uniform two-story arcade housing the shops of mer-<lb/>
chants dealing in precious gems, gold, silk, and medici-<lb/>
nal drugs. Within the square itself, tents and awnings were thrown up on weekly market days for dealers sell-<lb/>
ing furs, jewelry, and pearls as well as for traders of cloth, spices, vegetables, and fruit. At such times, it was a place for prostitutes to solicit business and for jugglers, tightrope walkers, acrobats, magicians, and wrestlers to entertain crowds. Spectacular punishments took place there, providing whatever moral instruction was intended as well as satisfying the human appetite for cruelty. From a great platform supported by eighteen pillars behind the Ali Qapu, or Lofty Gateway, on the western side of the <name type="pname">Maydan-e-Shah</name>, the <name type="pname">Shah</name> and his retinue could watch polo, a game native to the Middle East, and many lively tournaments featuring feats of derring-do similar to the events of a contemporary rodeo.</p>
<pb n="117"/>
<pb n="117" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-111">
<graphic url="CH3_021.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p>The Imperial Mosque was built at the southern end of the <name type="pname">Maydan-e-Shah</name> in <date when="1612">1612</date>. Because its plan was rotated to orient the mosque toward <name type="place">Mecca</name>, <name type="pname">Shah Abbas</name>'s architects had to resolve the structural transi-<lb/>
tion between the Maydan and the mosque. This was done with the construction of a portal, an open vesti-<lb/>
bule, and two stories of <hi rend="italic">iwans</hi>, the large nichelike vaults originally conceived by the Parthians, fully developed by Sasanian architects, and deployed here and else-<lb/>
where throughout the Islamic world. This mosque is a dazzling display of Persian architectural genius. Multi-<lb/>
colored tiles, predominantly light and dark blue, cover interior walls as well as the exterior of the large dome in a richly interlacing pattern, their intricate reflective surfaces dematerializing the solid masonry beneath them.</p>
<p>Imperial storerooms and the workshops for arti-<lb/>
sans engaged in the production of fine embroideries, rugs, illuminated manuscripts, jewelry, and other pre-<lb/>
cious objects lay within the palace grounds. Instead of a single large palace, <name type="pname">Shah Abbas</name> built several garden pavilions and palaces, such as the <name type="pname">Chehel Sotun</name>, or Hall of Forty Columns, with its great open porch and easy interpenetration of outdoor and indoor living spaces (fig. 3.19). Two large square fountains guarded by four water-spouting lions were set into the floor of the great porch. The ethereal character of this structure was enhanced by brightly painted wood mosaic inlaid with mirrors as well as by its tranquil, reflective pools of water.</p>
<p>Anchored on the north by the palace grounds, the <name type="pname">Chahar Bagh Avenue</name> runs along a slightly sloping grade for nearly a mile to the river, then across a two-<lb/>
story arcaded bridge to terminate on the south in the huge royal estate known as the <name type="pname">Hezar Jarib</name>. One-hun-<lb/>
dred-eighty-feet (55-meters) wide, the Avenue was planted in <name type="pname">Shah Abbas</name>'s time with eight rows of plane trees and poplars, with roses and jasmine growing in between them. Five runnels of water divided the ave-<lb/>
nue. The large central one was lined with onyx and punctuated at each change of water level with individ-<lb/>
ually designed square or oct-agonal pools and foun-<lb/>
tains. Gardens built by courtiers and rich merchants bordered this promenade on either side. These were entered through small pavilions. Larger pavilions with such evocative names as Garden of the Vineyard, Mul-<lb/>
berry Garden, and Garden of the Nightingale stood in the center of each. Passersby on the <name type="pname">Chahar Bagh Ave-<lb/>
nue</name> could glimpse these now mostly vanished gardens through latticework walls and, for a small price, gain entrance. Tantalizing descriptions of their contents come from visitors to the Safavid court.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-112">
<graphic url="CH3_022.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.19. <name type="pname">Chehel Sotun</name>, <name type="place">Isfahan</name>, with dome and minarets of the Royal Mosque in the distance. From <hi rend="italic">Voyage en Perse</hi> by <name type="pname">E. Flandin</name> and <name type="pname">P. Coste</name>, <date when="1851">1851</date></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Extending the <name type="pname">Chahar-Bagh</name> axis was the bridge with its thirty-three arches and, on the south side of the
<pb n="118"/>
<pb n="118" type="orig"/>
river, 3-mile-long garden-bordered avenue. It led to <name type="pname">Shah Abbas</name>'s <hi rend="italic">pairidaeza</hi>, the <name type="pname">Bagh-e Hezar Jarib</name>, which according to French jeweler <name type="pname">Jean Chardin</name>, who visited the city around <date when="1670">1670</date>, was a mile square and laid out in twelve terraces. A tree-<lb/>
lined road to the west connected this garden with the <name type="pname">Bagh-e Farahabad</name> (Abode of Joy), built for <name type="pname">Shah Sultan Husayn</name> (ruled <date when="1694">1694</date>&#x2013;<date when="1722">1722</date>) around <date when="1700">1700</date>. This garden contained large pools with islands supporting summer pavilions.</p>
<p>A teeming center of aristocratic privilege and commerce, <name type="place">Isfahan</name>, with its extraordinary site and numerous gardens, combined secular commerce with the Muslim ideal of paradise, harnessing water to bring lushness to the high desert. Less overtly sensuous, but as culturally pervasive was the Christian manifestation of paradise in land-<lb/>
scape terms as an enclosed, inward-focused realm informed with religious symbolism.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">III. Paradise Contained: Walled Cities and Walled Gardens of the European Middle Ages</hi></hi></head>
<p>After the fall of the western provinces of the Roman Empire in the fifth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, followed by the advance of Islam in the Mediterranean basin, civiliza-<lb/>
tion became more highly regionalized throughout <name type="place">Europe</name>. Without centralized administration over these former imperial territories, the great road and aqueduct systems built by the ancient Romans fell into partial disuse and extensive disrepair, and as we shall see in Chapter Four, the capital itself shrank within its walls. The disruption caused by successive challenges to cen-<lb/>
tralized power produced new kinds of reciprocal rela-<lb/>
tionships in relation to land tenure, an economic and social system often characterized as "feudal."</p>
<p>Like <name type="pname">C&#x00F3;rdoba</name> and the Islamic centers of learning, monasteries continued to serve as repositories of knowledge, and many ancient Roman towns were per-<lb/>
petuated as episcopal seats. The Carolingian period, lasting from the middle of the eighth century into the tenth century, helped to reanimate in a limited fashion some of the grandeur of ancient Roman cities, which now served as the fortified settlements and seats of bishops and counts. The Cistercian monastic revival of the eleventh century promoted agricultural improve-<lb/>
ments, which in turn stimulated the regrowth of cities. By the middle of the eleventh century, revived mari-<lb/>
time trade boosted the fortunes of <name type="place">Genoa</name>, <name type="place">Pisa</name>, and <name type="place">Venice</name>, which began its dazzling rise from watery ref-<lb/>
uge to immensely prosperous mercantile center. In the Low Countries and along the Baltic and North Sea coasts as well as in the valleys of the Rh&#x00F4;ne, Rhine, and Danube, conditions were also favorable for the rise of towns as centers of production and trade. <name type="pname">Constan-<lb/>
tinople</name>, capital of the Eastern Roman Empire, remained an important center for crafts manufacture and the international exchange of goods, and this was a stimulus to trade in the West.</p>
<p>In the late Middle Ages, beginning in the elev-<lb/>
enth century and accelerating as <name type="place">Europe</name> recovered from the effects of the Black Death in the middle of the fourteenth century, there was a revival of trade and the emergence of banking houses. This was coupled with a wary but growing conviction on the part of feudal lords that a stimulus to their own prosperity lay in franchises granted to independent towns from which they could obtain handsome revenues. Seeking greater independence from feudal lords, townspeople formed trade guilds and municipal councils. As a powerful merchant class came into being and cities became more prosperous through trade, their jeal-<lb/>
ously guarded privileges exempted them from control by the Church or local barons. Our survey of Euro-<lb/>
pean cities in the Middle Ages is necessarily limited to this last late flowering of urbanism during the period often termed <hi rend="italic">Gothic</hi> and comprising roughly the late twelfth through the fifteenth centuries.</p>
<p>Like most cities heretofore throughout history, these medieval ones were necessarily walled for rea-<lb/>
sons of defense. Girdled towns stood in stony contrast to their surrounding fields. Towered castles and church spires etched their profiles on the otherwise unpunctuated skyline. The inward-focused peristyle garden of <name type="place">Rome</name> became the medieval cloister garden, a paradisiacal jewel within the bosom of the monastic precinct. This stout containment of various units of the built environment, with some walled structures nest-<lb/>
ing within others, was obviously done for reasons of security. But such enclosure can also be read as an expression of the way in which medieval intellectuals sought to order knowledge within a self-contained framework.</p>
<p>The Dominican monk <name type="pname">Thomas Aquinas</name> (<date when="1225">1225</date>&#x2013;<date when="1274">1274</date>), the most influential theologian and philosopher of the Late Middle Ages, brought Christian doctrine and Aristotelian logic into a syncretic intellectual sys-<lb/>
tem. By inquiring into the nature of nature, he laid the foundations of the scientific revolution. His approach to knowledge was not one of open-ended speculation, but rather one that attempted to order all knowledge into a comprehensive, God-ordained harmony of parts, or <hi rend="italic">summa</hi>. Although it served as an expandable framework, <name type="pname">Aquinas</name>'s system was, like that of <name type="pname">Aristo-<lb/>
tle</name>, a closed one based on the notion of an Aristotelian
<pb n="119"/>
<pb n="119" type="orig"/>
geocentric universe in which all matter was spherically contained within Earth and its surrounding atmosphere and all contents ultimately knowable.</p>
<p>The Late Middle Ages was a period in which reli-<lb/>
gious allegory flourished and sharp distinctions were drawn between good and evil, heaven and hell, human and divine. Paradise was an ever present and almost palpable cultural concept. But the route to paradise lay through earthly travail and self-denial, and the blessed abode necessarily remained an invisible vision, a viv-<lb/>
idly imagined reward for faith and endurance of the trials of this life. Virtues and vices were personified and paired in opposition to one another. This Christian the-<lb/>
ology was illuminated in manuscripts, carved in the stones of cathedrals, fashioned into stained-glass win-<lb/>
dows, and depicted in fresco and mosaic on wall sur-<lb/>
faces.</p>
<p>The great epic poem of the period, <name type="pname">Dante</name>'s <hi rend="italic">The Divine Comedy</hi> of <date when="1321">1321</date>, joined Christian theology and classical astronomy into a vast symbolic structure. <name type="pname">Dante</name>'s reordering of pagan cosmology into a moral drama was, like the system of <name type="pname">Aquinas</name>, both all-em-<lb/>
bracing and self-contained. Since Christian teaching encouraged the sublimation of sexual desire to reli-<lb/>
gious belief, <name type="pname">Dante</name>'s <name type="pname">Beatrice</name> is an ideal of virtuous womanhood, his virginal guide to paradise. As in the <hi rend="italic">Romance of the Rose</hi>, physical love in <hi rend="italic">The Divine Comedy</hi> is hedged in, contained, like a garden sur-<lb/>
rounded by a high wall or fence. The concept of enclo-<lb/>
sure was so inherent a part of the medieval garden that a gate and fence, with only a few rudimentary plants inside, became its convenient graphic symbol (see fig. 3.2).</p>
<p>Although the values that the late medieval world portrayed were decidedly spiritual, the period was remarkably full of worldly energy and new advances in technology. Entrepreneurial capitalism had begun to supersede feudalism. Human nature asserted itself lust-<lb/>
fully as well as spiritually, and gardens served not only as symbolical representations of paradise but also as aristocratic preserves for lovemaking. Horticulture as a craft was re-established, and the foundations of Renaissance science and humanism were laid as this cultural era drew to its dynamic close.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Walled Cities</hi></hi></head>
<p>More than merely defensive units for the protection of local populations, the European walled cities of the Late Middle Ages were active centers to which the privilege of entry for the purpose of doing business was granted to outsiders. Toll revenues collected at their gates from peasant farmers coming to market or merchants from abroad formed a substantial part of their wealth. Their organic growth patterns along major routes within and immediately outside their walls reflect the burgeoning medieval market economy.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-113">
<graphic url="CH3_023.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.20. Plan of 17th-century <name type="place">Mainz</name>, <name type="place">Germany</name>, showing walls and fortifications. The military technology that occasioned the construction of walls as earth-works and bastions with arrow-headlike projections did not occur until the sixteenth century. At that time, cannon fire rendered obsolete high crenellated walls and machicolated towers with floor openings from which molten lead, boiling oil, or missiles could be dropped on attackers advancing with battering rams.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-114">
<graphic url="CH3_024.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 3.21. Bridge, walls, and towers of Toledo, <name type="place">Spain</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Because the growing towns existed as islands within the uncertain seas of feudal combat and local rebellion, their safety depended upon high, thick walls with crenellations, which shielded the archers defend-<lb/>
ing them (fig. 3.20). Round or square towers punctuated these walls at intervals of every hundred feet or so. Small openings cut into the towers permitted a wide range of crossfire when a town was under siege. Gates, the necessary portals of the city, were inevitably the weak points of a town wall. They were therefore doubly guarded by massive flanking towers. Because towns often grew on both sides of a river, the two ends where the river bisected the walls also received additional for-<lb/>
tification in the form of strong towers, as did the ends of bridges leading to walled towns built on a single riv-<lb/>
erbank (fig. 3.21). Not all of the newly created towns that sprang up in the eleventh-and twelfth-century urban revolution were initially built with these walls. But for successful towns, particularly those that devel-<lb/>
oped under royal or ecclesiastical aegis, investment in massive fortifications was imperative.</p>
<pb n="120"/>
<pb n="120" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-115">
<graphic url="CH3_025.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.22. <name type="place">Campo</name>, <name type="place">Siena</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Inasmuch as the construction of monumental walls and towers represented public works projects of considerable magnitude, medieval cities were usually made as compact as possible in order to minimize their circumference and hence the extent of their perimeter fortifications. This and the imperatives of the city's market economy dictated a rounded urban form with radial streets emanating from a central square and trading area to its several gates. In former Roman colonial cities, these radial thoroughfares simply surrounded and fed into the grid with its ancient <hi rend="italic">cardo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">decumanus</hi> and became organi-<lb/>
cally integrated with its pre-existing street pattern (see fig. 2.23). Around the central market square, town halls were built when the administrative func-<lb/>
tions of increasingly complex urban units made civil governance a necessity. In the jockeying for position within the medieval city, in which site occupancy denoted relative degrees of urban power, the most powerful guild halls received greater centrality. The cloth hall wherein the wool trade&#x2014;the mainstay of the medieval economy&#x2014;was conducted, often boasted a pre-eminent location. If the town was an important episcopal seat, sometimes the main square was dominated by a cathedral; however, cathedrals were often sited a short distance away at the point where the old grid and the newer medieval urban fab-<lb/>
ric commingled. In such a location there would develop a cathedral square, and inevitably certain regional and temporary market functions would coalesce around and within it.</p>
<p>Additional market squares developed, some close to the center, some adjacent to parish churches, and others near the town's principal gates. The last came about because, once inside the walls, those granted the privilege of doing business in the town created a public trading area in the most immediately convenient location. Because the towns were, in effect, market organisms built for the production and trade of goods&#x2014;with home, workshop, and salesroom combined within the same structure&#x2014;there was considerable competition for space throughout. Streets could be narrow, and houses often encroached upon their boundaries or pushed upper stories into the space above them. The medieval street might thus acquire a highly irregular &#x2014;and to later eyes picturesque&#x2014;character.</p>
<p>In such notable instances as <name type="place">Florence</name> and <name type="place">Siena</name>, civic pride&#x2014;the luxury of late medieval prosper-<lb/>
ity&#x2014;began to assert itself. An urban aesthetics that was specific to individual cities became apparent. In <name type="place">Florence</name>, where there already existed the example of a Roman orthogonal grid with its <hi rend="italic">cardo, decumanus</hi>, and central forum, citizens sought beautiful, wide, straight streets. Streets received more sunlight after the imposition of building codes governing balconies and other projections. In <name type="place">Siena</name>, hilly topography con-<lb/>
spired with the elegant curvilinear Gothicism that remained a local ideal in art as well as town planning, with the result that building lines were made to con-<lb/>
form to the gentle arcs of its principal thoroughfares and shell-shaped central Campo (fig. 3.22).</p>
<p>With prosperity, medieval towns became increasingly dense; however, there was still within their walls a good deal of green open space. Behind dwellings, yards contained animals, fruit trees, and kitchen gardens. In the wedge-shaped areas between the radial streets there was room, particularly near the periphery of the town, to site new abbeys and monas-<lb/>
teries. As surging enterprise drew an illiterate and impoverished peasantry from the surrounding coun-<lb/>
tryside, mendicant orders, such as those of the Fran-<lb/>
ciscans and Dominicans, arose in response to the increasingly turbulent, uneasy, and afflicted life of medieval cities. These orders were dedicated to main-<lb/>
taining the social order, suppressing heresy, and min-<lb/>
istering to the population through preaching and caring for the sick and the indigent. They formed hospices and hospitals on remaining open lands in the less trafficked zones between the major thorough-<lb/>
fares and near the peripheries of cities. Here another medieval innovation, the urban university, found sim-<lb/>
ilar accommodation. Although these institutions had long been considered the province of the Church, in the cities, where wealth was independent of ecclesi-<lb/>
astical patronage, they soon acquired independent status. The public bath reappeared, becoming a late medieval center of relaxation and social intercourse.</p>
<p>The market forces governing the growth of cities in the eleventh and twelfth centuries were often dynamic enough to stimulate development outside the walls as well as within. Suburban settlements known as <hi rend="italic">faubourgs</hi> sprang up in the zones immediately out-<lb/>
side certain principal gates even before the towns became crowded inside.<ref target="#CH3-n22"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref> Because the taxes imposed
<pb n="121"/>
<pb n="121" type="orig"/>
upon those doing business within the town walls could be avoided here, lively market squares formed within them. As the growing cities within the walls exerted pressure to expand, and as this need combined with their desire to annex the profitable <hi rend="italic">faubourgs</hi>, a new band of walls was built enclosing the area occupied by one or, often, several <hi rend="italic">faubourgs</hi>. This situation, from the point of view of the <hi rend="italic">faubourg</hi> residents, was also desirable since, offsetting the burden of taxation, true citizenship brought with it various legal privileges, economic advantages, and greater physical security. With the cre-<lb/>
ation of the new walls, the old inner circle of walls was usually, though not always, removed, and a new cycle of <hi rend="italic">faubourg</hi> creation began near the gates along the redrawn town periphery.</p>
<p>Although enjoying a large degree of communal autonomy, medieval cities and towns were still embed-<lb/>
ded within the larger power structure in which the king and other great secular magnates held sway, retaining their holdings through military prowess. Living off revenues generated by the city as well as the countryside, feudal lords had interests that were funda-<lb/>
mentally inimical to those of the townspeople. Never-<lb/>
theless, they, along with the king, served as military protectors, a role that was effectively expressed in the defensive architecture of the castle and its protective siting on a hillside above the town. Alternatively, princes and bishops built residences in strategic loca-<lb/>
tions at vulnerable positions within the fortified walls. Though situated within cities, these aristocratic com-<lb/>
pounds were not part of urban life, acting as barriers to public circulation and obstacles to the towns' natural development.</p>
<p>Most of the maps and views of medieval cities are not medieval; they are, as a rule, engravings of the six-<lb/>
teenth and seventeenth centuries. But, because street patterns are typically resistant to alteration and urban structural turnover in pre-industrial times was slow, these nevertheless serve as fairly accurate plans and per-<lb/>
spectives of medieval towns (see fig. 3.20). Today the historic gates or portals depicted in these engravings survive only as monuments and place-names, commem-<lb/>
orating former walls. Although a few walled medieval cities still exist, their walls are tourist attractions and no longer function as barriers to entry. In cities that have continued to experience periods of growth, such as <name type="place">Paris</name>, <name type="place">Vienna</name>, and <name type="place">Florence</name>, former walls can be traced as boulevards and ring roads.</p>
<p>Beyond security and taxation&#x2014;the primary func-<lb/>
tional reasons for urban enclosure&#x2014;there were sym-<lb/>
bolical and psychological reasons for the inward focus of medieval cities and the institutions and structures within them. The cathedral itself was a sanctuary enclosing a sacred mystery. In this regard, it was not unlike the nature sanctuaries of antiquity; its cool, dim interior was analogous to that of a cave or grotto. Out-<lb/>
side many churches, behind the apse, there was often a space called "paradise" where flowers to decorate altars, statues, and shrines were grown. Within cloister gardens, in addition to the four paths emanating from a central fountain or well like the biblical rivers of the Garden of <name type="place">Eden</name>, fruit trees and other plants symbolized the renewal of life in the green groves of heaven. Thus, like the <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">chahar bagh</hi></name>, which was a physical and sym-<lb/>
bolical manifestation of the Islamic paradise described in the Quran, the quadripartite cloister garden was emblematic of the equally idyllic (if less sybaritic) par-<lb/>
adise found in the Hebrew and Christian Bible.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Walled Gardens</hi></hi></head>
<p>In the medieval garden the best productions of wild nature were concentrated and enhanced through hus-<lb/>
bandry and horticulture. Game, fish, fruit, grapes for winemaking, and flowers were found there. The medi-<lb/>
eval garden was also meant to be a <hi rend="italic">locus amoenus</hi>, an earthly paradise, a sanctified spot from which the wicked (or uninitiated) were excluded, the province of such deserving souls as princes, poets, and lovers as well as monks and gardeners (fig. 3.23).</p>
<p>In horticulture, as in so many other areas, Euro-<lb/>
pean knowledge declined after the eclipse of Roman civilization. We have seen how Arabic scholarship at <name type="pname">C&#x00F3;rdoba</name> kept alive ancient agricultural practices inher-<lb/>
ited from antiquity. A great boost to the revival of hor-<lb/>
ticulture in the West occurred when the Bolognese lawyer <name type="pname">Piero de' Crescenzi</name> (<date when="1230">1230</date>&#x2013;<date when="1305">1305</date>) wrote his <hi rend="italic">Liber ruralium commodorum</hi> consisting of twelve books on the practical aspects of agriculture (fig. 3.24). <name type="pname">Crescenzi</name> was an early participant in the rediscovery of classical writing. His treatise relied substantially on the works of such ancients as <name type="pname">Cato</name> the Elder (234&#x2013;149 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), <name type="pname">Marcus Terentius Varro</name> (116&#x2013;27 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), and <name type="pname">Lucius Columella</name> (first century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) as well as <hi rend="italic">De veg-<lb/>
etabilibus</hi> by <name type="pname">Albertus Magnus</name> (c. <date when="1200">1200</date>&#x2013;<date when="1280">1280</date>), written a half century earlier.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-116">
<graphic url="CH3_026.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.23. <hi rend="italic">Maugis &amp; Orlande in a Garden</hi>. Miniature from manuscript 5072, folio 71 of Renaud de Montauben, Bruges. <date when="1462">1462</date>&#x2013;<date when="1470">70</date>. Biblioth&#x00E8;que Nationale, <name type="place">Paris</name>. Turf benches were common features in medieval gardens.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb n="122"/>
<pb n="122" type="orig"/>
<figure xml:id="fig-117">
<graphic url="CH3_027.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.24. <hi rend="italic">Crescentius Discussing Herb Planting</hi>,_ detail of a_page from "<hi rend="italic">Le Livre des prouffis champestres et ruraux</hi>," a Bruges manuscript painted by the Master of <name type="pname">Margaret</name> of <name type="place">York</name>, c. <date when="1470">1470</date>. Ms. 232, folio 157. The Pierpont Morgan Library, <name type="place">New York</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-118">
<graphic url="CH3_028.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 3.25. Schematic plan for the monastery at <name type="pname">St. Gall</name>, <name type="place">Switzerland</name>, c. 819. Drawing after a 9th-century manuscript illustration. Near the lower right-hand corner is a vegetable garden with eighteen rectangular beds carefully labeled with the names of various types of produce. Next to this garden lay the cemetery, which was also the orchard. The herb garden in the upper right-hand corner of the plan is located logically next to the infirmary. Until the rise of medical schools in the late Middle Ages, when a new professional class tried to outlaw the practice of monastic medicine, monks acted as physicians not only within their own communities but also to patients from outside the monastery. The medicines that they and the trained doctors who were their successors used were herbal ones, and the pharmacopoeia they derived from plants was extensive.</figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Presented, like <name type="pname">Columella</name>'s first-century treatise, as a series of books on the practical aspects of farming and estate management (including site selection and overall layout of domicile, farm buildings, orchards, and gardens), its value to us is twofold: first, as a description of medieval gardening practices and design and, second&#x2014;because of the numerous illustrated manuscript and published editions&#x2014;as a visual source of the ideal, if not the actual, appearance of many medieval gardens. It is primarily a "how-to" manual, detailing the proper ways of tilling the soil, sowing and reaping crops, growing fruit and shade trees, tending vines, making wine, and managing livestock, fish, and game. While <name type="pname">Piero</name> gives prescriptions, rather than descriptions, of actual gardens, it is fair to assume that the gated walls, square planting beds, vine-clad arbors and trellises, flowery turf benches, fountains and well-<lb/>
tended fruit trees that we see in illustrations of the <hi rend="italic">Liber ruralium commodorum</hi> reflect the appearance of actual medieval gardens in his day and later. What is most apparent in studying these manuscript paintings and early book prints is the absence of spatial compo-<lb/>
sition. The principle of subordinating the garden's parts to an overall plan in which spatial considerations are paramount does not seem to govern their layout.
<pb n="123"/>
<pb n="123" type="orig"/>
These are gardens of objects&#x2014;plants, walks, and structures&#x2014;the arrangement of which is primarily for utility and the pleasure they afford in and of them-<lb/>
selves.</p>
<p>Indeed, most medieval gardens were utilitarian arrangements designed to provide cooking and medicinal herbs, fruit, and vegetables. Although con-<lb/>
siderably earlier than the period we are examining here, the ninth-century Plan of <name type="pname">St. Gall</name> showing the ideal layout of a monastery was probably a valid pro-<lb/>
totype for similar Late Medieval communities (fig. 3.25). The <name type="pname">St. Gall</name> scheme is probably more orderly than the gardens in real monasteries, where vegeta-<lb/>
bles were often grown in the random spaces around the various workshops and in individually tilled plots behind the monks' cells.</p>
<p>Most of the great rural monasteries have van-<lb/>
ished, but there are still to be found within certain urban monasteries and convents, like carefully guarded jewels, old cloister gardens with the sancti-<lb/>
fied atmosphere of medieval times. Notable among these are three in <name type="place">Rome</name>: that of the <name type="place">Basilica of SS. Quattro Coronati</name> (Four Crowned Saints) (fig. 3.26), that of <name type="pname">St. John</name> in the Lateran, and that of <name type="pname">St. Paul</name>'s Outside the Walls. The colonnettes framing the clois-<lb/>
ter garden are often twisted or braided and inlaid with glittering bits of mosaic in the decorative style known as Cosmatesque.</p>
<p>Between these and two other Roman cloister gardens&#x2014;that of <name type="pname">S. Giovanni Battista dei Genovesi</name> and that of the <name type="pname">Palazzetto Venezia</name>&#x2014;a profound sty-<lb/>
listic change is evident. Although the cloister's basic form and intended symbolism remain unaltered, one senses in these the influence of the theories of <name type="pname">Leone Battista Alberti</name> (<date when="1404">1404</date>&#x2013;<date when="1472">1472</date>), the great humanist scholar, poet, mathematician, and architect, who pro-<lb/>
moted the development of an architectural style along principles derived from classical antiquity. In these early Renaissance examples, the decoratively con-<lb/>
ceived, comparatively insubstantial colonnettes of the earlier cloister gardens have given way to solid, unadorned columns with simple foliated capitals derived from ancient Roman architecture.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-119">
<graphic url="CH3_029.jpg"/>
<figDesc>3.26. Cloister Garden, <name type="pname">SS. Quattro Coronati</name>, <name type="place">Rome</name>. Early 13th century, with a 12th-century fountain</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure xml:id="fig-120">
<graphic url="CH3_030.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below</hi>; 3.27. Fra Angelico, <hi rend="italic">The Annunciation</hi>. <date when="1435">1435</date>&#x2013;<date when="1445">45</date>. Tempera on panel. The Prado, <name type="place">Madrid</name></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Even devout men like painter Fra Angelico found inspiration in the forms of pagan antiquity, as is evident in his contemporary panel of <hi rend="italic">The Annunci-<lb/>
ation</hi> (c. <date when="1440">1440</date>&#x2013;<date when="1450">50</date>) (fig. 3.27). Like other painters of his day, Fra Angelico was influenced by the theory and practice of <name type="pname">Alberti</name> as he began to define three-di-<lb/>
mensional spaces for his figures to inhabit. <name type="pname">Mary</name> is depicted in an enclosed convent garden, a symbol of her virginity and a paradisiacal space, or "third" nature, elevated in meaning above the cultivated fields of "second" nature and the fearful connotations of wilderness, or "first" nature. However, the archi-<lb/>
tecture of the loggia where the heavenly visitation occurs is similar in style to that which we will exam-<lb/>
ine in the next chapter in our discussion of the Renais-<lb/>
sance villa and its interweaving of landscape and architectural space. To understand better the import-<lb/>
ant changes that were occurring in the relationship between human beings and the landscape and the ways in which the concept of three natures was elab-<lb/>
orated by allegory at this time, it will be necessary to look more closely at the cultural and intellectual movement called humanism.</p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<pb n="124"/>
<pb n="124" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Three</hi></hi></head>
<note xml:id="CH3-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p>According to <name type="pname">Xenophon</name> (c. 430&#x2013;c. 355 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), the Greek soldier, writer, and disciple of <name type="pname">Socrates</name>, Persian parks also served as open spaces for the purpose of flood control and as "parade grounds" in which to muster the army. In Hebrew, the word <hi rend="italic">pardes</hi>, meaning also park or garden, became associated in apoca-<lb/>
lyptic and rabbinical tradition with a blessed place where the virtuous dead receive their reward. In the transformation of the Persian <hi rend="italic">pairidaeza</hi> to the Greek <hi rend="italic">paradeisos</hi>, the word gained the connotation of a garden or, rather, two specific gardens: the Abode of the Blessed Dead and, in the literature of postbiblical times, the Garden of <name type="place">Eden</name>. The Latin <hi rend="italic">paradisus</hi> appropriated the three meanings of the Greek <hi rend="italic">paradeisos:</hi> garden or park (ordinary gardens for the practice of horticulture as well as enclo-<lb/>
sures for wild animals); celestial paradise (Heaven); and earthly paradise (the Garden of <name type="place">Eden</name>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p>_<hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi>_2: 8&#x2013;10 (The New English Bible).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p>Ibid.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Homer</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Odyssey</hi>, trans. <name type="pname">Robert Fitzger-<lb/>
ald</name> (Garden City, <name type="place">New York</name>: Doubleday &amp; Company, <date when="1961">1961</date>), lines 561&#x2013;68, p. 81.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Homer</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Odyssey</hi>. "The Garden of Alci-<lb/>
nous," trans. <name type="pname">Robert M. Torrance</name>. <hi rend="italic">Encompass-<lb/>
ing Nature: A Sourcebook</hi>, ed. <name type="pname">Robert M. Torrance</name> (<name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>: Counterpoint, <date when="1998">1998</date>), p. 281.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Hesiod</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Works and Days</hi>. "The Five Ages," trans. <name type="pname">Apostolos Athanassakis</name>. In <hi rend="italic">The Norton Book of Ciassical Literature</hi>, ed. <name type="pname">Ber-<lb/>
nard Knox</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: W.W. Norton &amp; Com-<lb/>
pany, <date when="1993">1993</date>), p. 193.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p>Dracontius, <hi rend="italic">De Laudibus Dei</hi>,_Book I. "The Earthly Paradise," trans. <name type="pname">Robert M. Torrance</name>. In <hi rend="italic">Encompassing Nature: A Sourcebook</hi> (<name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>: Counterpoint, <date when="1998">1998</date>), p. 600.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p>Ibid., p. 601.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p>Sura 76. The Koran,_trans. <name type="pname">N. J. Dawood</name>. (<name type="place">Harmondsworth, Middlesex, England</name>: Pen-<lb/>
guin, 4th rev. ed., <date when="1974">1974</date>), p. 18.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Firdausi</name>, <name type="pname"><hi rend="italic">Shahnamih</hi></name>, I, 157. As quoted in <name type="pname">William L._Hanaway, Jr.</name>, "Paradise on Earth" in <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Garden</hi> (<name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>: Dumbarton Oaks and Trustees for Harvard University, <date when="1976">1976</date>), p. 53.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p>The Song of Songs 4:12</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Claudian</name>, <hi rend="italic">Epithalamium de Nuptiis Honorii Augusti</hi>, lines 78&#x2013;85, trans. <name type="pname">A. Bartlett Gia-<lb/>
matti</name>. In A. Bartlett Giamatti, <hi rend="italic">The Earthly Para-<lb/>
dise and the Renaissance Epic</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, <date when="1966">1966</date>) Norton paper-<lb/>
back edition, p. 51.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Giovanni Boccaccio</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Decameron</hi>, trans. <name type="pname">G.H. McWilliam</name> (<name type="place">Harmondsworth, Mid-<lb/>
dlesex, England</name>: Penguin, <date when="1972">1972</date>), p. 233.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p>For a discussion of the etymology of the word <hi rend="italic">garden</hi>, which represents the notion of separation from, and enhancement of, nature, see <name type="pname">John Dixon Hunt</name>, <hi rend="italic">Greater Perfections</hi> (<name type="place">Philadelphia</name>: University of Pennsylvania Press, <date when="1999">1999</date>). Here, too, the reader will find treated the relationship between landscape design and literature in various cultures throughout history.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p>For an excellent discussion of gardens of Islamic <name type="place">Spain</name> and their relationship to the sur-<lb/>
rounding landscape both literally and symboli-<lb/>
cally, see <name type="pname">D. Fairchild Ruggles</name>, <hi rend="italic">Gardens, Landscape, and Vision in the Palaces of Islamic <name type="place">Spain</name></hi> (<name type="place">University Park, Pennsylvania</name>: The Pennsylvania State University Press, <date when="2000">2000</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p>The word <hi rend="italic">alc&#x00E1;zar</hi> is derived from the Arabic word <hi rend="italic">al-qasr</hi>, which means "fortress."</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p>According to 1 Kings, 7:23&#x2013;26, the temple of <name type="pname">King Solomon</name> had a large basin that rested on the backs of twelve oxen. Between 1056 and 1066, <name type="pname">Yusuf</name>, a Jewish vizier in <name type="place">Granada</name>, which was then controlled by the <name type="pname">Zirids</name>, the Berber clan whose caliphs ruled from 1013 until they were conquered by the Almoravids in 1090, built a magnificent palace and garden with a fountain that was likened by a contem-<lb/>
porary poet to that of <name type="pname">Solomon</name>, except that "&#x2026; not on oxen it stands, / But there are lions, in phalanx by its rim&#x2026; / Whose bellies are well-<lb/>
springs that spout forth / through their mouths floods like streams." Although it is not possible to support with certainty the claim of one scholar (<name type="pname">Frederick Bargebuhr</name>) that the lions of this very fountain were reused to support the fourteenth-century, twelve-sided basin of the fountain in the Court of the Lions, the sophisti-<lb/>
cated Islamic and Jewish elite who saw the fountain in the Court of the Lions at that time would have readily associated with royal Solo-<lb/>
monic imagery its inscription: "For truly, what else is this fountain but a beneficent cloud pouring out its abundant supplies over the lions underneath? / Like the hands of the Caliph when he rises in the morning to distribute plen-<lb/>
tiful rewards among his soldiers the lions of war." For a good discussion of the implied sym-<lb/>
bolism of the fountain in the Court of the Lions, see <name type="pname">D. Fairchild Ruggles</name>, <hi rend="italic">Gardens, Land-<lb/>
scape, and Vision in the Palaces of Islamic <name type="place">Spain</name></hi>, pp. 163&#x2013;166, 199&#x2013;200, 213.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p>The Spanish ambassador to the court of <name type="pname">Tamerlane</name>, <name type="pname">Ruy Gonz&#x00E9;lez de Clavijo</name> (d. 1412), left a description of these festive gatherings and of the gardens in which they took place. See <name type="pname">Ruy Gonz&#x00E9;lez de Clavijo</name>, <hi rend="italic">Embassy to <name type="pname">Tamerlane</name>, <date when="1403">1403</date>&#x2013;<date when="1406">1406</date></hi>, trans. <name type="pname">Guy Le Strange</name> (<name type="place">London</name>: G. Routledge, <date when="1928">1928</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p>As this garden type moved from <name type="place">Central Asia</name> into northern <name type="place">India</name>, <hi rend="italic">chahar</hi>, meaning "four," and <hi rend="italic">bagh</hi>, meaning "garden" underwent a slight spelling change. Thus, the fourfold Mughal garden in <name type="place">India</name> is known as a <hi rend="italic">char bagh</hi>.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">20.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">James L. Wescoat</name>, "Gardens of invention and exile: The precarious context of Mughal garden design during the reign of <name type="pname">Humayun</name> (<date when="1530">1530</date>&#x2013;<date when="1556">1556</date>)," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Garden History</hi>. vol. 10, no. 2, p. 114.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">21.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Elizabeth B. Moynihan</name>, <hi rend="italic">Paradise as a Gar-<lb/>
den in <name type="place">Persia</name> and Mughal <name type="place">India</name></hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: George Braziller, <date when="1979">1979</date>), p. 112.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH3-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">22.</hi></seg><p>In <name type="place">France</name>, these newly urbanized zones were called <hi rend="italic">faubourgs</hi>, from the Old French <hi rend="italic">fors</hi>, meaning "outside," and <hi rend="italic">borc</hi>, the archaic "town." Hence, when we speak today of the districts of <name type="place">Paris</name> known as Faubourg Saint-Ger-<lb/>
main or Faubourg Saint-Antoine, we are refer-<lb/>
ring to parts of the city that were outside the old walls.</p></note>
</div>
</div>
</div>
