<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/html/tei.xsl"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY</title>
                <author>ELIZABETH BARLOW ROGERS</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>HARRY N. ABRAMS, INC.,</publisher>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY by ELIZABETH BARLOW
                    ROGERS</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div type="chapter"><pb n="165"/><pb n="165" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER FIVE</hi> POWER AND GLORY: THE GENIUS OF <name type="pname">LE N&#x00D4;TRE</name> AND THE GRANDEUR OF THE BAROQUE</head><figure xml:id="fig-177"><graphic url="CH5_001.jpg"/></figure><p>In seventeenth-century <name type="place">France</name>, the nature of monarchy changed in a functional way Feudal kings in the late Middle Ages had traveled with their retinues, holding court in castles scattered throughout their kingdoms or enjoying the hospitality of vassal lords. The Renaissance princes of the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries were peripatetic, enjoying the pleasures of the hunt in several royal forests and performing affairs of state while entertaining in the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teaux</hi> of the Loire Valley and the <name type="pname">&#x00CE;le de France</name>, some of which we examined in the previous chapter. It was not until the rule of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> (ruled <date when="1643">1643</date>&#x2013;<date when="1715">1715</date>) that this situation changed. Although the king and his retinue traveled to various royal seats&#x2014;Fontainebleau, <name type="pname">SaintGermain-en-Laye</name>, <name type="pname">Chambord</name>, and, later, <name type="pname">Marly</name>&#x2014;residing in these for considerable periods of time, the court of <name type="place">France</name> increasingly revolved in the orbit of Versailles, as <name type="pname">Louis</name>'s attachment to his father's old hunting lodge and his determination to make it the radiant center and symbol of his reign grew. It was here that a distinctive style expressing authoritarian order and elegant rationality matured.</p><p>This style might never have gained pre-eminence as an international design idiom had not <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> heeded <name type="pname">Cardinal Jules Mazarin</name>'s deathbed recommendation and appointed <name type="pname">Jean-Baptiste Colbert</name> (<date when="1619">1619</date>&#x2013;<date when="1683">1683</date>) as his finance minister. <name type="pname">Colbert</name> soon reformed the system of taxation, making it more honest, and during the first part of the king's long reign, <name type="pname">Colbert</name>'s brilliant reorganization of finance and industry increased the prosperity of <name type="place">France</name>. <name type="pname">Louis</name> was able during most of his reign to enjoy its benefits and turn them to both personal and national advantage.</p><p>Through the elevation of all the arts to new heights of excellence, as well as through astute political diplomacy, <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> established <name type="place">France</name> as the leading power in <name type="place">Europe</name>, making it a great state and also the exemplar of style. Both <name type="pname">Colbert</name> and the king understood well the role that all the arts, especially the fine arts&#x2014;architecture, painting, and sculpture&#x2014;would play in that process. <name type="pname">Colbert</name> belonged to the prestigious Acad&#x00E9;mie Fran&#x00E7;aise, established by <name type="pname">Cardinal Richelieu</name> and incorporated in 1635, and was instrumental in founding several academies for the advancement of the arts and sciences. The establishment of these ushered in an era of important building projects sponsored by the king.<ref target="#CH5-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref></p><p>The king gave dance, music, and theater new dignity and status. He founded the Acad&#x00E9;mie Royale de Danse in 1661, and the Acad&#x00E9;mie Royale de Musique (the <name type="place">Paris</name> Opera) in 1669. Moli&#x00E8;re's troupe of actors was the precursor of the Com&#x00E9;die Fran&#x00E7;aise, which was officially chartered by the king in 1680. <name type="pname">Louis</name> himself was a dancer and performed in several ballets in his youth. Thus, <name type="pname">Louis</name> over the years, with the assistance of <name type="pname">Colbert</name>, supported and institutionalized the diverse talents that were responsible for forging a rich and sophisticated culture within which the French seventeenthcentury style flourished as a powerful political and social statement and tangible manifestation of the power and glory of monarchy.</p><p>We have seen how readily the French appropriated the idiom of the Italian Renaissance and how thoroughly they transformed it into a style with a distinctly French inflection. Building upon this French Renaissance style, the architects and planners who served <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> now took inspiration from contemporary Italian Baroque art and architecture, adapting it into yet another distinctive style. It is a style of sober grandeur, which is differentiated from the robust plasticity and exuberant theatricality of its Italian models by its linear elegance and by the application of mathematical principles to produce designs of eminent rationality.</p><p>There was a moment, however, at the beginning of the young king's reign when this outcome may have been in doubt. <name type="pname">Colbert</name> understood that work on the unfinished Louvre Palace should be recommenced as a first major building project of the new regime. In 1665, displeased with the plans submitted by French architects, he summoned to <name type="place">Paris</name> the distinguished Italian architect and sculp<pb n="166"/><pb n="166" type="orig"/>tor <name type="pname">Gianlorenzo Bernini</name> (<date when="1598">1598</date>&#x2013;<date when="1680">1680</date>) in order to commission a design that would glorify the young king with the same kind of dynamic, robustly theatrical architecture that Bernini had brought to papal <name type="place">Rome</name>. But the Italian's three proposals, vast in scale, would have demolished the existing palace. His solution, moreover, although also neoclassical in its inspiration, would have taken French architectural aesthetics in a dynamically Baroque direction rather than the more chaste one advocated by the king's advisors.</p><p><name type="pname">Louis</name>, ceding to <name type="pname">Colbert</name>'s counsel after several months of consideration, dismissed Bernini's proposals and put the problem in the hands of a committee consisting of <name type="pname">Claude Perrault</name> (<date when="1613">1613</date>&#x2013;<date when="1688">1688</date>), an expert on the architecture of antiquity, the architect <name type="pname">Louis Le Vau</name> (<date when="1612">1612</date>&#x2013;<date when="1670">1670</date>), and the painter <name type="pname">Charles Le Brun</name> (<date when="1619">1619</date>&#x2013;<date when="1690">1690</date>). The East Front of the Louvre, which represents the solution their collaboration produced, has a central Roman-style pavilion, colonnaded wings with paired columns, and symmetrical pavilions at each end. The whole architectural composition is upheld by a ground-floor podium. In choosing an architectural vocabulary that directly linked <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> symbolically with the might of imperial <name type="place">Rome</name>, especially with the cool Olympian grandeur of the classicizing styles of emperors <name type="pname">Augustus</name> and <name type="pname">Hadrian</name>, the Louvre design committee substituted its own brand of neoclassicism for that of the Italian Baroque. Even though the architects who worked for <name type="pname">Louis</name> used such Italian Baroque forms as high domes and curving walls with verve and skill, the path of austere grandeur that is represented by the term <hi rend="italic">French classicism</hi> is one that they never relinquished, and the Baroque elements that they did appropriate were submitted to its firm authority.</p><p>Except for the Louvre and a few other projects, <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>, unlike <name type="pname">Henry IV</name>, took only a secondary interest in beautifying the capital, concentrating instead upon making the palace and gardens of Versailles into a cynosure of universal renown. That he was able to accomplish this astonishing feat is due not only to the circumstances of patronage that he and <name type="pname">Colbert</name> established but also to the presence of genius at his side. That genius belonged to a remarkable generation of French designers, in the front rank of whom stood <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> (<date when="1613">1613</date>&#x2013;<date when="1700">1700</date>), a man who throughout his long life was honored to bear the title of king's gardener.</p><p>In <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s hands, Renaissance garden style&#x2014;which we today frequently characterize as "formal"&#x2014;assumed a new scale and, as it did so, forsook small-scale compartmentalization and intricate effects in favor of unified spatial composition and monumentality expressive of the evolving French style of regal grandeur in landscape terms. Formal order was made to merge with nature, and boundaries appeared to dissolve into distant prospects. The walled gardens of <name type="pname">Catherine de M&#x00E9;dicis</name>, though large by Renaissance standards, were suddenly dwarfed by the dimensions of the new gardens. The former are composed of axially arranged, visibly contained spaces, inwardly focused and walled, whereas the latter are commensurate with their illusion of limitlessness&#x2014;that is, large enough to have distant and generally imperceptible boundaries and axes that carry the eye to the horizon line.</p><p>This illusion of indeterminate axial extension provides a landscape analogue to the spatial concepts of <name type="pname">Ren&#x00E9; Descartes</name> (<date when="1596">1596</date>&#x2013;<date when="1650">1650</date>), the French philosopher, mathematician, and founder of analytical geometry. <name type="pname">Descartes</name> believed that starting from skepticism the human intellect could comprehend the mathematical principles underlying God's creation. His rigorous methodology viewed the natural world in mechanistic terms, as objectively measurable. With <name type="pname">Descartes</name>, the scientific enterprise itself became boundless, and this new mode of open-ended inquiry helped establish fresh cosmological premises. The seventeenth-century cosmology, which <name type="pname">Descartes</name>'s philosophy synthesized, provided the groundwork for modern physics. <name type="pname">Descartes</name> built his cosmology on that of the German astronomer, physicist, and mathematician <name type="pname">Johannes Kepler</name> (<date when="1571">1571</date>&#x2013;<date when="1630">1630</date>), who explained how planets moved in eliptical orbits. To <name type="pname">Kepler</name>'s theories <name type="pname">Descartes</name> added the concept of a heliocentric universe previously expounded by the Polish astronomer <name type="pname">Nicolaus Copernicus</name> (<date when="1473">1473</date>&#x2013;<date when="1543">1543</date>). Because of the invention of the telescope by <name type="pname">Galileo Galilei</name> (<date when="1564">1564</date>&#x2013;<date when="1642">1642</date>), the universe was now known to be much vaster than previously imagined. <name type="pname">Descartes</name> held that space was indefinitely divisible and that all movement is in a straight line. Accordingly, extension (<hi rend="italic">extensio</hi>) is the essence of both space and matter, which are equated with each other and which determine the nature of quantity, dimension, and the measurement of distance. This meant in effect the abandonment of the Aristotelian notion of <hi rend="italic">topos</hi>, the idea that place is coterminous with contained and defined space. Cartesian space, by contrast, is boundless and, with regard to the concept of place, value-neutral, since space could now be conceived as a universal grid of mathematical coordinates with places existing merely as locational points along its infinitely extensible planes.<ref target="#CH5-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref></p><p>In this view, place is secondary to matter and space. Its nondistinctive status helps account for the abstract character of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s designs, which express <name type="pname">Descartes</name>'s attempt to geometricize all nature rather than to explicate <hi rend="italic">topos</hi>. The geometric formality of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s designs is also due to his employment of Cartesian analytic geometry as a practical compositional tool; the precisely calculated proportions of their component parts and his calculation of the effects of perspective on the viewer manifest an understanding of Cartesian mathematics. Although <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> may not have intended explicitly to portray the Cartesian vision of heliocentric cosmic space, an impossibility in any case, Cartesian philosophy is implicit in the indefinitely extended axes of the serenely grand gardens he designed for <name type="place">France</name>'s Sun King.</p><p>In addition to giving expression to a new cosmology, <name type="pname">Descartes</name> assisted in the overthrow of Aristotelian Scholasticism by espousing a philosophy based upon the belief that the human mind could, through deductive reasoning, grasp and control the world. The optimism inherent in the Cartesian belief that, through their own powers of intellect, human beings could master the inner workings of nature and direct these toward progressive ends is echoed by the confident grandeur of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s gardens. It was the Sun King's duty to symbolize in his divinely appointed person and to project through his royal authority <name type="place">France</name>'s position as the intellectual leader of the modern Western world, and it was <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s job to portray this absolute power through landscape design. Both king and gardener realized, however, the difference between<pb n="167"/><pb n="167" type="orig"/>reality and suggestion. <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> created a garden that implied rationality yet was based on an illusion, human dominance over nature; for his part, the king realized the limits of rationalism as a tool of power and means to accomplish his political goals in a world filled with passion and intrigue.<ref target="#CH5-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref></p><p>While it is often assumed that <name type="pname">William Kent</name> in eighteenthcentury <name type="place">England</name> was the first designer to "leap the wall" of the garden to embrace all of nature, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>, operating under the cultural influence of <name type="pname">Descartes</name>, had performed this feat nearly a century earlier. But unlike the naturalistic style of the English garden formulated by <name type="pname">Kent</name> and his followers, the confident, world-embracing idiom of the French classical style with its extended axes and geometrically derived layouts celebrated absolute monarchy, not libertarian values.</p><p>The work of transforming ordinary countryside into stepped terraces, grand canals, artificial cascades, and axial promenades was accomplished at the price of villages and fields laid waste and peasants relocated. It was also achieved at a huge monetary cost, even at the low prevailing wage rates. It was certainly seen as impressive just for that reason; the enormous expenditure was an important aspect of the seventeenth-century French gardens' message, demonstrating the king's economic power and superior taste. Furthermore, these gardens were designed to serve as stages upon which the members of an aristocratic society played out the dramas of their lives with theatrical ritual as they met one another upon balustraded terraces, walked along sweeping <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi>, or trysted within the relative privacy of <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi>.</p><p>Theaters of social life, the gardens of seventeenth-century <name type="place">France</name> often served as real stages for the performing arts. Within them, concerts, ballets, plays, fireworks, and banquets took place with increasing regularity. Theatrical entertainments were part of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>'s means of keeping an otherwise bored nobility in check. <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> knew the composer <name type="pname">Jean-Baptiste Lully</name> (<date when="1632">1632</date>&#x2013;<date when="1687">1687</date>) and the playwright <name type="pname">Moli&#x00E8;re</name> (<name type="pname">Jean-Baptiste Poquelin</name>, <date when="1622">1622</date>&#x2013;<date when="1675">1675</date>) and organized his spaces with their performance requirements in mind.</p><p>French classical gardens were theatrical in yet another sense. Had they been merely expositions of Cartesian logic, elegantly defined empty stages for aristocratic intercourse and entertainment, they would have been boring. But with their abundant water jets and populations of stone gods and goddesses, they provided the spectator with movement and a rich mythological companionship. Like the Renaissance villa gardens of <name type="place">Italy</name> from which they are derived, they were programmatic texts in stone, water, and vegetation. <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> and his collaborators (notably <name type="pname">Le Brun</name>, whose express charge was the sculptural program of the gardens at Vauxle-Vicomte and Versailles) had a sufficient humanistic education to continue the Renaissance practice of garden arrangement according to elaborate programs of allegorical allusion.</p><p>The elegant rationality of the style <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> forged in collaboration with the architects, artists, and artisans of his day influenced courts throughout <name type="place">Europe</name>. Just as <name type="place">France</name> under <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> became the dominant military power in <name type="place">Europe</name>, so the French classical landscape style became prevalent during and after his reign. Although inflected according to regional conditions of taste and topography, it rapidly spread to the <name type="place">Netherlands</name>, <name type="place">England</name>, <name type="place">Germany</name>, and <name type="place">Russia</name>.</p><p>The French classical garden was influential even in <name type="place">Italy</name>, as is apparent a century later in the scale and plan of the royal gardens of Caserta near Naples. But Italian landscape design was so imbued with the robust theatricality of local taste that French classicism was never thoroughly integrated into it. Rather, the currents of Italian Baroque style continued to flow northward as various European monarchs and princes summoned artists and craftsmen to mingle their talents with those of French designers. In <name type="place">Italy</name> itself, a wealthy clergy and its related aristocracy brought the art of villa garden building to a triumphant and spectacular close. Humanistic iconography, at first in the service of the princes of the church and state, was finally abandoned altogether and ornament became an end in its own right. Thus, the elaborate symbolical programs that informed such gardens as the Villa d'Este gave way to the kind of sculptural tableaux one finds at Caserta (see fig. 41).</p><p>Grand-scale geometrical landscape composition in the French manner initiated another tradition, that of monumental city planning, beginning already in the time of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> and carried forward in the eighteenth century in <name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name> and <name type="place">St. Petersburg</name>, as discussed in the next chapter, and in the nineteenth century, most spectacularly in <name type="place">Paris</name> itself, as we shall see in Chapter Ten. And although they may work with an entirely contemporary sensibility and no longer have as their primary philosophical reference the Cartesian cosmological view that was a principal <hi rend="italic">raison d'&#x00EA;tre</hi> for axial extension in the seventeenth century, many of today's French landscape designers stand squarely in <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s long shadow as they rebuild the public spaces of <name type="place">Paris</name> and other French cities. For all of these reasons it is worthwhile to examine more closely the career of this remarkable royal servant.</p><div type="section"><pb n="168"/><pb n="168" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps">I. The Making of Vaux-le-Vicomte and Versailles: <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name></hi></head><figure xml:id="fig-178"><graphic url="CH5_002.jpg"/><figDesc>5.1 <hi rend="italic">Ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and gardens of <name type="pname">Petit Bourg</name>, <name type="pname">Corbeil</name>, <name type="place">France</name>. Design attributed to <name type="pname">Fran&#x00E7;ois Mansart</name>, ca. 1650. Engraving by <name type="pname">Adam P&#x00E9;relle</name>, 1727</figDesc></figure><p>By luck, <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> was born at the moment when all the fashionable and newly wealthy men of seventeenth-century <name type="place">France</name>, following <name type="pname">Cardinal Richelieu</name>'s example, sought to display their taste and status in an increasingly grand manner and on an increasingly lavish scale by constructing new <hi rend="italic">h&#x00F4;tels</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teaux</hi> or extensively remodeling old ones. As these city mansions and country estates were furnished with gardens, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> obtained many commissions during his long professional life.</p><p>It was not only royalty and the nobility who were in a position to offer <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> commissions; the new financial elite, the <hi rend="italic">surintendants</hi> and <hi rend="italic">intendants</hi>, who were in charge of collecting taxes and maintaining the country's finances and administration, formed a class that rose to prominence during the decades when the old nobility's wealth was declining after prolonged religious and civil wars. The newly wealthy professional administrators were sufficiently enriched to own property of a scale to demand the services of architects and landscape designers, thus providing opportunities to consolidate the previous century's experiments.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s Predecessors and Teachers</hi></head><p><name type="pname">Fran&#x00E7;ois Mansart</name> (<date when="1598">1598</date>&#x2013;<date when="1666">1666</date>) was the most original architect and garden designer among <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s immediate predecessors, carrying Italian Renaissance axial planning to a new scale.<ref target="#CH5-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref> This design achievement had a cultural basis. As human confidence and the desire to dominate nature increased in the seventeenth century with the opening of new continents through exploration and the expansion of mental horizons through science, <name type="pname">Mansart</name> grasped the possibility of projecting the garden outward in an open-armed gesture of seemingly illimitable axial extension. He stretched axes in long perspective lines emanating from, and converging upon, the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>. At <name type="pname">Maisons</name>, <name type="pname">Berny Balleroy</name>, <name type="pname">Fresnes</name>, <name type="pname">Petit Bourg</name>, <name type="pname">Gesvres</name>, and elsewhere, he elaborated approaches and forecourts, running axial vistas through village and forest (fig. 5.1). He and his followers placed the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> within a field of successive sight lines, dramatically revealing it along intersecting axes.</p><p><name type="pname">Jacques Lemercier</name> (<date when="1585">1585</date>&#x2013;<date when="1654">1654</date>), the architect employed by <name type="pname">Cardinal Richelieu</name> on several projects,<pb n="169"/><pb n="169" type="orig"/>was also an important influence for the young <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>. <name type="pname">Lemercier</name>'s commissions from the cardinal included his country retreat, Rueil, where he built an impressive architectural cascade, and the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and new town that bore the cardinal's name. At <name type="pname">Richelieu</name>, <name type="pname">Lemercier</name> laid out an abstract grid that encompassed the extensive grounds of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and canalized the river Mable as an important cross axis (fig. 5.2). This early application of Cartesian geometry to landscape design helped set the course that <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> would follow and perfect.</p><p>In his youth, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> may have worked with <name type="pname">Mansart</name>; it is clear that his genius owes a debt to that of this temperamental and arrogant master builder. But <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s pivotal, enduring accomplishment had much deeper sources than this purported apprenticeship. Indeed, history offers few examples of the marriage of vocational destiny, natural genius, and opportunity more complete than that of <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>. His grandfather, <name type="pname">Pierre</name>, had been <hi rend="italic">Ma&#x00EE;tre Jardinier</hi> in the service of <name type="pname">Catherine de M&#x00E9;dicis</name>, and his father, <name type="pname">Jean</name>, held the title of <hi rend="italic">Premier Jardinier du Roi</hi>. Born in the gardeners' quarters of the Tuileries Gardens in 1613, <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9;</name> grew up constantly exposed to his future profession. The companions of his infancy and childhood were members of the Mollet and Desgots families, gardeners who were also lodged in the Tuileries. Ties of closest friendship and even marriage knit their members into a solid professional clan.</p><p>Not only did <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> inherit his father's title upon the latter's retirement, but, more important, he displayed a quick intellect in receiving the education to which his father directed him. That education was the one prescribed by <name type="pname">Jacques Boyceau</name> in his treatise of 1638; it incorporated among other things the means to give physical form to Cartesian rationality through newly formulated laws of geometry, perxspective, and optics.</p><p><name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s education also included a sensory approach to, and appreciation of, line, proportion, and color, which he acquired during his apprenticeship in the studio of the painter <name type="pname">Simon Vouet</name> (<date when="1590">1590</date>&#x2013;<date when="1649">1649</date>). The fact that <name type="pname">Jean Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>, his father, placed him with <name type="pname">Vouet</name> in order to develop his draftsmanship and general aesthetic perceptions illustrates the position landscape gardening now occupied in relation to the fine arts. Later, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> became a notable connoisseur and collector of works of art.<ref target="#CH5-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref></p><p>In addition to his training with <name type="pname">Vouet</name>, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> seems to have received a sound education in architecture. It is likely that he was instructed by both <name type="pname">Mansart</name> and <name type="pname">Lemercier</name>. Certainly, his gardens are so imbued with architectural principles and architectural intelligence that it would have been impossible for <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> to have designed them without a thorough academic training in architecture. Endowed with practical experience from his earliest years as well as personal gifts and technical skills that enabled him to be more than a talented practitioner of a well-respected craft, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> took on the task of transforming the tenets of French Renaissance garden design into a new idiom.</p><figure xml:id="fig-179"><graphic url="CH5_003.jpg"/><figDesc>5.2. View of <hi rend="italic">Parterre</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Demie Lune</hi>, <name type="pname">Richelieu</name>, <name type="pname">Touraine</name>, <name type="place">France</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Jacques Lemercier</name>. <date when="1631">1631</date>&#x2013;<date when="1639">39</date>. Engraving by <name type="pname">P&#x00E9;relle</name>, 1688</figDesc></figure><p>Shortly after <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> took over the reins of government, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> had the good fortune to have as a client the king's minister of finance, the ambitious and cultivated <name type="pname">Nicolas Fouquet</name> (<date when="1615">1615</date>&#x2013;<date when="1680">1680</date>). <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> knew how to solicit from artists their best and most imaginative work and how to add an educated client's eye and discernment to the collaborative process necessary for realizing a notable design. Like other passionate builders, he was willing to spare no expense to achieve perfection. Thus equipped by taste and temperament and enriched by the emoluments of office, <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> approached, at the age of forty-one, the task of creating the monument of his brilliance and also of his doom, Vaux-le-Vicomte, the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and garden that epitomize the French classical style.<ref target="#CH5-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref></p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Vaux-le-Vicomte</hi></head><p>Lying within the broad agricultural plain that is the predominant landscape of the &#x00CE;le de <name type="place">France</name>, Vaux-leVicomte was a small estate that <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> had inherited in 1640 from his father. It was an unremarkable piece of countryside, bereft of the topographical drama of contemporary villa gardens in <name type="place">Italy</name>, where patrons and designers sought hillside sites because they considered them inherently salubrious and scenic. Such manipulations of topography as were necessary to realize the design of Vaux-le-Vicomte would have to be achieved by brute labor.</p><p>Expectation and surprise&#x2014;or, put another way, rationality and mystery&#x2014;are both present in a masterpiece of landscape architecture. Vaux-le-Vicomte is rich in both elements. It has a plan of complete<pb n="170"/><pb n="170" type="orig"/><q>VAUX-LE-VICOMTE</q><figure xml:id="fig-180"><graphic url="CH5_004.jpg"/><figDesc>5.3. Vaux-le-Vicomte, Melun, <name type="place">France</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>. <date when="1656">1656</date>&#x2013;<date when="1661">61</date></figDesc></figure><q><hi rend="bold">V</hi>aux-le-Vicomte opens up like a play in several acts. There is, first, the drama of entry that many visitors approaching from the modern parking lot are apt to miss. Approaching instead along the central axis, which runs through the middle of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and the garden beyond it, one walks down a slight incline toward a beautiful grille punctuated at intervals with tall stone herms and terminated by symmetrical pedimented pseudoportals. The moat is sunk well below the balusters, and its sudden appearance produces the first of many grade-manipulated surprises. Only as one attempts to follow visually one of the arms of the moat around the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> can one guess that the elaborate screen of grille, pseudoportals, and service buildings has been masking something magnificent beyond.</q><q>Standing at the entrance to the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>, one now can see on either side verdant grass <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi>, the edges of which are punctuated with yews clipped into precise identical cones, and, through the far windows of the central pavilion, one glimpses more manicured verdure. With the same anticipation that is to be felt upon the rising of the curtain in a theater, one walks through the central vestibule and oval salon out to the terrace. There lie the <hi rend="italic">parterres de broderie</hi>, parallel beds of box and gravel patterned like brocade (fig. 5.4). Fountains, pools, sculpture, topiary, hedges, and trees are all laid out along a grand central axis that finally turns from graveled promenade into a grassy ramp upon which stands a colossal gilded <name type="pname">Hercules</name>, symbol of virtuous strength and intended somewhat arrogantly by <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> as a reference to himself (fig. 5.7). Still this axis continues banked by forest groves, until it seems to melt into the luminous sky.</q><q>Strolling along the central axis one finds changes in level that were not apparent at first. The axis, from successive vantage points, extending from the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> all along the distance of the central promenade, deceptively appears to flow in one unbroken sweep to meet the grassy ramp and gilded <name type="pname">Hercules</name>; in fact. <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> has manipulated the ground plane to produce several surprising results.</q><q>A few feet beyond the circular pool at the end of the <hi rend="italic">parterre de broderie</hi> just beyond the garden's first principal cross axis, which is emphasized by a pair of previously invisible long rectangular pools, there is a slight shift in the elevation. Descending, the visitor continues along the central promenade. Here one walks along a barely perceptible incline past flower-filled urns that today mark what was once the All&#x00E9;e d'Eau, so named for the evenly spaced low jets of water bordering it. The mild slope of this part of the garden allowed the runoff from the aqueous balustrade formed by the water jets to flow in two clear streams on either side of the central <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi>. This part of the garden terminates in a large square pool.</q><q>Beyond the pool, and now suddenly visible, is one of the most impressive surprises in the entire garden. The elaborate architectural grotto, which from a distance appears to rise from the far end of the square pool, does not in reality do so. Here, the ground abruptly drops, revealing a huge chasm. This chasm contains the garden's second major cross axis in the form of a wide canal. As unexpected as this sight is, it is only half of the surprise, for at the bottom of the stairs to the canal, the entire supporting wall of the terrace above becomes a giant water feature, the <name type="pname">Grandes Cascades</name> (fig. 5.5), a mighty wall of water, commensurate in effect with the scale of the canal beside it and a dramatic counterpoint to the grotto opposite. Now dry, it must be it imagined with the roar and gurgle of water spouting from grotesque masks into cupped bowls and upturned shells.</q><q>To approach the grotto one must walk to the far end of the canal and back along the opposite bank. Its architecture of rusticated stone forms a massive support for the terrace above. Beneath the flanking pair of broad stairs that rise to meet this terrace repose giant classical river gods, one symbolizing the Tiber, the other the local Anqueil, the river feeding the canal (fig. 5.6). The grotto steps contain a carved lion and squirrel. The agile high-vaulting squirrel was <name type="pname">Fouquet</name>'s emblem, and the lion symbolized his protector, the king. Herms carved in bold relief separate the grotto into seven niches containing artificial rockwork over which water was made to flow into a large rectangular basin. The balustrade of the terrace above the grotto was originally decorated with sculptures. Behind it a jet of water known as the Gerbe, was, according to contemporary accounts, as thick as a man's body and rose a lofty five meters (16&#x2032;5&#x2033;) into the air.</q><q>The Gerbe, when operable, must have appeared as a shimmering base for the gilded <name type="pname">Hercules</name>. Modeled on the Farnese <name type="pname">Hercules</name>, the scale of this colossus is not apparent from the terrace of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>. When apprehended, it makes one aware of the great distance&#x2014;half a mile (800 meters)&#x2014;one has traveled in a straight line from the spot where it first appeared in view.</q><q>Beneath the towering base of the <name type="pname">Hercules</name> is an ordinary stone bench. From this vantage point one may gaze back at the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> (fig. 5.7). Now all the games with geometry, perspective, and optics are played all over again in reverse. The canal and cascade are no longer visible; all the garden's cleverly interlocking parts are visually compressed into a single flattened plane. The garden presents itself once again as a unified image, the undisputed focus of which is the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> with its swelling roof dome breasting the sky, the centerpiece of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s and Le Vau's collaboration, to which all its component parts now adhere.</q><pb n="171"/><pb n="171" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-181"><graphic url="CH5_005.jpg"/><figDesc>5.4. <hi rend="italic">Ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and Grand <hi rend="italic">Parterre</hi>, Vauxle-Vicomte. Engraving by <name type="pname">Adam</name> and <name type="pname">Nicholas P&#x00E9;relle</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Recueil des Veues des Plus Beaux Lieux de <name type="place">France</name></hi>, 1688</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-182"><graphic url="CH5_006.jpg"/><figDesc>5.5. <name type="pname">Grandes Cascades</name>, <name type="pname">Vaux-le-Vicomte</name>. View by <name type="pname">Isra&#x00EB;l Silvestre</name>, engraving by <name type="pname">Adam P&#x00E9;relle</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Recueil des Veues des Plus Beaux Lieux de <name type="place">France</name></hi>, 1688</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-183"><graphic url="CH5_007.jpg"/><figDesc>5.6. River god. Grotto, Vaux-le-Vicomte</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-184"><graphic url="CH5_008.jpg"/><figDesc>5.7. View of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> of Vaux-le-Vicomte from the base of the <name type="pname">Hercules</name> sculpture</figDesc></figure><pb n="172"/><pb n="172" type="orig"/>clarity, a design in which one may grasp the whole composition and from its organizing axes infer the principal spaces, a design in which there is a deft interlocking of parts and a logical progression from one to another. It also contains much more than meets the eye when the eye enjoys its first satisfying survey of the harmoniously proportioned whole. And even that whole is not revealed at first glance, but rather through a process of unexpected discovery.<ref target="#CH5-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref></p><p>It is by the laws of geometry, perspective, and optics that Vaux achieves, within the framework of logic, a number of masterly surprises, an accomplishment belonging not only to <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>, but also to the architect <name type="pname">Louis Le Vau</name> and the painter <name type="pname">Charles Le Brun</name> with whom he worked in close collaboration. <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> had in all probability read the <hi rend="italic">Trait&#x00E9; de la section perspective</hi> (1636) by the mathematician and engineer-architect <name type="pname">Girard Desargues</name> (<date when="1591">1591</date>&#x2013;<date when="1661">1661</date>), who attempted to modify Cartesian theory with the notion of a properly geometric infinity. The subtle alterations of grade and multiplicity of perspectives at Vaux dramatize and dignify the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and carry the eye along an axial progression to carefully established focal points within the garden, as well as to the remote horizon beyond. These effects are the result of precise mathematical calculation. The application of this mathematical knowledge allowed <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> to conceal certain elements of the garden until the visitor, progressing through its sequenced spaces, finds them revealed as if by some sort of legerdemain (figs. 5.3&#x2013;5.7). In this orchestration of garden experience, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> exhibits his kinship with the Renaissance designers responsible for hide-and-reveal tactics found at the <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name> and elsewhere.</p><p>As is well known in the annals of garden history, <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> a party to celebrate his achievement on <date when="1661-08-17">August 17, 1661</date>. To it he invited the entire court and the young king. Not only had <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> naively deluded himself with regard to the effect that so much ostentation and fashionable display would have upon his master <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> but, ever confident of his ability to charm and flatter his way into power, he had been foolhardy in offering financial advice and credit to the king's mistress, <name type="pname">Louise de La Valli&#x00E8;re</name>, offending her and enraging the king. In addition, he had as an enemy <name type="pname">Jean-Baptiste Colbert</name>, who, eager to succeed him, was able to persuade the dying <name type="pname">Cardinal Mazarin</name> to denounce Fouque<name type="pname">t</name>. Whether or not <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> actually did use public funds to build Vaux, its magnificence and size certainly suggest that this might have been the case.</p><p>The party itself lives on in history, not only because of its ironic, if predictable, outcome, but because it expanded the scale of garden festivities, just as Vaux had expanded the scale of the garden itself, to unprecedented dimensions. First, there was a royal tour through the garden with its dancing waters and allusive sculptural program developed perhaps by the fabler La Fontaine.<ref target="#CH5-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref> Then a lavish banquet was held indoors, followed by a comedy and fireworks. The guests returned outside after the banquet to watch <hi rend="italic">Les F&#x00E2;cheux</hi>, written for the occasion by the young Moli&#x00E8;re, who was one of the actors. This was performed in front of the <hi rend="italic">Grille d'eau</hi>, a beautiful tiered fountain at one end of the first cross axis. Moli&#x00E8;re begged the king to help him by commanding the garden itself to cooperate in producing the spectacle. Thereupon, statues appeared to come to life, trees to move, and rocks to open.<ref target="#CH5-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref> When night fell, the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> was lit by hundreds of lanterns placed upon the cornices; the grotto, too, was illuminated. Elaborate fireworks rained down from above, some in the form of <hi rend="italic">fleurs de lys</hi>. A mock whale swam the length of the canal discharging more fireworks. Then, as the king prepared to depart, rockets shot from the dome of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>, setting the whole sky ablaze.</p><p>On <date when="--09-05">September 5</date>, <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> was arrested on charges of high treason and embezzlement. Although judged innocent on counts that might have warranted the death penalty, <name type="pname">Fouquet</name> was imprisoned for life. <name type="pname">Louis</name>, having immediately appropriated much of the sculpture and new plantings he had seen at Vaux-leVicomte, as well as the services of its creators, began redesigning both the gardens of Fontainebleau and those his father had laid out at Versailles.<ref target="#CH5-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref></p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Versailles</hi></head><p>Shortly after <name type="pname">Fouquet</name>'s arrest, the three principal designers of <name type="pname">Vaux-le-Vicomte&#x2014;Le Vau</name>, <name type="pname">Le Brun</name>, and <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>&#x2014;were hard at work transforming <name type="pname">Louis XIII</name>'s old hunting lodge at Versailles into a place for entertainment with a suitably grand suite of apartments for the young king and queen. Le Vau was in charge of remodeling the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> without altering its basic lines; he was also asked to create an orangery. <name type="pname">Le Brun</name> was made responsible for the decoration of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>. To <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> fell the task of developing the plan that would enlarge the gardens to a monumental scale, defying both the site's marshy and highly irregular terrain and <name type="pname">Colbert</name>'s assertion that Versailles was but meanly proportioned as a symbol of monarchical magnificence.<ref target="#CH5-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref></p><p>As Superintendent of the King's Buildings, <name type="pname">Colbert</name> oversaw the financing and coordination of the entire construction process, a task in which he was assisted by <name type="pname">Charles Perrault</name> (<date when="1628">1628</date>&#x2013;<date when="1703">1703</date>), First Clerk and later Comptroller of Buildings. <name type="pname">Perrault</name>, whose more enduring fame rests upon a much-loved collection of fairy tales, was probably responsible for the development and construction in the 1660s and 1670s<pb n="173"/><pb n="173" type="orig"/>of the heliocentric iconography that celebrated the glory of the Sun King and the sun's&#x2014;and therefore <name type="pname">Louis</name>'s&#x2014;mythological representative, Apollo, throughout the gardens of Versailles (fig. 5.8).</p><p>As the iconography of the Sun King became elaborated in several garden compositions, Versailles more and more became the center of court life. After 1678, when <name type="pname">Jules Hardouin-Mansart</name> (<date when="1645">1645</date>&#x2013;<date when="1708">1708</date>), the grandnephew of <name type="pname">Fran&#x00E7;ois Mansart</name>, had succeeded Le Vau as official architect to the king, <name type="pname">Louis</name> decided to make his favorite <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> the seat of government. Throughout the early building campaigns at Versailles, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> guided the design of the gardens. In creating in the central <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> the smooth greensward of the <hi rend="italic">tapis vert</hi> and its flanking <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi> of geometrically arranged trees, in laying out the <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi> beside <name type="pname">Hardouin-Mansart</name>'s 1683 Orangerie, and in building the gardens of the Trianon and the long canal that extended the principal axis to the distant reach of the garden, he worked steadily with professional collaborators, workmen, and gardeners.</p><p>But because Versailles was not conceived as a single unified scheme, as was Vaux-le-Vicomte, it does not have the coherence of its predecessor. Its size is gargantuan, a mighty sprawl over hundreds of acres. And yet <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> maintained a rigorous logic in its design; its central axis and several transverse axes provide a strong framework around which various features were arranged and rearranged over the years. Within this framework, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> and his collaborators contributed much pleasing incident in the form of fountains, pools, treillage, sculpture, and crisply geometric topiary. It was <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s genius to substitute for the ordered intricacy of the older French Renaissance gardens a new clarity, simplicity, austerity, and refinement, creating a style of great architectonic strength. He drove his axes into the indefinite distance, erasing all visible garden boundaries, creating the paradigm of a world-embracing landscape. In so doing, he also laid down the premises for a new urban order.</p><figure xml:id="fig-185"><graphic url="CH5_009.jpg"/><figDesc>5.8. Apollo Fountain, Versailles. Sculpture by <name type="pname">Jean-Baptiste Tuby</name>. <date when="1668">1668</date>&#x2013;<date when="1671">71</date></figDesc></figure><p>It is a style in which monumentality is achieved not so much by architectural means as through spatial ones. Because of its role as a model for future garden and urban design, the plan for Versailles as it existed shortly before the king's death is worth studying in regard to its organization of space (figs. 5.9, 5.10). By the application of Cartesian mathematics, landscape is geometricized on a grand scale. Space is projected by axes and defined by cross axes. Radiais converge as a <hi rend="italic">patte d'oie</hi>, or goose foot, upon the palace; these are tree-lined boulevards, the principal avenues of the town of Versailles&#x2014;a planned community of red brick and stone buildings of regulated height, which was laid out as a grid with public squares at certain intersections.</p><pb n="174"/><pb n="174" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-186"><graphic url="CH5_010.jpg"/><figDesc>5.9. Plan of 1710 by <name type="pname">Pierre Le Pautre</name> of the palace, gardens, and town of Versailles</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-187"><graphic url="CH5_011.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 5.10. Aerial view, Versailles</figDesc></figure><p>The gardens are elaborated within an overall structure and subdivisions that are inventively geometric, and the entire composition, which necessarily had to take its point of departure from <name type="pname">Louis XIII</name>'s Versailles, is a remarkable demonstration of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s genius for producing a sense of rational order under awkward conditions. The palace sits athwart the main axis. The first cross axis of the garden bisects <hi rend="italic">parterres de broderie</hi>, embroidery-like designs in boxwood and colored gravel. Here, where it is seen from the palace windows at close range, the design is intricate and the scale compact. Several successive cross axes and axes paralleling the principal one create a grid within the old stand of forest trees. These are subdivided by paths forming geometric designs, each with a central feature, usually a fountain basin with sculpture. For instance, along the axis of the Parterre du Nord near the palace, the All&#x00E9;e d'Eau&#x2014;twin rows of fountains supported by cherubs&#x2014;leads to the circular Bassin du Dragon.<ref target="#CH5-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref></p><p>The principal axis, which would be vapid if simply projected the length of the garden as an <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> of uniform grade, width, and surface material, is enlivened by changes of level and dimension; alternations between gravel, grass, and water; and the addition of several important sculptural features celebrating the Sun King. The first of these, which is reached by a broad flight of stairs descending from a horseshoe-shaped terrace located just beyond the second cross axis of the garden, is the 1670 masterpiece of <name type="pname">Jean-Baptiste Tuby</name> (<date when="1630">1630</date>&#x2013;<date when="1700">1700</date>), the Fountain of Latona, mother of Apollo. The sculptural grouping depicts Latona and her two children, <name type="pname">Apollo</name> and <name type="pname">Diana</name>, surrounded by the wicked Lycian peasants who had refused them water and who, as victims of divine retribution, are in the process of being metamorphosed into frogs (fig. 5.11).<ref target="#CH5-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref> This allegorical composition based on a story from <name type="pname">Ovid</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Metamorphosis</hi> refers to the Fronde, the civil war in which a rebellious faction representing the parliament of <name type="place">Paris</name> opposed the crown during the minority of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>, a threat a to royal power the king never forgot or forgave. Here the anti-authoritarian <hi rend="italic">frondeurs</hi> are symbolized by the discomfited former peasants, now frogs.</p><p>Beyond the two mirror-image <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi> adjacent to this fountain, the axis turns from gravel into grass, with side <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> flanked by <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi>. This strip of lawn, or <hi rend="italic">tapis vert</hi>, is terminated by another major sculptural feature punctuating the axis: the Basin of Apollo with Tuby's sculpture of the god rising as the morning sun from the water in a chariot drawn by splendid horses, his appearance heralded by horn-blowing tritons (see fig. 5.8). Cast of lead and then gilded, this group remains one of the principal sights of Versailles as the morning sun illuminates its frontal, east-facing side or the setting sun washes it from the rear. On the far side of the Basin of Apollo, the axis becomes a canal that appears to stretch in a watery line to the horizon, now marked by two giant poplars. It has an important cross axis, giving it a cruciform shape. The<pb n="175"/><pb n="175" type="orig"/>northern arm extends to an embankment beside the Trianon, the pavilion and gardens <name type="pname">Louis</name> built as a private retreat in 1671 and reconstructed in 1687.</p><figure xml:id="fig-188"><graphic url="CH5_012.jpg"/><figDesc>5.11. Latona Fountain, Versailles</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-189"><graphic url="CH5_013.jpg"/><figDesc>5.12. <name type="pname">Isra&#x00EB;l Silvestre</name>'s suites of engravings of the memorable F&#x00EA;tes de Versailles (<name type="place">Paris</name>: <hi rend="italic">Les Plaisirs de L'Isle Enchant&#x00E9;e</hi>, 1673) provide a fine example of Versailles' ability to accommodate theatrical spectacle. The engravings depict the entertainments that both glorified the king and demonstrated his power. The first celebrated his alliance with his mistress, <name type="pname">Louise de La Valli&#x00E8;re</name>, during five days at the beginning of <date when="1664-05">May 1664</date>, The marriage of nature and stagecraft is apparent in several tableaux of various events and is discernible even in a banqueting scene, where torchbearers form a line of "footlights" in front of the guests, while, behind them, costumed waiters hold aloft trays of mounded delicacies as they move with balletic grace and precision in front of the security guards that hold back the gathered spectators. In a similar fashion, a proscenium arch was erected to frame a garden perspective that served as the living backdrop for both a ballet and a play, which was given on the second day of the <hi rend="italic">f&#x00EA;te</hi>.</figDesc></figure><p>An octagonal basin forms the head of the canal and the point of departure for a major cross axis and two pairs of diagonal axes. These diagonal axes set up a new series of alignments as they and other minor axes crisscrossing them project the garden's space outward in a dynamic fashion. Beyond the canal, a <hi rend="italic">rondpoint</hi> creates a starburst of axes, which is echoed elsewhere in the garden by other circles with axes radiating out from them. It is as if <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> were trying to demonstrate in a terrestrial manner <name type="pname">Descartes</name>'s proposition of <hi rend="italic">extensio</hi>, the indefinite extension of cosmic space. Practically, the plan of Versailles furnished the inspiration for thousands of landscape creations, serving as the wellspring for gardens and city plans throughout <name type="place">Europe</name> and, later, all across the globe.</p><p>Over the years, <name type="pname">Louis</name> directed <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> to revise several parts of the gardens. He caused the fountains and <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi> containing sculpture illuminating the Apollonian theme to become the tourist attraction they have remained ever since. Because <name type="pname">Louis</name>'s life was lived almost entirely in public amid the busy swarm of his ever-present court, there was an almost endless stream of visitors from home and abroad to admire the gardens. <name type="pname">Madeleine de Scud&#x00E9;ry</name>, a contemporary to whom we owe a lively account of the unforgettable but unfortunate festivity at Vaux-le-Vicomte, in 1669 produced <hi rend="italic">La Promenade de Versailles</hi>, an itinerary for visitors. In 1674, the artist and historiographer <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; F&#x00E9;libien</name> published his guidebook entitled <hi rend="italic">Description sommaire du chasteau de Versailles</hi>. The king often conducted tours and was the author of a periodically revised guide, first issued in 1689, which peremptorily advised one where to stand and what to notice.</p><p>The engravings of <name type="pname">Isra&#x00EB;l Silvestre</name>, <name type="pname">Adam P&#x00E9;relle</name>, and <name type="pname">Antoine Le Pautre</name> are all animated by human figures in aristocratic dress, lending a measure of scale to buildings, <hi rend="italic">palissades</hi>, and fountain jets and bringing the gardens to life with many telling social details. The gardens at Versailles were, moreover, not only intended as a stage for the pageantry of aristocracy; <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> and his collaborators created elaborate temporary stages and areas suitable as outdoor theaters for the actual dramas and other spectacles that soon became an indispensable part of court life (fig. 5.12). The composer Lully collaborated with <name type="pname">Moli&#x00E8;re</name> on several of the spectacles that were staged there. <hi rend="italic">Palissades</hi> served as theatrical wings; similarly, arches of plaster, masonry, and greenery could be used as side<pb n="176"/><pb n="176" type="orig"/>entrances. Sometimes these were enlarged to define a proscenium in the same way that the frame of a picture defines its illusionistic space and focuses the viewer upon its perspective lines.</p><figure xml:id="fig-190"><graphic url="CH5_014.jpg"/><figDesc>5.13. Grotto of Thetis. Engraving by <name type="pname">Adam</name> and <name type="pname">Nicholas P&#x00E9;relle</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Recueil des Veues des Plus Beaux Lieux de <name type="place">France</name></hi>, 1688</figDesc></figure><p>In 1665, work was begun on the Grotto of Thetis, which had a reservoir on its roof to supply water for the gardens' numerous fountains (fig. 5.13). One of the last and most opulent of such architectural grottoes to be built, it stood on the upper terrace between the north side of the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and the Parterre du Nord. <name type="pname">Charles Perrault</name> developed the concept for the grotto, relying on <name type="pname">Ovid</name>'s <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi> for the story of Apollo driving his fiery steeds across the sky all day and then repairing at nightfall to the underwater palace of the sea goddess Thetis. Its three niches contained sculptural groups depicting the repose of Apollo, who is being bathed by the nymphs of Thetis, and the grooming of the horses of the Sun by Tritons. The interior walls were richly ornamented with shell mosaic, and the exterior of the grotto was equally decorative. <name type="pname">Perrault</name> credited his brother <name type="pname">Claude</name>, a physidan-architect, with designing the gilded grilles forming a sunburst pattern in its three wroughtiron arched gates. When these gates were opened, the richly decorated facade and well-lit interior became the backdrop for theatrical productions, including that of Moli&#x00E8;re's <hi rend="italic">Le Malade imaginaire</hi> in 1674. The descent of Apollo and his horses into the sea, which was expressed in the grotto's exterior frieze by <name type="pname">G&#x00E9;rard van Opstal</name>, was symbolically paired with Tuby's horses rising with the god in the Basin of Apollo.</p><p>The extensive building period to which the construction of the Grotto of Thetis, the decoration of the Basin of Apollo, and the installation of the Latona Fountain belong coincided with the king's taking the witty and accomplished Ath&#x00E9;na&#x00EF;s Rochechouart de Mortemart, Marquise de Montespan, for his new mistress in 1668.<ref target="#CH5-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref> Her establishment was followed by the construction of Le Vau's Enveloppe, or the Ch&#x00E2;teau Neuf, as it was also called. Because its broad fa&#x00E7;ade destroyed the floral <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi>, or queen's garden, on the south side of the old <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi>, the king, who loved flowers, sought another part of Versailles where he could enjoy the fragrance and colorful display of exotic specimens in carefully arranged beds. He also wished to have a pleasant retreat where he could retire with Madame de Montespan and a few favorites, away from the public glare of the large, wellpopulated Ch&#x00E2;teau Neuf.</p><p>It was for these reasons that in 1671, on the site of the former village of Trianon, the Trianon de Porcelaine, so named for the Delft ceramic tiles that decorated its roof, was built. Throughout the long period in which the Trianon de Porcelaine was in use, Madame de Montespan remained the favorite; its demolition in 1687, when <name type="pname">Hardouin-Mansart</name>'s Grand Trianon (the Trianon de Marbe) was built, marked her replacement by Fran&#x00E7;oise d'Aubign&#x00E9;, Madame de Maintenon. <name type="pname">Michel Le Bouteux</name>, the husband of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s niece, was in charge of the nurseries that supported the lavish floriculture of this section of Versailles. He was also responsible for ordering and planting many exotic flowers, such as tuberoses, which gardeners installed at every season of the year in floral <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi>. The ability to procure these exceedingly rare treasures symbolized absolute monarchy as much as did <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s commanding axes and Versailles's heliocentric iconography celebrating <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>'s role as Sun King.</p><p>During this period, by which time the main architectonics of Versailles were established, increasing attention was paid to the development of the <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi> (fig. 5.14). <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> created several of these green theaters within the Petit Parc, including Le Marais, a fanciful rectangular pond surrounded by metallic reeds and containing a tree, also of metal, in the <hi rend="italic">bosquet</hi> just beneath the terrace sustaining the Parterre de Nord; L'&#x00C9;toile, a starlike maze of treelined paths converging upon a central Montagne d'Eau formed of <hi rend="italic">rocaille</hi> (rustic rockwork); and the Labyrinthe located to the west of the Orangerie on the south side of the Petit Parc where various turnings and cul-de-sacs were punctuated by fountains with sculptures depicting animals from the <hi rend="italic">Fables</hi> of Aesop. The ground to the west of the Labyrinthe was low-lying and spongy. Here, in <date when="1671">1671</date>&#x2013;<date when="1674">74</date>, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> used two units of his <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi>-gridded plan to form a large water feature consisting of a semicircular basin known as the Miroir and a larger basin containing the Isle Royale. He emphasized the garden's dominant theme by making the Isle Royale circular like the Sun and projecting sixteen raylike <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> from the edges of the water basin in which it sat. The Enclade, the only remaining <hi rend="italic">bosquet</hi> built before 1680, has in its center<pb n="177"/><pb n="177" type="orig"/>a round pool in which <name type="pname">Gaspard Marsy</name>'s giant sprawls, felled in his hubris by the mountain he tried to erect to heaven. It is an arresting piece reminiscent of Giambologna's Appenino at Pratolino, less in keeping with the elegant classicism of Versailles than with the theatricality of Italian Baroque art.</p><p>The 1680s, which opened with <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s return from <name type="place">Italy</name> (where he had traveled only to learn that the most advanced concepts in landscape design were now originating in <name type="place">France</name>), also constituted the period in which <name type="pname">Jules Hardouin-Mansart</name> was busy directing the last major building phase of Versailles. <name type="pname">Louis</name>, at the height of his power and passion for building, now sought a new retreat, one even more private than the Trianon. At <name type="pname">Marly</name>, overlooking the Seine and Saint-Germain in the distance, he commissioned <name type="pname">Hardouin-Mansart</name> to design a new small <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> with separate guest pavilions in order to ensure the king's privacy (fig. 5.15). By 1683, he was able to host entertainments in the unfinished gardens. Because <name type="pname">Marly</name>, unlike Versailles, enjoyed a hillside location, the king was eager to have <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> design for it a cascade such as the ones he had seen on his recent trip to <name type="place">Italy</name>. However, it was not until <date when="1697">1697</date>&#x2013;<date when="1699">99</date>, just before <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s death, that the project of building La Rivi&#x00E8;re on the slope behind the <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> was accomplished.</p><p>Today all but a few of the marble sculptures that once decorated <name type="pname">Marly</name>, together with an abundance of bronze and marble vases and statues, are displayed at the Louvre. The <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> and guest pavilions have vanished. Only a broad stripe of green turf marks the course of the king's cascade. This piece of grass symbolizes the chief problem that beset not only <name type="pname">Marly</name>, but also Versailles and the Trianon: an insufficiency of water for the more than 1,400 dazzling waterworks these gardens contained. The grotto, <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi> of the Petit Parc at Versailles and the gardens of the Trianon were in the time of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> enlivened with water cascading, purling, leaping, or lying quietly in basins. Water served as one of the principal performers in the pageantry of these landscapes, mirroring their architecture of stone and verdure and animating perspectives. There was, in fact, an insatiable demand to furnish the ever-multiplying fountains, which constantly taxed the ingenuity of the <hi rend="italic">fontainiers</hi>, plumbers, and engineers who worked to increase and maintain water supply and pressure.</p><figure xml:id="fig-191"><graphic url="CH5_015.jpg"/><figDesc>5.14. Plan of the <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi> of Versailles. <date when="1664">1664</date>&#x2013;<date when="1713">1713</date></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-192"><graphic url="CH5_016.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 5.15. <name type="pname">Ch&#x00E2;teau de Marly</name>. Engraving from <hi rend="italic">Recueil des Veues des Plus Beaux Lieux de <name type="place">France</name></hi> by <name type="pname">Adam</name> and <name type="pname">Nicholas P&#x00E9;relle</name>, 1688</figDesc></figure><p>To operate the fountains at Versailles required a corps of highly disciplined workers under a master<hi rend="italic">fontainier</hi>. Rarely was there adequate water to allow all of the fountains to play at once. Boys were commanded to serve as runners when the king or other important visitors toured the gardens, blowing whistles to alert plumbers to turn on valves as the royal entourage approached. The king's hydraulic engi<pb n="178"/><pb n="178" type="orig"/>neers undertook many elaborate and costly schemes to increase the water supply. Between 1682 and 1688, they built a vast contraption known as the Machine de Marly. It was equipped with fourteen huge wheels that powered pumps conveying water from the Seine uphill to two reservoirs, whence it was distributed to the gardens of Marly, Versailles, and the Trianon, But even then the fountains could not all flow simultaneously. After 1684, the military engineer <name type="pname">S&#x00E9;bastien Le Prestre de Vauban</name> directed an ambitious scheme to divert the waters of the Eure River 28 miles (70 kilometers) distant; as many as 30,000 soldiers were set to work, and huge sums of money were spent. In the face of the War of the League of Augsburg, <name type="pname">Louis</name> abandoned the project.</p><figure xml:id="fig-193"><graphic url="CH5_017.jpg"/><figDesc>5.16. Cascade. Sceaux</figDesc></figure><p>The treatment of the royal gardens of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> as vast public works projects employing both military and civilian workers in the movement of earth on a scale hitherto unknown&#x2014;leveling viewobstructing hills, excavating low-lying marshes to form canals, and filling in depressions to create enormous level terraces&#x2014;is evident even in the Potager du Roi, the vegetable garden at Versailles. Here, between 1677 and 1683, <name type="pname">Jean-Baptiste de la Quintinye</name> (<date when="1626">1626</date>&#x2013;<date when="1688">1688</date>), the king's head gardener for fruits and vegetables, oversaw the creation of a 20-acre walled enclosure on low-lying lands to the southeast of the palace with dredged spoil from the Pi&#x00E8;ce d'Eau des Suisses and topsoil from the Satory Hills. A statue of this highly respected man today presides over the extensive <hi rend="italic">potager</hi> with its planting beds carefully delineated by many varieties of espaliered fruit trees.</p><p>It was <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s genius to consolidate the work of such predecessors as <name type="pname">Boyceau</name> and <name type="pname">Lemercier</name> into a style of great architectonic strength, carrying their achievements to a logical conclusion and substituting for the ordered intricacy of the older Renaissance gardens a new clarity, simplicity, austerity, and refinement. <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s legacy lies in his treatment of space as an abstract, geometrical entity, his understanding of spatial optics, and his expansion of landscape design to a monumental scale. This far-reaching legacy is expressed not only at Vaux-le-Vicomte and Versailles, but also in the gardens <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> designed at other royal and noble residences near <name type="place">Paris</name>. He reorganized Fontainebleau according to a grandly simple plan. At Saint-Germain-en-Laye he laid out a new rectangular garden, which replaced that of Henri IV, and at Saint-Cloud, he employed the hilly terrain to good effect, creating a broad <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> that dropped and then ascended to a high point, affording a fine view of <name type="place">Paris</name> in the distance. He gave expression to the power and the optimism of the age at <name type="pname">Colbert</name>'s <hi rend="italic">ch&#x00E2;teau</hi> of Sceaux in the construction of a spectacular cascade and the digging of a 3,465-foot- (1056-meter-) long canal that today, with its reflected border of tall swaying poplars, serves as a canyonlike cloud chamber (fig. 5.16). In another major feat of design and hydraulic engineering, he created the Grand Canal, a great circular basin, and magnificent oval pools at Chantilly between 1671 and 1681 (fig. 5.17).</p><p>In 1700, shortly before <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s death, <name type="pname">Louis</name> and his gardener toured the gardens of Versailles for the last time. Because of his advanced years, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> was invited to ride in a chair wheeled by a footman. With characteristic modesty and frank delight, <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> was heard to exclaim: "Alas! my poor father, had he been alive to see this poor gardener, his own son, riding in a chair beside the greatest king on earth, his happiness would have been complete."<ref target="#CH5-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref></p><p>Between <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s death in 1700 and his own in 1715, <name type="pname">Louis</name> faced family tragedy and became increasingly stoical as he anticipated his own approaching end amid disastrous military defeats and the declining economic power of <name type="place">France</name>.<ref target="#CH5-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref> The vanished glory of his age was soon after captured by eighteenth-century painters such as <name type="pname">Jean-Honor&#x00E9; Fragonard</name> in scenes of figures disporting themselves in the now-derelict great gardens of the epoch of the Sun King, which they saw in their abandonment as sweetly picturesque (see fig. 7.41). A similar air of melancholy vacancy appears in the photographs Eug&#x00E8;ne Atget made of some of Le N&#x00F4;tr&#x00E9;'s gardens at the beginning of the twentieth century.<ref target="#CH5-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref></p><p>The reaction to a static and authoritarian order had already begun to set in as new ideas and voices challenged the spirit of the <hi rend="italic">ancien r&#x00E9;gime</hi>. But <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s influence remained strong. His practice was inherited and his style continued by his nephew <name type="pname">Claude Desgots</name> (d. 1732). In <name type="pname">Antoine-Joseph Dezallier d'Argenville</name> (<date when="1680">1680</date>&#x2013;<date when="1765">1765</date>) <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> found an author who codified his design method in the treatise that he had never found time to write. <name type="pname">Dezallier</name>'s book became a manual for designers commissioned by the courts of <name type="place">Europe</name> to create gardens in the French classical style. As combined with the lingering influence of the Italian garden, it evolved through the first two-thirds of the eighteenth century into an international garden style, which was inflected according<pb n="179"/><pb n="179" type="orig"/>to local conditions and taste. It is a style that is still influential, as can be seen in some of the gardens of the American landscape architects <name type="pname">Dan Kiley</name> and <name type="pname">Peter Walker</name>, for example. It can also be observed in <name type="place">France</name> itself, where the recently built Parc Citro&#x00EB;n in <name type="place">Paris</name> shows how its enduring principles can be translated into a contemporary idiom.</p><figure xml:id="fig-194"><graphic url="CH5_018.jpg"/><figDesc>5.17 Chantilly. Engraving from <hi rend="italic">Recueil des Veues des Plus Beaux Lieux de <name type="place">France</name></hi> by <name type="pname">Adam</name> and <name type="pname">Nicholas P&#x00E9;relle</name>, 1688</figDesc></figure></div></div><div type="section"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">II. The Garden as Theater: Italian Baroque and Rococo Gardens</hi></head><p>The austere harmonies of French classicism never penetrated very deeply into the Italian design ethos. The seventeenth-century Italian style, like that of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>, was an integrative one in which individual parts were organized into a unified composition. But instead of achieving compositional unity with authoritarian axes flung down along lines apparently extending into infinity, the builders of Italian gardens&#x2014;often encouraged by topography&#x2014;wove dramatic hanging terraces and ornamental flights of stairs into hillsides to produce theatrical arrangements of landscape. The dramatic potential of moving water continued to be exploited in the construction of elaborate sculptural cascades like the one at Villa Lante (see fig. 4.25). Unlike French garden designers, whose struggles to furnish water to their fountains, pools, and cascades were herculean and often intensely frustrating as well as wasteful both of capital and human lives, Italian architects were more fortunate in their ability to convey water to their sites in copious quantities, albeit also at the expense of much backbreaking labor and often intense politics. Their gardens were vehicles for princely pomp and display, and the glorification of their patrons became ever more explicit as decorative coats of arms and other family emblems were prominently featured instead of being merely encoded symbolically into the landscape.<ref target="#CH5-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref></p><p>Not only were dramatic astonishment and theatrical perspective effectively used in the layout of Italian Baroque gardens, but also many of the gardens of this period contained actual outdoor theaters with a grassy stage, hedges for wings, and sometimes, peeping forth from the greenery, terra-cotta figures representing stock characters of the <hi rend="italic">commedia dell'arte</hi> tradition popularized by troupes of Italian actors since the second half of the sixteenth century (fig. 5.18). Pastoral drama was echoed in the sculptural Satyrs and Pans that populated garden woods or the edges of garden walks, as well as in the taste for genre figures of peasants engaged in a variety of tasks.</p><p>Italian designers probably found the Cartesian paradigm of non-place-specific axial planning less congenial than one that recognized place as particular and bounded. This may be explained by the fact that the topography throughout much of <name type="place">Italy</name> is hilly, thereby promoting greater opportunity visually for spatial enclosure than for spatial extension. In<pb n="180"/><pb n="180" type="orig"/>addition, Italian designers were more likely to retain, however unconsciously, the concept of <hi rend="italic">topos</hi>&#x2014;the philosophical notion of emplacement derived from <name type="pname">Aristotle</name>&#x2014;because it was already abundantly manifested in the antique classical landscape tradition to which they were heirs. Although much larger than their Italian Renaissance counterparts, on the whole, Italian gardens in the seventeenth century were more intimately scaled than those of contemporary <name type="place">France</name>, and though axes might dissolve into nature, they did not appear to extend into the indefinite distance as if to meet the line of the horizon. In conservative Tuscany, this observation holds true to an even greater degree. A predilection for comparatively simple familial pastimes resulted in relatively small gardens composed of well-proportioned "rooms" of greenery. One French feature, the <hi rend="italic">parterre de broderie</hi>, did gain popularity. By the end of the seventeenth century it had mostly replaced the geometric compartments of traditional <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi>.</p><figure xml:id="fig-195"><graphic url="CH5_019.jpg"/><figDesc>5.18. Green theater with <hi rend="italic">commedia dell'arte</hi> terra-cotta figures. Villa Marlia, near Lucca, <name type="place">Italy</name></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-196"><graphic url="CH5_020.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 5.19. Water Theater with spiral pillars, and Cascade in the background, Villa Aldobrandini, Frascati, <name type="place">Italy</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Giacomo della Porta</name>, <name type="pname">Carlo Maderno</name>, and <name type="pname">Giovanni Fontana</name>. <date when="1601">1601</date>&#x2013;<date when="1621">1621</date>. Engraving by <name type="pname">Giovanni Battista Falda</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Le Fontane delle Ville di Frascati</hi>. Atlas stands beneath the cascade carrying a celestial globe signifying divine wisdom. Originally a figure of <name type="pname">Hercules</name> (now gone) assisted Atlas. Similarly, <name type="pname">Cardinal Aldobrandini</name> wished to be seen as helping <name type="pname">Pope Clement VIII</name> to uphold Christian truth.</figDesc></figure><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Villa Aldobrandini</hi></head><p>By the mid-sixteenth century, nepotism had become thoroughly institutionalized within the Catholic Church, and it was common practice for a pope to appoint a nephew as cardinal to serve in the capacity of trusted assistant during his pontificate. The cardinal-nephew thereby became a strong candidate to suc<pb n="181"/><pb n="181" type="orig"/>ceed him at a later date. At the very least, the influence of this relative as a member of the Church establishment would perpetuate the prestige and wealth of the papal family. Papal villa gardens and those created by the cardinal-nephews were therefore opulent essays in power politics.</p><figure xml:id="fig-197"><graphic url="CH5_021.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Far left:</hi> 5.20. Polyphemus, Water Theater, Villa Aldobrandini. This figure and that of a centaur (fig. 5.21) illustrate a common humanist theme: the struggle of reason over bestiality.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-198"><graphic url="CH5_022.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 5.21. Centaur figure, Water Theater, Villa Aldobrandini</figDesc></figure><p><name type="pname">Frascati</name>, a hillside town outside <name type="place">Rome</name>, was famed, like Tivoli, as a locale of the <hi rend="italic">villeggiatura</hi>, the annual summertime retreat to the country from the heat of the city. It gained prominence after the election of <name type="pname">Pope Clement VIII</name> in 1592, when his nephew <name type="pname">Cardinal Pietro Aldobrandini</name> undertook at great expense the introduction of water from the Molara Springs on Monte Algido. The provision of a waterworks allowed the construction of an impressive cascade and magnificent water theater at the villa he built for himself and his uncle. The architect <name type="pname">Carlo Maderno</name> (c. <date when="1556">1556</date>&#x2013;<date when="1629">1629</date>), assisted by the fountain engineer <name type="pname">Giovanni Fontana</name>, was responsible for this impressive design.</p><p>The relaxed, ample, architectonic muscularity of this garden sequence epitomizes the Italian Baroque garden style. The architectural robustness and play of light and shade characteristic of the period are particularly evident in the semicircular arcaded water theater facing the ground floor of the villa (fig. 5.19). Its sculptural decor displays the naturalistic character, compositional arrangement into counterbalanced diagonals, and thrusting movement into space that we associate with Baroque art in general. The iconographic program, however, is still allusively symbolic&#x2014;a late example of the humanistic messagegarden (figs. 5.20&#x2013;5.21).</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">The Farnese Gardens at Caprarola and on the Palatine Hill, <name type="place">Rome</name></hi></head><p>At Caprarola, near Viterbo, in the first third of the sixteenth century, <name type="pname">Cardinal Alessandro Farnese</name> had commissioned <name type="pname">Antonio da Sangallo</name> the Younger (<date when="1483">1483</date>&#x2013;<date when="1546">1546</date>) to build a fortified palace, a huge pentagonal building with bastions. In 1556, with fear of renewed Spanish invasion diminishing, the cardinal commissioned the architect <name type="pname">Vignola</name> to transform his fortress into a summer villa. It has been saved for discussion here because the additions, which were made around 1620 by <name type="pname">Girolamo Rainaldi</name> (<date when="1570">1570</date>&#x2013;<date when="1655">1655</date>), illustrate the evolution of Italian garden design from a metaphorical fusion of art and nature within the context of a carefully conceived humanistic iconography into a more purely aesthetic architectural statement.</p><p><name type="pname">Caprarola</name>'s significance in the history of landscape design lies in the creation of the Barchetto, a secluded retreat with a <hi rend="italic">casino</hi> and herm-guarded <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi> approached by a quarter-mile-long path leading through the woods from the summer garden next to the palace (figs. 5.22&#x2013;5.25). It was built five years after <name type="pname">Vignola</name>'s death in 1573, probably according to the design of <name type="pname">Giacomo del Duca</name>. Its design as a series of descending terraces built into a hillside, its fountain flanked by reclining river gods, and its curvilinear <hi rend="italic">catena d'acqua</hi>, or water cascade, imitate <name type="pname">Vignola</name>'s achievement at Bagnaia.</p><p>The Barchetto at Caprarola, created in two epochs of garden building&#x2014;with its original form echoing <name type="pname">Vignola</name>'s design at the Villa Lante and its later additions by Rainaldi&#x2014;provides a unique and<pb n="182"/><pb n="182" type="orig"/><q>BARCHETTO, CAPRAROLA</q><figure xml:id="fig-199"><graphic url="CH5_023.jpg"/><figDesc>5.22. Plan of Barchetto, Caprarola. Designed by <name type="pname">Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola</name>, Giacomo del Duca, and Girolamo Rainaldi. <date when="1556">1556</date>&#x2013;<date when="1620">1620</date>. Drawing by <name type="pname">J. C. Shepherd</name> and <name type="pname">G. A. Jellicoe</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Italian Gardens of the Renaissance</hi>, 1925</figDesc></figure><q><hi rend="bold">O</hi>ne approaches the Barchetto today on the same fir-lined path, passing through woods of chestnut, beech, ilex, and holm oak, as did <name type="pname">Cardinal Farnese</name> when he wished to enjoy the privacy of the <hi rend="italic">casino</hi> he had built for summer dining. It is pleasantly surprising to encounter the first of a series of terraces carved into this woodland setting. Here one finds a circular fountain basin above which rises a beautiful water chain modeled on that at the Villa Lante (fig. 5.23; <hi rend="bold">A</hi>). This is composed of pairs of wriggling dolphins, and the playful effect of the water's undulations as it slips over the scalloped basins between the dolphins is similar to the shimmering flow between the curvilinear borders describing an elongated crayfish of <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>'s water channel. Here the gentle cascade is bordered by ramps leading up to a piazza, where river gods recline on either side of a huge vase-shaped fountain <hi rend="bold">B</hi>. From this, jets of water patterned to form the Farnese lily spill water into a basin below (fig. 5.25). Curving ramps lead up to the <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi> <hi rend="bold">C</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">casino</hi> <hi rend="bold">D</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">casino</hi> has a double loggia at its base and a single loggia above where the <hi rend="italic">piano nobile</hi> opens onto an upper terrace. These are the main components of the sixteenthcentury Barchetto.</q><q>The seventeenth-century additions by <name type="pname">Rainaldi</name> exploit the architectural character and dramatic potential of the original scheme. Large torsos of Prudence and Silence, as these figures are known, were mounted on grand carved double pedestals in front of the sixteenth-century walls outlining the sides of the first terrace, adding theatrical intensity and an augmented air of mystery to the space. Boldly scaled rusticated pavilions set between the outer sloping walls on either side of the circular pool and the inner walls, which also slope upward as they define the edges of the twin ramps beside the water chain, give additional architectonic power to the composition. At the piazza of the Vase Fountain, along the curving wall embracing the stairs that lead to the terrace above, forcefully articulated rusticated pilasters framing niches of rough stonework have replaced the sixteenth-century surface, which was probably decorated with stucco reliefs. Also part of the seventeenth-century revision are copies of large antique heads set into the niches and upon the scrolling brackets that ornament the curving walls of rough, banded stonework.</q><q>Ascending the stairs one enters the <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi>. Here the seventeenthcentury planners gave a more powerful spatial definition to the sixteenth-century garden by substituting large herms with expressive faces and gestures for the globe finials that originally decorated the perimeter parapet (fig. 5.24). The vases on their heads give a uniform "cornice line" to the green room of box compartments they preside over, thereby increasing the architectural character of the space. In contrast to <name type="pname">Vignola</name>'s summer and winter gardens adjacent to the palace below, where grottoes, fountains, and classical figures furnished a specific symbolism, there is no special iconographie message to decode here; the herms, believed to be the work of <name type="pname">Pietro Bernini</name> (<date when="1562">1562</date>&#x2013;<date when="1629">1629</date>), are satyric gods gathered in an ordered clearing within the wild woodland, allusive only of the mysterious life forces present in an enchanted spot.</q><pb n="183"/><pb n="183" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-200"><graphic url="CH5_024.jpg"/><figDesc>5.23. <hi rend="italic">Catena d'acqua</hi>, Caprarola</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-201"><graphic url="CH5_025.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 5.24. <hi rend="italic">Giardino segreto</hi> and stairway with a water banister of stone dolphins, Caprarola</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-202"><graphic url="CH5_026.jpg"/><figDesc>5.25. River gods and Vase Fountain, Caprarola</figDesc></figure><pb n="184"/><pb n="184" type="orig"/>beautiful example of the transformation of Italian Renaissance landscape design into innovative Baroque expression. <name type="pname">Rainaldi</name>'s robust architecture and the use of high staircase walls and large-scale sculpture to control movement and shape space in a plastic and dynamic way constitute new developments in the course of landscape design history.</p><figure xml:id="fig-203"><graphic url="CH5_027.jpg"/><figDesc>5.26. Farnese Gardens, Palatine, <name type="place">Rome</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola</name>, <name type="pname">Giacomo del Duca</name>, and <name type="pname">Girolamo Rainaldi</name>. Late 1560s&#x2014;1618. Engraving by <name type="pname">Giovanni Battista Falda</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Li Giardini di Roma</hi>, c. 1670</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-204"><graphic url="CH5_028.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 5.27. Aviary, Farnese Gardens, Palatine, <name type="place">Rome</name>, c. <date when="1618">1618</date>&#x2013;<date when="1633">33</date>. Engraving by <name type="pname">Giovanni Battista Falda</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Li Giardini di Roma</hi>, c. 1670</figDesc></figure><p>One thinks today of Italian gardens primarily in terms of architectural stone and greenery, forgetting the once-important role of flowers. The <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi> of the Farnese palace at Caprarola as well as the one in front of the <hi rend="italic">casino</hi> and the large terrace garden behind it were originally filled with exotic flowers. From old records, we know that several kinds of roses, marigolds, violets, lilies, crocuses, hyacinths, and narcissi, as well as fruit trees&#x2014;oranges, pomegranates, citrons&#x2014;grew in these gardens.<ref target="#CH5-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref> The Farnese pope, Paul III (papacy <date when="1534">1534</date>&#x2013;<date when="1549">1549</date>), was avidly interested in botany an enthusiasm that was continued by his grandson, <name type="pname">Cardinal Alessandro Farnese</name>, as well as by the cardinal's nephew and heir, <name type="pname">Cardinal Odoardo Farnese</name>. Indeed, the scientific interest in botany, a development of the Renaissance, was given new impetus in the seventeenth century, an age of exploration and discovery, when plants from the Americas and <name type="place">Asia</name> were eagerly sought by many wealthy collectors and by botanical gardens, such as those founded at Padua in 1545 and Leiden in 1587. It is not therefore surprising to find in <name type="place">Rome</name> a famous early botanical collection of the wealthy Farnese family, begun in the sixteenth century and continued throughout the seventeenth.</p><p>The Farnese Gardens built atop the Palatine in <name type="place">Rome</name> over the ruins of the palaces of the emperors Tiberius and Domitian were created by various members of the great Farnese family including <name type="pname">Pope Paul III</name>, <name type="pname">Cardinal Alessandro</name>,<ref target="#CH5-n20"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref> and <name type="pname">Cardinal Odoardo Farnese</name> (fig. 5.26). They span the same period from the late Renaissance to the end of the seventeenth century as the successive stages of the Farnese gardens at Caprarola and were probably designed by the same architects&#x2014;<name type="pname">Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola</name>, <name type="pname">Giacomo del Duca</name>, and <name type="pname">Girolamo Rainaldi</name>. They constituted a renowned center for plant propagation and exhibition until archaeologists digging the ruins of imperial <name type="place">Rome</name> in the eighteenth century destroyed them.<ref target="#CH5-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">21</hi></hi></ref></p><p>Several flights of stairs lead to an upper terrace where the main axis is punctuated by a fernencrusted water theater set between the bases of twin aviaries and flanked by a pair of staircases leading up to gardens on the crest of the Palatine (fig. 5.27). The aviaries, which were completed in the first third of the seventeenth century, still stand, but the elaborate gardens that lay beyond them exist only as a partial, pleasing but not historical, twentieth-century design amid the archaeological excavations.</p></div><div type="subsection"><pb n="185"/><pb n="185" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Country Retreats of the Roman Aristocracy: Villa Borghese and Villa Pamphili</hi></head><p>Two of the great estates within <name type="place">Rome</name> assembled by princes of the Church between the last years of the sixteenth century and the end of the seventeenth&#x2014;Villa Borghese and Villa Pamphili&#x2014;today serve as popular public parks. Two other important gardens, Villa Montalto and Villa Ludovisi, were destroyed in the nineteenth century, the former to accommodate the train terminal and rail yards next to the Baths of Diocletian and the latter to profit speculators in the new housing market that was created when <name type="place">Rome</name> became a national capital following the reunification of <name type="place">Italy</name>.</p><p>When <name type="pname">Cardinal Camillo Borghese</name> became <name type="pname">Pope Paul V</name> (papacy <date when="1605">1605</date>&#x2013;<date when="1621">1621</date>), he promptly conferred a cardinalate upon his nephew <name type="pname">Scipione Caffarelli</name>, thereafter known as <name type="pname">Cardinal Borghese</name>. The new cardinal and his relatives soon began amassing land for a large suburban estate, or <hi rend="italic">vigna</hi>, on the Pincian Hill just outside the northern walls of the city. Family pride, sporting pleasure, and aesthetic delight motivated the design of their villa in the early years of the seventeenth century. Although suffering today from insufficient maintenance&#x2014;like many Italian public parks&#x2014;the gardens of the Villa Borghese remain a popular amenity for modern Romans, and its art galleries constitute a museum of international renown. The casino designed by Flaminio Ponzio (<date when="1560">1560</date>&#x2013;<date when="1613">1613</date>), with its extensive decoration completed by the Flemish architect <name type="pname">Jan van Santen</name> (<name type="pname">Giovanni Vasanzio</name>), was conceived as a close cousin of the nearby <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> both in plan and in the heavy ornamentation of its exterior walls (stripped of their sculpture by <name type="pname">Napoleon</name>).</p><p>When completed, the Borghese Gardens consisted of three separate enclosures, or <hi rend="italic">recinti</hi> (fig. 5.28). The first <hi rend="italic">recinto</hi> was a <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> of regular <hi rend="italic">boschetti</hi> (compartments of trees) planted in the 1620s in front of the villa. This section was accessible to the public. A second <hi rend="italic">recinto</hi>, which was reserved for the private use of the family, lay behind the villa. It was planted with groves of holm oak. The third <hi rend="italic">recinto</hi> consisted of a well-stocked game park on the irregular lands to the north. Between the first and second <hi rend="italic">recinti</hi>, the villa was constructed, with an intimately scaled private garden&#x2014;<hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi>&#x2014;placed on either side of it. High walls surrounded the entire estate.</p><p>The wall that originally screened the two <hi rend="italic">giardini segreti</hi> from the transverse avenue running in front of the villa was torn down during the nineteenthcentury modernization in the English style. The condition of these small gardens today is considerably altered from that of the seventeenth century, when they were filled with espaliered citrus trees, freestanding orange trees, and, in the springtime, masses of exotic bulbs. Gone, too, are the birds that sang in copper-netted cages in the twin aviaries that still stand in the northern garden. Beyond the aviaries, which were probably inspired by those of the Farnese Gardens atop the Palatine, is the Meridiana, a sundial.</p><figure xml:id="fig-205"><graphic url="CH5_029.jpg"/><figDesc>5.28. Villa Borghese, <name type="place">Rome</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name>. Main gateway and casino designed by <name type="pname">Flaminio Ponzio</name>. <date when="1609">1609</date>&#x2013;<date when="1617">1617</date>, with decoration by <name type="pname">Giovanni Vasanzio</name>. Gardens laid out beginning in 1608. Engraving by <name type="pname">Simone Felice</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Li Giardini di Roma</hi>, c. 1670</figDesc></figure><p>Aesthetic and sensual pleasures motivated the creation of the Villa Borghese. Art collecting, social entertainment, and hunting were the principal purposes it served. Sculpture was used decoratively in its application to the villa facades and throughout the garden. To understand the change that took place in Italian villa design between the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, one can compare the siting of the Villa Borghese with that of the nearby <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name>. As at the <name type="pname">Villa Aldobrandini</name>, the <name type="pname">Villa Giulia</name> and its garden are powerfully united through axial composition (see fig. 4.12). The Borghese Villa, on the other hand, is not the principal organizing force and focus of axial planning, but simply one element within a broader landscape composition. The landscape itself is treated<pb n="186"/><pb n="186" type="orig"/>in a less particular, more loosely articulated fashion than those of earlier gardens. In all these ways, the Villa Borghese announces its participation in a new era of Italian landscape design.</p><figure xml:id="fig-206"><graphic url="CH5_030.jpg"/><figDesc>5.29. Villa Pamphili, <name type="place">Rome</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name>. Casino designed by <name type="pname">Alessandro Algardi</name>. Casino and gardens built <date when="1644">1644</date>&#x2013;<date when="1648">48</date>. Engraving by <name type="pname">Simone Felice</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Li Giardini di Roma</hi>, c. 1670</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-207"><graphic url="CH5_031.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 5.30. <hi rend="italic">Giardini segreti</hi>, Villa Pamphili</figDesc></figure><p>The tenets of this later style are further illustrated in the Villa Pamphili, atop the <name type="place">Janiculum Hill</name> in <name type="place">Rome</name>. In 1640, <name type="pname">Camillo Pamphili</name> increased the size of the <hi rend="italic">vigna</hi> he had inherited from his father at that location by acquiring another one adjacent to it. Then, upon the election of his uncle as <name type="pname">Pope Innocent X</name> in 1644, <name type="pname">Camillo</name> was chosen to fill the cardinal-nephew position. Although in 1647 he was permitted to resign his cardinalate in order to perpetuate the Pamphili family by marrying <name type="pname">Olimpia Aldobrandini</name>, land purchases continued until 1673, when, under his son, the <hi rend="italic">vigna</hi> reached its ultimate size of 240 acres.</p><p>Begun in 1644, the beautiful <hi rend="italic">casino</hi>, tall, compact, and richly decorated with sculpture and frescoes in the manner of the Villa Borghese, was completed by 1648. Like the Villa Borghese, its primary function was as an art gallery and a place for social entertainment. There were no bedrooms, as the family residence lay a short distance to the west on the Via Aurelia. Although the plan of the <hi rend="italic">casino</hi> was traversed by two of the several wide axes dividing the grounds into a notably regular composition, the elegant structure was not a focal point in the overall design of the gardens (fig. 5.29).</p><p>The low <hi rend="italic">parterres de broderie</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">giardini segreti</hi> next to the villa show French influence on later Italian garden design (fig. 5.30). The transformation of the original compartmentalized design of these <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi> to an embroidered pattern probably did not occur until the eighteenth century, as Italian gardeners long resisted this style, although it had been popularized elsewhere in the mid-seventeenth century through French pattern book engravings.<ref target="#CH5-n22"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref></p><p>Like the Villa Borghese, the Villa Pamphili illustrates the grand scale and quasi-public character of the seventeenth-century Roman garden parks where some members of the populace were occasionally permitted entry. In their rich display of architecture and sculpture to ennoble and dramatize landscape, these great Roman villas memorialize the opulent lives of the princes of the Church in an age of proudly ambitious aristocracy.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Tuscan Garden Design: Villa Garzoni and La Gamberaia</hi></head><p>In Tuscany, outside the Italian center of international power, the breadth of scale and architectural grandeur found in the Villa Borghese and the Villa Pamphili remained foreign. Although in villas around <name type="place">Florence</name> and Lucca one finds Roman design idioms&#x2014;for instance, hanging hillside terraces with vase-topped balustrades, cascades, and ornamental sculpture&#x2014;these characteristics are manifested in a far less<pb n="187"/><pb n="187" type="orig"/>extravagant manner. Most of the gardens of Tuscany built in the seventeenth century have an affinity with earlier gardens such as those of the <name type="pname">Villa Medici</name> at <name type="place">Fiesole</name>. Their designs are conservative, usually composed as a series of outdoor rooms with views of the surrounding agricultural landscape of olive trees and vineyards. One of these is usually a <hi rend="italic">limonaia</hi>, a walled garden filled with potted lemon trees, which were removed in the winter to an adjacent long, barnlike conservatory (fig. 5.31). But Tuscan gardens show innovative and evolutionary tendencies as well, first those characteristic of a Baroque sensibility, and later those of the graceful Rococo style of the eighteenth century, when many additions or remodelings of old gardens were made.</p><p>Where the nineteenth-century fashion for English-style gardens did not obliterate the original designs and restoration has been possible, present-day maintenance costs and a preference for abstraction have caused the planting schemes of these old gardens to be simplified. But in the best-preserved of them, we may still find the exuberant curvilinear movement and ornamentation characteristic of the Baroque style. It is to be seen in the black-and-white pebbleornamented walls, the pebble mosaic paving, the sculptural hedges, the lavish use of ornamental statuary (much of it in terra-cotta), the water theaters, and the intimate green theaters in which <hi rend="italic">commedia dell'arte</hi> performances were held&#x2014;all of which are characteristic of this golden age of Tuscan garden design.</p><p>The outlying garden closest in spirit to the Roman Baroque models is that of the Villa Garzoni in Collodi, near Lucca, a composition of hillside terraces with robust balusters and lighthearted sculptural decoration, arabesque floral <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi> with heraldic devices in colored pebble mosaic, and a water cascade issuing from a grotto, above which soars a figure of Fame trumpeting her horn (figs. 5.32, 5.33). The villa itself bears a curious relationship to the garden because of its origins as a defensive castle strategically sited with a ramp leading from the town below.<ref target="#CH5-n23"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">23</hi></hi></ref> Purchased by the Garzoni family from the Republic of Lucca in the early years of the seventeenth century, it was transformed into a villa with gardens on the adjacent slope several decades later. Subsequent improvements, such as the addition of a bathhouse near the apex of the cascade, were made in the eighteenth century under the direction of the Lucchese architect Ottaviano Diodati.</p><figure xml:id="fig-208"><graphic url="CH5_032.jpg"/><figDesc>5.31. <hi rend="italic">Limonaia</hi>. <name type="place">Vicobella</name>, <name type="place">Siena</name></figDesc></figure><p>Central niches reinforce the main axis between each set of double stairs. In keeping with the more frivolous spirit of the later age, these and various side niches are inhabited by a whimsical blend of genre figures and pagan deities. Here and elsewhere, in the company of Apollo, <name type="pname">Diana</name>, Pomona, Ceres, Bacchus, and other familiar mythological garden residents including fauns and herms, one finds sculpted peasants engaged in agricultural pursuits. Thus, the grotto with Neptune rising in his horse-drawn chariot from the sea occupies the niche on a middle terrace, while a peasant holding a cask is contained in the terrace below, and a peasant with a <name type="place">turkey</name> stands in the one above. These three niches are heavily framed with rusticated stone set against walls of <hi rend="italic">rocaille</hi>-work fashioned into black-and-white arabesques. Black-and-white pebble-mosaic paving ornaments the ground plane in<pb n="188"/><pb n="188" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-209"><graphic url="CH5_033.jpg"/><figDesc>5.32. Plan of Villa Garzoni, Collodi, near Lucca, <name type="place">Italy</name>. Drawing by <name type="pname">J. C. Shepherd</name> and <name type="pname">G. A. Jellicoe</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Italian Gardens of the Renaissance</hi>, 1925</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-210"><graphic url="CH5_034.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 5.33. Villa Garzoni</figDesc></figure><pb n="189"/><pb n="189" type="orig"/>several places, continuing the characteristically Baroque curvilinear surface patterning. A terra-cotta band of twelve monkeys playing ball adds piquant charm to the balustrades of the upper terraces (fig. 5.34).</p><p>From here one can look down and appreciate the arabesques of box <hi rend="italic">broderie</hi> surrounding twin circular pools, the elaborate floral and stone mosaic <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> with the Garzoni monogram and heraldic devices, and the curvilinear cresting of the sculptured yew hedge that contains the whole of the lower garden in a generous embrace. An outer hedge parallels this hedge, creating a shady walkway around the perimeter of the lower garden.</p><p>Close association of the garden with its agrarian environs; intimacy of scale and conservative retention of old forms such as lemon gardens; shady <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> of ilex trees, terra-cotta figures, sculptured hedges, and pebble mosaic walks&#x2014;all characteristic elements of the Tuscan garden&#x2014;can be found at La Gamberaia in Settignano on the outskirts of <name type="place">Florence</name> (figs. 5.35&#x2013;5.38). The artful twentieth-century restoration of this garden forsakes historic accuracy, instead emphasizing the abstract geometries of its Baroque shapes and animating its period character in other ways that are pleasing to contemporary taste.</p><p>The place takes its name from that of the original owners of the property, the Gambarelli family. According to a plaque over the door, in 1610, <name type="pname">Zanobi Lapi</name> erected the handsome simple villa around a central court. The garden was laid out between 1624 and 1635 by his nephews and heirs. During the eighteenth century, the Capponi family owned the property, and they altered and embellished it with statuary fountains, and a long green bowling alley. A <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi> was set into the hillside beneath the lemon garden at this time. Seriously mutilated during World War II, La Gamberaia was subsequently acquired by <name type="pname">Marcello Marchi</name>, who restored it to its present excellent condition.</p><figure xml:id="fig-211"><graphic url="CH5_035.jpg"/><figDesc>5.34. Staircase with monkeys, Villa Garzoni</figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Extravagant End of an Era: Isola Bella and Caserta</hi></head><p>Entirely different in spirit from the quiet conservatism and unassuming beauty of Tuscan gardens, Isola Bella, Count Carlo Borromeo's grandiose fantasy in Lake Maggiore in northern <name type="place">Italy</name>, is unsurpassed as an illustration of the theatrical character of Italian Baroque design (fig. 5.39, see pp. 2&#x2013;3). Today Isola Bella is more lush and romantically patinated by time than it was when, from 1630 to 1670, the Borromeos leveled an island off the coast of Stresa in Lake Maggiore and erected the great tiered galleon of a garden named in honor of Count Carlo's wife, <name type="pname">Isabella</name>. The fundamental theatricality of this unusual landscape comes from its phantasmagorical appearance, rising improbably like a ghostly vessel from the clear mountainfringed waters of Lake Maggiore. Its wedding cake of terraces opens out to embrace the view, and its high cresting sculptures gesture into space (fig. 5.40).</p><p>Because of the shape of the island, the garden is not on axis with the palace; the relationship of the two is camouflaged by trees, and one does not realize that upon climbing the stairs of the interconnecting Courtyard of <name type="pname">Diana</name>, with its pebble-faced, arched niches and statue of the goddess, one has changed directions. The <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi> above were originally laid out as <hi rend="italic">broderies</hi> in the French fashion. Facing these is a<pb n="190"/><pb n="190" type="orig"/><q>LA GAMBERAIA</q><figure xml:id="fig-212"><graphic url="CH5_036.jpg"/><figDesc>5.35. Plan of La Gamberaia Settignano, near <name type="place">Florence</name>, <name type="place">Italy</name>. Garden built <date when="1624">1624</date>&#x2013;<date when="1635">35</date>; altered and embellished by Capponi family after 1717; restored with water <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi> by Princess Ghyka, early twentieth century. Drawing by <name type="pname">J. C. Shepherd</name> and <name type="pname">G. A. Jellicoe</name>, from <hi rend="italic">Italian Gardens of the Renaissance</hi>, 1925 <hi rend="bold">A</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nymphaeum</hi>. <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Bowling lawn. <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Entrance. <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Bosco. <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Lemonaia. <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Water <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi></figDesc></figure><q><hi rend="bold">O</hi>ne enters La Gamberaia from a gate that leads up a long hedge-bordered drive to the principal portal of the villa. To the right, facing west, overlooking its immediate landscape of olive trees and, beyond this, the city of <name type="place">Florence</name>, is a grassy terrace contained by a low parapet surmounted by Baroque finials and stone dogs. To the left of the villa entrance, extending all along its eastern side and beyond to the north and south, lies the turf bowling alley flanked by a high, urn-surmounted retaining wall of stucco. The long surface of this wall is broken by painted panels of geometric design and enlivened by a pattern of dark stucco resembling a balustrade. Tall cypresses mark the northern end of the bowling green, and there one finds a <hi rend="italic">nymphaeum</hi> of decorative black-andwhite <hi rend="italic">rocaille</hi>-work with reliefs of two musicians on the outside and Neptune flanked by lions on the inside. To the south, this avenue of grass ends in a balcony overlooking Tuscan vineyards and olive trees.</q><q>The retaining wall separates the bowling lawn from an elevated <hi rend="italic">bosco</hi> of mature ilex and a fine lemon garden. This lemon garden overlooks the eighteenth-century <hi rend="italic">giardino segreto</hi>, a narrow court of elaborate <hi rend="italic">rocaille</hi>-work, now filled with pots of hydrangeas (fig. 5.36). Surrounded by a balcony balustrade decorated with stone busts and urns as well as a figure of the god Pan at its eastern end, it is entered by ornamental staircases on either side. Light and shadow play over its wisteriadraped, fern-sprouting rustic walls and terra-cotta statues set within niches. La Gamberaia's <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> garden has wellproportioned pools of water instead of planting beds, a curving hedge with arched openings overlooking the Arno Valley, and stone putti peeping forth from immaculately clipped topiary (figs. 5.37, 5.38).</q><pb n="191"/><pb n="191" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-213"><graphic url="CH5_037.jpg"/><figDesc>5.36. <hi rend="italic">Giardino segreto</hi>, La Gamberaia</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-214"><graphic url="CH5_038.jpg"/><figDesc>5.37. Villa La Gamberaia</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-215"><graphic url="CH5_039.jpg"/><figDesc>5.38. Water <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi>, La Gamberaia</figDesc></figure><pb n="192"/><pb n="192" type="orig"/>water theater. One mounts a set of concave-convex stairs to arrive at the terrace upon which this extravagant confection, encrusted with pebbles and decorated with niches framing giant scallop shells and statuary, rears against the sky. Projecting into the blue Alpine backdrop is the family emblem&#x2014;a prancing unicorn&#x2014;and plume-capped obelisks, as well as several oversized statues. Behind the water theater, from another small <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> garden, one may look down upon other Borromean splendors: fountains, exotic plants, rare flowers, and a flock of white peacocks.</p><figure xml:id="fig-216"><graphic url="CH5_040.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Top:</hi> 5.39. Isola Bella, Lake Maggiore, <name type="place">Italy</name>. c. <date when="1630">1630</date>&#x2013;<date when="1670">70</date></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-217"><graphic url="CH5_041.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Above:</hi> 5.40. Gardens, Isola Bella</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-218"><graphic url="CH5_042.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 5.41. Cascade, La Reggia, Caserta, near Naples, <name type="place">Italy</name>. Designed by <name type="pname">Luigi Vanvitelli</name>. 1752</figDesc></figure><p>By the eighteenth century, courts all over <name type="place">Europe</name> were imitating the design concepts developed a century earlier by <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> in <name type="place">France</name>. At Caserta, near Naples, <name type="pname">Charles III</name>, the Bourbon king of <name type="place">Spain</name>, Naples, and Sicily, hired Luigi Vanvitelli (<date when="1700">1700</date>&#x2013;<date when="1773">1773</date>) to design the gardens of La Reggia in 1752 in a manner and on a scale clearly meant to rival Versailles. The immensely long canal axis, nearly 2 miles (5 kilometers), does not stretch illusionistically into the distance, however, but ends in an Italian-style hillside cascade (fig. 5.41). This monument to Bourbon grandeur is made vacuous by its sheer size, since it lacks the same understanding of optics based on laws of perspective, the same integration of parts into mathematical harmonies of scale, and the artful grade manipulations and incidents of intricacy that give variety and surprise to <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s grand compositions. In short, the subtle intelligence that provided both grace and power in <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s designs is largely absent in Vanvitelli's work, and Caserta remains interesting primarily for the ambition it displays.</p><p>The French classical style, as we have seen, was informed by Cartesian mathematics and the politics of authority. It was forged in the crucible of the postCopernican view of the cosmos as not being Earthcentered and spherically contained, but heliocentric and open-ended. The Italian Baroque style, on the other hand, expresses a lofty confidence based less on science than upon its rich patrimony from the antique past. This confidence was combined with theatrical zest to produce bold architectural effects and grandiose sculptural compositions. Together, these two traditions were imitated in countless places, sometimes separately, sometimes in combination, often with modifications because of local culture and topographic conditions. Until revolution and Romanticism discredited the royal and aristocratic patronage that had created them, they constituted a formal design vocabulary that became the idiom of courts and cities throughout <name type="place">Europe</name>.</p></div><div type="subsection"><pb n="193"/><pb n="193" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Five</hi></head><note xml:id="CH5-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Robert W. Berger</name>, <hi rend="italic">In the Garden of the Sun King: Studies on the Park of Versailles Under <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name></hi> (<name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>: Dumbarton Oaks, 1985), Chapter 2, for a good discussion of the role of Petite Acad&#x00E9;mie (later renamed the Acad&#x00E9;mie Royale des Inscriptions et Medailles) in determining the iconographic program at Versailles. The Petite Acad&#x00E9;mie was an institution devoted to developing an iconography of royal glorification that could be applied to the creation of medals commemorating the deeds of the king as well as to the decoration of royal buildings. Richelieu by his own example was responsible for initiating a building craze among the aristocracy. During the first half of the seventeenth century more than three hundred new <hi rend="italic">h&#x00F4;tels</hi> and gardens were built in <name type="place">Paris</name>. French pride in their capital dates from this period, and although <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> had no particular desire to live there, he was nonetheless supportive of the city's increasing beautification.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p>According to philosophy <name type="pname">professor Edward Casey</name>, for <name type="pname">Descartes</name> "the spatial world is to be grasped as a plenary, seamless realm of <hi rend="italic">res extensae</hi>&#x2014;of material things whose very nature consists in their extension." See <name type="pname">Edward Casey</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Fate of Place: A Philosophical History</hi> (<name type="place">Berkeley</name>: University of California Press, 1997), p. 154.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p>The king, fearing the political consequences of rationalism, forbade the teaching of <name type="pname">Descartes</name>'s theories in French schools.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p>For my discussion of <name type="pname">Mansart</name>, I am indebted to <name type="pname">Kenneth Woodbridge</name>, <hi rend="italic">Princely Gardens: The Origins and Development of the French Formal Style</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Rizzoli, 1986), pp. 166&#x2013;78. Much of what follows in this chapter describing seventeenthcentury French gardens and landscape designers is derived from my reading of this indispensable volume on the subject.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre</name> collected painting and sculpture, bequeathing near the end of his life to <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>, the king whom he had served so long and so well, his fine collection of <name type="pname">Poussins</name>, <name type="pname">Claude Lorrains</name>, and other masters of the French School along with many fine antique marble and bronze sculptures.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Fouquet</name>'s device, appropriately enough, was the high-vaulting squirrel; his enemy and successor <name type="pname">Colbert</name>, with greater wisdom, chose as his symbol the lowly grass snake.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p>A useful guide for experiencing the unfolding perspectives of Vaux-le-Vicomte is that provided by the architectural historian Franklin Hamilton Hazelhurst, whose diagrams and sketches illustrate <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>'s manipulations of grade and perspective to achieve a masterfully rational yet boldly dramatic design. See <hi rend="italic">Gardens of Illusion: The Genius of <name type="pname">Andr&#x00E9; Le Nostre</name></hi> (<name type="place">Nashville, Tenn.</name>: Vanderbilt University Press, 1980), pp. 17&#x2013;45.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Denise</name> and <name type="pname">Jean-Pierre Le Dantec</name>, <hi rend="italic">Reading the French Garden: Story and History</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge, Mass.</name>: MIT Press, 1990), pp. 116&#x2013;17. The authors' assertion that La Fontaine was possibly associated in some way with Vaux is supported by the fact that he was a few years later directly responsible for the thematic development of the Labyrinthe at Versailles. For a complete discussion of his contributions to the iconographic program there, see Robert W. Berger, <hi rend="italic">In the Garden of the Sun King</hi> (<name type="place">Washington, D.C.</name>: Dumbarton Oaks, 1985), Chapter 4.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p>From an account by La Fontaine, <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres diverse</hi>, La Pl&#x00E9;iade, pp. 522&#x2013;27, as quoted in <name type="pname">Bernard Jeannel</name>, <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name></hi> (<name type="place">Paris</name>: Fernand Hazan, 1985), p. 42.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p>At the time of <name type="pname">Fouquet</name>'s memorable party, <name type="pname">Louis</name> was deeply in love with <name type="pname">Louise de La Valli&#x00E8;re</name>, his first publicly acknowledged mistress. And it was to honor his love for <name type="pname">Louise</name>, as well as to create the spaces for the delightful summer entertainments that would celebrate his reign, that he commissioned work to progress during the greater part of the 1660s. As the garden historian <name type="pname">William Howard Adams</name> has remarked, "The sequence of the development of the gardens at Versailles is intimately related to the emerging power of the King, his concept of the monarchy, and his love affairs. All three influences were at times entangled in the expansion and use of the gardens to further the King's policies or to celebrate an amorous conquest." See <name type="pname">Howard Adams</name>, <hi rend="italic">The French Garden <date when="1500">1500</date>&#x2013;<date when="1800">1800</date></hi>, (<name type="place">New York</name>: George Braziller, 1979), p. 84.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p>Almost twenty years older than the king, <name type="pname">Colbert</name> tried to lecture the young monarch on the unsuitability of such a poor place as the symbolic representation of the greatest king in the world. But <name type="pname">Louis</name> was an absolute monarch firmly in command of his own will, and <name type="pname">Colbert</name> was forced to gracefully submit as he took on the job of overseeing <name type="pname">Louis</name>'s ambitious building program at Versailles. See <name type="pname">Jeannel</name>, op. cit., p. 46.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Louis XIV</name> had been king since the age of five. He had lived through the civil disturbances known as the Fronde, lasting from 1648 to 1653, during which time a rebellious Parlement in league with <name type="pname">Louis Il de Bourbon</name>, prince of Cond&#x00E9;, had attempted to wrest power from the Queen Mother, Anne of Austria, and her chief minister, <name type="pname">Cardinal Mazarin</name>. This left a lasting impression on the king, who was forever suspicious of any challenge to his supreme authority or the concentration of power, however slight, in any hands other than his own. The Dragon, like the Python, was used as a symbol of the rebellion of the Fronde, and, as the swans surrounding this figure were the attributes of Apollo, the putti riding the swans can be read as the youthful <name type="pname">Louis</name> resisting the plotters against the divine right of kings. See <name type="pname">Berger</name>, op. cit., p. 26.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Latona</name> with her two children can be read as the mother of <name type="pname">Louis XIV</name>, who, with her sons, <name type="pname">Louis</name> and <name type="pname">Philippe</name>, suffered the indignities of the <hi rend="italic">frondeurs</hi>, or rebels, whose representation here as frogs carries the explicit message of royal triumph. See <name type="pname">Berger</name>, op. cit., p. 26</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p>Seeking the king's attentions, <name type="pname">Ath&#x00E9;na&#x00EF;s</name> had become the friend and confidante of her predecessor, <name type="pname">Louise de La Valli&#x00E8;re; Madame de Montespan</name>, in turn, was replaced in 1675, after she had borne the king several children, by their governess, <name type="pname">Madame Scarron</name>&#x2014;or <name type="pname">Madame de Maintenon</name> as she had become known after the king, following <name type="pname">Madame Montespan</name>'s pleas, bought for her the estate of Maintenon.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p><name type="pname">Louis</name>, <name type="pname">Duc de Saint-Simon</name>, <hi rend="italic"><name type="pname">Saint Simon</name> at Versailles</hi>, ed. <name type="pname">Lucy Norton</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Harper Brothers, 1958), pp. 58&#x2013;59.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p>The tragedies of the king's old age included the loss of the two heirs-apparent: his son, the <name type="pname">Dauphin</name>, in 1711, and his grandson, the duc de Bretagne, who along with his wife, the princess of Savoy, died of measles in 1712.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p>For an excellent discussion of Atget's work in the gardens of <name type="pname">Le N&#x00F4;tre</name>, see <name type="pname">William Howard Adams</name>, <hi rend="italic">Atget's Gardens</hi> (Garden City, <name type="place">New York</name>: Doubleday &amp; Company, Inc., 1979).</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p>The Villa Lante provides a useful example illustrating this point: <name type="pname">Cardinal Gambara</name>'s crayfish is cunningly woven into the fabric of the sixteenth-century garden, whereas <name type="pname">Cardinal Montalto</name>'s device of three mountains surmounted by a star, which was added in the seventeenth century, is much more obviously and ostentatiously displayed in the central fountain of the <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> garden where it is held aloft by the figures of four youths with lions (see fig. 4.27).</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">David Coffin</name>, <hi rend="italic">Gardens and Gardening in Papal <name type="place">Rome</name></hi> (<name type="place">Princeton, N. J.</name>: Princeton University Press, 1991), p. 198; also <name type="pname">Georgina Masson</name>, <hi rend="italic">Italian Gardens</hi> (<name type="place">Woodbridge, Suffolk</name>: Antique Collector's Club, 1987), pp. 140&#x2013;41.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">20.</hi></seg><p>The financial resources, opulent lifestyle, intellectual curiosity, and aesthetic sensibilities of this prince of the Church can be gauged by the fact that, in addition to the Orti Farnese and the villa at Caprarola, he purchased and enjoyed the old Chigi villa on the banks of the Tiber, designed by <name type="pname">Baldassare Tommaso Peruzzi</name> (<date when="1481">1481</date>&#x2013;<date when="1536">1536</date>) and decorated by <name type="pname">Raphael</name>, which has since been known as the Farnesina.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">21.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Coffin</name>, op. cit., p. 208.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">22.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Coffin</name>, op. cit., pp. 160&#x2013;62. Coffin suggests that, since the mid-seventeenth century engravings of Villa Pamphili that depict embroidered <hi rend="italic">parterres</hi> were by a French engraver, they may have been represented according to the contemporary French convention well in advance of their actual conversion to this style.</p></note><note xml:id="CH5-n23" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">23.</hi></seg><p>The road actually passed through the villa until its most recent restoration and remodeling in the 1950s.</p></note></div></div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>