<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/html/tei.xsl"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY</title>
                <author>ELIZABETH BARLOW ROGERS</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>HARRY N. ABRAMS, INC.,</publisher>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY by ELIZABETH BARLOW
                    ROGERS</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter">
                <pb n="434"/>
                <pb n="434" type="orig"/>
                <head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER THIRTEEN A NEW LANDSCAPE AESTHETIC: THE MODERNIST
                        GARDEN</hi></head>
                <figure xml:id="fig-534">
                    <graphic url="CH13_001.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Since the beginning of the nineteenth century, an eclectic application of past
                    styles of landscape design had substituted for one expressing in a forthright,
                    forceful, and original manner the tenets of contemporary Machine Age culture. Le
                    Corbusier railed famously against "the Styles," and when architectural modernism
                    at last found widespread acceptance, it became doctrinal in its radical break
                    with tradition. No longer would architects camouflage the structural engineering
                    systems of new buildings with the decor of previous eras as had been the case in
                    modern nineteenth-century <name type="place">Paris</name>, where carved masonry
                    was applied as a veneer over industrial materials. In the same way that modern
                    artists sought to abandon old formalist values including single-point
                    perspective as the generally accepted convention of spatial representation,
                    architects sought to express an entirely new aesthetic that was functionalist,
                    democratic, and overtly expressive of machine technology. The avoidance of
                    Neoclassical planning principles and handcrafted ornamentation became an article
                    of faith for modern architects. Yet, while modern architecture overthrew
                    eclecticism and developed its own radically functionalist aesthetic, landscape
                    architecture lagged behind.</p>
                <p>A somewhat debased version of Arts and Crafts garden style was well suited to the
                    agenda of an expanding nursery industry with a broad array of plant materials
                    and garden ornaments for sale. Moreover, the machinelike precision found in
                    modernist architecture and a good deal of modern art was never wholly applicable
                    to landscape design, because nature is biological and tectonic, not static.
                    However hard-edged a ground plan may be, if it contains plants and soil and
                    responds to the dynamics of natural ecosystems, its forms are inevitably subject
                    to growth, decay, and the resulting organic transformation these processes
                    involve. So argued those who sought to maintain a traditionalist approach to
                    landscape design in the face of architectural modernism. In the United States,
                    throughout the <date when="1930">1930</date>s the Harvard's Graduate School of
                    Design, the leading professional school for training in landscape architecture,
                    remained firmly committed to a Beaux-Arts-based curriculum with its emphasis
                    upon an Italianate stylistic vocabulary, even as Walter Gropius was transforming
                    the school's architecture department into an outpost of the European
                    avant-garde.</p>
                <p>But as provincialism and reactionary taste succumbed to the establishment of
                    modern art and as modern architecture gained status and began to seem less
                    revolutionary, American professionals began at last to participate in the spirit
                    of landscape design innovation that the French had pioneered at the <date
                        when="1925">1925</date> Exposition Internationale des Arts D&#x00E9;coratifs
                    et Industriels Modernes (International Exhibition of Modern Decorative and
                    Industrial Arts). Unlike previous World's Fairs, which had emphasized
                    technological progress, this one was distinguished by the impulse on the part of
                    the French to establish cultural leadership in the design arts. Within the
                    Fair's articulation of a vocabulary of design forms&#x2014;now nostalgically
                    recalled and revived as Art Moderne or Art Deco&#x2014;existed several early
                    experiments that attempted to ally landscape with modernism. But modernism had
                    many faces besides the one of streamlined luxe known as Art Deco, including the
                    machine aesthetic of the Bauhaus and of Le Corbusier, whose architecture was
                    represented as one of the fair's pavilions. A Mediterranean spirit often
                    informed it. Chinese and Japanese influences were present, too.</p>
                <p>By the late <date when="1930">1930</date>s, the carriers of modernism's several
                    cultural crosscurrents included Mexican and South American landscape designers
                    as well as European and American ones. Like architecture, landscape design
                    became a regionally inflected international idiom. Although the United States
                    still looked to Europe in cultural matters, the country's prosperity and the
                    developments in industrial design as new consumer goods were produced following
                    World War II created a climate that was congenial to innovation<pb n="435"/><pb
                        n="435" type="orig"/>and the eventual assumption of a leadership role in the
                    arts. This process was no doubt encouraged by the immigration to the United
                    States from the <date when="1930">1930</date>s onward of several European
                    artists of rare genius. In addition, now, more than ever, travel abroad was seen
                    as a valuable extension of the professional education of American designers
                    along with the study of internationally circulated periodicals and books
                    portraying the new. A stripped-down form of Beaux-Arts landscape design
                    prevailed in a good deal of American public park design as late as the <date
                        when="1950">1950</date>s, as is evident from the parks built in <name
                        type="place">New York</name> City and under the administration of <name
                        type="pname">Robert Moses</name> (see Chapter Twelve). Nevertheless,
                    traditional landscape architecture based on Neoclassical planning principles had
                    begun to seem anachronistic within the context of modernism's disavowal of
                    historic styles and the premium it put on a certain shock value in the arts.</p>
                <p>Moreover, within the context of a democratic society traditionalism was
                    associated with a conservative elite. Progressive landscape architects needed to
                    produce plans that were suitable for the construction budgets, lot sizes, and
                    lives of middle-class homeowners. The emphasis modern people put on sports and
                    physical recreation caused them to want houses and gardens that were more casual
                    in appearance than those of former times, with open floor plans and informal
                    ground plans that permitted the same unconstricted movement as did the relaxed
                    clothing they now wore. This casual lifestyle, especially in <name type="place"
                        >California</name> where a freewheeling cultural ethos prevailed overall,
                    encouraged a fresh approach to landscape design. Here and in other warm-climate
                    areas, outdoor entertaining and relaxation in and around a swimming pool were
                    important elements in the landscape designer's program.</p>
                <p>The spirit of radical innovation that characterized art and architecture of the
                    modernist period gave license to the landscape designer to experiment with new
                    forms and materials. New design concepts&#x2014;the use of overlapping planes
                    rather than axial alignment to provide spatial continuity, experimentation with
                    both traditional and nontraditional materials, use of abstract biomorphic forms
                    as emblems and expressions of organic fluidity, and an innovative application of
                    the machine aesthetic to garden structures furnished the modernist landscape
                    with its own distinctive idiom as it addressed the age-old problem of exploiting
                    visually the juxtaposition of the natural and the artificial.</p>
                <p>Compensating for the elimination of applied ornament in Machine Age modern
                    architecture was the new status given freestanding sculpture. The visual impact
                    of the bronze nude by Georg Kolbe in the courtyard of the Barcelona Pavilion
                    Mies van der Rohe built for that city's <date when="1929">1929</date> World's
                    Fair is enhanced by the duty it performs, which is beyond all inherent aesthetic
                    merit, as the only nonmachine form within the structure, demonstrating the power
                    of a single art object to arrest and satisfy the eye as it completes its
                    movement through the building's serenely impersonal overlapping spatial planes.
                    So, too, as landscape architecture became more avowedly functional and abstract,
                    several designers found that the perfectly placed piece by Jacques Lipchitz or
                    Henry Moore gave compositional focus to their plans. Sculpture had, of course,
                    been at home in the garden since ancient times, as we have amply discovered in
                    this book, but with the advent of modernism it took up residence in the
                    landscape devoid of the didactic or memorial intent of former times. In the
                    modern garden sculpture was not intended as part of any allegorical program, nor
                    was it meant to serve as commemoration; it was displayed simply as aesthetic
                    object. The installation of outdoor sculpture according to the reputation of the
                    artist rather than that of the subject depicted is a modernist contribution to
                    landscape design. Corporations took a major role in this regard, and the same
                    companies that commissioned prestigious modern architects to design their
                    headquarters also installed major works of sculpture in adjacent plazas or
                    surrounding industrial parks.</p>
                <p>The challenges facing twentieth-century designers who sought to practice within
                    the broader context of a rapidly transforming society with objectives that were
                    more democratic in purpose than the provision of corporate prestige or idyllic
                    retreats for the wealthy were considerable. As had been true in past ages, many
                    of the patrons who commissioned modern gardens, corporate campuses, and
                    high-style modern buildings with sculpture courts or plazas were indeed wealthy.
                    Modernism's confidence in design as a primary means of addressing social
                    problems now seems overweening and, in light of the record, often wrongheaded.
                    This has promoted the current return to neo-traditional principles in urban
                    planning that we will examine in Chapter Fifteen. But the landscape architects
                    who came of age in the first half of the twentieth century shared the same
                    optimism that we observed in the previous chapter as we studied the regional
                    planners who sought to rationally guide metropolitan growth or the starry-eyed
                    futurists who displayed their upbeat technologically oriented scenarios for the
                    World of Tomorrow at the <name type="place">New York</name>
                    <date when="1939">1939</date> World's Fair. Especially in <name type="place"
                        >America</name>, which was less scarred than Europe by the twentieth
                    century's two World Wars, modernism held forth a sense of immense possibilities,
                    and in an age that has become fetishistic about preserving and replicating the
                    past, this optimism about the future may seem enviable to some.</p>
                <div type="section">
                    <pb n="436"/>
                    <pb n="436" type="orig"/>
                    <head><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Transitional Experimentation: Design Idioms of the
                            Early Twentieth Century</hi></head>
                    <p>The <date when="1925">1925</date> Exposition Internationale des Arts
                        D&#x00E9;coratifs et Industriels Modernes (International Exhibition of
                        Modern Decorative and Industrial Arts) in <name type="place">Paris</name>
                        was guided by impulses different from those that stimulated the <name
                            type="place">New York</name> World's Fair of <date when="1939"
                            >1939</date>. The <name type="place">New York</name> fair was a
                        demonstration of burgeoning American industrial might and the consumerist
                        future. The <date when="1925">1925</date>
                        <name type="place">Paris</name> Exhibition was undertaken in large measure
                        as a chauvinistic means of reasserting <name type="place">France</name>'s
                        traditional hegemony as a stylistic trendsetter and unrivaled leader in the
                        decorative arts.<ref target="#CH13-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                >1</hi></hi></ref>Coming between the waning Arts and Crafts
                        tradition and the rise of international modernism, the <name type="place"
                            >Paris</name> fair represented not only a pivotal point in design
                        history but also a definitive moment in the final stages of the cultural
                        transition from an ethos of privilege to one of equality, which had been
                        under way since the eighteenth century. Unlike the <date when="1939"
                            >1939</date>
                        <name type="place">New York</name> fair, which held out a clear vision of
                        mass prosperity, the one in <name type="place">Paris</name>, in spite of its
                        declared intention to honor "art in life," nevertheless exuded an imagery of
                        opulence and luxury, albeit in Machine Age terms and on a compact scale in
                        keeping with the economic realities of the times.</p>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">The French Modernist Garden</hi></head>
                        <p><name type="pname">Jean-Claude Nicolas Forestier</name> (<date
                                when="1861">1861</date>&#x2013;<date when="1930">1930</date>), the
                            landscape architect who had had design responsibilities for several of
                            the parks of <name type="place">Paris</name> since <date when="1887"
                                >1887</date>, was put in charge of all parks and gardens at the
                            exhibition. Clearly evident was his own stylistic preference for Gallic
                            formality softened by an Arts and Crafts horticultural palette and
                            enlivened eclectically through the influence of Persia and southern
                            Spain. Also evident was the influence of Cubism, Surrealism, and
                            functionalism. The fair's purposeful endorsement of modernity was made
                            somewhat superficial by the impulse to showcase design style, as implied
                            by the word <hi rend="italic">d&#x00E9;coratif</hi> in the exposition's
                            title. Several of the gardens of the fair were conceived as outdoor
                            manifestations of Art Deco, the sleekly ornamental style found in the
                            luxurious but spare furniture and architectural design of the period. A
                            consensus that these modernistic gardens should be architectonic in
                            character as well as architectural extensions of the house caused them
                            to be more mineral than vegetal in character.</p>
                        <p>On a triangular site framed on two sides by glass walls, <name
                                type="pname">Gabriel Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian</name> (<date
                                when="1900">1900</date>&#x2013;<date when="1970">1970</date>)
                            designed the Garden of Water and Light, the most avant-garde garden at
                            the <date when="1925">1925</date>
                            <name type="place">Paris</name> Exposition (fig. 13.1). Forestier
                            commissioned it, expecting Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian to create a viewing
                            garden, a <hi rend="italic">tableau-jardin</hi> "in the modern spirit
                            with elements from Persian decor."<ref target="#CH13-n2"><hi rend="sup"
                                        ><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref>Its triangular shape
                            announced the geometric motif contained in the small opaque pinkish
                            panes of glass forming its screening walls, the zigzag pattern of flower
                            beds arranged on an inclined plane, the subdivisions of its tiered pool,
                            and some of the facets of an electrically illuminated, revolving,
                            polyhedral sphere in its center. As a modernistic garden designer,
                            Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian did not consider plants interesting in their
                            own right but deployed them simply as bedded masses of bold shapes and
                            striking colors.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-535">
                            <graphic url="CH13_002.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.1. Jardin d'Eau et de Lumi&#x00E8;re.
                                    Exposition Internationale des Arts D&#x00E9;coratifs et
                                    Industriels Modernes, <name type="place">Paris</name>, designed
                                    by Gabriel Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian. <date when="1925"
                                        >1925</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-536">
                            <graphic url="CH13_003.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.2. Garden view
                                    from lawn terrace, Villa Noailles, Hy&#x00E8;res, <name
                                        type="place">France</name>, designed by Gabriel
                                    Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian. <date when="1928"
                                >1928</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p><name type="pname">Charles de Noailles</name>, an enthusiastic collector
                            of modern art, was so impressed with Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian's creation
                            at the fair that he commissioned him to design a garden in Hy&#x00E8;res
                            where the architect Robert MalletStevens was building a villa for him
                            and his wife Marie-Laure. Here, in <date when="1927">1927</date>,
                            Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian created a garden in a space that appeared like
                            the bow of a beached ship (fig. 13.2). Divorced from the surrounding
                            landscape by stark white converging walls forming an elongated isosceles
                            triangle, the sharp geometries of<pb n="437"/><pb n="437" type="orig"
                            />rectangular flower beds, mosaic paving panels, and pool set within
                            these uncompromising boundaries assert a mathematical, antinatural
                            angularity. Though often called a Cubist garden, it is unavoidably
                            threedimensional because it is an architectural space and cannot
                            therefore have the elusive, tensile interplay between picture surface
                            and picture space of a Cubist painting.<ref target="#CH13-n3"><hi
                                    rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref>The Noailles garden
                            did have, however, one element that linked it with the modern abstract
                            art movement, a revolving sculpture by <name type="pname">Jacques
                                Lipchitz</name> (<date when="1891">1891</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1973">1973</date>) called <hi rend="italic">La Joie de vivre
                                (The Joy of Life).</hi> Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian gave this pride of
                            place at the apex of the isosceles triangle, the "prow" of the Noailles
                            garden "ship." As modern garden design increasingly assumed a minimalist
                            approach to horticulture, designers frequently placed large-scale works
                            of sculpture like this Lipchitz piece in their landscape compositions
                            simply for aesthetic effect. This quite naturally gave rise in time to
                            gardens where the designers' primary goal was to arrange an outdoor
                            setting for the display of works of art. Notable later examples in the
                                <name type="place">New York</name> metropolitan area include the
                            sculpture garden of the Museum of Modern Art in <name type="place">New
                                York</name> City, Storm King Art Center in Mountainville, and the
                            Isamu Noguchi Garden Museum in Long Island City.</p>
                        <p>At the time of the <date when="1925">1925</date> exposition, <name
                                type="pname">Charles</name> and <name type="pname">Marie-Laure de
                                Noailles</name> commissioned a second modernist essay in garden
                            design on the 5,000-squarefoot (1,524-square-meter) triangle of land
                            adjacent to their nineteenth-century <hi rend="italic">h&#x00F4;tel</hi>
                            in <name type="place">Paris</name> (fig. 13.3). Like their garden by
                            Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian in Noailles, the Parisian garden by
                            Andr&#x00E9; Vera (<date when="1881">1881</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1971">1971</date>) and his brother <name type="pname">Paul
                                Vera</name> (<date when="1882">1882</date>&#x2013;<date when="1957"
                                >1957</date>), a decorative artist, in collaboration with their
                            friend <name type="pname">Jean-Charles Moreau</name> (<date when="1889"
                                >1889</date>&#x2013;<date when="1956">1956</date>) was primarily a
                            viewing garden, its vegetation being limited to low shrub masses and
                            ground covers set within a ground plane of paving stones, pebbles, and
                            gravel. A lattice-topped wall of lightcatching mirrors reflected back
                            upon the garden images of itself and the <hi rend="italic"
                                >h&#x00F4;tel.</hi></p>
                        <p>These and other avant-garde expressions of possible new directions in
                            landscape design pioneered in <name type="place">France</name> in the
                                <date when="1920">1920</date>s were to influence the approach of a
                            new generation of landscape architects in <name type="place"
                                >America</name>, notably Fletcher Steele and Thomas Church. Steele's
                            work on the East Coast and Church's in <name type="place"
                                >California</name> were pivotal in bringing a modernist sensibility
                            to American landscape architecture.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Fletcher Steele and the Transitional Modernist
                                Garden</hi></head>
                        <p>Avid study of the gardens of the <date when="1925">1925</date>
                            <name type="place">Paris</name> exposition by the American critic and
                            landscape architect <name type="pname">Fletcher Steele</name> (<date
                                when="1885">1885</date>&#x2013;<date when="1971">1971</date>)
                            demonstrated to him the "real impetus [of the French] to gardening in
                            the new manner."<ref target="#CH13-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >4</hi></hi></ref>Steele, a native of Rochester, <name
                                type="place">New York</name>, graduated in <date when="1907"
                                >1907</date> from Williams College in western <name type="place"
                                >Massachusetts</name> where he developed an appreciation of the
                            rolling Berkshire landscape and American Colonial architecture. Harvard
                            had just initiated the country's first graduate program in landscape
                            architecture, and there Steele studied for a year with Frederick Law
                            Olmsted, Jr., and Arthur Shurtleff, another member of the Olmsted firm.
                            Their design approach was that of the prevailing Beaux-Arts system with
                            its respect for axial planning and architectural integration of building
                            and site. The arduous curriculum combined these planning principles with
                            studies in art history, architecture, surveying, hydrology, road and
                            wall construction, geology, meteorology, physiography, botany,
                            horticulture, plant identification, planting design, mathematics,
                            languages, and contracts and specifications.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-537">
                            <graphic url="CH13_004.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.3. Noailles Garden, Place des
                                    &#x00C9;tats-Unis, <name type="place">Paris</name>, designed by
                                    Andr&#x00E9; and Paul Vera with <name type="pname">Jean-Charles
                                        Moreau</name>. c. <date when="1926"
                                >1926</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Rather than return to Harvard the following year, Steele accepted the
                            offer made by <name type="pname">Warren Henry Manning</name> (<date
                                when="1860">1860</date>&#x2013;<date when="1938">1938</date>), a
                            landscape architect trained by Olmsted Sr., to serve as his personal
                            assistant and supervisor of planting for the firm. The son of a
                            wellestablished nurseryman and the author of much of the planting plan
                            for the Biltmore estate, Manning was an acknowledged plantsman. Having
                            designed the park system for <name type="place">Harrisburg</name>, <name
                                type="place">Pennsylvania</name>, he was also a city planner, as
                            well as busy professional with many important private commissions.
                            Steele's apprenticeship with Manning lasted six years. It gave the
                            aspiring young landscape architect a practical education that he valued
                            above Harvard's academic one. His experience in Manning's <name
                                type="place">Boston</name> firm, combined with his intelligence,
                            gift with words, and social skills, enabled Steele to begin an
                            independent practice after returning from an extended study tour of
                            European gardens in <date when="1913">1913</date>. In this new phase of
                            his career he absorbed the ideas of his friend, the Gothic Revival<pb
                                n="438"/><pb n="438" type="orig"/>architect <name type="pname">Ralph
                                Adams Cram</name> (<date when="1863">1863</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1942">1942</date>), as well as ideas gleaned from frequent
                            travels abroad. After service as a photographer in World War I, he
                            resumed his practice and gained a reputation as an outspoken shaper of
                            opinion, engaging lecturer, and frequent contributor to professional and
                            popular periodicals such as <hi rend="italic">Landscape Architecture,
                                House Beautiful,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Garden Club of <name
                                    type="place">America</name> Bulletin.</hi></p>
                        <p>The <date when="1920">1920</date>s were mostly prosperous years up until
                            the Great Depression, and Steele's practice flourished as wealthy
                            clients called upon his services. But his interests in landscape design
                            went beyond estate design. In Steele's view, the middle-class suburban
                            garden should be a place of privacy with hedges or tall shrubbery
                            screening it from passersby, a place for family life, friendship, and
                            daydreaming. Modern psychology, with its emphasis upon the facets of
                            individual personality and the importance of dreams, was a significant
                            ingredient in his approach to garden design. Increasingly, Steele
                            intended his gardens to serve as quasi-magical private realms where
                            landscape art encouraged relaxation into a state of reverie and fantasy,
                            spaces in which their owners would find freedom from the conventions
                            that governed their daily lives.</p>
                        <p>In <date when="1924">1924</date>, he published <hi rend="italic">Design
                                in the Little Garden.</hi> Here he argued for functional domestic
                            arrangements, advising home builders to eliminate useless front lawns,
                            place kitchen, garage, and laundry yard on the street side for
                            convenience, and screen them from public view with shrubbery. If this
                            were done, "our living-rooms should open on the old despised back-yards
                            now turned into gardens and terraces, no matter how small. . . . With
                            such a scheme we may be content that not a foot of room has been wasted;
                            that everything is where use and common sense would have it; and that
                            finally we have cleared the old back-yard to make ready for a proper
                            setting for our out-of-door life."<ref target="#CH13-n5"><hi rend="sup"
                                        ><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>In his writing Steele was bold enough to criticize the Olympian serenity
                            of Le N&#x00F4;tre, suggesting that in landscape design rationality
                            should be tempered with sensuality and a degree of poetic mystery. But
                            French culture exerted a powerful hold upon his imagination, and he kept
                            abreast of the published works of Forestier and Andr&#x00E9; Vera and
                            returned from the <name type="place">Paris</name> exposition of <date
                                when="1925">1925</date> filled with both positive and negative
                            opinions on all that he had seen. He was excited by modernism's design
                            potential for the creative landscape architect, and on subsequent trips
                            to <name type="place">France</name> he continued to study such gardens
                            as the one Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian created for the Noailles in
                            Hy&#x00E8;res. His article, "New Pioneering in Garden Design," published
                            in <hi rend="italic">Landscape Architecture</hi> in <date when="1930"
                                >1930</date>, praises Tony Garnier for giving the garden "a marked
                            vibration" by modifying symmetrical axial planning in a way that "the
                            axis is broken again and again, although rarely entirely lost."<ref
                                target="#CH13-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >6</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>Steele's enthusiasm for abstract, nonassociational design concepts was
                            transmitted to a new generation of young landscape architects, among
                            them Garrett Eckbo, James Rose, and Daniel Urban Kiley (like Steele, an
                            apprentice in Warren Manning's firm). This group of American modernist
                            landscape designers also learned from Steele how to take into account
                            their clients' twentieth-century lifestyle, with its more casual
                            domesticity, fewer servants, and increased appreciation for the
                            outdoors. They perceived rightly that Steele was both a link with the
                            Beaux-Arts tradition and, because of his openness to experiment and
                            innovation, the profession's foremost modernist influence in <name
                                type="place">America</name>.</p>
                        <p>Steele's masterpiece, Naumkeag, the estate of Mabel Choate in <name
                                type="place">Stockbridge</name>, <name type="place"
                                >Massachusetts</name>, begun in <date when="1926">1926</date>, bears
                            witness to the synthesis of his BeauxArts training and deep appreciation
                            of historic examples with his delight in modernism's abstract shaping of
                            space and exploration of bold new materials, forms, and color. To this
                            synthesis he added his own desire to design individualized garden spaces
                            that were highly experiential outdoor rooms. Steele found the garden
                            already there to be satisfactory in many respects. It had been designed
                            by Nathan Barrett of <name type="place">Boston</name>, the author of two
                            early land-planning developments&#x2014;the industrial community of
                            Pullman, <name type="place">Illinois</name>, and the residential suburb
                            of Tuxedo Park, <name type="place">New York</name>&#x2014;after Joseph
                            Choate had chosen to ignore Frederick Law Olmsted's advice to situate
                            the house half-way down the hillside near a particularly fine oak tree,
                            preferring instead the top of Prospect Hill.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-538">
                            <graphic url="CH13_005.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.4. Afternoon Garden, Naumkeag, <name
                                        type="place">Stockbridge</name>, <name type="place"
                                        >Massachusetts</name>, designed by Fletcher Steele. <date
                                        when="1926">1926</date>&#x2013;35. Steele explained, "We can
                                    bring the sky to our feet in a mirror. We can use plants with
                                    silver foliage and bright flowers: we can bring merry jets of
                                    water, the more the better...."</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Here Steele set about doing the thing he liked best, shaping landscape
                            space, analyzing existing and desirable conditions in order to determine
                            the outlines of Mabel Choate's proposed new terrace, or Afternoon
                            Garden: its relationship to the house (a location was chosen next to the
                            library), a wall to screen the entrance drive, the inclusion of a large
                                elm<pb n="439"/><pb n="439" type="orig"/>tree within its embrace, a
                            means of framing the view (fig. 13.4). Ingeniously, he decided to have
                            an Italian sculptor carve old oak pilings from <name type="place"
                                >Boston</name> harbor in a bold "Norwegian" manner. The masts were
                            nevertheless meant to evoke the posts used for tying up gondolas in the
                            canals of <name type="place">Venice</name>, and their flaring
                            finial-crowned, multicolored tops were painted to resemble "medieval
                            trappings." These imaginative uprights framed the splendid view of the
                            rolling Berkshires, and nothing more was needed to give the terrace a
                            sense of spatial enclosure than a swag of rope festooned with clematis
                            and <name type="place">Virginia</name> creeper running between the
                            vertical posts. A sculpture, <hi rend="italic">Boy with Heron,</hi> by
                                <name type="pname">Frederick MacMonnies</name> (<date when="1863"
                                >1863</date>&#x2013;<date when="1937">1937</date>), was taken from
                            inside the house and placed, not on the terrace as one might expect, but
                            at the perimeter, where it could act as a foreground foil to the
                            landscape beyond.</p>
                        <p>Steele then enlivened the ground plane with "four little fountains,
                            memories of the Generalife" gardens in Granada (see fig. 3.9). Their
                            scalloped edges set in motion a series of curves that, like "an old
                            French knot," consisted of an edging of miniature box within which blue
                            lobelia mulched with coal, yellow santolina, and pink crushed marble
                            provided color, while a small black-glass-lined pool reflected the sky.
                            Irregular brown flagstones surrounded the "giddy carpet" Steele had thus
                            flung down, and on this paving with its green cushions of arenaria
                            squeezing through the crevices and on the rustic masonry retaining walls
                            of the terrace he now placed pots filled with fuchsias, calla lilies,
                            agapanthus, and bamboo like those he had seen in the quiet patios of
                            Seville or C&#x00F3;rdoba. Beds of ferns and lilies in the corners, a
                            quietly dripping wall fountain, and "thrones" with matching footstools
                            of pink concrete completed the evocative picture.<ref target="#CH13-n7"
                                    ><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>Steele's growing originality as a designer was manifested in a second
                            campaign to improve the landscape at Naumkeag between <date when="1929"
                                >1929</date> and <date when="1935">1935</date>. Now more than ever,
                            he saw his art not only as one of shaping space, but also as one of
                            making foreground and background enter into a design dialogue similar to
                            that found in the Japanese garden when borrowed scenery is a
                            compositional element. Together client and landscape architect discussed
                            the problem of the South Lawn and its relationship to the spectacular
                            view. The collaborators' stroke of genius was the creation of what Robin
                            Karson, Steele's biographer, calls "the first modern earthwork in this
                            country," a bold curve sculpted of landfill Miss Choate appropriated
                            from a nearby excavation for a new house foundation. The line of its
                            sloping ridge and the sweeping arc it traced on the ground provided a
                            harmonious foreground echo of the view toward Bear Mountain that had
                            been revealed by tree pruning. As Steele later commented, "The only
                            resource was to create an abstract form in the manner of modern
                            sculpture, with swinging curves and slopes which would aim to make their
                            impression directly, without calling on the help of associated ideas,
                            whether in nature or art."<ref target="#CH13-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi
                                        rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref> A line of locust trees with
                            globular heads emphasize this form in the landscape (fig. 13.5). Steele
                            and Choate then fashioned an original bit of <hi rend="italic"
                                >chinoiserie</hi> out of recycled ornamental cast iron, which they
                            placed at the terminus of the South Lawn, later setting within it a
                            Chinese-scholar garden rock on a Ming pedestal.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-539">
                            <graphic url="CH13_006.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.5. America's "first modern earthwork," a
                                    curving berm at Naumkeag</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-540">
                            <graphic url="CH13_007.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.6. Blue Steps,
                                    Naumkeag</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Steele designed the Blue Steps, the most celebrated feature of the
                            Naumkeag landscape, for the purely functional purpose of enabling Choate
                            to descend the hillside to her greenhouse and cutting garden more
                            comfortably and safely. Here four shallow arched grottoes, painted
                            bright blue, flanked by four paired staircases, give a modernist twist
                            to a design tradition dating to the Italian Renaissance (fig. 13.6). The
                            motion of descent is fluidly expressed in the handrails, which Steele
                            fashioned from whitepainted tubular steel. As an inspired
                                afterthought,<pb n="440"/><pb n="440" type="orig"/>prompted by the
                            presence of native birches elsewhere on the property, Steele planted a
                            dense grove of these trees in the intervening spaces between the four
                            sets of stairs. The tonal correspondence of the white trunks and the
                            white railings, together with the juxtaposition of the stylishly crafted
                            industrial material and the poetic evocation of nature, have made this
                            scene the emblem of Steele's creative genius.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-541">
                            <graphic url="CH13_008.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.7. Rose Garden, Naumkeag</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>In <date when="1952">1952</date>, Steele and Choate laid out a rose
                            garden <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> south of Naumkeag's <hi
                                rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> of tall arborvitae trees (fig.
                            13.7). Drawing once more upon a Chinese motif, a curvilinear imperial
                            scepter, Steele delineated three sinuous, rhythmically repeating paths
                            of pink crushed stone punctuated with small scalloped rose beds. The
                            gently sloping square lawn in which the rose <hi rend="italic"
                                >parterre</hi> was set lay several feet below the terrace that
                            formed its eastern edge, and a spill of semicircular steps fanned out in
                            the angle of its northeast corner.</p>
                        <p>Mabel Choate's will turned over her thirty-year garden-building project
                            to the Trustees of Reservations, the <name type="place"
                                >Massachusetts</name> organization that served as a model for the
                            National Trust of <name type="place">England</name>. Steele had
                            counseled his client to do so, being convinced that regionally based,
                            privately controlled organizations like the Trustees of Reservations are
                            "most efficient, enthusiastic and understanding when it comes to the
                            conservation and administration of local landmarks of natural beauty and
                            historic interest."<ref target="#CH13-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >9</hi></hi></ref>He well knew that the future of his
                            profession lay not with wealthy clients such as Mabel Choate, but with
                            the government agencies that were responsible for the national, state,
                            and municipal parks and parkways. He probably counted himself lucky to
                            have been able to work at a high professional level for such a long time
                            purely on the basis of his own talent for amusing himself and others, a
                            gift for warm friendship, and the creative intelligence of a true
                            artist.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Innisfree: An American Garden Inspired by Chinese
                                Painting</hi></head>
                        <p>Included in the small and vanishing circle of monied Americans who could
                            indulge a passion for landscape design on their private estates than
                            could <name type="pname">Mabel Choate</name> were <name type="pname"
                                >Walter Beck</name> (<date when="1864">1864</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1954">1954</date>) and his wife, <name type="pname">Marion
                                Burt Stone Beck</name> (<date when="1876">1876</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1959">1959</date>). On the 950-acre property she owned in
                            Millbrook, <name type="place">New York</name>, when they married in
                                <date when="1922">1922</date>, the couple set out to create an
                            English-style landscape surrounding their newly completed Queen
                            Anne-style house, which was modeled on Wisley, the experimental plant
                            headquarters of the Royal Horticultural Society in <name type="place"
                                >England</name>.<ref target="#CH13-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi
                                        rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref>Beck was an artist with a deep
                            appreciation of Chinese landscape painting. Around <date when="1930"
                                >1930</date>, after having studied descriptions and images of the
                            famous garden of Wang Wei, the Tang dynasty official who was a poet,
                            painter, and garden builder (see Chapter Eight), he became convinced
                            that Chinese design principles, rather than English ones, should govern
                            Innisfree, as the couple called their garden after the poem of that
                            title by William Butler Yeats.</p>
                        <p>Paintings after Wang Wei's original painting of his Wangchuan Villa
                            garden consist of twenty scenes, compositional groupings of pines and
                            other trees with various small structures set beside a broad river,
                            which is cradled by softly rounded mountains. The bowl-like character of
                            this landscape of rising forms rimming the river basin, as well as the
                            gently cupped aspects of the individual scenes within it, appealed to
                            Beck, who began to create around the lake in Millbrook a series of
                            highly poetic "cup gardens" using weathered stones in carefully balanced
                            compositions. With a work crew of twenty, Beck mined promising parts of
                            the estate where boulders with the fine sculptural qualities prized by
                            Chinese garden-builders lay partially buried in the knobby glacial till.
                            He then ordered these excavated treasures to be transported to the sites
                            where he wished to compose his cup gardens. One of these gardens might
                            take the form of a rock- and vegetationrimmed hollow. Another might
                            appear as an overturned teacup, thereby resembling one of the softly
                            rounded, mist-wreathed mountains in a painting of Wang Wei's garden.
                            Beck took exquisite care in placing his rocks, using well-concealed
                            cement to anchor them after achieving an intuitively "just right," often
                            precarious, balance. He also took pains to find the appropriate
                            compositional "dialogue" between<pb n="441"/><pb n="441" type="orig"
                            />landscape and rocks and among the various individual rocks (fig.
                            13.8). Having invested the carefully selected stones with pictorial
                            character, he then gave them names&#x2014;Tiptoe Rock, Dragon Rock, Owl
                            Rock, and Turtle Rock.</p>
                        <p>A comprehensive treatment of the entire landscape surrounding the lake on
                            the Becks' Millbrook property had to await the integrative vision
                            supplied by Lester Collins (<date when="1914">1914</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1993">1993</date>), a Harvard-trained landscape architect who
                            had spent two years in China followed by a year in Kyoto. The Becks met
                            Collins during his student days; he became instrumental in the garden's
                            creation, and at Marion Beck's invitation after her husband's death in
                                <date when="1954">1954</date>, its principal creative force and the
                            author of the plan transforming it from a private Elysium into a garden
                            for public visitation. Collins took over Innisffee's design in <date
                                when="1960">1960</date> where Beck had left off, arranging the
                            several cup gardens into an integrated composition threaded with paths
                            to link them. He made the overall landscape kinetically experiential. A
                            knowledgeable horticulturist, as was Marion Beck who also contributed
                            ideas, Collins enhanced some of Beck's cup gardens with vegetation and
                            created special effects of his own. He also constructed several earthen
                            berms, recontouring the land in order to frame views, direct movement,
                            or develop a topographical profile that would either terminate a vista
                            or else stimulate interest in what lay beyond. He designed the garden's
                            wood bridges and the eighty wooden chairs in which visitors can now
                            repose. Collins compared the Innisfree garden with its many individual
                            scenes connected by paths and bridges with the Yuan Ming Yuan, the
                            famous garden begun by the Yongzheng emperor and completed by the
                            Qianlong emperor in the eighteenth-century Qing dynasty (see Chapter
                            Eight).</p>
                        <p>In scale, the Millbrook garden is analogous to this imperial garden, and
                            its studied tranquility evokes the mood of the broad river-valley
                            scenery depicted in paintings of Wang Wei's garden; these, not the
                            miniaturized landscapes of the Suzhou scholar-gardens, were the
                            exemplars for Beck and Collins at Innisfree. But while the designers may
                            have had the Yuan Ming Yuan most clearly in mind, Innisfree can also be
                            compared with two other cupped lake-gardens examined in Chapters Seven
                            and Eight: Henry Hoare's Stourhead and Shugakuin Rikyu, the lifework of
                            the retired Japanese emperor Go-Mizunoo. Like these, Innisfree is a
                            highly personal aesthetic statement, an exercise in garden poetics. Beck
                            and Collins merely applied Chinese landscape design principles and rock
                            vocabulary toward this end; they had no intention of replicating a
                            Chinese garden in any more exact sense. Beck's inventiveness and
                            training as an artist are evident not only in his Chinese-inspired rock
                            arrangements but also in his retaining walls and stair steps. His
                            technical ability as both an artist and a craftsman is especially
                            apparent in the patterned brick-and-slate terrace he designed, with a
                            dragon panel incised by him (fig. 13.9).</p>
                        <p>Collins's year in <name type="place">Japan</name> resulted in his
                            translation of the <hi rend="italic">Sensai Hisho</hi> or <hi
                                rend="italic">Secret Garden Book.</hi> Its principles, particularly
                            those concerning the construction of waterfalls, proved instructive as
                            he and Beck worked together to achieve some of Innisffee's most
                            beautiful effects.<ref target="#CH13-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >11</hi></hi></ref>Few drawings of the gardens at Innisfree
                            exist, although Collins was a practicing landscape architect and an
                            academic dean. All was created on the site, using Beck's own work crew.
                            Garden hoses outlined a future shoreline or path, and stakes or a human
                            figure stood in the landscape to help determine the position of a
                            boulder. Patient experiment was needed to engineer a waterfall in such a
                            way that it produced a cloud of mist, the merest trickle over a rock
                            lip, a fluid sheet glossing a surface of schist or granite, a pluming
                            jet, or a silvery runnel (fig. 13.10). Engineering expertise conducted
                            this water into the ground where a carefully constructed drainage system
                            carries it to the water table or the lake.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-542">
                            <graphic url="CH13_009.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.8. "Rock dialogue," Innisfree, Millbrook,
                                        <name type="place">New York</name>, garden design by Walter
                                    Beck and Lester Collins. Begun <date when="1930"
                                    >1930</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-543">
                            <graphic url="CH13_010.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.9. Terrace,
                                    Innisfree, designed by Walter Beck</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Collins's disciplined partnership with nature, which includes the
                            application of modern engineering in the form of concealed pumps and
                            electrical lines as well as the harvesting of algae from the lake, is
                                the<pb n="442"/><pb n="442" type="orig"/>unromantic secret of
                            Innisfree's continuing evolution from an ordinary second-growth woodland
                            and glacial pond into a poetic landscape. Thus, unlike many modernist
                            gardens, which openly exploit the design potential of industrial
                            materials and express new methods of spatial composition, Innisfree
                            conceals its technological apparatus beneath an Arts and Crafts
                            aesthetic informed by Chinese art and organizes space in the manner of a
                            traditional stroll garden. Collins's ability to effect a synthesis
                            between art and nature through design and technology helped transform
                            Innisfree from a private dreamworld into a publicly accessible one. He
                            gave due consideration to visitor interest, comfort, and safety; at the
                            same time he cut staff in order to work within the budget of the
                            Innisfree Foundation, which owns and operates the garden.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-544">
                            <graphic url="CH13_011.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.10. Rock lip waterfall, Innisfree,
                                    engineered by Walter Beck. <date when="1938"
                                >1938</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Abstract Art and the Functional Landscape:
                            Gardens for Modern Living</hi></head>
                    <p>Personal Elysiums like Naumkeag and Innisfree, throwbacks to an earlier
                        tradition of great estate landscapes, illustrate the growing influence of
                        East Asian ideals on Western gardens. Like the Edwardian gardens we have
                        studied, their fundamental purpose was to serve as idyllic retreats from the
                        Machine Age. In <name type="place">England</name>, in the <date when="1930"
                            >1930</date>s, the long-lingering aesthetic of the Picturesque, the
                        mellowing hand of the Arts and Crafts Movement, the energies of plant
                        hybridizers, and a vigorous nursery trade still actively informed public
                        taste, perpetuating this conservative landscape tradition. At the same time,
                        however, a committed modernist dared to voice the grounds for radical change
                        and to examine how the planning principles of the Japanese garden might
                        stimulate a new approach to landscape design.</p>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Christopher Tunnard's Influential
                            Book</hi></head>
                        <p><name type="pname">Christopher Tunnard</name> (<date when="1910"
                                >1910</date>&#x2013;<date when="1979">1979</date>) was a
                            Canadianborn landscape architect who worked in <name type="place"
                                >England</name> and then took up permanent residence in the United
                            States where he became a professor of city planning first at Harvard and
                            then at Yale.<ref target="#CH13-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >12</hi></hi></ref>No one who knew him in <name type="place"
                                >America</name>, where he was a strong advocate of historic
                            preservation, would have guessed that he had been an early firebrand in
                            the cause of landscape modernism while still a young man living in <name
                                type="place">England</name>. But Tunnard, like Fletcher Steele, had
                            taken note of Gu&#x00E9;vr&#x00E9;kian's bold departure from tradition,
                            and other new landscape design developments in <name type="place"
                                >France</name> and elsewhere in Europe. A member of the Modern
                            Architectural Research Group (MARS), the British affiliate of the
                            Congr&#x00E8;s Internationaux d'Architecture Moderne (CIAM), Tunnard was
                            impressed with the polemical rhetoric and the work of <name type="pname"
                                >Adolf Loos</name> (<date when="1870">1870</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1933">1933</date>) and Le Corbusier.</p>
                        <p>Tunnard was also familiar with landscape design history and English
                            gardening tradition. Without considering the relationship between older
                            landscape idioms and cultural values, in <hi rend="italic">Gardens in
                                the Modern Landscape</hi> (<date when="1938">1938</date>), a loosely
                            woven collection of revised essays on the subject, he adopted the
                            radical stance then current among modern architects of debunking past
                            styles. Having set up this foil of discredited history, Tunnard was
                            ready to study how "as an element inseparable from the problems of
                            housing, and urban and rural development, garden planning can, with the
                            least opposition, achieve its modern form." Quoting Loos ("To find
                            beauty in form instead of making it depend on ornament is the goal to
                            which humanity is aspiring") and Le Corbusier ("The styles are a lie"),
                            he set forth his own doctrine: "The functional garden," he wrote,
                            "avoids the extremes both of the sentimental expressionism of the wild
                            garden and the intellectual classicism of the formal' garden; it
                            embodies rather a spirit of rationalism and through an aesthetic and
                            practical ordering of its units provides a friendly and hospitable
                            milieu for rest and recreation. It is, in effect, the social conception
                            of the garden."<ref target="#CH13-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >13</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>He declared that "China's symbolical landscape gardens with their islands
                            of eternal youth and happiness&#x2014;scenes which provoked a century of
                            Naturecopyism in the West&#x2014;hold little for us." But in Japanese
                            gardens he found a congenial minimalism,<pb n="443"/><pb n="443"
                                type="orig"/>integration of indoor and outdoor space, and the
                            compositional principle he called "occult balance," whereby counterpoise
                            was achieved through an asymmetrical arrangement of parts in equilibrium
                            along a diagonal axis. The Japanese editorial hand that pruned away
                            unnecessary vegetation and carefully arranged those plants that remained
                            for subtle but maximum effect was in keeping with modernism's movement
                            away from a "barbaric massing of color" toward "an acceptance of form,
                            line and economy of material as being of first importance."<ref
                                target="#CH13-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >14</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>Tunnard allied himself with such modern architects as Le Corbusier and
                            Frank Lloyd Wright. The former's country villas, raised from the ground
                            by pilotis, were dissociated from nature but nevertheless presided over
                            broad views that were an important aspect of their architectural
                            planning and expressed a pastoral tradition harking back to Virgil.<ref
                                target="#CH13-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >15</hi></hi></ref>The houses of the latter, on the other hand,
                            sometimes grasped raw nature in an intimate embrace, as is particularly
                            evident in Fallingwater of <date when="1937">1937</date>, Wright's most
                            famous work, poised above Bear Run, in western Pennsylvania. Both of
                            these modernists created architecture that corresponded with what
                            Tunnard called the "empathic" approach to landscape planning whereby
                            "nature is not to be regarded as a refuge from life, but as an
                            invigorator of it and a stimulus to body and mind."<ref
                                target="#CH13-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >16</hi></hi></ref>If one of the unstated motives of such Picturesque
                            theorists as Uvedale Price and Richard Payne Knight had been to make
                            untamed nature more agreeable by considering it as art, that was now no
                            longer an issue. By the mid-twentieth century, much of nature had been
                            tamed, and it needed no apologists; it was simply there in the form of
                            sunlight, fresh air, and good views to be actively, <hi rend="italic"
                                >functionally</hi> enjoyed. Included in the empathic, functionalist
                            layout were outdoor dining areas, decks, swimming pools, tennis courts,
                            and other accoutrements of modern life with its orientation to leisure
                            and recreation. Tunnard's later follower, Garrett Eckbo, called this a
                            "landscape for living." (These aspects of design did not engage the
                            imaginations of either Le Corbusier or Wright, who were more romantic
                            than functionalist in their approach to nature.)</p>
                        <p>Further, Tunnard urged the collaboration of modern artists in the
                            landscape design process; architects were already working with sculptors
                            and painters. Mies van der Rohe's Barcelona Pavilion of <date
                                when="1929">1929</date> was a notable recent example of the
                            symbiosis of Machine Age architectural form and materials and a single
                            perfectly placed work of sculpture. The Noailles garden in Hy&#x00E8;res
                            showed how effective the sculpture by Lipchitz was as an element in the
                            landscape.</p>
                        <p>Tunnard's own career as a landscape architect was brief, and he later
                            retreated from radical modernist advocacy. But the work he presented in
                                <hi rend="italic">Gardens in the Modern Landscape,</hi> enhanced by
                            the drawings of Gordon Cullen, illustrates how in the <date when="1930"
                                >1930</date>s at Bentley Wood in Halland, East Sussex, the home of
                            the architect Serge Chermayeff (<date when="1900"
                                >1900</date>&#x2013;<date when="1996">1996</date>), and in his own
                            house at St. Ann's Hill, Chertsey (fig. 13.11), Tunnard practiced the
                            landscape modernism he preached.</p>
                        <p>The Chermayeff house of steel-framed, weatherboarded construction, with
                            expansive south walls of glass opening toward a distant rural view, had
                            a terrace sheltered by a plate-glass screen away from the house. For a
                            year before the house was built, he carefully removed trees in a
                            second-growth woodland to open a view toward the distant horizon. He
                            attempted no planting except for a mass of naturalized daffodils, a few
                            carefully grouped trees and shrubs near the house, and some narrow
                            flower beds along the terrace edge and its sheltering wall. Near the far
                            open corner of this protected sundeck, there was a sculpture of a
                            reclining female by Henry Moore (<date when="1898"
                                >1898</date>&#x2013;<date when="1986">1986</date>), carefully
                            positioned according to Tunnard's principle of occult balance.</p>
                        <p>In prescribing a modern landscape style, Tunnard expressed his own
                            fundamental love of plants and scenery. Stripped of sentimental
                            association, these were to be enjoyed, like abstract art, in terms of
                            color, form, texture, and compositional balance. Whereas functionalist
                            architects and planners usually paid little attention to horticulture,
                            Tunnard urged that "[we] not let the humanism of the gardener's
                            philosophy depart from us." At the same time, he saw the modern
                            landscape as a space to be enjoyed collectively, not "the hedged,
                            personal, half-acre of today, but a unit of the broad green landscape
                            itself, controlled for the benefit of all."<ref target="#CH13-n17"><hi
                                    rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-545">
                            <graphic url="CH13_012.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.11. Christopher Tunnard's house at St. Ann's
                                    Hill, Chertsey, Surrey. The drawing by Gordon Cullen shows
                                    Tunnard's functional, empathie, and artistic approach to
                                    landscape design. Humans and nature meet on friendly, equal
                                    terms, and, according to Tunnard's caption in <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Gardens in the Modern Landscape,</hi> this is "an
                                    architectural garden, part axial, part asymmetrical," in which
                                    "screen walls frame distant views. A sheltered position allows
                                    many halfhardy subjects to be grown, including cordylines and
                                    the chamaerops palm. The sculpture on the right of the sketch is
                                    by Willi Soukop." Particular attention has been given to the
                                    framing of distant views.</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>The last chapter of Tunnard's <hi rend="italic">Gardens in the<pb n="444"
                                    /><pb n="444" type="orig"/>Modern Landscape</hi> is devoted to
                            "the wider planning [of] civic landscape architecture."<ref
                                target="#CH13-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >18</hi></hi></ref>Here he called for a new regional idiom linking
                            society and nature, city planning and landscape architecture, the garden
                            and the large-scale recreational park. Tunnard wished to promote
                            egalitarian land planning synthesizing the talents of the
                            engineer&#x2014;"whose activities are perhaps the greatest contribution
                            made to the landscape in the last one hundred years"<ref
                                target="#CH13-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >19</hi></hi></ref>&#x2014;the landscape architect, and the architect.
                            His planning philosophy celebrating the builders of roadways and bridges
                            as well as the makers of gardens and the designers of recreational
                            facilities was similar in spirit to that of <name type="pname">Robert
                                Moses</name>. At this hopeful moment in the <date when="1930"
                                >1930</date>s it was possible to dream of a future of well-organized
                            urban growth in which decision-making power was vested in planners
                            capable of rationally premising their work on functionality and human
                            needs as they wedded technology and nature into a grand design.</p>
                        <p>It is remarkable just how principled was the spirit of early modernism
                            with its frank avowal of machine-made materials and its honest and
                            optimistic search for an aesthetic that served and expressed a new
                            social order. Although later shorn of its youthful idealism, the
                            exploration of the problem raised by modernism with regard to landscape
                            design continued in the belief that scientifically rational planning
                            combined with an aesthetic of pure form and new spatial concepts could
                            serve as expressive ends in themselves, replacing older cultural values
                            emanating from cosmology, religion, philosophy, horticulture, and
                            history. And, much as the Becks had suspected when they saw the work of
                            Le Corbusier and his followers as being more appropriately situated in
                                <name type="place">South America</name> than in Millbrook, <name
                                type="place">New York</name>, it was in Brazil, where a significant
                            spark&#x2014;the Sao Paulo Modern Art Week of <date when="1922"
                                >1922</date>&#x2014;had ignited a remarkable cultural and aesthetic
                            revolution, that the modernist landscape in collaboration with modern
                            architecture found one of its most creative exponents.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Roberto Burle Marx and the Garden as Abstract
                                Art</hi></head>
                        <p><name type="pname">Roberto Burle Marx</name> (<date when="1909"
                                >1909</date>&#x2013;<date when="1994">1994</date>) was a protean
                            artist&#x2014;painter, sculptor, muralist, and craftsman&#x2014; with an
                            affinity for nature and the baroque morphology of the tropical
                            vegetation of his native Brazil. Given the opportunity to collaborate
                            with architects who were modernist innovators, he found his most
                            expressive m&#x00E9;tier as a landscape designer. His approach to
                            landscape paralleled his approach to painting; he employed a graphic
                            style that treated the ground plane in the same abstract manner as Le
                            N&#x00F4;tre or Capability Brown had but with a modernist sensibility
                            sympathetic to the undulating lines and biomorphic shapes found in the
                            art of Jean Arp, Joan Mir&#x00F3;, and Alexander Calder. The strong
                            curvilinear forms of the Brazilian coastal landscape around Rio de
                            Janeiro coincidentally echoed the biomorphic forms found in their work,
                            and this native scenery had an obvious effect on Burle Marx as a
                            designer. With a scientist's curiosity and an unrivaled botanical
                            collection from his own expeditions in the Brazilian hinterlands, he
                            confidently deployed luxuriant, vividly colored tropical plants, some
                            with highly architectonic forms, in visually strong compositions that
                            evoked and often directly echoed the local landscape, drawing it into
                            the garden in the manner of Japanese "borrowed" scenery. This style
                            effectively complemented and enriched the austere lines of functionalist
                            buildings.</p>
                        <p>In <date when="1934">1934</date>, at the inviation of Lima Cavalcanti,
                            the governor of the state of Pernambuco, Burle Marx accepted a job in
                            Recife redesigning and restoring the public gardens of that faded
                            provincial capital. During his two-year sojourn in Recife, Burle Marx
                            became an active member of the city's intellectual community, making
                            friends and establishing lasting relationships among a group of young
                            poets, painters, writers, and musicians. He developed his graphic
                            approach to garden design as he prepared India ink perspectives of
                            several public squares and parks, including the Euclides da Cunha Square
                                (<date when="1935">1935</date>), which he envisioned as a cactus
                            garden (fig. 13.12). For this project he went into the dry northeastern
                            region of Brazil called the <hi rend="italic">caatinga</hi> to collect
                            various kinds of succulents, which he then arranged and installed.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-546">
                            <graphic url="CH13_013.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.12. Euclides da Cunha Square, Recife,
                                    Pernambuco, Brazil, designed by Roberto Burle Marx. <date
                                        when="1935">1935</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Burle Marx's participation in a coterie with leftist views caused him to
                            fall into disfavor with the mayor, prompting his resignation and return
                            to Rio in <date when="1937">1937</date>. There he set up an atelier and
                            resumed contact with his friends from the School of Fine Arts. The
                            architect L&#x00FA;cio Costa (b. <date when="1902">1902</date>) had
                            invited Le Corbusier to come to Rio to advise on the design of a new
                            building for the Ministry of Education and Public Health, a
                            controversial early modernist structure where Burle Marx assisted the
                            well-known artist C&#x00E2;nido Portinari (<date when="1903"
                                >1903</date>&#x2013;<date when="1962">1962</date>) in painting a
                            large mural<pb n="445"/><pb n="445" type="orig"/>representing the
                            economic cycles of Brazil. Probably at Costa's suggestion, Burle Marx
                            was asked to also participate on the architectural design team, which
                            included, in addition to Costa, Oscar Niemeyer and several other young
                            Brazilian modernists. Burle Marx was put in charge of designing the
                            ground-level plaza, the minister's office terrace garden, and a roof
                            garden. This last occupied the top of the low-rise section of the
                            building and therefore functioned as an oldfashioned <hi rend="italic"
                                >parterre,</hi> being designed for viewing from above, in this case
                            from the windows of the raised slab housing the offices of the
                            ministry.</p>
                        <p>The gardens for the Ministry of Education and Public Health demonstrated
                            Burle Marx's method of treating the garden plane in a manner analogous
                            to a painter's canvas. Upon the roof garden, for instance, he "drew"
                            curvilinear abstract forms reminiscent of aerial views of Brazilian
                            rivers. Texture and color played important roles. There were spiky
                            bird-ofparadise plants and other plants&#x2014;agaves, dracaenas, and
                            palms&#x2014;laid out as sculptural accents or single masses of color.
                            His approach to landscape design as aestheticized nature was essentially
                            the same as his approach to painting. "My message is purely pictorial,"
                            he once declared, "it revolves around color, rhythm, and form, trying to
                            abstain from the anecdotal, believing that pictorial language begins
                            when the word loses the reason for being."<ref target="#CH13-n20"><hi
                                    rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>Burle Marx's vision of the modernist garden as pure visual experience
                            unencumbered by textual meaning can be appreciated in both the gouache
                            plan and the realized landscape of the Odette Monteiro Garden (now the
                            Luiz Cezar Fernandes Garden) in Correas in the state of <name
                                type="pname">Rio de Janeiro</name> (<date when="1948">1948</date>)
                            (figs. 13.13, 13.14, 13.15). Although he often worked in close
                            collaboration with modern architects, he was unlike the garden
                            formalists who followed Reginald Blomfield's prescription for
                            integrating house and garden in a unified, axially coordinated scheme,
                            or such landscape modernists as Tunnard, who wished to do the same thing
                            in an asymmetrical manner. Instead, he saw garden design as a generally
                            independent, nonarchitectural, <hi rend="italic">contrapuntal,</hi> and
                            primarily artistic endeavor. On the Monteiro estate, he virtually
                            ignored the house by Wladimir Alves Souza. His aim here was to reiterate
                            in certain ground plane forms the profile of the surrounding
                            mountainscape.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-547">
                            <graphic url="CH13_014.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.13. Plan of the Luiz Cezar Fernandes Garden
                                    (formerly the Odette Monteiro Garden), Correas, Rio de Janeiro,
                                    designed by Burle Marx. <date when="1948"
                                >1948</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-548">
                            <graphic url="CH13_015.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 13.14. Luiz Cezar
                                    Fernandes Garden (formerly the Odette Monteiro
                                Garden)</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-549">
                            <graphic url="CH13_016.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.15. Luiz Cezar
                                    Fernandes Garden (formerly the Odette Monteiro
                                Garden)</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>By the time Burle Marx designed the Odette Monteiro Garden, the landscape
                            design and construction business he was running with his brother
                            Siegfried had grown. In addition, he wanted space for his expanding
                            botanical collection and the nursery where the brothers propagated and
                            grew plants for the firm's projects. In <date when="1949">1949</date>,
                            they were able to purchase a former coffee plantation, S&#x00ED;tio
                            Santo Antonio da Bica (Saint Anthony of the Spring), in Campo Grande,
                            nineteenmiles south of Rio. On this hilly site offering a series of
                            microclimates, he installed his collection of tropical plants, which was
                            becoming one of outstanding scientific merit, thanks to his friendship
                            and collaboration with Henrique Llahmeyer de Mello Barreto, a botanist
                            and the head of Rio's zoological garden, with whom he undertook several
                            phytogeographical excursions into the Brazilian interior. At the<pb
                                n="446"/><pb n="446" type="orig"/>S&#x00ED;tio&#x2014;now his
                            weekend home, painting studio, and horticultural laboratory&#x2014;he
                            grew bromeliads, calatheas, philodendrons, anthuriums, and heliconia in
                            shade houses. On higher ground, above the remodeled plantation house
                            where he lived and entertained his many friends and visitors, he grew
                            cactus, orchids, palms, and more bromeliads.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-550">
                            <graphic url="CH13_017.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.16. Pond Garden with architectural fragments
                                    from demolished Rio buildings, S&#x00ED;tio Santo Antonio da
                                    Bica, Campo Grande, Brazil, designed by Roberto Burle Marx. From
                                        <date when="1949">1949</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-551">
                            <graphic url="CH13_018.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.17. Copacabana
                                    Beach, Rio de Janeiro, designed by Roberto Burle Marx. <date
                                        when="1970">1970</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Although a knowledgeable plantsman and committed environmentalist
                            concerned about the protection of the rain forest, art was for Burle
                            Marx a more fundamental interest than science, for it was as an artist
                            that he sought to use individually interesting plant species as a means
                            of establishing accents, filling the biomorphic outlines of his planting
                            beds, and shaping space. It was as an artist, too, that he salvaged bits
                            of old architectural fabric from buildings that were being torn down as
                            Rio's modernization rushed forward, and these he recomposed within the
                            gardens of the S&#x00ED;tio (fig. 13.16). Here, where the slightly
                            menacing air of tropical fecundity is interwoven with these enigmatic
                            and melancholy-seeming fragments, one senses Burle Marx's affinity for
                                Surrealism.<ref target="#CH13-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >21</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>The same spirit of improvisational protean creativity that characterized
                            life at the S&#x00ED;tio also pervaded Burle Marx's office in Rio where
                            he presided like a Renaissance <hi rend="italic">capo di bottega</hi>
                            over an artisans' workshop. From here flowed floral decorations for
                            receptions, sculptures, murals, jewelry, textile designs, and stage sets
                            as well as more than 2,000 plans for various landscapes and cityscapes.
                            Although he achieved some of his finest results as a collaborator with
                            modern architects such as Rino Levi with whom he designed the estate of
                            the industrialist Olivo Gomes, in Sao Jos&#x00E9; dos Campos, Sao Paulo,
                            he remained as interested as he had been as a young park designer in
                            Recife in applying his modernist landscape approach to public spaces. In
                                <date when="1954">1954</date>, he received a commission for the
                            289acre Flamengo Park on landfill adjacent to Guanabara Bay near the
                            heart of Rio. Like the recreational facilities that were built in
                            conjunction with the waterfront parkways of <name type="pname">Robert
                                Moses</name>, Flamengo Park was undertaken as part of a coastal
                            highway project designed to relieve the city's growing automobile
                            congestion. Burle Marx executed his plan with characteristic boldness,
                            engendering a visual dialogue between the park and the baroque landforms
                            that rim the city and its bay.</p>
                        <p>In <date when="1970">1970</date>, in a second landfill project, he
                            extended his work along Rio's coastline with his design for the
                            promenades and parkways along Copacabana Beach (fig. 13.17). Here, for
                            the palm-tree-edged promenade, he employed a traditional Portuguese
                            paving technique <hi rend="italic">(pedra portuguesa)</hi> to create a
                            black, white, and red mosaic that echoes the undulating line of the
                            nearby surf. In contrast, he designed the roadbed median and sidewalk
                            along the building edge as a series of individually conceived abstract
                            panels with green planting pockets set at irregular intervals within
                            them. The entire strip, including the sandy bathing beach, was thus
                            transformed into a vibrant linear <hi rend="italic">parterre</hi> for
                            viewing from the windows of the contiguous skyscraper hotels and
                            apartment buildings.</p>
                        <p>In <date when="1956">1956</date>, the planning of <name type="place"
                                >Brazil</name>'s new capital, Bras&#x00ED;lia, began. Many were
                            dismayed that for political reasons officials did not consult Burle Marx
                            during the initial planning of this exercise in modernist urban design.
                            Finally, in <date when="1965">1965</date>, he received a commission to
                            work with the architect Oscar Niemeyer on designs for the gardens of the
                            Ministries of the Army, Justice, and Foreign Affairs. Here as elsewhere
                            he exploited the reflective qualities of pools of water and his own
                            fertile imagination to good effect. At the Ministry of Foreign Affairs,
                            for instance, he reached beyond images derived from Brazil's colonial
                            past to<pb n="447"/><pb n="447" type="orig"/>ones from the Roman
                            colonial past of its mother country, Portugal, drawing upon the gardens
                            of an excavated Roman house in Conimbriga as inspiration for his
                            floating planting beds (figs. 13.18, 13.19).</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-552">
                            <graphic url="CH13_019.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.18. <hi rend="bold">Central Peristyle, House
                                        of the Fountains, Conimbriga, Portugal. 3rd century
                                        C.E.</hi></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-553">
                            <graphic url="CH13_020.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.19. Gardens of the Ministry of Foreign
                                    Affairs, Bras&#x00ED;lia, designed by Roberto Burle Marx. <date
                                        when="1965">1965</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Luis Barrag&#x00E1;n and the Landscape of
                                Surrealist Expressionism</hi></head>
                        <p>Burle Marx developed a visually dynamic style that was an abstract,
                            organic counterpoint to the modern architecture within or adjacent to
                            it, a style only slightly tinged with Surrealism. His contemporary, the
                            Mexican architect Luis Barrag&#x00E1;n (<date when="1902"
                                >1902</date>&#x2013;<date when="1988">1988</date>), with starker
                            Surrealist affinities and more influenced by American regionalist
                            modernism as represented by Frank Lloyd Wright and certain Californian
                            architects, forged an expressive style that wedded domestic space with
                            raw, even violent, nature.</p>
                        <p>Trained in his native Guadalajara, Barrag&#x00E1;n traveled for a year
                            and a half in Europe and then left his home city to establish himself in
                            the capital in <date when="1936">1936</date>. He carried with him
                            remembered images from his sojourn in Europe&#x2014;Surrealist
                            paintings, Islamic patios in Spain, and the idyllic Mediterranean
                            gardens of the writer, caricaturist, and illustrator Ferdinand Bac
                                (<date when="1859">1859</date>&#x2013;<date when="1952">1952</date>)
                            at Les Colombi&#x00E8;res in Menton, <name type="place">France</name>.
                            At Les Colombi&#x00E8;res on the C&#x00F4;te d'Azure, Bac had employed a
                            pastiche of vaguely allusive Mediterranean forms in which an Arts and
                            Crafts approach and an Italianate stylistic sensibility were mingled to
                            create a garden of memory and meditation.<ref target="#CH13-n22"><hi
                                    rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref>Barrag&#x00E1;n, in
                            a similar manner, gave his gardens a certain dreamlike character,
                            imbuing them with memories of vernacular Mexican architecture and the
                            rural landscape he had known as a child on his family's ranch near the
                            village of Mazamitla. Working in a climate similar to Bac's
                            Mediterranean, he created an architecture that completely fused interior
                            and exterior spatial planning. Thoroughly abreast of modernist
                            developments in his profession, Barrag&#x00E1;n forged an indigenous
                            style devoid of stylistic specificity, a spare, stripped-down version of
                            his native architecture that owed a strong debt to the influence of the
                            Bauhaus and Le Corbusier. He particularly wished to avoid designing in
                            the popular "<name type="place">California</name> Colonial" idiom of
                            ornate stucco and red tiles that some affluent Mexicans had begun to
                            favor.</p>
                        <p>The practice he established in Mexico City was as a designer-developer,
                            and he built about thirty, mostly speculative houses and small apartment
                            buildings during his first four years there. With profits from these, he
                            purchased and remodeled for himself a house in the Tacubaya district,
                            for which he created a garden. He also created behind high buttressed,
                            redearth-colored walls a strange and enigmatic garden of "aestheticized
                            desolation and decay"<ref target="#CH13-n23"><hi rend="sup"><hi
                                        rend="bold">23</hi></hi></ref>in San Angel on a property
                            called El Cabr&#x00ED;o at the edge of the Pedregal, the lava field
                            south of Mexico City. Before the volcanic eruption of Xictli around 100
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.,</hi> this was the site of the Aztec
                            ceremonial centers of Cuicuilco and Copilco. Because of its contorted
                            topography, peculiar plant life, and the eerie legends associated with
                            its weird basaltic landscape, the Pedregal was considered by respectable
                            people as a place to be avoided. But Barrag&#x00E1;n's taste for the
                            surreal attracted him to explore and then, beginning in <date
                                when="1944">1944</date>, to buy 865 acres (later increased to 1,250)
                            of this inexpensive wasteland where he had decided to create a unique
                            modernist garden suburb for prosperous middle-class Mexicans.</p>
                        <p>With lots one-acre minimum in size, houses occupying no more than 10
                            percent of the entire area of the subdivision, lava rock and indigenous
                            plant life<pb n="448"/><pb n="448" type="orig"/>protected from removal,
                            and roads laid out to conform with the terrain, the San Angel Gardens of
                            the Pedregal were to constitute a Surrealistic celebration of the
                            violent inhuman forces that reside in the larger Mexican landscape.
                            Asserting possession of this landscape, which bore no trace of colonial
                            occupation but evoked a pre-catastrophe Aztec empire, was also
                            symbolically important at a time when Mexican intellectuals, artists,
                            and political leaders were concerned with issues of national identity.
                            To choose a site such as this for domestic purposes was, like Wright's
                            choice of a cantilevered platform over Bear Run for <name type="pname"
                                >Edgar J. Kaufmann</name>'s Fallingwater, to state a modernist's
                            confidence in technology, even in the face of nature's turbulence. It
                            affirmed the idea that humans had reached a point where nature had
                            become a subject of desire and personal dominion rather than an object
                            of awe or admiration. Landscape in this sense meant an intimate coupling
                            of architecture and nature. There would be no transition from the
                            artificial to the natural environment through an intermediate zone in
                            which the traditional skills of garden design and horticulture played a
                            significant part.<ref target="#CH13-n24"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >24</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-554">
                            <graphic url="CH13_021.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.20. House at 140 Fuentes, San Angel Gardens,
                                    El Cabr&#x00ED;o, El Pedregal, <name type="place">Mexico</name>,
                                    designed by Luis Barrag&#x00E1;n and Max Cetto. <date
                                        when="1951">1951</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-555">
                            <graphic url="CH13_022.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.21. <name
                                        type="pname">Edgar J. Kaufmann</name> House, Palm Springs,
                                        <name type="place">California</name>, designed by <name
                                        type="pname">Richard Neutra</name>. <date when="1946"
                                        >1946</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Although the winding streets of El Pedregal were similar to those of
                            nineteenth- and twentiethcentury suburbs in the United States, the
                            continuous front lawns of the typical North American suburb were
                            replaced, in conformity with a Mediterraneanderived Latin American
                            tradition, by high walls at the line of the street or sidewalk. For
                            Barrag&#x00E1;n these walls offered opportunities to create slightly
                            mysterious "garden-streets" with "sex appeal."<ref target="#CH13-n25"
                                    ><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">25</hi></hi></ref>The houses
                            behind these walls, however, were rational, functionalist essays in
                            modernism. In their cubic massing, flat roofs, concrete construction,
                            expansive picture windows, open floor plans, and interpenetration of
                            indoors and outdoors, they echoed current architectural modernism in
                            Europe, the United States, <name type="place">Japan</name>, and other
                            parts of Latin America. Instead of enclosing a landscaped patio in the
                            manner of countless Mediterranean-style exemplars, these houses were
                            made simply to emerge out of the rugged landscape (fig. 13.20). In
                            discussing their design of one of the Pedregal properties,
                            Barrag&#x00E1;n's collaborator, Max Cetto, spoke of the lava ridge that
                            partially defined the edge of the swimming pool and all but dove into
                            the living room as "the master key" that "made the house click."<ref
                                target="#CH13-n26"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >26</hi></hi></ref>Here, instead of the house's extending into the
                            landscape by means of axial relationships, the landscape appears to be
                            extending itself into the house.</p>
                        <p>Cetto was a German emigr&#x00E9; modernist, and the style of
                            functionalist architecture that he and Barrag&#x00E1;n professed, with
                            its smooth, unadorned, white, planar surfaces, contrasted powerfully
                            with the tortuous dark-gray basalt. The same mixture of spare, open-plan
                            modernism and dramatic siting can be found in the work of the
                            Austrian-born American architect Richard Neutra (<date when="1892"
                                >1892</date>&#x2013;<date when="1970">1970</date>), especially in
                            the house he designed in <date when="1946">1946</date> for <name
                                type="pname">Edgar J. Kaufmann</name> in Palm Springs, <name
                                type="place">California</name> (fig. 13.21). Barrag&#x00E1;n knew of
                            the developments in modern architecture in <name type="place"
                                >California</name> and had established a personal friendship with
                            Neutra. Californian landscape architects such as Thomas Church and
                            Garrett Eckbo were forging a regional modernism that drew upon factors
                            similar to those in Mexico: Hispanic cultural heritage, starkly
                            beautiful natural scenery, and a climate that fostered luxuriant
                            vegetation. Barrag&#x00E1;n's residential landscapes were meant to be,
                            like theirs, private realms in which modernism was informed by
                            vernacular traditions, places where garden and house merged to
                            accommodate an informal lifestyle, and spaces of refuge and retreat from
                            the turmoil of modern life.</p>
                        <p>This is eloquently evident at San Cristobal, an estate on the outskirts
                            of Mexico City where Thoroughbred horses are raised and trained (fig.
                            13.22). Barrag&#x00E1;n's only remaining legacy that has not been
                            severely altered, this complex of house, swimming pool, stable, and
                            horse pool is a poetic meditation on his childhood memories of the rural
                            village of Mazamitla, as well as an abstract composition of great
                            sophistication and refinement in which color plays a role similar to
                            that in the works of Color Field<pb n="449"/><pb n="449" type="orig"
                            />painters such as Mark Rothko (<date when="1903"
                                >1903</date>&#x2013;<date when="1970">1970</date>). Here as
                            elsewhere the architect gave his austere, unornamented architecture
                            warmth and animation as well as a Surrealist intensity by his use
                            brilliant pinks and fuchsias against which the complementary green tones
                            of the landscape act as a foil.</p>
                        <p>In terms of physical climate and a cultural climate hospitable to bold
                            gestures and innovation, Mexico and southern <name type="place"
                                >California</name> are closely related. Both places are conducive to
                            the use of a Mediterranean plant palette and the interweaving of indoor
                            and outdoor space found in Mediterranean lands. The patio of Spain, with
                            its debt to Islamic models, and the loggia and casino of <name
                                type="place">Italy</name>, where villa owners had pioneered the art
                            of open-air dining and entertaining, were forerunners of the paved,
                            well-furnished garden court and terrace with pool and adjacent
                            lanai.</p>
                        <p>In <name type="place">California</name>, in the altered economic and
                            social structure of the post&#x2014;Great Depression years, an informal
                            way of life stressing low maintenance requirements, casual dress, easy
                            hospitality on the part of hosts without servants, and a proclivity for
                            homecentered recreation contributed to the development of the modernist
                            garden in <name type="place">California</name>. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Sunset,</hi> an early lifestyle magazine published in Menlo Park,
                                <name type="place">California</name>, and directed to western
                            homeowners, promoted this agreeable mode of living and the flow between
                            indoors and outdoors that it implied. It found a ready audience among
                            the eastern and midwestern migrants pouring into the rapidly growing
                            state. As David Streatfield, an authority on <name type="place"
                                >California</name>'s gardens, remarks, "The new garden designs
                            united indoor and outdoor space to create a setting for a relaxed, often
                            hedonistic way of living [in which] gardens were fully used as outdoor
                                rooms."<ref target="#CH13-n27"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >27</hi></hi></ref>It was a Beaux-Arts-trained landscape
                            architect open to experimentation who was able to make the creative leap
                            from stylistic imitation and reinterpretation of Spanish and Italian
                            models, which we examined in Chapter Eleven, to the innovation of this
                            new, in turn influential, landscape design idiom.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-556">
                            <graphic url="CH13_023.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.22. Water tank with waterfeeding trough,
                                    Egerstrom House and Stables. San Cristobal, Los Clubes, <name
                                        type="place">Mexico City</name>, designed by Luis Barragan.
                                        <date when="1967">1967</date>&#x2013;69</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas Church's Gardens for People</hi></head>
                        <p>Thomas Church (<date when="1902">1902</date>&#x2013;<date when="1978"
                                >1978</date>) grew up in southern <name type="place"
                                >California</name>. He earned a landscape architecture degree from
                            the University of <name type="place">California</name> at <name
                                type="place">Berkeley</name> in <date when="1922">1922</date>,
                            pursued further studies at the Harvard Graduate School of Design, and
                            traveled extensively, studying Spanish and Italian garden design on a
                            six-month fellowship in <date when="1927">1927</date>. Thus trained in
                            the prevailing BeauxArts curriculum, he began a long and successful
                            practice centered primarily upon residential landscapes, receiving
                            commissions in both the Bay Area and southern <name type="place"
                                >California</name>. Florence Yoch (<date when="1890"
                                >1890</date>&#x2013;<date when="1972">1972</date>) had begun to
                            transform her style of eclectic originality into one that was more
                            abstract and informal with the design in <date when="1936">1936</date>
                            of a poolside garden for the film director George Cukor. Church, like
                            Yoch, was capable of making traditional-style gardens that were
                            aesthetically pleasing and functionally satisfying, which is what he did
                            for a growing roster of clients throughout the <date when="1930"
                                >1930</date>s. Like Yoch, he realized that a landscape designer
                            could make a virtue of a small lot by ignoring the tenets of his
                            training and adopting the aesthetic principles being pioneered by modern
                            architects and artists. On a second visit to Europe in <date when="1937"
                                >1937</date> he saw the work of Le Corbusier and Alvar Aalto (<date
                                when="1898">1898</date>&#x2013;<date when="1976">1976</date>) as
                            well as that of many modern painters and sculptors.</p>
                        <p>Beginning in the late <date when="1930">1930</date>s, Church began to
                            employ line, color, and texture in a bold and original manner. His use
                            of shifting, asymmetrical axes rather than the balanced, geometrically
                            oriented ones of Neoclassical design gave him the freedom to organize
                            space in new ways. He became a master at harmonizing the angular
                            geometries of architectural design with flowing, curvilinear forms. A
                            beach garden in Aptos, <name type="place">California</name>, shows
                            clearly his understanding of ground-plane line as a means of defining
                            space in a manner that energizes both the delineated, contained area and
                            the more natural surrounding terrain (fig. 13.23). At this Pacific Coast
                            beach house designed by Hervey Parke Clark, Church merged interior and
                            exterior space so skillfully that he earned a reputation among
                            architects as an ideal collaborator on site planning. As attentive to
                            the lives and desires of his clients as to the conditions of the site,
                            he conceived plans that were both functional and artistic. The pattern
                            and texture of paving or decking and the manner in which the texture,
                            scale, and structure of plants unite hard and soft surfaces is the
                            hallmark of a Church landscape.</p>
                        <p>Church's first book, <hi rend="italic">Gardens Are for People</hi> (<date
                                when="1955">1955</date>), adopts the tone of a professional offering
                            commonsense advice to homeowners. It gives excellent instruction on how
                            to appreciate visually the natural assets of a property and how to make
                            the most of it by orienting the plan to desirable sun angles and wind
                                expo<pb n="450"/><pb n="450" type="orig"/>sures, while considering
                            scenic view lines, topography, and existing vegetation. Church pointed
                            out how things had changed within a single generation: Garages had been
                            absorbed into the house; drinks on the terrace had replaced tea in the
                            parlor; modest attire had given way to bikini sunbathing; the circular
                            carriage-turnaround entry court had been replaced by the automobile
                            driveway; a service area for propagating and potting plants and
                            composting weeds had become a requirement in an era of do-it-yourself
                            gardeners; gunite and plastic swimming pools had made a former luxury
                            commonplace; and plant-filled nurseries and a scientific horticultural
                            industry had grown up to serve the average homeowner. The prescriptions
                            he offered stress the means of integrating house and garden so that they
                            constitute a unified living space. They continually directed attention
                            to the functional requirements of the entire family and its guests.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-557">
                            <graphic url="CH13_024.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.23. Beach Garden for <name type="pname">Mr.
                                        and Mrs. Charles 0. Martin</name>, Aptos, <name type="place"
                                        >California</name>, house designed by Hervey Parke Clark,
                                    garden designed by Thomas Church. <date when="1948">1948</date>.
                                    At this Pacific Coast beach house, Church extended the living
                                    space outdoors by means of redwood decking that complements the
                                    rectilinear planes of the house while assuming, in the raised
                                    perimeter seating, an assertive angularity that acts as a foil
                                    to the curvaceous line defining the rest of the edge of a "pool"
                                    of beach sand, the centerpiece of this low-maintenance
                                    garden.</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-558">
                            <graphic url="CH13_025.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.24. Plan of
                                    Donnell Garden pool area, designed by Thomas Church, <name
                                        type="place">Sonoma</name>, <name type="place"
                                        >California</name>, <date when="1948"
                                >1948</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>With the increasing popularity of home entertainment, Church sought to
                            dramatize the point of arrival even in modest houses, stressing the role
                            of attractive forecourt paving and planting as a means of welcoming
                            guests. He also believed that a generous scale for the vestibule would
                            signal the hospitality visitors were to receive as they proceeded into
                            the the house and its garden. Increasing the house's ambience of
                            cordiality sometimes involved removing heavy foundation plantings to
                            give it a cleaner, more inviting appearance. Conscious of maintenance
                            requirements in an era of rising labor costs, Church configured gardens
                            with open centers and broad strips of grass that could be easily
                            mowed.</p>
                        <p><name type="place">California</name>'s climate made the swimming pool an
                            especially appealing garden amenity and its surrounding paved area a
                            center for family life and entertaining friends outdoors. Church's best
                            known work, the Donnell Garden in Sonoma, which he designed in <date
                                when="1948">1948</date>, contains a kidney-shaped swimming pool.
                            Resembling also one of the biomorphic images in a painting by Jean Arp
                                (<date when="1887">1887</date>&#x2013;<date when="1966">1966</date>)
                            or Joan Mir&#x00F3; (<date when="1893">1893</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1983">1983</date>), it has assumed the role of an icon in the
                                <name type="place">California</name> modernist garden movement
                            (figs. 13.24, 13.25).</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-559">
                            <graphic url="CH13_026.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">Below right: 13.25. Donnell Garden, <name
                                        type="place">Sonoma</name>, <name type="place"
                                        >California</name>, designed by Thomas Church. <date
                                        when="1948">1948</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Modern sculpture, like modern painting, served as an inspiration for
                            early modernist landscape architects like Church, who were seeking a new
                            vocabulary of forms. They also employed modern sculpture as ornament.
                            Ever pragmatic and people-oriented in his approach, Church made the
                            sculptural feature he placed in the Donnell Garden swimming pool appear
                            to be an afterthought. "The first idea was to use one of the big
                            boulders from the site as a play island in the pool," Church explained.
                            "This was changed (the rock would have torn the swimmers to pieces) into
                                an<pb n="451"/><pb n="451" type="orig"/>island of concrete designed
                            by sculptor Adaline Kent."<ref target="#CH13-n28"><hi rend="sup"><hi
                                        rend="bold">28</hi></hi></ref>This biomorphic form invited
                            swimmers to sunbathe in its curvaceous embrace.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-560">
                            <graphic url="CH13_027.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.26. Church's false perspective achieved by a
                                        <hi rend="italic">trompel'oeil</hi> trellis, which
                                    camouflages a neighboring wall while illusionistically
                                    increasing the sense of space in a constricted <name
                                        type="place">San Francisco</name> town-house garden.
                                    Sculpture by Adaline Kent</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Church remained stylistically versatile, always taking his cues from the
                            client, considering his or her preferences, personal and family
                            requirements, and the conditions of the site. He never entirely
                            abandoned his Beaux-Arts training, employing past styles or motifs as he
                            deemed appropriate and in response to his clients' tastes. For some of
                            his Bay Area clients living in town houses as well as those in Santa
                            Barbara where there was a strong Italianate and Spanish Colonial design
                            tradition, he drew upon his knowledge of historic landscape idioms (fig.
                            13.26). Though destined, like Fletcher Steele, by the culture and
                            education of his time to straddle two design eras, he nevertheless
                            transformed himself into a modernist of conviction, sharing many of the
                            ideas of a slightly younger generation of landscape architects that
                            included fellow Californian Garrett Eckbo.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Garrett Eckbo's Landscapes for Living</hi></head>
                        <p><name type="pname">Garret Eckbo</name> (<date when="1910"
                                >1910</date>&#x2013;<date when="2000">2000</date>) grew up in a town
                            on Alameda Island in <name type="place">San Francisco</name> Bay. He
                            studied landscape architecture at the University of <name type="place"
                                >California</name> in <name type="place">Berkeley</name> and
                            Harvard's School of Graduate Design. At Harvard he met Daniel Urban
                            Kiley and James Rose, classmates who were, like him, sufficiently
                            progressive in their social attitudes to sense that the program they
                            were being offered was designed to serve the demands of a dwindling
                            elite and did not deal with the needs of an industrialized, democratic
                            society. Joseph Hudnut, the dean of the school, had recently brought
                            Walter Gropius (<date when="1883">1883</date>&#x2013;<date when="1969"
                                >1969</date>) to head the architecture department, and with him the
                            teaching agenda of the Bauhaus, with its emphasis upon large social
                            issues and the abandonment of historic styles for functionalist design
                            and industrial materials. However, the landscape architecture department
                            at Harvard retained its Beaux-Arts curriculum, which Henry Hubbard and
                            Theodora Kimball's textbook, <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to the
                                Study of Landscape Design</hi> had codified in <date when="1917"
                                >1917</date>.<ref target="#CH13-n29"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >29</hi></hi></ref>As Reuben Rainey points out, Hubbard and
                            Kimball's method united several approaches. It called for Beaux-Arts, or
                            formal, planning as a means of uniting house and garden along continuing
                            axes, then recommended an Olmstedian naturalistic, or informal, design
                            for the remainder of the property, often as a means of melding it with
                            the larger landscape. A transitional lawn was proposed to mediate the
                            stylistic contrast between these zones.</p>
                        <p>Eckbo was inspired by his own sense of possibilities derived from living
                            and working in a less tradition-bound atmosphere than the Atlantic
                            seaboard and by the current Zeitgeist&#x2014;a heady mixture of jazz,
                            film, fashion, industrial design, New Deal social progressiveness, the
                            recently arrived automobile culture, and the growing acceptance of
                            European modern art and architecture in America. Like his friends Rose
                            and Kiley, he worked diligently while chafing at the limitations of
                            Harvard's conservative approach to landscape architecture. The three
                            probably read with keen interest the articles of the well-traveled
                            Fletcher Steele, whose descriptions of modernist French gardens opened a
                            window upon innovative alternatives to their program of study. They
                            formed a receptive audience for Christopher Tunnard's <hi rend="italic"
                                >Gardens in the Modern Landscape</hi> when it appeared in <date
                                when="1938">1938</date>.</p>
                        <p>Eckbo saw the potential of landscape design for serving a middle-class
                            clientele. He thought of the modest row house and the suburban
                            subdivision with its small front yards and backyards as interesting
                            challenges, and he was skilled at manipulating spatial organization to
                            maximize the visual interest and pleasurable use of an entire property.
                            He explored these possibilities while still at Harvard in a student
                            project comprising a city block of eighteen equal-size townhouse lots in
                            which he demonstrated a synthesis of curvilinearity and angularity
                            similar to the one found in Church's Aptos beach house. Landscape
                            historian Marc Treib draws an instructive parallel between Eckbo's
                            compositions and the work of the modern painters Wassily Kandinsky
                                (<date when="1866">1866</date>&#x2013;<date when="1944"
                            >1944</date>), Kasimir Malevich (<date when="1878"
                                >1878</date>&#x2013;<date when="1935">1935</date>), and
                            L&#x00E1;szl&#x00F3; Moholy-Nagy (<date when="1895"
                                >1895</date>&#x2014;<date when="1946">1946</date>).<ref
                                target="#CH13-n30"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >30</hi></hi></ref>The cheerful, Jazz Age rhythms and explosive visual
                            energy set up by the counterplay of geometric and "organic" lines and
                            shapes in their paintings could inspire someone who wanted to substitute
                            the shaping of space as a central compositional principle for the
                            arrangement of views along static, single-perspective axes. In borrowing
                            the free-flowing<pb n="452"/><pb n="452" type="orig"/>lines of abstract
                            painting for his plans Eckbo found a means of creating a sense of mobile
                            dynamism in the landscape, which had been impossible within the confines
                            of Beaux-Arts spatial composition.</p>
                        <p>At the same time, the inspiration of architecture as derived from Mies
                            van der Rohe's Barcelona Pavilion remained influential in Eckbo's
                                work.<ref target="#CH13-n31"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                    >31</hi></hi></ref>With its grid of eight cruciform columns set
                            on a raised terrace, the Barcelona Pavilion organizes space in a way
                            that is clear and yet ambiguous. Here, Mies established a modular system
                            that performed the functions of framing the structure and supporting the
                            roof, giving underlying mathematical order to the building, and at the
                            same time freely modulating the interior space by positioning
                            non-load-bearing walls as freestanding screens, articulating
                            occupational zones without defining them precisely. The spatial
                            continuum thus created gives an impression of uninterrupted flow. This
                            type of construction also made possible the curtain wall composed of
                            panels of glass or a combination of glass and opaque cladding hung in
                            front of a steel frame. Because space is contained but not defined
                            within these glass walls, there is no unequivocal separation between
                            indoors and outdoors and no single point within the building that can be
                            called its center.</p>
                        <p>Eckbo returned to <name type="place">California</name> to establish his
                            practice, and at Menlo Park, where he designed a garden in <date
                                when="1940">1940</date>, he acknowledged his debt to Mies, placing
                            straight and curvilinear hedges in a manner he termed "a kind of de
                            Stijl-van der Rohe planning," which served as a means of "baffling of
                            garden space ... to increase sense of volume" (fig. 13.27).<ref
                                target="#CH13-n32"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">32</hi></hi></ref>
                            As in Mies's Barcelona Pavilion, the garden has an ordering geometric
                            grid&#x2014;the pear orchard into which it was set&#x2014;and
                            well-emphasized rectangular boundaries.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-561">
                            <graphic url="CH13_028.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.27. Garden in an existing pear orchard,
                                    Menlo Park, <name type="place">California</name>, designed by
                                    Garrett Eckbo.<date when="1940">1940</date></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Above all, like Church, Eckbo wanted to focus on domestic human needs and
                            the humanized landscape that was expanding with the population growth of
                                <name type="place">California</name>. He called his first book <hi
                                rend="italic">Landscape for Living.</hi> Published in <date
                                when="1950">1950</date> when his reputation was well established and
                            illustrated with the work of his office, it implied the role of human
                            beings as partners with nature, realizing their legitimate needs through
                            science and technology rather than basing their spatial arrangements
                            upon historic styles reflecting the aspirations and needs of people in
                            other times and places.</p>
                        <p>After returning to <name type="place">California</name> and before
                            setting up a private practice, Eckbo had worked for more than four years
                            for the Farm Security Administration designing fifty landscape plans for
                            camps built to house 225 to 350 families of migrant and permanent
                            agricultural workers. His concern for ordinary humanity was expressed in
                            this context in the interesting spatial arrangements and varied palette
                            of vegetation he provided, which probably offered some greater sense of
                            place and therefore an element of psychological comfort to the
                            populations living in the otherwise unremarkable surroundings of the
                            camps of trailers and spartan temporary housing. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Landscape for Living</hi> illustrates his plans for several of
                            these camps along with some of his designs for single-family residences,
                            campuses, parks, and tract-housing, selected from a portfolio that
                            amounted to more than a thousand commissions during his years of
                            practice.</p>
                        <p>As subsequently developed by Ian <name type="pname">McHarg</name> and the
                            landscape planners he trained at the University of Pennsylvania, one
                            approach to landscape architecture was through environmental science
                            (see Chapter Fifteen). For Eckbo and other landscape functionalists of
                            his generation, science was more a matter of professional perspective, a
                            questioning approach to design problems, the discipline of asking the
                            theoretical "why" as well as the practical "how." Wishing to advocate no
                            style and to be an heir to all historic styles, Eckbo created his own
                            design vocabulary to express the dynamic aspect of modernity, his
                            preference for areal over axial design, and his commitment to democratic
                            values. Even in such structures as garden pavilions, his emphasis was
                            upon space, not mass. He saw plants as upthrusting verticals, sculptural
                            objects, and vegetative texture, and for him they were a means of
                            defining space, not an end in themselves. By contrast, he saw rocks as
                            being pulled by gravity toward the center of the earth, and he sometimes
                            used groupings of these to anchor and stabilize parts of his design.
                            Like Church and other landscape architects in <name type="place"
                                >California</name>, he designed many pools in the shape of amoebas,
                            kidneys, and boomerangs. In his designs the pool became "a positive
                            space-organizing element which controls physical movement."<ref
                                target="#CH13-n33"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                            >33</hi></hi></ref></p>
                        <p>In <date when="1956">1956</date>, when the Aluminum Corporation of <name
                                type="place">America</name> (Alcoa) asked Eckbo to develop a
                            landscape plan promoting the use of this modern metal in the garden, he
                            decided to create the Aluminum Garden<pb n="453"/><pb n="453"
                                type="orig"/>on his own property in Wonderland Park, a subdivision
                            in the Hollywood Hills above Laurel Canyon. The subdivision was situated
                            on a steeply terraced slope, and Eckbo's contribution to its planning
                            resulted in successive layers of vegetation along the side of the canyon
                            and a unified appearance rather than the fragmented look characteristic
                            of other suburban developments. Until his death in <date when="2000"
                                >2000</date>, Eckbo remained a fierce and opinionated advocate of
                            the "social-culturalnatural approach" to landscape design.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Daniel Urban Kiley's Synthesis of FRenCH
                                Influence and Miesian Modernism</hi></head>
                        <p>In contrast to Eckbo, whose experimental approach to landscape
                            architecture was fostered by the innovative, freewheeling culture of
                                <name type="place">California</name> and by his commitment to
                            low-cost housing for the mass society, <name type="pname">Daniel Urban
                                Kiley</name> (b. <date when="1912">1912</date>) became increasingly
                            drawn to Andr&#x00E9; Le N&#x00F4;tre's principles of French
                            seventeenth-century garden design. This was apparent after <date
                                when="1955">1955</date> when <name type="pname">Mr. and Mrs. J.
                                Irwin Miller</name> chose him to work in collaboration with
                            architect <name type="pname">Eero Saarinen</name> (<date when="1910"
                                >1910</date>&#x2013;<date when="1961">1961</date>) on the design of
                            their house and garden in Columbus, Indiana (fig. 13.28). Posted
                            overseas in <date when="1945">1945</date> during his military duty,
                            Kiley was able to tour European gardens for the first time, and his
                            exposure to the masterpieces of Le Notre made a lasting impression upon
                            him. At the same time, he shared with his former classmates Eckbo and
                            Rose a reverential fascination with the Barcelona Pavilion.</p>
                        <p>In <date when="1955">1955</date>, when hired by the Millers to work with
                            his friend Saarinen, Kiley had already been practicing for nineteen
                            years, using a vocabulary of multiple, shifting axes and free-form,
                            nonorthogonal, areal definitions similar to that of Eckbo and Rose. Now,
                            having discovered his affinity for Le N&#x00F4;tre and being given the
                            opportunity to work with an architect who shared his appreciation of
                            Mies van der Rohe's asymmetrical but rhythmically balanced way of
                            organizing space by means of freestanding walls set in overlapping
                            planes within a modular grid, he changed course.<ref target="#CH13-n34"
                                    ><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">34</hi></hi></ref>Henceforth, he
                            practiced a form of modern landscape architecture that married the
                            classical geometrical planning principles of the French master with the
                            dynamically ambiguous yet elegantly ordered spatial concepts of the
                            German architect. In Mies's work architectural space had the appearance
                            of being no longer contained. Space for Mies was an infinity-implying
                            continuum similar to that of Le N&#x00F4;tre's gardens, whose axes were
                            metaphors for Descartes's principle of <hi rend="italic">res
                                extensa,</hi> or the indefinite extension of the universe (see
                            Chapter Five). As landscape architect Gregg Bleam points out, "Perhaps
                            more than any other architect of his time, Mies represented a synthesis
                            of what would seem to be the conflicting conceptions of neoclassicism
                            and modernism."<ref target="#CH13-n35"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >35</hi></hi></ref>Kiley, like Frank Lloyd Wright and
                            Christopher Tunnard, found inspiration in Japanese design, where a
                            similar underlying asymmetrical compositional balance and continuous,
                            interpenetrating spatial organization are achieved.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-562">
                            <graphic url="CH13_029.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.28. Plan of <name type="pname">J. Irwin
                                        Miller</name> Garden, <name type="place">Columbus</name>,
                                    Indiana, designed by Daniel Urban Kiley. <date when="1955"
                                        >1955</date>
                                    <graphic url="CH13_030.jpg"/> Staggered Hedges <graphic
                                        url="CH13_031.jpg"/> Horsechestnut <hi rend="italic"
                                        >All&#x00E9;e</hi>
                                    <graphic url="CH13_032.jpg"/> Locust <hi rend="italic"
                                        >All&#x00E9;e</hi>
                                    <graphic url="CH13_033.jpg"/> Flatrock River</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Organized as a series of separate but overlapping zones, Kiley's
                            functional and ornamental garden spaces carry the centrifugal movement
                            of Saarinen's plan for the house into the surrounding landscape. The
                            house, placed within a large square of their combined grid plan, is
                            defined on three sides by clipped arborvitae hedges planted in a
                            staggered pattern rather than as a single continuous line. Around the
                            house are<pb n="454"/><pb n="454" type="orig"/>a series of geometrically
                            ordered gardens reminiscent of the <hi rend="italic">bosquets</hi> and
                                <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> of Le N&#x00F4;tre, but they do
                            not employ Le N&#x00F4;tre's axial symmetries. Freely arranged within
                            their own grid in a manner that complements Saarinen's pinwheel
                            disposition of the elements of the house, these geometrical garden
                            spaces flow fluidly and expand outward. To define the remaining side of
                            the square Kiley placed a honey locust <hi rend="italic"
                                >all&#x00E9;e</hi> adjacent to the house, with a platform terrace at
                            either end for the display of sculpture (fig. 13.29).</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-563">
                            <graphic url="CH13_034.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.29. Locust <hi rend="italic"
                                        >all&#x00E9;e,</hi>
                                    <name type="pname">J. Irwin Miller</name> Garden, with sculpture
                                    by <name type="pname">Henry Moore</name></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-564">
                            <graphic url="CH13_035.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.30. Fountain
                                    Place, Allied Bank Tower, <name type="place">Dallas</name>,
                                        <name type="place">Texas</name>, designed by Daniel Urban
                                    Kiley</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>For the platform terrace at the north end the Millers chose a reclining
                            female figure in bronze by Henry Moore. At the other end of this <hi
                                rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e,</hi> they installed a sculpture by
                            Jacques Lipchitz. Stairs lead down to a lawn that slopes toward the
                            floodplain beside the Flatrock River. Trees planted both in regular
                            configurations and naturalistic clumps form walls on either side of the
                            lawn. Some of the Miller garden's finest effects are due to the clients'
                            horticultural knowledge, original plant selections, and intelligent
                            replanting over the years. These include the entrance drive planted as
                            an <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> of horse chestnuts to remind
                            Miller of the chestnut <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;es</hi> he had
                            admired in French gardens when he was a graduate student in the <date
                                when="1930">1930</date>s; the weeping beeches in the front entry and
                            on the terrace on the western side of the living room where they serve
                            the function of exterior draperies; the planting of a glen of redbud
                            trees outside the dining room; the substitution of red maples for the
                            row of sycamores in the <hi rend="italic">all&#x00E9;e</hi> leading to
                            the river; and the installation of willows, in the meadow near the
                            water.</p>
                        <p>Kiley's cool reinterpretation of the Beaux-Arts French Neoclassical
                            heritage along lines suggested by the architecture of Mies van der Rohe
                            made him a logical partner for the high-style modern architects who
                            received commissions to build prestigious buildings that served as
                            corporate status symbols. His important contributions in this area in
                            the later years of his career illustrate the growing importance of
                            corporations in shaping both the urban and suburban landscape and their
                            financial ability to supersede local governments as providers of
                            attractive public spaces. From General Motors to Pepsico to Disney to
                            Exxon and Time-Life, big companies have played an increasingly large
                            role both directly and indirectly in the development of the American
                            landscape. Large institutions such as the Ford Foundation and Lincoln
                            Center, both clients of Kiley's, have adopted the same understated
                            Olympian grandeur as corporations in creating an image through
                            architecture and landscape design</p>
                        <p>Within the discipline of an abstract geometrical order, Kiley seeks the
                            sensuously grand gesture. Like his contemporary, <name type="pname"
                                >Lawrence Halprin</name> (see Chapter Fifteen), he is interested in
                            extending the expressive potential of both still and animated water in
                            reflecting pools, fountains, and cascades. His architectural imagination
                            and ability to think boldly in terms of scale and spatial arrangement
                            are qualities that have made him a congenial collaborator with some of
                            the most eminent architects of the twentieth century, including Louis
                            Kahn, Eero Saarinen, <name type="pname">I. M. Pei</name>, and <name
                                type="pname">Kevin Roche</name>. In <name type="place"
                            >Dallas</name>, <name type="place">Texas</name>, he worked with <name
                                type="pname">Peter Ker Walker</name> in designing Fountain Place, a
                            large water garden built in conjunction with the Pei firm's Allied Bank
                            Tower (fig. 13.30). Here, he planted bald cypress trees in circular
                            concrete tubs set according to a grid within a broadly stepped cascade,
                            which is further animated by 263 bubbler fountains placed in staggered
                            rows between the trees. The cooling effect and pleasant roar of the
                            sparkling, tree-shaded water, together with a grid of fountain jets that
                            play according to various computer-programmed patterns, have made this
                            corporate gift of public space a muchappreciated popular attraction.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">James Rose's Functionalist and Zen
                            Approach</hi></head>
                        <p><name type="pname">James Rose</name> (<date when="1910"
                                >1910</date>&#x2013;<date when="1991">1991</date>) used a caustic
                            pen and an original and deliberately unconventional eye to challenge
                            established taste and convention. He found a forum for his ideas in the
                            magazine <hi rend="italic">Pencil Points</hi> (later <hi rend="italic"
                                >Progressive Architecture</hi>) where he coauthored three articles
                            with <name type="pname">Kiley</name> and <name type="pname">Eckbo</name>
                            and also submitted pieces of his own. The freshness of his opinionated
                            prose and perspective on landscape design won him an instant sympathetic
                            readership, especially among architects. Rose's mission throughout his
                            career was to create an intimate relationship between human<pb n="455"
                                /><pb n="455" type="orig"/>beings, nature, and architecture. This
                            aspiration drew him into a close friendship with Christopher Tunnard.
                            Like the architect Richard Neutra, Rose considered the separation
                            between indoors and outdoors as a series of transparent planes, and his
                            interlocking of exterior and interior forms promoted spatial fusion.</p>
                        <p>Rose compartmentalized garden space, always with a light hand to allow it
                            visual flow. He did this sometimes with screens of modular wood-framed
                            panels containing a plastic-impregnated wire mesh, sometimes with
                            translucent plastic Japanese shoji screens, sometimes minimally with
                            vertical strings of nylon parachute cord strung along a plane at
                            intervals, sometimes with panels of twisted, slatted bamboo, or
                            sometimes with the slender trunks of white birch trees (fig. 13.31).
                            These screens filtered light and enriched the garden with their own
                            pattern and that of silhouetted tree branches. Overhead, Rose's
                            trellises carried modular grid patterns into the garden, supporting
                            vines and framing the sky Sometimes these extended horizontal roof
                            lines; at others they acted as freestanding open-air awnings, which were
                            often canted skyward, giving the garden a jaunty angularity. His
                            ground-plane patterns and plant forms combined with those of the
                            vertical and horizontal planes above to create a three-dimensional
                            composition with a combination of spatial definition and ambiguity.</p>
                        <p>Rose had a craftsman's aesthetic sensibility and a spiritual bent, which
                            he nourished by frequent trips to <name type="place">Japan</name>, and
                            at home, by the practice of Zen Buddhism. The garden was, for him, both
                            a functional space and a place for reverie. For this reason the private
                            garden, not the large-scale landscape, was his chosen m&#x00E9;tier.
                            With a less extensive practice than either Kiley or Eckbo, Rose's method
                            of approaching each commission was a highly personal one and involved
                            his presence on the site much more than at a drafting table. He liked to
                            shape his landscapes improvisationally, and he often participated in
                            their long-term maintenance. No other modern landscape designer gave as
                            much attention to ground-plane texture as Rose did, and his compositions
                            in gravel, river-worn rocks, flagstones, ground covers, and shrubs are
                            masterful essays in landscape craftsmanship (fig. 13.32).</p>
                        <p>In <date when="1952">1952</date>, Rose designed his own small house in
                            Ridgewood, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>. He used it as a protest
                            against the subsidiary role the landscape architect was usually assigned
                            by the architect and subdivision developer. In his house, according to
                            Rose, "The landscape is of the house instead of attached to it, and the
                            space is one."<ref target="#CH13-n36"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold"
                                        >36</hi></hi></ref>We can only speculate on what the
                            appearance of the American suburb might be today if the prescriptions of
                            Rose and Eckbo for site planning and the integration of architecture and
                            landscape in a single design process had been broadly influential.</p>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-565">
                            <graphic url="CH13_036.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold">13.31. Depicted in <hi rend="italic">Creative
                                        Gardens,</hi> this James Rose Tea Garden is captioned as
                                    follows: "This fabric of natural and man-made materials, woven
                                    in three dimensions, gives one the sense of being within
                                    something while still out of doors. Surface: a pattern of brick
                                    perforated with grass, pachysandra, day lilies and baby's
                                    breath. Sides: translucent shoji in removable panels, white
                                    birch stems, and the common grape vine. Ceiling: the trellis,
                                    overhanging branches, and the sky."</hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure xml:id="fig-566">
                            <graphic url="CH13_037.jpg"/>
                            <figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 13.32. Garden by
                                    James Rose, Ridgewood, <name type="place">New
                                Jersey</name></hi></figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <p>Society is influenced, but rarely led, by visionaries. The urge to
                            regulate, systematize, and follow is too strong. Legislation creates
                            town building codes, and banks and federally sponsored loan programs
                            create requirements for mortgage financing that stifle deviation from
                            standardized norms. With some exceptions such as <name type="pname"
                                >James Rouse</name> (<date when="1915">1915</date>&#x2013;<date
                                when="1996">1996</date>), the developers who shaped <name
                                type="place">America</name> in the second half of the twentieth
                            century proved to be much less socially minded than the regional
                            planners and landscape architects of the first half, who believed in
                            rational science as a <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> and
                            industrial technology as a positive force for raising the living
                            standards of society through good engineering and design. The dreams of
                            these idealists were soon deflated by the arrival of a future much less
                            agreeable than the one they had imagined. The media, perhaps the most
                            culturally influential area of corporate power, became a growing
                            influence, urging people toward consumption, and popular entertainment
                            became a mass industry affecting every corner of society. The
                            manufacturers of the private automobile, the vanguard of consumer
                            marketing, proved particularly adept at influencing government decision-
                            making and the authorization of funding for highways. In the late
                            twentieth century, private property as commodity, leisure as lifestyle,
                            and the automobile as the dominant mode of transportation had a profound
                            effect upon landscape, especially in America.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <pb n="456"/>
                    <pb n="456" type="orig"/>
                    <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Thirteen</hi></head>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >1.</hi></seg><p> For an excellent discussion of the social,
                            political, economic, and cultural forces underlying the <date
                                when="1925">1925</date>
                            <name type="place">Paris</name> International Exhibition of Modern
                            Decorative and Industrial Arts, see Doroth&#x00E9;e Imbert, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Modernist Garden in <name type="place"
                                    >France</name></hi> (<name type="place">New Haven</name>: Yale
                            University Press, <date when="1993">1993</date>), chap. 3. I am indebted
                            to this author for her analysis of the exposition and of the work of
                            several forceful and original French landscape designers of the <date
                                when="1920">1920</date>s and <date when="1930">1930</date>s who
                            honored tradition and simultaneously attempted a radical break with the
                            past.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >2.</hi></seg><p>
                            <name type="pname">Jean-Claude-Nicolas Forestier</name>, "Les jardins
                            &#x00E0; l'exposition des arts d&#x00E9;coratifs," <date
                                when="1925-09-12">12 September 1925</date>, p. 526, as quoted in
                            Imbert, op. cit., p. 128.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >3.</hi></seg><p> For perceptual differences between
                            painting&#x2014;a medium that allows the eye to experience optical
                            shifts between the plane of the canvas and a series of ambiguous
                            illusions of depth&#x2014;and sculpture, architecture, and landscape
                            design&#x2014;arts in which three-dimensionality is objective&#x2014;
                            see Imbert, op. cit., pp. 63&#x2013;68.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >4.</hi></seg><p> Fletcher Steele, "New Pioneering in Landscape
                            Design," <hi rend="italic">Landscape Architecture Quarterly</hi> 20, no.
                            3 (<date when="1930-04">April 1930</date>), p. 165, as quoted in Imbert,
                            op. cit., p. 27. For Steele's life and career, which I have summarized
                            below, see Robin Karson, <hi rend="italic">Fletcher Steele, Landscape
                                Architect: An Account of the Gardenmaker's Life, <date when="1885"
                                    >1885</date>&#x2013;<date when="1971">1971</date></hi> (<name
                                type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Harry N.
                                Abrams</name>, Inc./Sagapress, Inc., <date when="1989"
                            >1989</date>).</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >5.</hi></seg><p>
                            <name type="pname">Fletcher Steele</name>, <hi rend="italic">Design in
                                the Little Garden</hi> (<name type="place">Boston</name>: The
                            Atlantic Monthly Press, <date when="1924">1924</date>), pp.
                            17&#x2013;18.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >6.</hi></seg><p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Landscape Architecture</hi> 20 (<date when="1930-04"
                                >April 1930</date>): 163&#x2013;64, as cited in Karson, <hi
                                rend="italic">Fletcher Steele, Landscape Architect,</hi> p.
                        159.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >7.</hi></seg><p> The quotations in this paragraph are derived from
                            Steele's own descriptions of the Naumkeag Garden as cited in Karson, op.
                            cit., pp. 116&#x2013;17.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >8.</hi></seg><p> "Naumkeag Gardens Develop" (Essay, Library of
                            Congress, <date when="1947-05">May 1947</date>), p. 8, as cited in
                            Karson, op. cit., p. 135.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >9.</hi></seg><p> Fletcher Steele letter dated <date
                                when="1948-03-27">March 27, 1948</date>, Library of Congress, as
                            cited in Karson, op. cit., p. 267.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >10.</hi></seg><p> The Becks interviewed Le Corbusier in <name
                                type="place">Paris</name> with the idea of commissioning him to
                            design their house, but they decided that his work was better suited for
                                <name type="place">South America</name> than Millbrook, <name
                                type="place">New York</name>. See Lester Collins, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Innisfree: An American Garden</hi> (<name type="place">New
                                York</name>: Sagapress/Harry N. Abrams, Inc., <date when="1994"
                                >1994</date>), p. 3. This book, published posthumously a year after
                            Collins's death, provides an excellent understanding of how two Western
                            collaborators applied East Asian principles of landscape aesthetics to
                            the creation of an American landscape.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >11.</hi></seg><p> See Collins, op. cit., pp.
                        17&#x2013;20.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >12.</hi></seg><p> According to Lance Neckar, "At Harvard he
                            [Tunnard] had the extraordinary opportunity to shape some of the ideas
                            of the principal progenitors of modern design in the postwar era,
                            including his friends Garrett Eckbo, Dan Kiley, and James Rose and his
                            students <name type="pname">Lawrence Halprin</name>, Philip Johnson, and
                            Edward Larrabee Barnes." See "Christopher Tunnard: The Garden in the
                            Modern Landscape," <hi rend="italic">Modern Landscape Architecture: A
                                Critical Review,</hi> ed. Marc Treib (<name type="place"
                                >Cambridge</name>, Mass.: MIT Press, <date when="1993">1993</date>),
                            p. 154.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >13.</hi></seg><p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Gardens in the Modern Landscape</hi> (<name
                                type="place">London</name>: The Architectural Press, <date
                                when="1938">1938</date>), p. 81.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >14.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 92</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >15.</hi></seg><p> Tunnard included an illustration of Le
                            Corbusier's Villa Savoye at Poissy in <hi rend="italic">Gardens in the
                                Modern Landscape</hi> with this quote from the architect: "I shall
                            place this house on columns in a beautiful corner of the countryside; we
                            shall have twenty houses rising above the long grass of a meadow where
                            cattle will continue to graze. Instead of the superfluous and detestable
                            clothing of garden city roads and byways, the effect of which is always
                            to destroy the site, we shall establish a fine arterial system running
                            in concrete through the grass itself, and in the open country. Grass
                            will border the roads; nothing will be disturbed&#x2014;neither the
                            trees, the flowers, nor the flocks and herds. The dwellers in these
                            houses, drawn hence through love of the life of the countryside, will be
                            able to see it maintained intact from their hanging gardens or from
                            their ample windows. Their domestic lives will be set within a Virgilian
                            dream."</p><p>Here Le Corbusier does not consider who will maintain this
                            Virgilian dream or how, as Tunnard is quick to point out, the larger
                            landscape can be organized in relationship with the house to accommodate
                            the functional needs of human beings. Dryly, he wrote, "Few people want
                            to be condemned to languish at a window and exercise exclusively on a
                            roof garden." See Tunnard, op. cit., p. 79.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >16.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 107.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >17.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 137</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >18.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 159.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >19.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 161.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >20.</hi></seg><p> Soria Cals, <hi rend="italic">Roberto Burle Marx:
                                Uma fotobiografia</hi> (Rio de Janeiro: Sindicato Nacional dos
                            Editores de Livros, RJ, <date when="1995">1995</date>), p. 157
                            (translation of Portuguese text accompanying photograph on p.
                        29).</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >21.</hi></seg><p> See <name type="pname">Walker</name> and <name
                                type="pname">Simo</name>, <hi rend="italic">Invisible Gardens: The
                                Search for Modernism in the American Landscape</hi> (<name
                                type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: The MIT Press, <date
                                when="1994">1994</date>), pp. 64&#x2013;65 for a discussion of the
                            Surrealist aspect of Burle Marx's work, derived from the recomposition
                            of found objects into haunting compositions.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >22.</hi></seg><p> See <name type="pname">Lawrence Joseph</name>,
                            "The Garden of Ulysses: Ferdinand Bac, modernism and the afterlife of
                            muth," <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History of Gardens &amp;
                                Designed Landscapes,</hi> 20:1 (January-March <date when="2000"
                                >2000</date>), pp.6&#x2013;24.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n23" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >23.</hi></seg><p>
                            <name type="pname">Keith Eggener</name>, "Postwar Modernism in <name
                                type="place">Mexico</name>: Luis Barrag&#x00E1;n's Jardines del
                            Pedregal and the International Discourse on Architecture and Place" in
                                <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society of Architectural
                                Historians</hi> 58:2 (<date when="1999-06">June 1999</date>):
                            125.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n24" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >24.</hi></seg><p>
                            <name type="pname">Joseph Hudnut</name>, dean of the Harvard Graduate
                            School of Design, understandably took exception to such complete
                            reliance on the dramatic potential of site planning as was practiced by
                            Wright. In an essay, "Space and the Modern Garden," reprinted in
                            Christopher Tunnard's <hi rend="italic">Gardens in the Modern
                                Landscape</hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: The Architectural
                            Press, <date when="1938">1938</date>), he reasoned: "Certainly a harmony
                            between the modern house and its site is more evident when the site,
                            like the house, has escaped both romance and an oppressive formality;
                            but a deep or persuasive unity cannot be attained when one and not the
                            other has submitted to a conscious control of form. Therefore I do not
                            despair of gardens which are, like houses, <hi rend="italic"
                                >designed."</hi></p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n25" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >25.</hi></seg><p> From the text of a <date when="1951">1951</date>
                            speech by Barrag&#x00E1;n, "Gardens for Environment: Jardines del
                            Pedregal," printed in <hi rend="italic">Journal of the A.I.A.</hi> 17
                            (April <date when="1952">1952</date>), p. 170, as referenced in Eggener,
                            op. cit., p. 127 (note 31). The architectural historian Keith Eggener
                            argues that, in addition to the social convention of walled streets and
                            domestic privacy inherited from Mediterranean antiquity, "El Pedregal's
                            walls and gates, and the guards and guardhouses often placed beside
                            them, evince both a substantial concern for security and a measure of
                            ostentatiousness. Walls, gates, and guards not only protect property but
                            also assert its value, its need for protection. Indeed, the security and
                            exclusiveness of this gated, guarded community were among its major
                            selling points; Barrag&#x00E1;n's advertising campaign for El Pedregal
                            placed considerable emphasis on these issues and on those design
                            features that addressed them."</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n26" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >26.</hi></seg><p> As quoted in Eggener, op. cit., p. 131</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n27" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >27.</hi></seg><p>
                            <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">California</name> Gardens: Creating
                                a New Eden</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Abbeville
                            Press, <date when="1994">1994</date>), p. 194.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n28" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >28.</hi></seg><p> Thomas Church, <hi rend="italic">Gardens Are for
                                People</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Reinhold Publishing
                            Company, <date when="1955">1955</date>), p. 231.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n29" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >29.</hi></seg><p> For an excellent description of the tenets of
                            Beaux-Arts landscape style as presented in Hubbard and Kimball's book
                            and Eckbo's opposition as articulated in his book, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Landscape for Living,</hi> see Reuben Rainey, "Organic Form in the
                            Humanized landscape': Garrett Eckbo's <hi rend="italic">Landscape for
                                Living"</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Modern Landscape Architecture: A
                                Critical Review,</hi> ed. Marc Treib (<name type="place"
                                >Cambridge</name>, Mass.: The MIT Press, <date when="1993"
                                >1993</date>), pp. 180&#x2013;205.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n30" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >30.</hi></seg><p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Garrett Eckbo: Modern Landscapes for Living</hi> (F.
                            W. Dodge Corporation: An Architectural Record Book with Duell, Sloan,
                            &amp; Pearce, <date when="1950">1950</date>), pp. 59&#x2013;69,
                        87.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n31" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >31.</hi></seg><p>
                            <name type="pname">Marc Treib</name> characterizes the Barcelona
                            Pavilion as "the true archetype of modern spatial composition." See
                            "Axioms for a Modern Landscape Architecture" in <hi rend="italic">Modern
                                Landscape Architecture: A Critical Review,</hi> p. 43. Reconstructed
                            because of its significance in the history of modern architecture at the
                            time of the <date when="1992">1992</date> Olympics held in Barcelona,
                            the original Pavilion stood for a mere six months. However, the
                            inclusion of it in plan and photographs in the Museum of Modern Art's
                            exhibition on <hi rend="italic">The International Style</hi> organized
                            by HenryRussell Hitchcock and Philip Johnson in <date when="1932"
                                >1932</date> made it a seminal and widely studied work of
                            modernism.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n32" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >32.</hi></seg><p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Landscape for Living</hi> (<date when="1950"
                                >1950</date>), p. 137.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n33" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >33.</hi></seg><p> Conversation with Marc Treib anf Doroth&#x00E9;e
                            Imbert, as quoted in Treib and Imbert, <hi rend="italic">Garrett Eckbo:
                                Modern Landscapes for Living,</hi> p. 73.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n34" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >34.</hi></seg><p> Mies van der Rohe's concept of space was one of a
                            modularly organized continuum of overlapping geometrical planes, which
                            fused Frank Lloyd Wright planning theories with the spatial concepts of
                            the De Stijl painters in Holland, especially Theo van Doesburg and Piet
                            Mondrian. For a sound analysis of such asymmetrical compositional
                            balance, see Gregg Bleam, "The Work of Dan Kiley" in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Modern Landscape Architecture: A Critical Review,</hi> ed. Marc
                            Treib, pp. 230&#x2013;37. Both Kiley and Eckbo were influenced by Mies's
                            brand of architectural modernism.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n35" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >35.</hi></seg><p>
                            <name type="pname">Gregg Bleam</name>, op. cit., p. 234. As cited by
                            Bleam, this conclusion is supported by Kenneth Frampton, "Notes on
                            Classical and Modern Themes in the Architecture of Mies van der Rohe and
                            Auguste Perret," in <hi rend="italic">Classical Tradition and the Modern
                                Movement</hi> (Helsinki: Finnish Association of Architects, Museum
                            of Finnish Architecture, Alvar Aalto Museum, <date when="1985"
                                >1985</date>), p. 22.</p></note>
                    <note xml:id="CH13-n36" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold"
                                >36.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 108.</p></note>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
