<div type="chapter">
<pb n="457"/>
<pb n="457" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER FOURTEEN HOME, COMMERCE, AND ENTERTAINMENT: LANDSCAPES OF CONSUMERISM</hi></head>
<figure xml:id="fig-567">
<graphic url="CH14_001.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p>Consumption, or material self-gratification, is the engine that fuels many modern industrial economies. Consumerism directs much of the course of landscape design today. In addition, the notion of the nuclear family as the primary social unit for child rearing, replacing the extended family, the clan, the tribe, and the state, has resulted in the elevation to new status of the individual home and the plot of land upon which it sits. Indeed, no previous societies have ever focused so attentively as present Western ones upon defining a dedicated spatial realm for families and children. The culture of childhood and the realm of juvenile fantasy have increasingly informed our subject area during the past half century. <name type="pname">Jean Piaget</name> (<date when="1896">1896</date>&#x2013;<date when="1980">1980</date>) and other child psychologists brought new social awareness of the value and purposes of play in the forma-<lb/>
tion of human personality. This is manifested in the home yard with its swing set and wading pool and in numerous neighborhood parks and playgrounds.</p>
<p>The realization of the American dream of home ownership and the fulfillment of a pioneer spirit that had long been ingrained in the national temperament by settling a new urban frontier, the original Western one having vanished, brought real psychic rewards to millions of citizens. In transforming the middle landscape advo-<lb/>
cated by Downing and Olmsted in the nineteenth century as an ideal combination of civilization and nature into suburbia&#x2014;a place replete with both urban amenities and pastoral greenery but increasingly autonomous and independent of the metropolis to which it is only loosely tied&#x2014;they created a new kind of urbanism that theorists are still attempting to define. The patterns woven by the first weavers of the suburban fabric were far from exemplary as environmentalists, sociologists, and urban planners soon dis-<lb/>
overed. But for the young families in <name type="place">America</name> at the end of World War II the suburban subdivision was an attractive ready-made cloth, which they gladly bought and soon cut to fit.</p>
<p>If democratic capitalism and the consumer society furthered the American ideal of a suburban realm, this middle landscape was enabled by the automobile. By the second half of the twentieth century, automobile and road engineering interests had been suc-<lb/>
cessful in enlarging the scale of the city as a physical entity, while retrofitting old urban streets as arteries for cars and trucks&#x2014;a detri-<lb/>
ment to their former function as sociable public space&#x2014;causing land use patterns to be rearranged in ways that left most people almost completely dependent on motor vehicular transportation. The automobile made it possible for the city to spread beyond all previously urbanized land as new areas became accessible and inter-<lb/>
connected by arterial roads and the entire metropolitan mass looped by a circumferential highway. The much shorter journey to work that was accomplished on foot when the city was still a series of multiple-use districts, with commerce and residence side by side, had become extended for middle-class breadwinners in the early twentieth century with the development of streetcar suburbs. Now, new residential neighborhoods spread into the spaces between the radial rail lines as well as into the rural fringe, and old center-city neighborhoods in the United States were abandoned to the poor-<lb/>
est members of society. The progressive outward migration related to increasing levels in income, with the wealthiest citizens of the city living farthest from the urban core, is a primarily American phenomenon. In continental European cities, by contrast, prestige still adheres to the urban center.</p>
<p>The great highway building period that ensued in the United States following the Highway Act of <date when="1956">1956</date> was rationalized as a boon to motorist safety, business accessibility, and civilian security, for with the escalation of the Cold War, government transporta-<lb/>
tion officials made a priority of planning for troop movement and urban evacuation in the event of a nuclear attack. The biggest finan-<lb/>
cial beneficiaries were the developers who bought land and con-<lb/>
structed mass-market housing on tracts of real estate close to the new highways and those who financed, built, and rented to com-<lb/>
<pb n="458"/>
<pb n="458" type="orig"/>
mercial tenants space in a new kind of retail facility, the suburban shopping center. The success of this new type of retail conglom-<lb/>
eration, which led to the development of the shopping mall, was highly instrumental in the disaggregation of the city and the replace-<lb/>
ment of its old single-core form with the multinucleated regional model with which Americans are familiar today.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-568">
<graphic url="CH14_002.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.1. <name type="place">Las Vegas</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>In the consumer society, the objects of dream and desire and the objects of industrial manufacture are often the same. Shopping malls are consumerist landscapes by definition, and their develop-<lb/>
ers have been extremely inventive in creating recreational environ-<lb/>
ments for commerce. These challenge older forms of urban design while providing a highly popular type of quasi-public space. In com-<lb/>
bining recreation with commerce, shopping malls have come increasingly to resemble another landscape form, the theme park.</p>
<p>Disneyland and its successors demonstrate the degree to which theater&#x2014;a venerable component of garden design&#x2014;has been subsumed by the fast-growing entertainment industry and how this industry, in turn, has affected landscape design. The pop-<lb/>
ularity of the theme park as a participatory experience in which consumers and "cast members" intermingle in a theatrical setting carefully contrived by "imagineers"&#x2014;the designers who create landscapes of association based on fairy tales, children's stories, animated cartoons, foreign countries, and heritage ideals&#x2014;is a twentieth-century cultural phenomenon to ponder. Phenomenal is the degree to which the themes and characters of theme parks have influenced the general public's attitude toward animals, plants, exotic lands, famous sights, and the women and men of history. In this we see the power of the media, another outgrowth of con-<lb/>
sumer capitalism, for televised images and advertising implant these visions in the minds of old and young, no matter how they trivial-<lb/>
ize the art and realities that inspired them in the first place. These pervasive images of consumer culture have become as significant perhaps to the present generation as the gods and heroes in the Homeric epics and the tales of Ovid were in other centuries.</p>
<p>Yet, verisimilitude compels our admiration. The wizardry of the stage-set environments in theme parks, with their elaborate invisible technological infrastructures, has been augmented with imagery derived from the camera, a machine that has been exert-<lb/>
ing a profound influence upon the experience of place for a cen-<lb/>
tury and a half. That some people prefer theme-park replications to the original models is due in no small part to the large role that various forms of photography have come to have in our lives. We trust the camera as a recorder of "reality," and we easily transfer emotional responses from the actual world around us to the sub-<lb/>
jects and scenes in photographs.</p>
<p>Photography's role with regard to landscape has several dimensions. A nineteenth-century invention, the stereopticon cam-<lb/>
era, created three-dimensional "magic lantern" views of famous landscapes for armchair tourists. Then, in the hands of actual tourists, cameras became a means of recording visited landscapes. But today, photography is more than another method for imaging reality. In consumerist democracies of the West, the mass appeal of familiar stories and images drawn from popular movies actively propels design. The relationship between theme parks and the movie industry is familial; the art of the Hollywood studio and the movie-set construction technology of the Hollywood back lot fostered Disneyland and its successors. Because of its popularity and commercial success, the thematic landscape is a growing phe-<lb/>
nomenon, especially in the United States.<ref target="#CH14-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref>Now, blurring the dis-<lb/>
tinction between the real and the virtual, entire cities and towns are being "themed." Las Vegas, which markets itself as a family vacation resort as well as the casino capital of the world, is the most conspicuous representative of this trend, having turned its famous strip into a fantastic m&#x00E9;lange of other times and other places, both fictional and real&#x2014;Monte Carlo, Treasure Island, ancient <name type="place">Egypt</name>, imperial Rome, modern <name type="place">New York</name> City (fig. 14.1). Some may find it appropriate that the nation that invented Hollywood should be reinvented by Hollywood in turn.</p>
<div type="section">
<pb n="459"/>
<pb n="459" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">I. A Home for tHe Family: The Landscape of Suburbia</hi></head>
<p>The full potential of the automobile to transform life in the United States and other industrial nations in ways that even the visitors to the Futurama exhibit at the <date when="1939">1939</date> <name type="place">New York</name> World's Fair would not have grasped only began to be realized with the passage by Congress of the <date when="1956">1956</date> Highway Act. This legislation contributed to the home-building explosion that accounts for sub-<lb/>
urbia, the wide ring of converging developer subdivi-<lb/>
sions surrounding major cities that succeeded the carefully planned garden suburbs of the <date when="1920">1920</date>s and the New Deal Greenbelt Towns of the <date when="1930">1930</date>s. The High-<lb/>
way Act authorized a federal Highway Trust Fund with revenues derived from taxes on fuel, tires, and new vehicles of all kinds, as well as a use tax on com-<lb/>
mercial trucks. The funds were to pay 90 percent of the cost of creating an interstate highway system, with the states paying the remaining 10 percent. The logic behind this extraordinary legislation was as simple as the consequences were far-reaching.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">The Landscape of Suburbia: The Early Postwar Years</hi></head>
<p>In the United States, the powers of the federal gov-<lb/>
ernment were extended during the Great Depression and following World War II in order to stimulate new housing construction and large-scale suburban devel-<lb/>
opment by means of two important loan insurance programs&#x2014;that of the Federal Housing Authority (FHA) and the Veterans Administration (VA). These proved a boon to developers and homeowners alike. The bias in <name type="place">America</name> toward home ownership is still enshrined in the income tax laws by the allowable deduction from gross income of mortgage interest and real estate taxes. Because banks as lenders must assess the financial reliability of mortgage loan appli-<lb/>
cants, credit qualification is a frequent obstacle to home ownership. The New Dealers who created the Federal Housing Authority in <date when="1934">1934</date> during the Great Depression did so in order to encourage investment of private capital in the construction industry and thereby stimulate employment within the building trades. Ten years later, the Servicemen's Readjustment Act, or GI Bill as it is popularly known, created the Veterans Administration to ease the transition of mil-<lb/>
itary men to civilian society. Because both of these programs made possible minimum down payments of 10 percent or less on the purchase price, young Americans starting their families in the years imme-<lb/>
diately following World War II flocked to inspect the model homes and thereupon to sign up for purchase in the first tract housing suburbs. They sprang up in metropolitan fringes across the country, from Levit-<lb/>
town on Long Island, to Lakewood in <name type="place">California</name> (fig. 14.2).<ref target="#CH14-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref>Increased affluence combined with widespread status seeking, television's portrayal of suburban mid-<lb/>
dle-class life, and the absence of household servants all stimulated the desire for mechanical conveniences, which had been pent up during the war. This occa-<lb/>
sioned the birth of the consumer society, and devel-<lb/>
opers were quick to see that furnishing their small, cheaply constructed houses with new household appliances was an important sales asset.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-569">
<graphic url="CH14_003.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.2. An early photograph of Levittown, Long Island</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Writing about Lakewood, which was built near the Douglas Aircraft Company and where he still lives in the house his parents bought in <date when="1946">1946</date>, <name type="pname">D. J. Waldie</name> describes the sales process:
<q>The salesmen did not encourage buyers to linger. Husbands and wives selected a floor plan, signed a sales contract, looked at a map of the tract, and accepted the house they were assigned. The salesman got a thirty-five-dollar commission on each sale. In the office, among displays showing construction photographs and sales brochures, the houses may have retreated slightly. If the buyers hesitated, astonished at what they were about to do, the salesman looked past them to the line of other husbands and wives watching their children in the bright light.<ref target="#CH14-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref></q></p>
<p>The economies of scale, factory methods of construction, relaxation of local building-code stan-<lb/>
dards, small and uniform lot sizes, and simplification of house designs to a few variants upon a basic pat-<lb/>
tern made possible cheap offering prices for new homes. For developers who agreed to adhere to the FHA standards, the federal programs acted as a tremendous incentive, since the federal mortgage
<pb n="460"/>
<pb n="460" type="orig"/>
guarantees encouraged banks to finance their entire costs: acquiring land, installing streets and utilities, and constructing houses. The programs even rec-<lb/>
ommended prototypical subdivision layouts (fig. 14.3). These things accounted for the cookie-cutter look that critics soon began to castigate. The equally harsh judgment that from the air the typical plan of curving streets with their cul-de-sac offshoots resem-<lb/>
bled a can of worms did not acknowledge that it was derived from highly respected earlier new town plan-<lb/>
ning models. One was Clarence Perry's <date when="1929">1929</date> hierar-<lb/>
chical community-based network of winding local streets, feeder roads, and connecting arterials (see Chapter Twelve). The curvilinear streets were also much simplified versions of nineteenth-century Pic-<lb/>
turesque principles, which put a premium upon sur-<lb/>
prise by eliminating corridor views and withholding from sight what was around the bend. At eye level, this strategy may have mitigated the bland sameness of the new houses built on uniform lots, 50 to 60 feet wide and 100 to 120 feet deep with uniform setbacks along blocks 600 to <date when="1300">1300</date> feet long by 200 to 300 feet wide. A less artificial picturesqueness accrued as trees matured and homeowners set about enclosing garages, building additions to their houses, planting gardens, and otherwise improving their individual piece of the American Dream.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-570">
<graphic url="CH14_004.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.3. "Original Plan" and "Sug-<lb/>
gested Revised Plan," as illus-<lb/>
trated in "Planning Profitable Neighborhoods, Technical Bulletin No. 7" by the Land Planning Division of the U.S. Housing Administration, <date when="1938">1938</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Although developers, in naming their subdivi-<lb/>
sions, usually included singly or in combination the words <hi rend="italic">park, wood, valley, hills, lake,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">meadow,</hi> thereby promoting the concept that the entire community was a park, they did not follow the builders of Rad-<lb/>
burn in making a green spine the armature of their plan. Such hills and valleys as existed were on the still-<lb/>
rural fringe of the new subdivision or in scraps of nat-<lb/>
ural terrain within it that had been left vacant because they were topographically unsuited for house lots. These were the small paradises in which children played. Waldie remembers the 10-foot-deep, open drainage ditches between Lakewood's neigh-<lb/>
borhoods as filled with cattails and tadpoles in the spring. He writes, "The ditches attracted boys in packs of four or five, as did any empty lot where there was enough room to dig."<ref target="#CH14-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Alfred Levitt, who was trained as an architect, laid out the lots of the Long Island Levittown with their near-identical Cape Cod Colonial houses around a series of "Village Greens," which contained neighborhood shops, a playground, and a swimming pool. But a more plentiful green space was to be found in the continuous lawn strip composed of contiguous front yards, the individual public face each neighbor-<lb/>
ing family presents. Unfenced, these essential emblems for American homeowners of proprietorship, domes-<lb/>
ticity, and lingering rural values form a greensward that serves as a collectively maintained park. "When I walk to work," writes Waldie, "I walk through a vista that is almost one continuous garden and lawn, bro-<lb/>
ken every fifty feet by a concrete driveway."<ref target="#CH14-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref>But the premium put on private space over this community space is evident in the fact that many subdivisions do not have sidewalks. The front porch no longer exists and has been replaced by a patio or deck in back. The phrase "right in your own backyard" denotes proxim-<lb/>
ity, convenience, and the premium put on space ded-<lb/>
icated to private family interests. Here, in addition to the swing sets and wading pools that equip innumer-<lb/>
able family-scale playgrounds are to be found barbe-<lb/>
cue grills and various pieces of lawn furniture as well as accoutrements for pets.</p>
<p><name type="pname">Joseph Eichler</name> (<date when="1900">1900</date>&#x2013;<date when="1974">1974</date>), a developer from <name type="place">New York</name> who took up residence in the Bay Area in <date when="1940">1940</date>, brought architectural attention to the design of the <name type="place">California</name> version of the suburban dream house. After having rented for three years a house designed by Frank Lloyd Wright in Hillsborough, <name type="place">California</name>, Eichler decided to bring some of Wright's modernist principles to bear on tract house design. He hired Robert Anshen, a young architect, to work for him. The result, as the architectural historian Gwendolyn Wright explains, was that "American residential design crossbred a modernist pedigree with everyday ver-<lb/>
nacular ‘livability.'"<ref target="#CH14-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref>The two-car garage is the most prominent feature of the front of an Eichler house,
<pb n="461"/>
<pb n="461" type="orig"/>
and the small landscaped entry courtyard has floor-<lb/>
to-ceiling, sliding glass doors, which increase its sense of airy openness (fig. 14.4). The open floor plan gave importance to the kitchen with its modern appliances, allowing eye contact between this area and the mul-<lb/>
tipurpose family room, a postwar innovation where children could play indoors, teenagers could listen to phonograph records, and everyone could watch tel-<lb/>
evision. Becoming more than shelter, in the postwar years the American home had simultaneously shrunk in interior size and been transformed, climate per-<lb/>
mitting, into the locus of outdoor living.</p>
<p>Connecting the street with the carport or garage&#x2014;no longer an ancillary structure in the back-<lb/>
yard but now firmly attached to the house&#x2014;the driveway assumed prominence as a recreational space, being an ideal surface for learning to ride a bicycle or toss a basketball. Cynthia Girling and Kenneth Help-<lb/>
hand call this the "most representative of American open spaces" because, "[t]he driveway sits at that junc-<lb/>
ture between . . . the traditional stability of home, neighborhood, and community, and the modern mobility of the automobile, speed, and travel."<ref target="#CH14-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref>Not surprisingly, in Herbert Gans's pioneering study of Levittown, for adolescents, "the commonest gripe is the shortage of ready transportation, which makes not only facilities but, more important, other teenagers inaccessible."<ref target="#CH14-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref>This observation merely underlines the fact that the postwar suburb, being the creature of the automobile and the highway, rein-<lb/>
forces the primacy of the automobile as the domi-<lb/>
nant mode of transportation and maroons its residents if they cannot drive. Because its existence made possible the development of certain new land-<lb/>
scape types, it is the indispensable means of access to these places, as is also obvious in an examination of two closely related phenomena: the shopping mall and the theme park.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-571">
<graphic url="CH14_005.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.4. Single-family suburban house, <name type="place">California</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Joseph Eichler</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">II. Commerce and Entertainment: Shopping Malls and Theme Parks</hi></head>
<p>The image of the city as a coherent mass with a uni-<lb/>
tary center&#x2014;a village green, main plaza, or court-<lb/>
house square&#x2014;has been superseded by that of the multinodal metropolis. This urban reconfiguration has been spearheaded by retailing. Indeed, the devel-<lb/>
opment of the highway-related shopping <hi rend="italic">center</hi> was the first step in a process of urban disaggregation and reformation according to a texture that, though more loosely woven, nevertheless has knots of commercial density, retail and entertainment nuclei that serve many of the functions formerly accommodated in the city centers Americans have long referred to as "downtown." Developers with the ability to seize the opportunity presented by the new suburban market &#x2014;its <hi rend="italic">auto-mobility</hi> and continually expanding desire for consumer goods of all kinds and in all price ranges, as well as the growing distance to downtown and the heightened parking congestion there&#x2014;were the pri-<lb/>
mary shapers of this new urban landscape.</p>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">From Shopping Center to Shopping Male</hi></head>
<p>The Levitts soon realized that the convenience stores in their Village Greens on Long Island were losing money to a new regional shopping center on the high-<lb/>
way, and when they developed the next Levittown in <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, they built a related regional shopping cen-<lb/>
ter to draw business from beyond their property's own boundaries. The developers of the postwar shopping centers did not invent this form of retailing clus-<lb/>
tering but relied on a growing body of experience dating from the <date when="1920">1920</date>s.<ref target="#CH14-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref>The pioneer of the first large-<lb/>
scale suburban shopping center, a 250-store shopping village as this type of new development became known, was <name type="pname">J. C. Nichols</name>, who developed the Coun-<lb/>
try Club Plaza in <name type="place">Kansas</name> City, Missouri, beginning in <date when="1922">1922</date> (fig. 14.5). Previously, commercial real estate developers assessed the potential markets implied by areas of suburban population, acquired land for shop-<lb/>
ping strips, and sold individual properties to busi-<lb/>
nesses. These establishments competed for the driver's attention with boldly scaled frontage signs. Nichols realized that an increasing number of women resid-<lb/>
ing in the affluent Country Club district of <name type="place">Kansas</name> City now drove cars. To attract their business, he cre-<lb/>
ated within several contiguous conventional street blocks designed for local traffic an architecturally homogeneous, domestically accented environment with ample parking. Shoppers left their cars in free, landscaped, off-street lots and at the curbside adjacent
<pb n="462"/>
<pb n="462" type="orig"/>
to stores whose tenants were selected on the basis of careful market analysis. Because it was an integrated building complex under a single management, the Country Club Plaza could be built with a unified appearance, and its agreeable neoSpanish Colonial architecture and carefully controlled signs broadcast the message that shopping was enjoyable, even a pleasant recreational pastime.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-572">
<graphic url="CH14_006.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.5. Country Club Plaza, <name type="place">Kansas</name> City, Missouri, the first large-scale shopping center in the United States. <date when="1922">1922</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Other successful early shopping centers in-<lb/>
cluded Shaker Square, serving the exclusive Shaker Heights suburb of <name type="place">Cleveland</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>. Though catering to the automobile, it was linked by public transit with the major downtown shopping and business complex at Terminal Tower. In contrast to the Tower's sky-<lb/>
scraper modernity, the square's neo-Georgian archi-<lb/>
tecture declared the symbiosis between shopping village and upscale residential suburb and defined the center's image as a gateway to genteel domesticity.</p>
<p>Hugh Prather, the developer of Highland Park Village, serving the 1,400-acre, prosperous Highland Park suburb of Dallas, based his plan on the county courthouse square prevalent in <name type="place">Texas</name>, substituting for the traditional edifice of justice a central cluster of shops surrounded by plenty of convenient parking. In focusing inward, Highland Park Village became the first shopping center to turn its back to the street. Seeking architectural distinction, Prather took his designers to <name type="place">California</name> and Spain to gain inspiration for "one of the more sophisticated adaptations of the Spanish Colonial Revival mode for commercial pur-<lb/>
poses."<ref target="#CH14-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref>The ideal of architectural theming as a means of crafting a highly distinctive, if borrowed, sense of place was thus well established in this early shopping center. Although the merchandising goals of Prather's selectively chosen commer-<lb/>
cial tenants were ambitious, the specialty items they offered did not compete seriously with the array of goods in downtown stores.</p>
<p>Suburban Square in Ardmore, Pennsylvania, on <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>'s Main Line began to alter the picture. Developed adjacent to Ardmore's existing commercial area and situated centrally rather than in relation to a specific residential enclave, Suburban Square did not seek a suburban image. Instead of fostering iden-<lb/>
tity in architecturally revivalist, domestically oriented, low-rise stores, it proclaimed its status as an impor-<lb/>
tant business center by attracting the first major department store branch to anchor a shopping cen-<lb/>
ter. The syndicate of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> businessmen who planned and developed Suburban Square reserved land from the start for ample off-street parking. They also encouraged the nascent trend of medical and other professionals opening offices close to their patients and clients by including in the Times Build-<lb/>
ing, home of the <hi rend="italic">Main Line Times,</hi> seven stories of space accommodating fifty offices.</p>
<p>Stymied from widespread multiplication by the Great Depression and World War II, these suburban shopping centers remained the prominent predeces-<lb/>
sors of the ones that began to proliferate along with the new subdivisions after the war. With less need to focus upon attracting the upper-middle-class patron by then, developers could adopt a more pragmatic and less costly architectural approach. With prof-<lb/>
itability assured as the suburban exodus mounted, they no longer felt they had to create what Richard Longstreth calls "distinct signifiers of place."<ref target="#CH14-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref>Gone was the passing parade of downtown pedestrians. Window dressing, which older department stores had carried to an art form, was no longer considered important because parking lots had replaced urban sidewalks. By the <date when="1950">1950</date>s, when the regional shopping mall&#x2014;an important centrifugal force in the growth of what is now termed "spread city"&#x2014;came into being, some of the earlier shopping villages declined. Today, however, in an atmosphere of revaluation of the city and its older suburbs, several have been revi-<lb/>
talized.<ref target="#CH14-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref></p>
<p>Planned to serve regional markets rather than specific suburbs, the shopping mall is frequently located at a highway interchange near the metropol-<lb/>
itan periphery. Products, like much of suburbia, of the federal highway building program and federal tax laws that assisted developers in depreciating their investments, the malls were often the advance guard of suburbanization. The suburban house, socially focused on the private realm of indoors and backyard, with automobile functions&#x2014;garage and driveway&#x2014; prominently assigned to the front where no sidewalks or other signs of accommodation to public life exist, is a domestic form of the shopping mall. The mall's distinguishing feature is a vast perimeter parking area, or several parking areas, ringed by an exterior circu-<lb/>
<pb n="463"/>
<pb n="463" type="orig"/>
lation road. Like the the house's little-used front yard, this exterior zone is often landscaped with planting islands of trees and other greenery.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-573">
<graphic url="CH14_007.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.6. Ice rink, <name type="place">Houston Galleria</name>, <name type="place">Houston</name>, <name type="place">Texas</name>, designed by Hellmuth, Obata and Kassabaum of St. Louis</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>The focus of the mall is its central, auto-free zone of stores. Here, the suburban shopper becomes separated from the necessary conveyance for arrival, a pedestrian like the urban shopper of former times. Pioneered by architect-planner <name type="pname">Victor Gruen</name> (<date when="1903">1903</date>&#x2013;<date when="1980">1980</date>) in the early <date when="1950">1950</date>s, mall layout soon became formulaic: a "dumbbell" plan consisting of two <hi rend="italic">magnet stores,</hi> one&#x2014;usually a high-end-retail department store branch&#x2014;placed so as to be seen from the highway at one end&#x2014;and the other&#x2014;often a national franchise operation selling useful products for the home and garden as well as less expensive items&#x2014;at the opposite end. In between, on either side of a pedestrian open space meant to evoke the historic <name type="place">New England</name> village green, were small shops selling gifts, books, recordings, cosmetics, and other items that visitors to the magnet stores might pur-<lb/>
chase on an impulse as they walked by.</p>
<p>During the <date when="1960">1960</date>s, the suburban mall became an enclosed pedestrian space. It also became much more commercial and urban in appearance. Its center no longer harked back to the <name type="place">New England</name> township but instead to the high, glass-vaulted shopping arcades, or <hi rend="italic">gallerias,</hi> in <name type="place">London</name>, Milan, <name type="place">Paris</name>, and other Euro-<lb/>
pean cities.<ref target="#CH14-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref>In <date when="1956">1956</date>, at Southdale, near Minneapo-<lb/>
lis, Gruen perfected as a development form what mall trade organizations call EMACs&#x2014;Enclosed Malls Air-<lb/>
Conditioned. In the enclosed mall's pseudo-urban environment, shoppers presumably needed visual relief from the density of detail where such an abun-<lb/>
dance of merchandise was on display. Gruen there-<lb/>
fore created a central atrium&#x2014;at Southdale called the Garden Court of Perpetual Spring&#x2014;a ground-to-roof navelike space filled with light, greenery, flowers, and fountains. Well maintained, such naturalistic oases enhanced the image of the mall as an uplifting place to visit, while also serving the ancillary function of channeling shoppers into side aisles next to the chapel-<lb/>
like shops.</p>
<p>The mall in this new enclosed form became increasingly a place for recreation. Like its European predecessor, the EMAC has three or four levels of shopping ranged around a skylit central court (fig. 14.6). Park benches invite its use as a quasi-public space, and many mall visitors come not necessarily to shop but because they are seeking an attractive, comfortable, safe, yet lively and sociable place where they can pass time. Early-bird mall walkers find secu-<lb/>
rity and pleasure in congregating in the morning to jog for fitness along the interior "streets" of many enclosed malls.</p>
<p>Often the mall in its asphalt sea of parking appears as a blight upon the local scenery. But some mall operators have tried to stitch their centers together with the adjacent urban fabric. The <name type="place">Hous-<lb/>
ton</name> Galleria, for instance, was instrumental in creat-<lb/>
ing a business improvement district in the Post Oak district, and this public-private corporation has spon-<lb/>
sored new street furniture and public art along the mall's periphery in an effort to acknowledge the Gal-<lb/>
leria's status as a second downtown, the city's most visited tourist attraction, and the location of its great-<lb/>
est concentration of retail and hotel space and high-<lb/>
<pb n="464"/>
<pb n="464" type="orig"/>
rise apartment units as well as the site of several office buildings, including the Transco Tower skyscraper (fig. 14.7).</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-574">
<graphic url="CH14_008.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.7. Streetscape, Post Oak Boulevard, <name type="place">Houston</name>, <name type="place">Texas</name>. The sleek, architect-designed street furniture and scattered elements of public art are gestures that recognize the area's importance as a second downtown.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Recreation and entertainment are becoming principal commodities for mall retailers and develop-<lb/>
ers. A symbiotic profitability has been discovered between games, rides, and other theme-park activi-<lb/>
ties and old-fashioned shopping. Retailers call this "adjacent attraction." Like the planners of Rockefeller Center in <name type="place">New York</name> City, the creators of <name type="place">Houston</name>'s Galleria placed an ice-skating rink at its center. The 5.3-million-square-foot (1.58-million-square-meter) West Edmondton Mall in Alberta, <name type="place">Canada</name>&#x2014;the world's largest when it was built between <date when="1981">1981</date> and <date when="1985">1985</date>&#x2014;contains 11 department stores, more than 800 small retail shops, 110 restaurants, 13 nightclubs, a 360-room hotel with theme-park decor, 20 movie the-<lb/>
aters, a 500,000-square-foot (46,450-square-meter) water park, and other similar-size amusement areas. Scattered throughout this immense bulky tourist des-<lb/>
tination are many recreational experiences, including a roller coaster, a golf course, and a replica of Christo-<lb/>
pher Columbus's <hi rend="italic">Santa Maria.</hi></p>
<p>West Edmonton Mall's kaleidoscopic juxtapo-<lb/>
sition of highly dissimilar images exemplifies the extent to which techniques of cinematic montage in the service of consumer psychology now govern design. The same principles account for the current renaissance of the downtown areas in many major American cities where old-fashioned department stores are being replaced by urban malls. The artful blending of stagecraft and retailing also explains the successes of James Rouse, the mall developer who transformed such historic districts as <name type="place">Boston</name>'s Quincy Market, <name type="place">New York</name>'s South Street Seaport, and <name type="place">Balti-<lb/>
more</name>'s Harborplace into "festival markets" for recre-<lb/>
ational shoppers and tourists. Old town centers from Santa Fe, <name type="place">New Mexico</name>, to Prague and <name type="place">Budapest</name> in Eastern Europe have been similarly reborn as com-<lb/>
modified representations of their former states. Cul-<lb/>
tural institutions, in turn, are becoming more mall-like in the manner in which they present art and science as well as in the way they create museum shops for the display and sale of commercial products associated with their collections and exhibits. To understand the underlying relationships among theme parks, shopping centers, cultural institutions, and historic districts and the trend toward increasing similarity in their market-driven design and management is to understand how the commodification of leisure has become a driving force in the economy and culture of Western societies and, as a conse-<lb/>
quence, the extent to which much contemporary landscape design has become a combination of enter-<lb/>
tainment-based narrative and commerce.<ref target="#CH14-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref></p>
</div>
<div type="subsection">
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">The Theme Park as a Commercial Institution and Definer of Place</hi></head>
<p>The motion picture industry proved that the visual consumption of stories was a marketable commod-<lb/>
ity. By making them experiential, too, <name type="pname">Walter Elias</name> ("Walt") Disney (<date when="1901">1901</date>&#x2013;<date when="1966">1966</date>) pioneered the art of theming, which now pervades much of the built envi-<lb/>
ronment and the approach of many professional designers.</p>
<p>The relationship between the theater and the garden has always been strong. The garden as a place of fantasy and spectacle is an old notion. Le Nôtre planned seventeenth-century French gardens as sequences of theatrical spaces, with Moli&#x00E8;re staging actual plays at Vaux-le-Vicomte and Versailles. Eigh-<lb/>
teenth-century British aristocrats designed the grounds of their country estates as places of associa-<lb/>
tion where scenery and monuments stimulated reflection and reverie in which narrative played a role. But Disney invented the concept of the garden-as-enter-<lb/>
tainment, a stage set in which the visitor could par-<lb/>
ticipate in the action of an already scripted plot.</p>
<p>Disneyland and its successors epitomize the val-<lb/>
ues of twentieth-century media-driven consumer cul-<lb/>
ture and the growing influence of large corporations in American life. They also stand within the tradition of visionary idealism that includes the attempts by nineteenth-century park builders and twentieth-cen-<lb/>
tury planners of new towns to improve the industrial city or provide an alternative model to overcome its
<pb n="465"/>
<pb n="465" type="orig"/>
perceived ills. Disney wished to offer a highly positive and didactic experience that would influence human behavior and engender human happiness. His inno-<lb/>
vative genius lay in realizing that a fantasy-infused simulated landscape could carry this mission and be successfully mass-marketed in alliance with the emerging medium of television.</p>
<p>Disney understood well the value of market analysis, so in <date when="1953">1953</date>, he hired the Stanford Research Institute to study siting options for a family enter-<lb/>
tainment park that, like the animated films that he produced, would be "a world of people past and pres-<lb/>
ent seen through the eyes of my imagination, a place of warmth and nostalgia, of illusion and color and delight."<ref target="#CH14-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref>With the Santa Ana Expressway being planned to connect Los Angles and Burbank with Orange County, his site-selection research team sug-<lb/>
gested Anaheim, <name type="place">California</name>. There Disney purchased 160 acres of orange groves. Although he knew pro-<lb/>
fessional architects in <name type="place">Los Angeles</name>, he was soon con-<lb/>
vinced that the vision he had&#x2014;an amalgamation of storybook settings, the locales in the animated movies he produced, and his boyhood hometown of Marce-<lb/>
line, Missouri&#x2014;could only be carried out by people with experience in set design and cinematic scripting techniques. This meant the employees in the Burbank studios of the Walt Disney Company: <name type="pname">Herbert Dick-<lb/>
ens Ryman</name> (<date when="1910">1910</date>&#x2013;<date when="1988">1988</date>), the Disney artist and ani-<lb/>
mator who drew the perspective sketches that became the basis upon which the project received the $17 million needed to finance it.</p>
<p>Although Disneyland would have exhilarating rides, it rigorously eschewed association with Coney Island and other beachside amusement parks. The world's fairs of the previous hundred years were instead its close cousins, the expositions where peo-<lb/>
ple gathered in large numbers in an atmosphere of pristine cleanliness to view exhibitions that introduced them to new industrial technologies, new products to improve the conditions of contemporary life, and the folkways and crafts of other cultures. Disney's visionary agenda stressed the rosy themes of applied science without negative environmental conse-<lb/>
quences, history without shame, and human diver-<lb/>
sity without conflict.</p>
<p>Disney wanted to distract his park's visitors from the problems of the everyday world by giving them a good time and by carrying them backward to his own golden-age vision of the American small town of around <date when="1900">1900</date>, when he was a boy. He also wanted to carry them forward imaginatively to the techno-<lb/>
logically improved future. His park would therefore be both a period piece and an optimistic scenario of the progressive perfection enabled by modern engi-<lb/>
neering. Disney <hi rend="italic">imagineers</hi>&#x2014;the title he coined for the members of his creative design team&#x2014;would recap-<lb/>
ture for the public in Disneyland his delight in model trains and scale models of stage sets nostalgically evoking the vigor and wholesomeness of America's fron-<lb/>
tier-, rural-, and early-industrial-era past. Today, part of a global corporation, Walt Disney Imagineering, the division that develops the architectural programs and plans the company's theme parks, has a studio team of 1,200 planners, designers, architects, land-<lb/>
scape architects, engineers, computer scientists, and construction managers.</p>
<p>Disney, like the developers of shopping malls, understood the value of a manageable, human-scale, auto-free environment that was friendly to pedestri-<lb/>
ans. His careful segregation of cars and people and the use of tramways and other technologically advanced modes of mass transportation distinguished his approach to planning. The Santa Ana Freeway would carry visitors to Disneyland but not into the area beyond the berm, the tree-planted, miniature-railway-<lb/>
encircled cordon sanitaire that sequestered the park from the parking lot. This berm defining the park's outer periphery also served as a metaphor that was often evoked to distinguish between the "real" world inside&#x2014;Disney insisted, "Imagination is the model from which reality is created"<ref target="#CH14-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref>&#x2014;and the chaotic, frus-<lb/>
trating world outside where social and personal prob-<lb/>
lems could not be banished by imagineering.</p>
<p>Superficially, the plan that originated in Disney's imagination and on Ryman's drawing board was not very different from that of the <name type="place">New York</name> World's Fair of <date when="1939">1939</date> (fig. 14.8; see figs. 12.35, 12.36). Using a con-<lb/>
ventional landscape formula combining Beaux-Arts and Picturesque planning principles, Ryman created a strong main axis, a promenade leading to a central hub beyond which rose a focal structure, or "wee-<lb/>
nie"&#x2014;slang for "wiener" or hot dog&#x2014;the spicy if inelegant term coined by Disney to denote the park's visual magnet. From the hub radiated various zones that became progressively more naturalistic in style. Near the berm, some contained irregularly config-<lb/>
ured lakes. Animators by training, with some back-<lb/>
ground in art and architecture, the imagineers working under Ryman conceived the park as they would a movie, as a series of <hi rend="italic">cinematic</hi> shots. Led by Disney, they were obsessive about exact replication of detail but cavalier with scale, knowing that optical effects were all-important. As set designers they were familiar with forced perspective&#x2014;the illusion of height gained by a progressive foreshortening of the vertical dimensions of a facade as it rises from ground level, so that the scale of the second floor is five-<lb/>
eighths that of the first, and so on&#x2014;a technique they exploited ingeniously at Disneyland.</p>
<p>Perhaps because they were producing the movie
<pb n="466"/>
<pb n="466" type="orig"/>
<hi rend="italic">Sleeping Beauty</hi> at the time but also because it seemed to strike just the right note of magic, Disney and his designers chose for their "weenie" Sleeping Beauty's Castle. Forced perspective gives it the illusion of ris-<lb/>
ing in the air, a soaring symbol of the fairy-tale qual-<lb/>
ity they wanted to pervade the park. Forced perspective was also an important design tool in the creation of Main Street, an evocation of Disney's hometown of Marceline, Missouri,<ref target="#CH14-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref>with Victorian period architectural detailing derived from Fort Collins, Colorado, because Harper Goff, one of Dis-<lb/>
ney's original imagineers had grown up there. This same effect was later repeated at Walt Disney World, near Orlando, <name type="place">Florida</name> (fig. 14.9). The Western flavor of Main Street is intentional; big city urbanism and the tawdry seediness of Coney Island&#x2014;Disney had a strong antipathy for both&#x2014;were associated with the East. "Scene One," as the designers called Main Street, is a m&#x00E9;lange of comforting impressions, which are reinforced by Disney's selectively recruited, highly trained employees, referred to as Cast Members. These personnel are encouraged to perfect a cheer-<lb/>
ful civility modeled on the perceived friendliness of Western small-town folk in bygone days.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-575">
<graphic url="CH14_009.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.8. Disneyland, <name type="place">Anaheim</name>, <name type="place">California</name>, the original theme park designed and developed by Walt Disney, in collabora-<lb/>
tion with <name type="pname">Herb Ryman</name>, <name type="pname">John Hench</name>, and the staff of Walt Disney Imagineering. <date when="1954">1954</date></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>Encouraged by Morgan "Bill" Evans, a nurs-<lb/>
eryman's son and landscape architect whom he hired to work for the company, Disney realized the capa-<lb/>
bility of the <name type="place">California</name> climate to support a widely diverse horticulture&#x2014;tropical, subtropical, and tem-<lb/>
perate-climate plants. He also saw how this broad array of plant material might creatively serve as the-<lb/>
matic background and how a specimen tree might even assume a starring role in one of his three-dimen-<lb/>
sional stories where guests and Cast Members min-<lb/>
gle in a setting of enhanced nature. Working in collaboration with studio artists, the staff of landscape architects at the Imagineering headquarters in Glen-<lb/>
dale, <name type="place">California</name>, pay close attention to color (fig. 14.10). In Fantasyland a palette of clear pinks, mauves, and lavender is echoed in the choice of floral and leaf tone. In Adventureland legumes and other plants keyed to a less dreamy, more action-oriented emo-<lb/>
tional pitch add splashes of vibrant red, flaming orange, and bright yellow to the scene. Disney horti-<lb/>
culturists provide plantings with the same high level of maintenance as would a botanical garden because the sight of healthy vegetation serves the company's upbeat happy-ending storytelling mission. This meticulousness is part of a general operational strat-<lb/>
egy. Instantaneous repair and cleanliness were from the beginning hallmarks of the Disney management style, and the upkeep of its simulated historic places
<pb n="467"/>
<pb n="467" type="orig"/>
goes far beyond anything the real ones ever enjoyed.</p>
<p>Adept at editing film sequences so that nothing is disjointed and everything flows seamlessly, Disney's imagineers carefully orchestrated the transitions between the park's zones or "lands"&#x2014;Frontierland, Adventureland, Fantasyland, and Tomorrowland. Everything, even the numerous litter receptacles, is styled in each "land's" particular flavor of place and period. Modernistic streamlining prevails in Tomor-<lb/>
rowland; Cambodian, Polynesian, and African motifs in Adventureland; nineteenth-century Western ver-<lb/>
nacular in Frontierland; and the reigning idioms of fairy tales&#x2014;Bavarian Picturesque and Old English&#x2014; in Fantasyland. Yet so skillfully did the designers medi-<lb/>
ate among these styles that some interfacing buildings, such as the Plaza Pavilion restaurant, dis-<lb/>
play on their opposing facades entirely different archi-<lb/>
tectural detailing. Throughout the park, costumed personnel interact with <hi rend="italic">guests</hi>&#x2014;the term the Disney organization prefers to <hi rend="italic">visitor</hi> or <hi rend="italic">customer</hi>&#x2014;enter-<lb/>
taining those in line and further blurring the distinc-<lb/>
tion between reality and fantasy. Disney's planners so perfected the art of crowd management that waiting in line became a form of entertainment in the guest-<lb/>
holding areas, where vendors also congregate and where souvenir shops abound. Disneyland's atmos-<lb/>
phere of corporate friendliness also makes visitors more susceptible to the messages of industrial spon-<lb/>
sors, and several of its original exhibits were financed by major companies. The Disney Company's own image as a kindly corporate wizard is in turn imparted to the corporations allied with it.</p>
<p>Unlike the eighteenth-century English garden with its merely suggestive agenda of poetical associ-<lb/>
ation in the landscape, Disneyland and its successors are tightly scripted. To achieve this objective, the orig-<lb/>
inal orange groves and all other preexisting features of the Disney property were removed when con-<lb/>
struction began in <date when="1954">1954</date>. Instead of eliciting "the genius of <hi rend="italic">the place"</hi> as did the creators of <name type="place">England</name>'s great estate parks, Disney imagineers ingeniously replicate <hi rend="italic">other places.</hi> In order to add some valuable foreign currency to their bank of intellectual capital the company sends them to faraway locales where they absorb impressions and take notes and photo-<lb/>
graphs. But Disney horticulturists do not, for obvious climatic reasons, adhere completely to the vegetative palette of those other environments but instead blend species native to many different countries to gain their desired effects.</p>
<p>Disneyland represents a new kind of American landscape. Built on the premise that an expanding population of automobile-owning families would pay to experience a richly storied environment at once nostalgic and future-oriented, where reality and imag-<lb/>
ination, fact and fiction, nature and technology were seamlessly blended and enhanced through entertain-<lb/>
ment, it launched the concept of the park as a com-<lb/>
mercial venture, something quite different from the park as a public trust, free to all. In this it was, as we have already remarked, akin to world's fairs, which were also built with corporate participation as the-<lb/>
matic, commercial ventures that aimed to entertain and uplift a mass audience.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-576">
<graphic url="CH14_010.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.9. Main Street, Magic King-<lb/>
dom, Walt Disney World, Orlando, <name type="place">Florida</name>, designed by Walt Disney Imagineering as a replication of Main Street at Disneyland, Anaheim, <name type="place">California</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>If the theme park is seen as a hybrid landscape derived from the world's fair, a nineteenth-century creation, and cinema and television, which have exerted a profound influence on all facets of culture since the second half of the twentieth century, it can also be viewed as influential in its own right. The treat-<lb/>
ment of history as narrative capable of stage-set expli-<lb/>
cation is a theme-park strategy that has been carried over into the preservation of historic towns and old urban centers. In <date when="1856">1856</date>, with prescient horror John Ruskin wrote in <hi rend="italic">Modern Painters, Volume IV</hi> of the transformation he foresaw at Lucerne, Switzerland:
<pb n="468"/>
<pb n="468" type="orig"/>
"Lucerne consisting of a row of symmetrical hotels around the foot of the lake, its old bridges destroyed, an iron one built over the Reuss, and an acacia prom-<lb/>
enade carried along the lake-shore, with a German band playing under a Chinese temple at the end of it, and the enlightened travelers, representatives of Euro-<lb/>
pean civilization, performing before the Alps, in each afternoon summer sunlight, in their modern manner, the Dance of Death."<ref target="#CH14-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref>One shudders to imagine what Ruskin might write about Lucerne today along with many other quaint old European towns whose natural picturesqueness has been self-consciously deployed in the interest of mass tourism, a strategy attended by advertising and marketing techniques he certainly never dreamed of.</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-577">
<graphic url="CH14_011.jpg"/>
<figDesc><hi rend="bold">14.10. Flower beds, EPCOT, Walt Disney World, <name type="place">Orlando</name>, <name type="place">Florida</name></hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<p>In <date when="1921">1921</date>, in "The Second Coming," the Irish poet William Butler Yeats lamented, "Things fall apart; the centre cannot hold; / Mere anarchy is loosed upon the world."<ref target="#CH14-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref>In a terrible century when old certain-<lb/>
ties about the existence of a God-ordained world order were challenged and Romantic intimations of Nature's inherent divinity waned, it is perhaps under-<lb/>
standable that the seat of moral philosophy as cultu-<lb/>
ral matrix would be superseded by mere storytelling, a theatrics of past and place in the interest of identity and present pleasure. Without denying that mass tourism and the theming of historic places has certain social and educational benefits, we should also rec-<lb/>
ognize that narrative place-making is part of a pro-<lb/>
foundly unsettling cultural pattern in which concepts of highly localized, particularized place are being replaced by a sense of universalized, instantaneously accessible, placeless "placeness." Thus, place is treated patronizingly as something easily replicable and fun-<lb/>
gible, and the unique qualities of particular places are curiously devalued even as they are being celebrated. This cultural bias away from place-making based upon ideological representation is symptomatic of the pres-<lb/>
ent Western world-view in which historical phenom-<lb/>
ena, especially those related to ethnicity and ethnic heritage, are signifiers of a multicultural perspective that has become a cultural value in its own right.</p>
<p>In pointing out the trend toward landscape "theming," we must not overlook the fact that preser-<lb/>
vationism also embraces a genuine reverence for important relics of the past that lies deeper than the exploitation of history as thematic entertainment, commercial asset, or political statement. Allied with the desire to preserve authentic landmarks is the awareness that the conservation of natural areas is vital both to planetary health and human happiness. In the face of the ease of mimesis in the new Infor-<lb/>
mation Age and the specter of increased wholesale destruction of "first nature" in the continuing Machine Age, we must now attempt to understand what landscape designers and artists have done in recent years as preservationists, conservationists, and creators of metaphorically meaningful Earthworks.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="section">
<pb n="469"/>
<pb n="469" type="orig"/>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Fourteen</hi></head>
<note xml:id="CH14-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p> It will be recalled (see Chap. 4, note 10) that a given landscape can belong to one or more of three realms: first nature (wilderness), second nature (cultivated fields), and third nature (the garden as nature perfected and the representation through art of certain cul-<lb/>
tural ideas and ideals). We might provision-<lb/>
ally term "fourth nature" a concept that recognizes the machine not as an alien intruder in the garden ("third nature") but rather as a commonplace adjunct to all nature, an often integral and expressive part of its fabric and, with the advent of Internet technology, the means of creating a new spatial realm independent of the material, physical world. Whether one takes a critical or neutral position about this, technology's penetration of the humanized landscape, which now encompasses even remote parts of the earth, is deep and irreversible.</p>
<p>Machinery in the form of automata and other kinds of operational infrastruc-<lb/>
ture has long been at home in the garden, agriculture in the industrialized countries is almost wholly dependent upon mecha-<lb/>
nization, and even wilderness is impinged upon at every turn by technology. But the notion posited here of a "fourth nature" encompasses a partnership that recog-<lb/>
nizes more fully the position that the machine and technology have come to occupy within the human psyche, and their role in animating landscape design.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p> A body of sociological and historical lit-<lb/>
erature has grown up documenting the three Levittowns in <name type="place">New York</name>, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, and Pennsylvania. The instant popularity of the $7,000, 750-square-foot, four-room Cape Cod houses&#x2014;predecessor to the "Rancher" and "Country Clubber" lines&#x2014; the manner in which Abraham Levitt and his sons William and Alfred introduced fac-<lb/>
tory management techniques and techno-<lb/>
logical innovations to the construction industry, and the ways in which homeown-<lb/>
ers modified their homes to meet their changing personal circumstances have been treated by Barbara Kelly in <hi rend="italic">Expand-<lb/>
ing the American Dream: Building and Rebuilding Levittown</hi> (<date when="1993">1993</date>). The sociologist and city planner Herbert Gans lived in Levit-<lb/>
town, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, for two years at its inception in <date when="1958">1958</date>, and he chronicled the life and politics of that community in <hi rend="italic">The Levit-<lb/>
towners; Ways of Life and Politics in a New Suburban Community</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Pantheon Books, <date when="1969">1969</date>). Ken-<lb/>
neth Jackson's <hi rend="italic">Crabgrass Frontier: the Suburbanization of the United States</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Oxford</name> University Press, <date when="1985">1985</date>) has a section on Levittown as does <hi rend="italic">Yard, Street, Park: The Design of Suburban Open Space</hi> by <name type="pname">Cynthia L. Girling</name> and <name type="pname">Kenneth I. Helphand</name>. Lakewood, an early and less famous working-class suburb built on a grid plan, rather than the FHA-recom-<lb/>
mended curvilinear layout, has been ren-<lb/>
dered as an historical phenomenon and place resonant with human memory by <name type="pname">Donald J. Waldie</name>, a lifelong resident and the author of <hi rend="italic">Holy Land</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, <date when="1996">1996</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p> <hi rend="italic">Holy Land,</hi> pp. 36&#x2013;37.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 40.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 59.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p> Gwendolyn Wright, <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">New York</name> Times,</hi> Sun-<lb/>
day, <date when="1999-02-07">February 7, 1999</date>, Section 2, p. 37.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Cynthia L. Girling</name> and <name type="pname">Kenneth I. Help-<lb/>
hand</name>, <hi rend="italic">Yard, Street, Park,</hi> p. 30.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p> Herbert Gans, <hi rend="italic">The Levittowners (<date when="1967">1967</date>),</hi> p. 207.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p> See Richard Longstreth, "The Diffusion of the Community Shopping Center Concept during the Interwar Decades," <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians,</hi> Sep-<lb/>
tember <date when="1997">1997</date>, pp. 268&#x2013;93.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 278.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 289.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p> For a good discussion of the evolution of the pedestrian mall and other American "retail realms," see Peter G. Rowe, <hi rend="italic">Making a Middle Landscape</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: MIT Press, <date when="1991">1991</date>), chap. 4, pp. 109&#x2013;47.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p> See Walter Benjamin, <hi rend="italic">The Arcades Pro-<lb/>
ject (Das Passagen-Werk,</hi> ed. Rolf Tiede-<lb/>
mann, <date when="1982">1982</date>), trans. <name type="pname">Howard Eiland</name> and <name type="pname">Kevin McLaughlin</name> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, Mass.: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, <date when="1999">1999</date>) for a discussion of the nineteenth-<lb/>
century French arcades, progenitors of the department store, which the author uses as a metaphorical device in developing his observations on modernity.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p> For the mall as an all-pervasive con-<lb/>
temporary cultural phenomenon, see Mar-<lb/>
garet Crawford, "The World in a Shopping Mall," <hi rend="italic">Variations on a Theme Park,</hi> ed. <name type="pname">Michael Sorkin</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: The Noonday Press, <date when="1992">1992</date>).</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p> As quoted in Beth Dunlop, <hi rend="italic">Building the Dream: The Art of Disney Architecture</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Harry N. Abrams</name>, Inc., <date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 25.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 14.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p> According to a <hi rend="italic"><name type="place">New York</name> Times</hi> article of <date when="1998-10-15">October 15, 1998</date>, "locals [in Marceline] still point out the garbage dump&#x2014;a former slag pit outside Disney's bedroom window that he commemorated as Magic Moun-<lb/>
tain," one of Disneyland's themed roller-<lb/>
coaster rides.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p> Quoted within the caption text for "Lucerne from the Lake" (<date when="1845">1845</date>), by Joseph Mallord William Turner (<date when="1775">1775</date>&#x2013;<date when="1851">1851</date>), in the exhibition "Ruskin's <name type="place">Italy</name>, Ruskin's <name type="place">England</name>" at the Pierpont Morgan Library, <date when="2000-09-28">September 28, 2000</date>-<date when="2001-01-07">January 7, 2001</date>. Ruskin had com-<lb/>
missioned this watercolor but sold it in <date when="1865">1865</date>, probably in part because he wanted to be no longer reminded of the Swiss Alpine vil-<lb/>
lage's alteration since he had first encoun-<lb/>
tered it as a young man.</p></note>
<note xml:id="CH14-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">William Butler Yeats</name>, "The Second Com-<lb/>
ing," <hi rend="italic">Michael Roberts and the Dancer</hi> in <hi rend="italic">The Collected Works of W. B. Yeats: Volume I, The Poems,</hi> rev. ed. (<name type="place">New York</name>: Macmil-<lb/>
lan Publishing Company, <date when="1983">1983</date>), p. 187.</p></note>
</div>
</div>
