<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/html/tei.xsl"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY</title>
                <author>ELIZABETH BARLOW ROGERS</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>HARRY N. ABRAMS, INC.,</publisher>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY by ELIZABETH BARLOW
                    ROGERS</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div type="chapter"><pb n="281"/><pb n="281" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER EIGHT NATURE AS MUSE: THE GARDENS OF <name type="place">CHINA</name> AND <name type="place">JAPAN</name></hi></head><figure xml:id="fig-328"><graphic url="CH8_001.jpg"/></figure><p><hi rend="bold">T</hi>he notion of landscape as a text with encoded meaning, a place of memory and association, an experiential space in which to stroll and enjoy the unfolding of sequential views or to sit quietly and ponder the thoughts prompted by the impressions of scenery upon the senses&#x2014;these fundamentals were common to both East Asian gardens and the gardens developed in <name type="place">England</name> in the eighteenth century. The reciprocal association between landscape design and painting that was first developed in <name type="place">China</name> and then later adopted in <name type="place">Japan</name> is similar to the eighteenth-century English sensibility that found in <name type="pname">Claude Lorrain</name>'s seventeenth-century paintings an appropriate idiom for the layout of the parks of great estates. Similarly, an affinity for landscape themes, prevalent in eighteenth- and nineteenth-century English literature, is especially common in the poetry of <name type="place">China</name> and <name type="place">Japan</name>. The Romantic appreciation for the sublime in nature, which caused <name type="pname">William Wordsworth</name> to attune his soul to "the sounding cataract &#x2026; the tall rock, the mountain, and the deep and gloomy wood," was akin to the reverence for nature of Chinese scholars and mystics many centuries before.</p><p>But in spite of this apparent similarity between East and West, at a certain point in time with regard to each culture's philosophical attitude toward landscape, the underlying differences between the historic gardens of Asia and those formed in <name type="place">Europe</name> and <name type="place">America</name> are fundamental and profound. Western environmentalists attempting to reforge the broken human contract with nature, who try to reason the causes for its rupture in the first place, must reckon with the Judeo-Christian tradition of a jealous God who tolerates no rivals and is situated in a remote Heaven, the true paradise as compared to the "false" paradise of this world. The ancient Greeks, who had dreamed their gods out of the ground and placed them in the sky upon Olympus, did not so thoroughly depopulate the earth of its divinities as did the monotheistic cultures of Judaism and Christianity. They journeyed to sacred places in nature, seeking oracular wisdom at Delphi and spiritual initiation at Eleusis. But it is to nature-oriented religions like Daoism and <name type="pname">Shinto</name> that one must look to find a more direct bond between people and Earth. In <name type="place">China</name> and <name type="place">Japan</name>, although nature was as thoroughly harnessed to serve human economic ends as in the West, the scholarly and ruling elites espoused and expressed through landscape design Buddhist precepts informed by <name type="pname">Daoist</name> and <name type="pname">Shinto</name> ideals emphasizing life lived in spiritual harmony with nature.<ref target="#CH8-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref> <name type="pname">Chinese Daoist</name> thought fostered perceptions of <hi rend="italic">qi</hi>, the "breath," or inherent energy, possessed by all phenomena. In <name type="place">Japan</name>, <name type="pname">Shinto</name> religion led participants to reverence <hi rend="italic">kami</hi>, the spirits found in nature.<ref target="#CH8-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref> Garden design in both countries reflected and nourished these ideals.</p><p>Rocks&#x2014;the mineral substance of nature&#x2014;had as strong an aesthetic and associative value in East Asian gardens as representational sculpture in carved stone and cast bronze did in Western ones. In <name type="place">China</name>, garden designers employed carefully selected, water-worn rocks with clefts and fissures. These spatially intricate rocks were usually intended to evoke the mist-shrouded mountain ranges of the larger landscape, for the Chinese attributed to their country's peaks the same in-dwelling mystery and connection with the divine as did other early civilizations. Such scenery might be termed <hi rend="italic">sublime</hi> according to the aesthetics of the West.</p><p>In <name type="place">Japan</name>, where mountains are less dramatically formed, designers sometimes employed rocks in compositions that intentionally evoked scenes from Chinese painting, but more often rocks were placed in water or gravel "streams" as metaphorical islands. Japanese garden designers also displayed particular ingenuity in their selection of beautifully shaped flat stepping stones, positioning them so as to form, in conjunction with moss, ground-plane patterns of highly pleasing pattern and texture. Like the rocks in Chinese gardens and their somewhat smaller counterparts displayed in the studies of Chinese scholars, Japanese garden rocks were often associated with mythical or real animals of symbolical import. In both cultures, the viewer was encouraged to enjoy the abstract beauty of these mineral forms while also imagining their resemblance to other things.</p><div type="section"><pb n="282"/><pb n="282" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">I. Mountains, Lakes, and Islands: Intimations of Immortality in the Chinese Garden</hi></hi></head><p>As in other parts of the ancient world, the practice of landscape design in <name type="place">China</name> originated within a cultural matrix of mythology and imperial authority. In 219 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, the first emperor of the Qin dynasty, Qin Shihuangdi (ruled 221&#x2013;206 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>), sent an expedition of young men and women to the eastern edge of the known world, where the immortals, known as <hi rend="italic">xian</hi>, were believed to dwell on enchanted islands upheld by giant tortoises.<ref target="#CH8-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref> The emperor charged their leader with the impossible task of discovering the sacred substance that prolonged the lives of the <hi rend="italic">xian</hi>. Although the expedition failed in its purpose, the notion of a paradisiacal quartet of islands&#x2014;<name type="pname">Penglai</name>, <name type="pname">Yingzhou</name>, <name type="pname">Fangzhang</name>, and <name type="pname">Huliang</name>&#x2014;remained embedded in Chinese mythology. The association of mountains and rocks that mimic mountains with immortality furnished the paradisiacal theme that runs throughout Chinese garden history, and the faraway <hi rend="italic">xian</hi>-inhabited islands were sometimes explicitly evoked in garden design as well as in poetry, painting, and the decorative arts.<ref target="#CH8-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref></p><figure xml:id="fig-329"><graphic url="CH8_002.jpg"/><figDesc>8.1. "Early Spring," a hanging scroll painting on silk, by <name type="pname">Guo Xi</name>. 1072, Northern Song Dynasty. Taipei, National Palace Museum</figDesc></figure><p>The Han emperor <name type="pname">Wudi</name> (<name type="pname">Liu Che</name>, ruled 140&#x2013;87 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>) built a lake garden in which rock constructions simulating the four island peaks of the immortals rose from the water, and later emperors, notably <name type="pname">Song Huizong</name> and <name type="pname">Khubilai Khan</name>, built imitations of these <hi rend="italic">xian</hi>-inhabited islands in their gardens. But even without the allusion to immortality, the premise that nature's own forms serve as a primary source of inspiration is a central principle of Chinese garden aesthetics. The combination of mountains (<hi rend="italic">shan</hi>) and water (<hi rend="italic">shui</hi>) (together meaning "landscape") furnished generations of garden builders with imagery for their compositions. These attempted to assemble in three dimensions the scenes found in Chinese landscape painting.</p><p>Although the Chinese practiced agriculture and horticulture in sophisticated ways within the larger agrarian landscape, designed gardens (as opposed to vernacular gardens) were the exclusive preserves of an aristocratic elite. Like almost all designed gardens until relatively recent times, they were created by rulers and nobles. Many members of the Chinese nobility were mandarins, high officials within the nine ranks of the imperial bureaucracy. A rigorous examination system admitted young men into this government service, and although the sons of the nobility had certain obvious advantages of birth and education, diligent commoners whose families could finance the rote education in Confucian classics necessary to pass the examination could attain mandarin status. Scholarship was therefore highly prized among those Chinese families who sought or wished to maintain social standing through connection with the court. Furthermore, scholarship was closely allied with connoisseurship and practice of the arts.</p><p>The Chinese scholar was adept at calligraphy, painting, or poetry, and often all three. These were the expected accomplishments of the usually well-born and always well-educated class that governed <name type="place">China</name>. Thus, power&#x2014;which always implied both imperial favor and personal merit based on scholarship&#x2014;and aesthetics went hand in hand. Even when favor was withdrawn because of political circumstances, the Chinese gentleman scholar was not without financial or intellectual resources, and with the increased leisure brought about by retirement from government service he would often turn to the enterprise of garden<pb n="283"/><pb n="283" type="orig"/>building. Understandably therefore, garden-making in <name type="place">China</name> was closely allied with the other arts practiced by the Chinese scholar. The mountainous landscapes of painting, the riverine scenery described in poems, and inscriptions whereby calligraphy glossed the meaning of both natural and constructed landscapes&#x2014;these three already intimately interconnected arts furnished both the imaginative resources and instruments of Chinese garden design (fig. 8.1). However, before the intricate artifice of the mature Chinese garden, with its compression of seas into island-studded lakes and mountains into hillocks of fantastically shaped rocks was achieved in the Southern Song (<date when="1127">1127</date>&#x2013;<date when="1279">1279</date>) and later periods, there was already a venerable history of garden-making. Not surprisingly, as in Persia, where the first known garden "paradise" was a royal hunting park, the Chinese garden had similar origins, as an imperial game reservation.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Qin and Han Landscapes</hi></hi></head><p>With the subjugation of all rival states in 221 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, emperor <name type="pname">Qin Shihuangdi</name> established his capital city of Chang'an (modern <name type="pname">Xi</name>'an) on the banks of the Wei River. Here he built his lofty and magnificent palace and a vast hunting preserve known as Shanglin Park.<ref target="#CH8-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref> Shanglin Park was encircled with stout walls, just as the empire itself was protected with stupendous fortifications. More than an imperial pleasure ground, this huge park, with its collected botanical and zoological riches, was perceived as a symbol of the empire's worldly supremacy and cosmic grandeur. Even when the empire of <name type="pname">Qin Shihuangdi</name> was overthrown, <name type="pname">Shanglin Park</name> was not destroyed, and the court poets of his Han successors extolled its size and magnificence as well as the abundance of its wildlife, no doubt seeing in its preservation a statement of their own masters' far-flung imperial power.</p><p>The relationship between gardens and the natural scenery of mountains and water was given further impetus when in 311 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> barbarian invaders breached the Great Wall, and the convulsions of political power that followed gave <name type="place">China</name> a second imperial center south of the <name type="pname">Chang Jiang</name> (Yangzi River) near present-day Nanjing. Here were found precipitous, mist-enshrouded mountains, smooth lakes, and meandering rivers. With the North under foreign control, the governing elite composed of highly educated imperial civil servants built country estates in the lush countryside outside their reestablished capital. This relocation in the scenic South fostered receptivity to Daoism, the nature-mysticism espoused by the legendary Laozi (b. 604 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>). As the old Confucian order continued to disintegrate, nature appreciation offered sensitive imperial bureaucrats an escape from the harsh political realities of the times.</p><p>With the growth of Buddhism, which had been introduced via the Silk Route sometime between 50 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> and 150 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, the Chinese gained a religion in which quiet meditation was a means toward spiritual awareness. Contemplative religious practice reinforced a Chinese proclivity for wilderness retreat, and many scholar poets and landscape artists joined Buddhist monks in seeking spiritual fulfillment in nature. In the extraordinarily beautiful <name type="pname">Lushan Range</name> appeared the soaring rooftops of the famous monastery founded by the Buddhist monk <name type="pname">Huiyuan</name> (c. 334&#x2013;416 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>), and here and there other Buddhist temples accented the lofty scenery. This scenery, which became virtually paradigmatic in Chinese landscape painting, expresses the ideal of complete human integration with nature. It is an ideal nourished not only by Buddhist thought but also by Daoism and the <name type="pname">Daoist</name> concept of transcendental <hi rend="italic">qi</hi>, the "breath" that animates all things, giving them their own inherent nature. Through syncretism Daoism became fused to some extent with the teachings of Buddhism and Confucianism, and the <name type="pname">Daoist</name> notion of a spiritual energy composed of the complementary yin and yang forces that pervade the universe became commonplace in Chinese thought. The grandeur of towering peaks and the misty vastness of successive ranges, with tiny figures defining the scale of human activity within their majestic presence, evoke the <name type="pname">Daoist</name> belief in the eternal unity of all things in nature. It is this illusion of total immersion in the infinitude of nature that distinguishes Chinese art from the more obviously homocentric, individualistic, and spatially explicit art of the West.</p><p>Paintings and poetic descriptions of the naturally scenic Lushan landscape furnished the ideal that underlies much subsequent Chinese garden design. <name type="pname">Huiyuan</name>'s followers, among whom were several painters and poets, carried the inspiration of mountain scenery of mossy paths, pine groves, steep cliffs, and precipitous waterfalls into the creation of their own Lushan "parks," private rustic retreats. These were not so much designed gardens as carefully selected spots in nature that could be enhanced with such things as a bamboo grove, a thatched hut, a flowering plum or peach tree. The poets <name type="pname">Xie Lingyun</name> (385&#x2013;433 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) and <name type="pname">Tao Qian</name> (365&#x2013;427 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) found beauty in the marriage of the sublime with the humble, "borrowing" the nearby Lushan mountain scenery while taking pleasure in fields, orchards, willow trees, and the sounds of barnyard animals. The rustication of gentleman scholars and their assumption of a quasi-hermitic way of life, often after a period of service in the imperial bureau<pb n="284"/><pb n="284" type="orig"/>cracy, became a fairly common phenomenon by the beginning of the Tang dynasty (618&#x2013;907 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>). Their economic and social standing permitted them to retire from worldly affairs when the situation at court or personal preference made this desirable.</p><p>In the Tang era <name type="place">China</name>'s population reached 160 million. Ancient forests were felled as new lands were put into rice production. A vast system of canals connected the populous Yangzi River valley with the cities of the Yellow River plain to the north and Hangzhou to the south. In addition, a system of roads converged like the spokes of a wheel upon the Tang capital at Chang'an, a teeming cosmopolitan trading center at the end of the Silk Road in the western province of Shaanxi. It was a period of commercial and urban growth, massive irrigation systems, and other public works projects. Although a powerful aristocracy governed the country, its systematic education in preparation for government service ensured homogeneous cultural values within a unified ideological framework and created an ingrained conservative political orientation.</p><p>The imperial administrative apparatus helped sustain Chinese civilization through periods of invasion and internal upheaval for the next thousand years. Those who became civil servants received extensive privileges and perquisites. They were not, however, allowed to serve in their home provinces nor to own land in those to which they were sent. Some were assigned to the court, where eunuchs and favorite concubines contributed to an atmosphere of political intrigue. In court, a scholar-administrator could easily fall into disfavor, or he could find himself on the wrong side of changing imperial policy and thus experience disgrace. Serving in a province remote from his homeland, he would often long to return to his family, friends, and property. Beset by these complexities, the scholar-administrators who constituted <name type="place">China</name>'s literate and affluent mandarin class, found escape from doctrinaire administration and factional politics in a life of refined retirement, pursuing <name type="pname">Daoist</name> philosophy and Buddhist study. Able to indulge in wilderness travel, urban culture, and rural ease, they became <name type="place">China</name>'s great calligraphers, poets, painters, musicians, and garden makers.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Wang Wei</name></hi></hi></head><p>In the front rank among Tang officials who were accomplished practitioners of the arts was <name type="pname">Wang Wei</name> (699&#x2013;759 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>). Having passed the civil service examination when he was twenty, he was appointed Assistant Secretary for Music at the court in Chang'an because of his musical abilities. Probably for some minor offense he was transferred to an insignificant provincial post where he served for several years before returning to the capital. He bought an estate 30 miles (48.3 kilometers) outside of Chang'an on the Wang River and in his retirement from public service flourished as an artist, combining his talents as calligrapher, painter, and poet.</p><p><name type="pname">Wang Wei</name> was a devout lay Buddhist, and his poetry and, no doubt, his paintings&#x2014;which survive only as copies&#x2014;demonstrate his sensory appreciation of such things as the tender green of willow trees by a stream, the moon's silver disk mirrored in water or shedding its white light on night-stilled nature, the blush of peach blossoms in springtime, the fragrance and gnarled beauty of pine trees, the pliancy of bamboo stirring in the breeze, the oriole's chirp, the peaks of distant mountains wreathed in mist, and tiny boatmen glimpsed from afar. His "broken ink" technique and special brushstroke for expressively rendering the rocky faces of old eroded mountains enriched the painter's vocabulary and probably promoted the appreciation of weathered rocks themselves, a significant fact for the subsequent development of the Chinese garden. <name type="pname">Wang Wei</name>'s most famous painting was that of <name type="pname">Wangchuan</name> Villa, his riverside estate, a scroll containing twenty scenes depicting several pavilions along a rocky riverbank and the views from them. The scroll, which no longer exists, was copied by later painters, and garden builders evoked its subject in their creations.</p><p>While solitary meditation beside a stream or in the mountains could deepen the spirit, scenes of nature were often enjoyed in company, and for <name type="place">China</name>'s literary and artistic intelligentsia, the garden became a favored locale for cherishing friendship and remembering particular friends. Wine was both a solace for worldly disappointment and a means of attaining a sense of oneness with the spirit of nature. In their gardens, many scholar-poets eluded the pain of living and achieved a state of ecstasy under the influence of alcohol, a condition that they often celebrated in literature.</p><p>Nor was drinking merely a solitary and escapist pleasure. The association of wine drinking, friendship, and nature appreciation through poetry in fact goes back at least to 353 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi> when <name type="pname">Wang Xizhi</name> composed a famous calligraphy scroll celebrating a springtime gathering of poets at the Orchid Pavilion near present-day Shaoxing in the province of Zhejiang. Upon that and many similar occasions over the centuries cups of wine would be sent downstream by servants as each literary gentleman raced to compose verses, or cap another poet's lines, before his cup arrived at the spot where he sat upon the banks writing. By the Tang era, the literary drinking party was an established form of entertainment in Chinese gardens, and pavilions were built with meandering stream courses incised into their floor paving to accommodate this garden<pb n="285"/><pb n="285" type="orig"/>game (fig. 8.2).</p><p>Several other scholar-officials besides <name type="pname">Wang Wei</name> fused their literary and artistic talents, becoming noted calligraphers and painters as well as poets. For the Chinese gentleman-scholar-poet-artist, calligraphy and painting were often one, sharing not only the common use of a brush, but also the same fundamental commitment to the expression of <hi rend="italic">qi</hi>. One aspect of Chinese painting is to be possessed of <hi rend="italic">qi</hi> in order to constitute a graphic expression of this invisible energy source. In a similar fashion, the Chinese garden designer selected rocks whose forms and surfaces were animated by <hi rend="italic">qi</hi> so that they became presences that were alive to eye, hand, and mind that viewed, touched, and contemplated them. Evocative of the mountains depicted in Chinese landscape painting and their association with immortality, these rocks furnished the garden with its paradisiacal iconography.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Northern Song Gardens</hi></hi></head><p>Cosmic landscape paintings&#x2014;silk wall hangings depicting mist-shrouded mountains within whose temple-studded vastness small figures beneath gnarled pines communed philosophically&#x2014;reached their epitome during the Northern Song period (960&#x2013;1127 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>), when the capital was at Bianjing, present-day Kaifeng. The Song emperor Huizong (ruled <date when="1100">1100</date>&#x2013;<date when="1125">1125</date> <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>), an accomplished painter, also patronized and thereby promoted a more intimate style of painting depicting jewel-like renderings of birds, blossoming fruit trees, and individual flower forms. From the contents of these paintings and from information about constructed landscapes of the period, we know that artists found inspiration in gardens, and the subject matter of their paintings in turn suggested forms and motifs for the creators of gardens.</p><p>Song Huizong was as interested in his imperial gardens as he was in painting. Assisted by practitioners of <hi rend="italic">feng shui</hi> ("wind" and "water"), professional geomancers (diviners of favorable sites and alignments who procured for human constructions the most beneficial influences of the local landscape's spiritual forces), he established his pleasure park of Genyue in the northwestern quarter of Kaifeng. There he collected a large number of fantastical rocks&#x2014;water-sculpted stones&#x2014;and many choice botanical specimens. By creating an artificial mountain called Wanshou Shan (Mountain of Numberless Years), Song Huizong followed the recommendation of his geomancers that he build a tall landmass as a means of blocking evil forces and concentrating good ones.</p><figure xml:id="fig-330"><graphic url="CH8_003.jpg"/><figDesc>8.2. Detail of <hi rend="italic">ru yi</hi> at Pavilion of Ceremonial Purification, Forbidden City, <name type="place">Beijing</name>. Testimony to the enduring popularity of the poetry contest as a garden pastime is found in the floors of certain garden pavilions. The imperial Pavilion of Ceremonial Purification within the Palace Garden of Peaceful Longevity inside <name type="place">Beijing</name>'s Forbidden City has a floor where the stone is channeled in a meandering pattern called <hi rend="italic">ru yi</hi> ("whatsoever you desire") to create a winding stream course.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-331"><graphic url="CH8_004.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 8.3. <hi rend="italic">Travelers Among Mountains and Streams</hi>, hanging scroll by <name type="pname">Fan Kuan</name>. The tradition of placing mountain-mimicking stones of great sculptural interest in Chinese gardens dates from at least the tenth century, Taipei, National Palace Museum</figDesc></figure><p>During the Song period, individual rocks became "collectibles" in their own right. Their shapes were akin to the tall, vertical "Emperor Mountain" of paintings, and they were frequently displayed with arrangements of subsidiary rocks representing lesser peaks. Their fissured and mottled surfaces were intended to evoke wild precipices, both real ones and those depicted by the painter's brushwork (fig. 8.3). Collectors especially prized fantastically shaped stones, hollowed in places, with light and shadow playing across their irregular surfaces. Song Huizong was a passionate collector, and the canals of Kaifeng were sometimes blocked for days to ordinary commerce and<pb n="286"/><pb n="286" type="orig"/>the delivery of food as his stones were transported to Genyue Park. His enthusiasm was shared by <name type="pname">Zhu Mian</name>, the commissioner he put in charge of procuring stones as well as rare plants from the southern provinces. <name type="pname">Zhu Mian</name>'s own garden, the Garden of Green Water, had a remarkable collection of both.</p><figure xml:id="fig-332"><graphic url="CH8_005.jpg"/><figDesc>8.4. <name type="pname">Xi Hu</name> (West Lake), Hangzhou</figDesc></figure><p>Song Huizong fulfilled his overweening passion for garden building at the expense of the protection of the empire at large. His extravagance and that of <name type="pname">Zhu Mian</name> weakened the treasury and left the borders vulnerable to invasion by the <name type="pname">Jurchen Tartars</name>. In <date when="1125">1125</date>, his beautiful garden was destroyed in the sack of the city as warriors from the north cut down trees, tore out bamboos, trampled flowers, and demolished rockwork except for the formidable peak of Wanshou Shan. <name type="pname">Zhu Mian</name> was beheaded and his property confiscated, but, because of family skill and reputation, his sons continued to engage in garden building.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Southern Song Gardens</hi></hi></head><p>With the invasion that unseated Song Huizong, foreign rule was established over <name type="place">China</name>'s northern provinces. Its lords, the Jin dynasty, chose <name type="place">Beijing</name> for their capital. In <date when="1138">1138</date>, after twelve years during which the Song court and the many ethnic Chinese attached to it lived in a series of temporary capitals, they relocated to Hangzhou in the south. There a brilliant epoch of artistic and literary accomplishment ensued. The beautiful lakes and hills around Hangzhou became an inspiration to painters and provided a more picturesque setting for palaces and gardens than the plains of Kaifeng.</p><p>In the century and a half that constitutes the Southern Song period (<date when="1127">1127</date>&#x2013;<date when="1279">1279</date>), the time of the Song court's transfer to Hangzhou, technical innovations, a money economy, and the expansion in agricultural productivity brought the country to a level of prosperity well in advance of the rest of the world at that time. Commerce and trade stimulated the growth of cities. Movable type, which the Chinese had invented in the eleventh century, encouraged a book publishing industry and stimulated literacy. The arts flourished, and many wealthy landowners built gardens. The tourist visiting West Lake today can see "fairy-tale" scenery picturesquely accented by waterside pavilions, which are part of famous views with names like those of poems or paintings: "Listening to Orioles Singing in the Waving Willows," "Autumn Moon over the Calm Lake," "Lotus Flowers Swaying in Quyuan Garden" and "Three Pools Mirroring the Moon." Today's versions of these pavilions and their surrounding scenery preserve only faint echoes of the intricately constructed poetic landscapes built there in Song times (fig. 8.4).</p><p>Many private residences in Hangzhou had fine gardens, and <name type="place">Suzhou</name>, a center of the silk industry and also an important cultural center, was the site of many more. In addition to numerous small, beautifully crafted urban gardens, aristocratic garden estates were built in the hills on the outskirts of the city. <name type="place">Suzhou</name>'s fame as a garden mecca was further enhanced by its location near Lake Tai, source of the water-modeled garden stones that are as highly prized in Chinese gardens as important works of sculpture might be in Western ones. The West Dongting Hill furnished an especially fine multicolored stone full of creases and cavities, and the Lingyan Hill yielded yellowish rocks, the hard, veined surfaces of which are streaked with white, red, and purple.</p><p>The Song official who had literary and artistic gifts liked to build a garden that reminded him and his visitors of the wild scenery sought by mountain recluses. Like the monochromatic landscape paintings that inspired his design, this garden prized line,<pb n="287"/><pb n="287" type="orig"/>form, and composition over color. Its elements were symbolical "mountains" of carefully selected and artistically positioned stones and arrangements of pine, bamboo, and plum&#x2014;"the three friends of winter." The names of some of the scholar-gardens of <name type="place">Suzhou</name>&#x2014;<name type="pname">Wang Shi Yuan</name> (Garden of the Master of the Fishing Nets), <name type="pname">Liu Yuan</name> (Garden to Linger In), <name type="pname">Zhuo Zheng Yuan</name> (Garden of the Unsuccessful Politician)&#x2014;evoke the idylls of a leisure class.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name>'s Garden Manual: The <hi rend="italic">Yuan Ye</hi></hi></hi></head><p>By the end of the Song period, the conventions of Chinese garden design were well established. As Chinese merchants prospered during the Ming dynasty, they, like the emperor himself, emulated the cultural elite, the mandarin class of scholar-officials. To help these arrivistes avoid the aesthetic blunders of the uneducated, garden designers began to write treatises that codified garden style and served as manuals for landscape builders.</p><p>Foremost among these was the <hi rend="italic">Yuan ye</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">The Craft of Gardens</hi>, by <name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name>. <date when="1582">1582</date>) of Wujiang in the province of <name type="pname">Jiangsu</name>.<ref target="#CH8-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref> A noted garden builder himself, as well as a poet and painter, he completed his comprehensive three-volume classic on landscape theory and practice in <date when="1634">1634</date>.</p><p><name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name>'s book is unusual, and perhaps unique, among garden manuals in its blend of practical advice and pattern-book instruction with poetic visualization and mood painting. Although specific in discussing the appearance of various kinds of stones and offering abundant diagrams for window and railing lattices, together with numerous door shapes and paving designs, the <hi rend="italic">Yuan ye</hi> offers no static prescription for garden planning. The author firmly states that "there is no definite way of making scenery; you know it is right when it stirs your emotions," stressing that it is <hi rend="italic">qi</hi>, the pulsating breath of life that must be the result of the designer's efforts.</p><p>Good siting is a primary ingredient of <name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name>'s prescription for garden making. A garden designer must screen out what is ugly and offensive and make use of "borrowed scenery" (<hi rend="italic">jie jing</hi>), whether a distant view of misty mountains, the rooflines of a nearby monastery, or the flowers of a neighbor's garden. A small piece of ground beside a dwelling can be turned into a garden by digging a pond, collecting stones with which to build up a "mountain," and making a welcoming gate for guests. Willows, a stand of bamboos, and some luxuriant trees and flowers are all that are needed to complete the picture and set the mood for poetry-writing parties and sitting in the company of one's favorite concubine melting snow water for tea.</p><p>In <name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name>'s manual, in the chapter "The Selection of Stones," he discusses in reverent detail the highly prized Lake Tai stones with their hollows and holes. He recommends that these be given pride of place like fine sculpture in front of big halls, within large pavilions, or beneath a stately pine tree. It is clear from the <hi rend="italic">Yuan ye</hi> that stone selection was a highly developed skill limited to a small number of individuals who could successfully quarry fine specimens from the mountains or find them in river and lake beds. Sometimes to be found in museum collections of Chinese art today these prize stones, with light and shade directing the eye as it travels in and out of their folds and hollows and up the flanks of an imagined mountain precipice, do appear to possess <hi rend="italic">qi;</hi> their vibrancy is akin to that found in works of painting and calligraphy in the same galleries.</p><p><name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name> also writes about wall design. The walls in Chinese gardens provide an important means of segregating space, screening from sight the mundane workaday reality of city streets while making the garden invisible to passersby, except for glimpses gained through latticed openings composed of thin tiles or cast bricks. The walls of Chinese gardens often rise and fall according to the elevation of the ground. Curved roof tiles, sometimes following a wavy line, produce a sense of animated movement, while bas-relief friezes frequently add ornamental interest.</p><figure xml:id="fig-333"><graphic url="CH8_006.jpg"/><figDesc>8.5. Bamboo Hat Pavilion seen through window with blue glass in Thirty-six Mandarin Ducks Hall, <name type="pname">Zhuo Zheng Yuan</name> (Garden of the Unsuccessful Politician), <name type="place">Suzhou</name>. This 10-acre garden originated in the Ming Dynasty and was extensively repaired and expanded in the <date when="1950">1950</date>s.</figDesc></figure><p>Walls outline various courts and corridors within the garden, subdividing it into discrete though linked scenic units. These are often pierced by windows with tracery, for which <name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name> provided many patterns (figs. 8.5, 8.6). Carefully placed windows and circular "moon gates" and vase- or gourd-shaped doors frame views of adjacent garden spaces (fig. 8.7). The whitewashed surfaces of these walls are often brush-rubbed with ground yellow river sand mixed with a small amount of chalk to give them a lustrous waxy polish.</p><pb n="288"/><pb n="288" type="orig"/><p>The function of a Chinese garden wall is not, however, ornamental; rather, it is meant to serve, like the neutral silk or paper of a painting, as a background, capturing shadows in calligraphic patterns and acting as a foil for the rocks and plants in front of it.</p><figure xml:id="fig-334"><graphic url="CH8_007.jpg"/><figDesc>8.6. Lattice window in gallery of <name type="pname">Liu Yuan</name> (Garden to Linger In), <name type="place">Suzhou</name>. The garden originated in the Ming Dynasty from two gardens: <name type="pname">Dong Yuan</name> (East Garden) and <name type="pname">Xi Yuan</name> (West Garden). The East Garden was rebuilt with Taihu stones arranged as twelve peaks during the Qing Dynasty. After being deserted for a period, it was rebuilt during the reign of <name type="pname">Emperor Guangxu</name>, at which time it acquired its present name.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-335"><graphic url="CH8_008.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Top:</hi> 8.7. Wall with Moon Gate, <name type="pname">Yi Yuan</name> (Garden of Ease), <name type="place">Suzhou</name>, founded by a high government official near the end of the Qing Dynasty</figDesc></figure><p>In plan, a typical Southern Chinese scholar-garden, built in the manner codified by <name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name>, arranges the functional parts of the mansion and its adjacent series of courts around the edges of the site. The principal hall faces a central pond, which occupies approximately three-tenths of the site (see fig. 8.9). Like the arms of a lake in nature, the ends of the pond are made to disappear from sight, in winding coves, behind bridges, or beyond covered walkways. Buildings, rocks, water, paths, and plants are parts of a harmonious whole, the intent of which is to frame compositions of scenery and furnish various vantage points from which to enjoy a sequence of views. These views are intended to remind one of the kind of journey in nature that one experiences when looking at a Chinese landscape painting, mentally climbing up tortuous mountain paths or following the indented shoreline of a lake.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Landscapes of Literature: The Story of the Stone</hi></hi></head><p>Much of the story in the great eighteenth-century novel by <name type="pname">Cao Xueqin</name> (c. <date when="1724">1724</date>&#x2013;<date when="1764">1764</date>), <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Stone</hi>, also known as <hi rend="italic">The Dream of the Red Chamber</hi>, takes place within the Jia family's aristocratic compound, which includes a scholar-garden called the Grand View Garden.<ref target="#CH8-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref> Almost an entire chapter is devoted to a detailed description of the annexation of additional family property to expand it into a new garden wherein the family can receive visits from a daughter who has just been elevated to the position of Imperial Concubine. We are told that "the digging of pools, the raising of hills, the siting and erection of lodges and pavilions, the planting of bamboos and flowers&#x2014;in a word, all matters pertaining to the landscaping and layout of the gardens, were planned and supervised by Horticultural Hu," an eminent landscape gardener.</p><p>We are then invited on a tour of the new garden as it is nearing completion. The reader-visitor enters through "a five-frame gate-building with a hump-backed roof of half-cylinder tiles," admiring the beautifully patterned latticework of the wooden doors, simple whitewashed walls, and fine, unostentatious craftsmanship. Directly the tourist of this imaginary landscape encounters a miniature mountain formed of "large white rocks in all kinds of grotesque and monstrous shapes, rising course upon course up one of its sides, some recumbent, some upright or leaning at angles, their surfaces streaked and spotted with moss and lichen or half-concealed by creepers, and with a narrow zigzag path only barely discernible to the eye winding up between them." A tunnel through a shoulder of this rock deposits the supposed wanderer in a lush artificial ravine. Below, through the trees, a clear rushing stream broadens into a wide pool edged by a marble baluster and spanned by a beautiful triple-arched marble bridge. Brightly painted, fancifully decorated, luxuriously furnished pavilions ascend the slopes of the ravine. Another pavilion is poised over the center of the bridge.</p><p>On the far side of the pool, a path threads its way between rocks and flowers and trees before suddenly coming upon whitewashed walls enclosing a dense thicket of bamboo. In the middle of this bamboo grove stands a small scholarly retreat. At the rear, this structure opens onto "a garden of broad-leaved plantains dominated by a large flowering pear tree." A stream gushes through an opening in the back wall into a narrow channel, which runs around one side of the house and then meanders through the bamboos before disappearing through another opening in the wall.</p><p>A climb around the base of a steeply sloping hill brings into view a mud-walled compound tucked into a fold halfway up the hillside. It contains an apricot orchard and a cluster of rustic cottages with thatched roofs. An irregularly shaped hedge formed by loosely interweaving the young shoots of mulberry, elm, hibiscus, and silkworm<pb n="289"/><pb n="289" type="orig"/>thorn trees stands outside the orchard wall, and below it a rustic well overlooks miniature fields of vegetables and flowers, the equivalent of a Western kitchen garden. The reader's tour through it engenders a lively discussion on the distinction between utilitarian landscapes such as this, which have obviously been planted by the human hand, and ones that presume to imitate nature with little appearance of artifice.</p><p>To manifest the difference, beyond the rustic village, the author takes us to a spot where we can hear the musical sound of water issuing from a vine-fringed cave in the rock. The "mountainous" topography of the garden is again evident as we scramble over this grotto, up a steep path, and then back down to the banks of the winding stream fringed with willows interspersed with "peach and apricot trees whose interlacing branches made little worlds of stillness and serenity beneath them. Blossoms float on the surface of the water."</p><p>The scarlet balustrade of a wooden bridge glimpsed through the screen of pendant willow branches beckons us to cross, whereupon we discover diverging paths leading to other parts of the garden. Ahead, an elegant pavilion stands in a courtyard containing a remarkable rock, with light and shade playing over its delicate surface of fissures and hollows. This miniature mountain&#x2014;a collector's specimen&#x2014;is surrounded by smaller rocks, but the courtyard is otherwise bare except for some vines and flowering plants of exquisite fragrance. Beyond this summerhouse stands the magnificent residence hall, from which "gold-glinting cat-faces, rainbow-hued serpents' snouts peered out or snarled down from cornice and finial."</p><p>In the eighteenth century, aristocratic families preserved the landscape design traditions formulated centuries before in the Song period. The new garden described by <name type="pname">Cao Xueqin</name> is an exceptionally large one, covering one-quarter square mile (.65 square kilometers) of the Jia family estate. Typically, the scholar-garden in an urban locale compressed a great deal of scenery of a similarly associative nature into a much smaller frame, as we shall see below when we examine an actual garden, contemporary with that of the novel.</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Stone</hi>, the characters are examining the newly built garden for the purpose of naming its different parts, inasmuch as Chinese garden makers considered a garden without calligraphy denoting the names of various rock and plant groupings, water scenery, viewing pavilions, and scholarly retreats to be incomplete. Inscriptions are an important part of a Chinese garden, and the carving of names and descriptive verse onto rocks and stone plaques is a time-honored custom. In this case, provisional inscriptions were to be painted on rectangular paper lanterns, pending approval by <name type="pname">Yuanchun</name>, the young woman who had been promoted to the Imperial Bedchamber and for whom the garden was being readied in anticipation of her occasional visits to her family.</p><p>The act of naming and the fusion of literary tradition with scenic appreciation are a venerable Chinese practice that goes beyond garden inscriptions to include actual scenes in nature. In <name type="place">China</name>, where the distinction between travel literature and the literature of landscape hardly exists, the descriptions of scenes along the traveler's route, like the scenes depicted on a landscape scroll, are more important than the personal adventures of the protagonist or the final goal of his journey. Travel writing as a genre has ancient roots in <name type="place">China</name>, and poetical inscriptions recording the sensations and impressions of earlier visitors were carved into rocks (fig. 8.8). Inscriptions were not seen as defacing nature, but rather as enhancing it through literary commentary.</p><p>Many famous views have accretions of rockcarved inscriptions around them. A very early example is found in <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of Mu</hi>, probably written sometime during the fifth to fourth century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>, in which <name type="pname">Emperor Mu</name>, who reigned six hundred years earlier, is described as having recorded his journey into the Xi Mountains with a rock inscription, after having planted a tree and named the spot Mountain of the Queen Mother of the West.<ref target="#CH8-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref></p><figure xml:id="fig-336"><graphic url="CH8_009.jpg"/><figDesc>8.8. Forest Rock inscription, Stone, <name type="pname">Suzhou Yunnan</name> Province</figDesc></figure><p>Matching name and reality was, according to Confucian ideology, a fundamental means of estab<pb n="290"/><pb n="290" type="orig"/>lishing moral order. The naming of famous scenes and places was a function of the ruling class, a way of asserting cultural identity over the breadth of the empire. Inscribing nature was rooted as well in <name type="pname">Daoist</name> philosophy, as scenic appreciation was a means of achieving transcendental harmony with the universe. By the end of the Song period, when landscape connoisseurship was well established, there was an extensive canon of Chinese travel literature, and the major sites of literary pilgrimage had received inscriptions and been marked on maps.</p><figure xml:id="fig-337"><graphic url="CH8_010.jpg"/><figDesc>8.9. Plan of <name type="pname">Wang Shi Yuan</name> (Garden of the Master of the Fishing Nets), <name type="place">Suzhou</name>. Qing Dynasty <hi rend="bold">A</hi> Visitors' Entrance <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Cottage to Accompany Spring <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Pavillion of the Arriving Moon and Wind <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Waterside Hall for Washing the Tassels of One's Hat <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Hall of Small Mountains and Osmanthus Spring <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Main Entrance</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-338"><graphic url="CH8_011.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 8.10. Pavilion of the Arriving Moon and Wind, <name type="pname">Wang Shi Yuan</name>, <name type="place">Suzhou</name></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Wang Shi Yuan</name> (Garden of the Master of the Fishing Nets)</hi></hi></head><p>The <name type="pname">Wang Shi Yuan</name>, or the Garden of the Master of the Fishing Nets, is one of several remaining scholar-gardens in <name type="place">Suzhou</name> that give some impression of the lives led by the educated and bureaucratic elite in imperial <name type="place">China</name>. Much literary meaning is packed into this one-and-a-half-acre garden of idyllically arranged scenery, and the spaces within it bear the kinds of poetical names that <name type="pname">Jia Zheng</name>'s son <name type="pname">Baoyu</name> was summoned to provide in <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Stone</hi>. First laid out in <date when="1140">1140</date>, in early Southern Song times by a high court official, it was restored in <date when="1770">1770</date> by another official, <name type="pname">Song Zongyuan</name>, as his retirement retreat. Though altered both before and after its appropriation by the municipal government in <date when="1958">1958</date>, its outlines and principal features remain the same as in the Qing period (<date when="1644">1644</date>&#x2013;<date when="1911">1911</date>). Like other scholar-gardens, it is highly compartmentalized, with courtyards and roofed structures interlocking like pieces of a puzzle (fig. 8.9).</p><p>In former times, visitors arriving by palanquin would have entered the <name type="pname">Wang Shi Yuan</name> through the main entrance on the south where the residential quarters are. Today access is through a narrow passageway from a side alley into the northern end of the complex, which leads more directly into the garden. In either case, the route into the Place for Gathering Breezes&#x2014;the central garden space, dominated by a lake&#x2014;is a circuitous one. Its chief focal point, as seen from the Duck Shooting Corridor adjacent to the family halls, is the Pavilion of the Arriving Moon and Wind, a delicate, six-sided structure with soaring rooflines collected in a high finial (fig. 8.10). Poised on its appropriately scaled rockery above the surface of the lake, it is a resting place where one can gaze dreamily at the reflections in the water. A mirror inside increases the sparkling play of light on its surfaces.</p><p>The visitor does not arrive by an obvious path to this spot but is diverted along the way by other pavilions and their adjacent courtyards. The Hall of Small Mountains and Osmanthus Spring is completely screened from the lake by a tall mountain of<pb n="291"/><pb n="291" type="orig"/>earth and rockwork. From inside, one views this composition through windows framed with lacy fretwork. On the south side of this structure lies a small courtyard containing many fine specimens of Lake Tai rocks placed in an undulating composition. The bright white wall of this courtyard constitutes the pictorial ground upon which the shadows of the fragrant osmanthus trees are cast, forming a tracery pattern that complements the fretwork of the small openings in it as well as that of the windows of the pavilion.</p><p>The Waterside Hall for Washing the Tassels of One's Hat sits at the water's edge on the south side of the lake opposite the Veranda for Viewing Pines and Looking at Paintings. The latter pavilion has a lake view seen through old pines and cypresses, which are set in a rockery. Besides these lakeside summerhouses, there are other garden pavilions, several of which serve the needs of the scholar. The Five Peaks Study, for instance, is a library. Since interior stairs are not favored in ornamental Chinese architecture, access to its second story was gained via steps set into a rockery next to its east wall. Adjacent to it is the House of Concentrated Study. Another study, the Cottage to Accompany Spring, had its own private pebble-paved courtyard garden to the south as well as another tiny courtyard on the north. The latter, which is framed from inside by beautifully carved window surrounds, contains a delicate composition of bamboo, rocks, and flowering plants.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Imperial <name type="place">Beijing</name></hi></hi></head><p>By <date when="1279">1279</date>, <name type="pname">Khubilai Khan</name>, the grandson of <name type="pname">Genghis Khan</name>, had toppled the Jin dynasty in the northern part of <name type="place">China</name>, captured Hangzhou, and gained control of the entire country at an estimated cost of 30 million lives. <name type="pname">Khubilai</name> moved the capital of his Mongol empire to <name type="place">Beijing</name> and assimilated the more sophisticated culture of the people he had conquered. The <name type="pname">Yuan</name> dynasty, as the Mongol rulership was styled, lasted until <date when="1368">1368</date>. Like other disaffected Chinese civil servants before them, a number of the mandarin elite went into permanent retirement rather than serve the foreign conqueror, some finding careers as artists whose works were in demand by the growing merchant class. Others went north to carry on their traditional duties, including artistic ones, at court.</p><p>The Jin emperors, whose occupancy of <name type="place">Beijing</name> preceded that of the Mongols, had excavated a canal and a marshy lake, the nucleus of the three contemporary lakes around which "sea palaces" and pleasure parks were built. <name type="pname">Khubilai Khan</name> further excavated this lake, which is known as Bei Hai, or Northern Sea, setting up hunting preserves around it and embellishing its shores with many trees and costly buildings. At its southern end he formed an island from the dredged spoil upon which he erected a "mountain" studded with rocks of lapis lazuli. To <name type="pname">Marco Polo</name>, this Green Hill presented a wondrous sight. According to him, the trees planted upon it were transported there by elephants.<ref target="#CH8-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref></p><p>The first emperor of the Ming dynasty (<date when="1368">1368</date>&#x2013;<date when="1644">1644</date>) located the capital at Nanjing where it remained until the third emperor, <name type="pname">Yongle</name> (ruled <date when="1403">1403</date>&#x2013;<date when="1424">1424</date>), reestablished the court at <name type="place">Beijing</name>. For fourteen years <name type="pname">Yongle</name>'s builders labored to erect a city modeled on the previous Ming emperor's capital at Nanjing. Guided by geomancy, Confucian symbolism, and cosmology, they gave physical representation to the emperor's rule under the "mandate of heaven." This was expressed as a hierarchical ordering of space in which were nested three rectangular walled enclosures containing the Inner City, the Imperial City, and the Forbidden City, all of which were centered on a great north-south axis punctuated by ceremonial gates (fig. 8.11).</p><figure xml:id="fig-339"><graphic url="CH8_012.jpg"/><figDesc>8.11. Plan of the Forbidden City, <name type="place">Beijing</name>, <name type="place">Suzhou</name> <hi rend="bold">A</hi> North Gate <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Palaces <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Hall of Supreme Harmony <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Wu Men (Meridian Gate) <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Duan Men <hi rend="bold">F</hi> Tian 'an Men (Gate of Heavenly Peace) <hi rend="bold">G</hi> <name type="pname">Qian Qing Men</name> (Gate of August Purity)</figDesc></figure><pb n="292"/><pb n="292" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-340"><graphic url="CH8_013.jpg"/><figDesc>8.12. View from Bao He Dian (Hall for the Preservation of Harmony) toward <name type="pname">Qian Qing Men</name> (Gate of August Purity), Forbidden City, <name type="place">Beijing</name></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-341"><graphic url="CH8_014.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below</hi> 8.13. Gate at Palace Museum, Forbidden City, <name type="place">Beijing</name></figDesc></figure><p>In <date when="1420">1420</date>, <name type="pname">Yongle</name>'s vast complex of walled enclosures and palatial buildings was ready for occupancy, and <name type="place">Beijing</name> officially became the Ming capital. The Altar of Heaven was also built in the reign of <name type="pname">Yongle</name> to the south of <name type="pname">Qian Qing Men</name> (Gate of August Purity), the great Front Gate of the Inner City. It was flanked by two circular temples, the Temple of Heaven and the Hall of Prayer for Good Harvests. During the reign of <name type="pname">Jiajing</name> (ruled <date when="1522">1522</date>&#x2013;<date when="1566">1566</date>) in the next century at the cardinal points just outside the Inner City additional magnificent altars were raised to the Earth, Sun, Moon, and Agriculture. At that time, about <date when="1550">1550</date>, another walled rectangle was constructed, enclosing the district to the south of the Inner City. Called the Outer City, it encompassed the Altar of Heaven and the Altar of Agriculture (replaced by a Worker's Stadium in the <date when="1950">1950</date>s).</p><p>Because of fires and other mishaps, the imperial buildings that one sees today are almost all reconstructions of the Qing dynasty, but Chinese conservatism has nonetheless ensured continuity of form, making it possible at least to imagine the appearance of the ancient Ming capital of the fifteenth century. In spite of the degradation of much of its elegant imperial architectural heritage under Communist rule, <name type="place">Beijing</name> still offers an unrivaled ceremonial progression along a central axis that thrusts northward through a hierarchical series of magnificent gates, symmetrically arranged courts, and majestic halls, passing first through the Outer City and then into the precincts of the Forbidden City (figs. 8.12, 8.13). Continuing through the <name type="pname">Shen Wu Men</name>&#x2014;the Gate of the Martial Spirit built to guard the Forbidden City from northern invaders&#x2014;and crossing a moat, the axis continues to <name type="pname">Jing Shan</name>, or Prospect Hill, also known as Mei Shan, Coal Hill.</p><p>Constructed in the fifteenth century with erosion material dredged from the moat that encircles the Forbidden City, Coal Hill is now a public park and the highest point in <name type="place">Beijing</name>. The siting of the Forbidden City in its lee, where it was sheltered from northerly winds and unfriendly spirits, is in accordance with the<pb n="293"/><pb n="293" type="orig"/>Chinese geomantic practice of <hi rend="italic">feng shui</hi>. In imperial times this eminence was planted with fruit trees and served as a bird sanctuary and place of retreat for the emperor and members of the court. During his long reign, the Qianlong emperor (ruled <date when="1736">1736</date>&#x2013;<date when="1795">1795</date>) built upon each of its five low peaks an open-framed pavilion housing a bronze statue of a deity. With their variously shaped roofs, these acted as "borrowed" scenery for the gardens within the Forbidden City.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name></hi></hi></head><p>While vowing simplicity and professing the modest ideals of a scholar-poet, the Qianlong emperor who built the pavilions on Coal Hill proved to be a lavish creator of landscapes. His vast project, the <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name>, or the Garden of Perfect Brightness, gave Europeans&#x2014;thanks to the publication of letters of the Jesuit missionary Father Attiret (<date when="1702">1702</date>&#x2013;<date when="1738">1738</date>) in the middle of the eighteenth century&#x2014;their first real knowledge of the Chinese garden.</p><p>One of five imperial parks created in the northwestern hills outside the city during the Qing dynasty, the <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name> was given its basic form by the Yongzheng emperor, who reigned between <date when="1723">1723</date> and <date when="1735">1735</date>. His son, the Qianlong emperor, made a pledge to practice restraint in regard to imperial works, but he soon broke it, setting a force of a thousand men to work on the <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name> (fig. 8.14). Lakes were dug, hillocks thrown up, fantastical rocks positioned in eye-catching arrangements, trees and flowers planted, and many pavilions, zigzag bridges, and other architectural features erected. The emperor then went on to embellish the <name type="pname">Chang Chun Yuan</name> (Garden of Everlasting Spring), which had been his grandfather's old retreat, in the same fashion. He also developed the Garden of Joyous Spring (<name type="pname">Ji Chun Yuan</name>), fusing it and the <name type="pname">Chang Chun Yuan</name> with the <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name> as a complex of three separate but linked gardens.</p><p>By this time the Chinese scholar-gardens of southern <name type="place">China</name> had a long and prestigious history, and this northern imperial garden was conceived somewhat as an eclectic "collection" of many famous southern garden scenes. For the pleasure of court ladies whose lives were narrowly circumscribed by palace garden walls, the emperor had a true-to-life shopping street created. On the northeast boundary of the <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name> he commissioned Father Attiret's fellow Jesuit missionary Father Giuseppe Castiglione to design and construct a collection of structures built in a curious pseudo-Baroque style that mingled European and Chinese elements (see fig. 6.35).</p><p>In <date when="1860">1860</date>, <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name> was completely destroyed by the British and French as the last vengeful act in a war in which <name type="place">Great Britain</name> and <name type="place">France</name> forced the Chinese to grant additional trade privileges to Western countries. On <date when="--10-18">October 18</date>, a British corps invaded the garden grounds, ransacked its buildings, and then set fire to the entire complex. The flames consumed not only the <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name>, but also several other adjacent pleasure palaces and their parks.</p><figure xml:id="fig-342"><graphic url="CH8_015.jpg"/><figDesc>8.14. Perspective view of <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name> (Garden of Perfect Brightness), painting by Tang Dai and <name type="pname">Shen Yuan</name>. Biblioth&#x00E8;que Nationale, <name type="place">Paris</name></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Yi He Yuan</name></hi></hi></head><p>Among the parks burned by the British and French in <date when="1860">1860</date> was the <name type="pname">Yi He Yuan</name>, the Garden of Ease and Harmony, one of the five major parks, including the <name type="pname">Yuan Ming Yuan</name>, that once adorned the Western Hills. This park, also the creation of Qianlong, who built it in honor of his mother's sixtieth birthday, was rebuilt by the <name type="pname">Dowager Empress Cixi</name> in celebration of <hi rend="italic">her</hi> sixtieth birthday in <date when="1894">1894</date>. Once more put to the torch by Europeans in the Boxer Rebellion of <date when="1900">1900</date>, it was restored again by the empress in <date when="1902">1902</date>.</p><p>In the center of the <name type="pname">Yi He Yuan</name> there is a sheet of light-reflecting, lotus-blooming water called Kunming Lake. It has a circumference of 4 miles (6.4 kilometers) and occupies approximately 500 of the park's 725 acres. Originally no more than a marshy pond, it was dredged and enlarged by the Qianlong emperor, who built an aqueduct system to feed it and other imperial lakes.</p><p>Stretching for almost half a mile (.8 kilometers) along the north side of Kunming Lake is the remarkable Long Gallery (Chang Lang), giving architectural definition to the gentle curves of the shoreline and providing, through ornamental frames of wooden latticework panels, picturesque views of the lake and its surrounding scenery (fig. 8.15). The Long Gallery's architecture and its function as a viewing<pb n="294"/><pb n="294" type="orig"/>platform are enhanced by the pavilions that punctuate it at particularly scenic points. Designed as small rooms, these offer privacy if desired, having doors that can shut off the main covered walkway. This remarkable waterfront promenade also functions as a gallery for the more than 14,000 painted panels that decorate the cross beams (fig. 8.16). These depict birds, animals, flowers, landscape scenes, and other graceful motifs.</p><figure xml:id="fig-343"><graphic url="CH8_016.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Top:</hi> 8.15. Long Gallery (Chang Lang) and view of Kunming Lake, <name type="pname">Yi He Yuan</name> (Garden of Ease and Harmony). Garden built in Qing Dynasty by <name type="pname">Emperor Qianlong</name>; rebuilt by <name type="pname">Dowager Empress Cixi</name>, <date when="1894">1894</date>; restored again by the empress, <date when="1902">1902</date>, following the Boxer Rebellion</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-344"><graphic url="CH8_017.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Above:</hi> 8.16. <hi rend="italic">Shu shi</hi>-style painted panels from the Long Gallery (Chang Lang), <name type="pname">Yi He Yuan</name></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-345"><graphic url="CH8_018.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 8.17. <name type="pname">Yu Dai Qiao</name> (Jade Belt Bridge), <name type="pname">Yi He Yuan</name> (Garden of Ease and Harmony), Summer Palace</figDesc></figure><p>The views looking west from the eastern shore of the lake are enriched by a series of bridges, each unique in its design. The causeway that traverses the lake, dividing it into one large lake and two smaller ones, incorporates six bridges. The most notable of these is the Jade Belt Bridge (<name type="pname">Yu Dai Qiao</name>), also called the Camel's Hump Bridge, which leaps with balletic grace over an inlet at the lake's western edge (fig. 8.17).</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Plant Material</hi></hi></head><p>Throughout its long history, the plants of the Chinese garden design remained those traditional ones celebrated in poetry and painting, which were derived from conventional symbolical association. Certain favorite flowers, such as peonies, were cultivated in masses, and their springtime bloom in the garden was the occasion for entertaining friends. Chrysanthemums, which like pines were revered as long-lived survivors, were the focus of special vantage points designed for fall viewing.</p><p>Indeed, consideration of the Chinese garden's movement through the cycle of the seasons counted as much for garden designers as its careful sequencing in spatial terms. It was thought that a light dusting of snow in the winter best revealed its essential architecture and the lines of force and mass that constituted a well-designed "mountain." Most apparent in that season are the "three friends of winter"&#x2014;pine, bamboo, and plum, with their respective symbolical associations of longevity, hardiness, and strength of character; pliable and supple nature capable of lasting friendship; and delicate beauty even in old age. In summer the mirrorlike surface of the pond traded its cloud reflections and reverse shoreline imagery for an efflorescence of lotuses. Lifting their stalks out of the mud, they formed a verdant mat of waxy leaves dotted with pale flowers, a symbol of the purity and victory of the spirit over the senses. Thus, change itself and the anticipation of change, with all the associations of life, death, and renewal implied by seasonal transformation, are a conscious dimension of Chinese garden design.</p><p>Today the perpetuation of this style of garden-making is more a matter of replication of historic models than one of authentic landscape creation inspired by poetry and painting. Its influence can be traced in other lands in gardens that also aspired to capture the spirit-force of nature through landscape art. Among these are the Chinese garden's direct descendants, which are found within the precincts of the temples and palaces of <name type="place">Japan</name>.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb n="295"/><pb n="295" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">II. Tea, Moss, and Stones: Temple and Palace Gardens of <name type="place">Japan</name></hi></hi></head><p>Chinese garden concepts arrived in <name type="place">Japan</name> along with Buddhism in the sixth century. Although sharing a similar aesthetic approach, the gardens built in the small, well-watered island nation of <name type="place">Japan</name> would ultimately differ from those of <name type="place">China</name>, a country of vastly greater dimensions, a land of contrasting wide plains and mountainous precipices. After appropriating Chinese garden concepts, instead of continuing to create "recollections" of famous scenes in nature in the Chinese manner, Japanese garden designers increasingly sought a generic ideal of nature in conformity with the scale and topography of their own natural landscape.</p><p>The eleventh-century treatise known as the <hi rend="italic">Sakuteiki</hi>, presumably written by <name type="pname">Tachibana no Toshitsuna</name> (<date when="1028">1028</date>&#x2013;<date when="1084">1084</date>), is <name type="place">Japan</name>'s earliest known manual of garden rules.<ref target="#CH8-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref> In it one finds prescriptions for the handling of stones set within moving water in the so-called "large river style." The <hi rend="italic">Sakuteiki</hi> counsels that, in order to make a proper garden, one should travel widely and become acquainted with beautiful scenes in nature, indicating that by this time the Japanese had singled out various famous views as prized components of their country's natural landscape. Besides giving precise instructions for building waterfalls and other garden features, the author encourages gardeners to orient their buildings to the south according to the principles of geomancy. Logically, streams should be placed on this, their most open, side. He prescribed that these flow from east to west in order to cleanse the evil air emanating from the northeast and ward off demons. In addition to following these prescriptions of the <hi rend="italic">Sakuteiki</hi>, Japanese garden designers often incorporated a distant vista in their designs in order to enlarge the visual sphere of the usually quite small garden and to reinforce its connection with the natural world. They referred to this technique of borrowing scenery as <hi rend="italic">shakkei</hi>.</p><p>Buddhist creation mythology and <name type="pname">Daoist</name> belief in the paradisaical Isles of the Blest furnished the lakeand-islands motif that underlies the composition of many Japanese gardens, even those compressed visions of a Zen Buddhist universe known as <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi>, or dry landscapes. Beginning in the thirteenth century, members of the newly imported Zen sect designed these spare, almost austere, gardens as aids to meditation. These are minimalist compositions of carefully positioned stones, which are meant to be read as islands in a dry "river" of carefully raked gravel or sand or as mountains in a landscape of mosses. Such Zen-inspired gardens played an important role among members of the ruling classes; certain emperors and even some shoguns&#x2014;powerful military dictators who ruled under the nominal authority of the emperor&#x2014;found garden-making to be a satisfying escape from court politics and civil strife. The tea ceremony, developed in the late fifteenth century, was not a religious exercise, but it nevertheless provided a disciplined experience of concentration and aesthetic and spiritual refreshment for which passage along a garden path of moss and stones offered a prescribed prelude and conclusion.</p><p>The Japanese combined their penchant for cultural appropriation with a talent for reinvention. <name type="place">Japan</name>'s island geography and a semi-isolationist policy during much of its history fostered the assimilation and transformation of those ideas and forms that were adopted from the outside into a vigorous native expression. The arrival of <name type="pname">Commodore Matthew Perry</name>'s American ships in <name type="place">Tokyo Bay</name> in <date when="1853">1853</date>&#x2013;<date when="1854">54</date> ended the country's previous two centuries of closure to all but Dutch and Chinese traders, whose access was strictly limited. Increasing transactions with the West started <name type="place">Japan</name> on a path of profound change. Without some degree of cultural isolation and the focused aestheticism that matured the Japanese garden into a great art form, the slow but creative evolution that counts as development within a traditional artistic idiom came to a standstill. Its assimilative energies directed toward building a powerful economy and its political life reshaped since <date when="1945">1945</date> as a capitalist democracy, <name type="place">Japan</name> has become today a conservator of its cultural heritage. As in other countries where the government and cultural institutions protect a "golden age" of previous artistic accomplishment, in <name type="place">Japan</name> the state and the religious establishments of Kyoto maintain the incomparable imperial and Buddhist temple gardens as much-appreciated heritage icons and tourist attractions.</p><p>The talents of Japanese landscape designers today contribute to the pluralistic internationalism of garden art rather than to the continued development of a specifically indigenous style. The <hi rend="italic">vocabulary</hi> of Japanese garden design&#x2014;its abstract compositional harmonies, its elegant rusticity, its "borrowed" views, its asymmetrical configuration of design elements, its attention to ground plane patterns and textures in the arrangement of moss and stones&#x2014;has furnished inspiration to modern garden designers in other countries. To appreciate more fully the richness of simplicity in this carefully matured language of landscape, we must now review the history of Japanese gardens.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps"><name type="pname">Shinto</name> Sanctuaries</hi></hi></head><p>The Japanese word for garden, <hi rend="italic">niwa</hi>, was first used to denote a sanctified space in nature set apart for the worship of <name type="pname">Shinto</name> gods. A sacred rock (<hi rend="italic">iwakura</hi>), rock<pb n="296"/><pb n="296" type="orig"/>grouping, tree, or other natural object might be revered for its indwelling spirit (fig. 8.18). Like the <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi>, the sacred precinct of ancient Greek religion, the <name type="pname">Shinto</name> shrine exists as a clearly marked space within a natural setting of assigned spiritual power. But unlike the <hi rend="italic">temenos</hi>, an enclosed space, the <name type="pname">Shinto</name> shrine exists merely as a marked place, its boundaries set not by walls, but rather implied by a <hi rend="italic">torii</hi> gate framing a sacred object or space in nature (fig. 8.19). Where greater architectural definition is sought, an apron of white gravel may isolate the revered place or object. Ropes, straw fencing, and sometimes cloth banners may also be used as means of demarcation.</p><figure xml:id="fig-346"><graphic url="CH8_019.jpg"/><figDesc>8.18. <hi rend="italic">Iwakura</hi> (sacred rock). Aichi Shrine, Okayama Prefecture. The purified area around these sacred stones, believed to be inhabited by <hi rend="italic">kami</hi>, or spirits, is marked by straw ropes (<hi rend="italic">shime-nawa)</hi>.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-347"><graphic url="CH8_020.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below</hi>; 8.19. Sacred rocks at Ise</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-348"><graphic url="CH8_021.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 8.20. Ise Shrine, Ise City, Mie Prefecture, <name type="place">Japan</name></figDesc></figure><p>The holiest spot in <name type="place">Japan</name> is considered to be the <name type="pname">Shinto</name> shrine at Ise in Mie Prefecture. The shrine enclave includes the Geku, or Outer Shrine, which is dedicated to the provider of grain, and the Naiku, or Inner Shrine, sacred to the heaven-illuminating sun goddess Amaterasu, from whom <name type="place">Japan</name>'s imperial clan once claimed descent. The Inner Shrine is set within a clearing within a cryptomeria forest and is reached by a ceremonial path that passes through <hi rend="italic">torii</hi>, over the Isuzu River, and through the forest to the clearing (fig. 8.20).</p><p>The Inner Shrine precinct contains the <hi rend="italic">honden</hi>, the main hall of the Inner Shrine, and two treasure houses. All are enclosed within three concentric fences and accessible only through gates on the short ends of the rectangular plot of white gravel on which they sit; adjacent and sharing common fencing within the clearing is an identical rectangular plot of gravel that serves as the alternate building site. The active shrine consists of a group of simple unpainted wooden structures roofed with the bark of Cyprus trees. Every twenty years&#x2014;most recently in <date when="1993">1993</date>&#x2014;the <hi rend="italic">honden</hi>, whose simple form is derived from Yayoi-period (c. 300 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.e.</hi>&#x2013;c. 300 <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>) raised rice granaries, is rebuilt and rededicated. Only a small structure in the middle of the otherwise empty plain of gravel protects the <hi rend="italic">shin no mihashira</hi>, or heart post, a structural member of the previous shrine, which is left standing.</p><p>Historians believe that white gravel aprons such as this are predecessors of the <hi rend="italic">yuniwa</hi>, the entry court of palaces and other monumental structures, a purified space that is empty or contains at most a pair of symbolic trees. The more worldly culture of a later period turned the <hi rend="italic">yuniwa</hi> of noble residences into a secular, landscaped space, but those relating to shrines remained as religiously austere as the one at Ise. The majesty of the towering cryptomeria trees constitutes the more grand architectural expression of the Ise<pb n="297"/><pb n="297" type="orig"/>shrine site, but the humble structures of ancient origin, the fenced compound containing them, and the adjacent cleared space create a moving statement of the desire for human order within the greater order of the cosmos.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Nara and Heian Courts</hi></hi></head><p>Buddhism was introduced from <name type="place">China</name> into <name type="place">Japan</name> in 552. Under the regent, <name type="pname">Prince Shotoku</name> (573&#x2013;621), who promoted it and built temples, it gained the kind of institutional status enjoyed by Christianity in the West after the reign of <name type="pname">Constantine the Great</name>. The acceptance of Buddhism, together with contacts with Korea and the first official Japanese embassy to <name type="place">China</name> in the early seventh century, stimulated the adoption of Chinese artistic and architectural forms. Formerly, rulers had constructed their dwellings in the vernacular style of the structures at the Ise Shrine. Moreover, because of the premium put upon spatial purification and ritual rebuilding, the capital was moved at the beginning of each new reign. In 710, however, the court was established at Nara, and there it remained for the next seventy-five years through several reigns.</p><p>The plan of the city, with its hierarchical ordering of space within a grid layout, was, at a lesser scale, a conscious imitation of that of Chang'an, the Chinese Tang dynasty capital. The temples constructed to house large images of <name type="pname">Buddha</name> were unlike any previous Japanese architectural forms. The spatial layout of their surrounding compounds also followed Chinese models.</p><p>Korean craftsmen were brought to Nara to help develop imperial gardens in the Chinese manner, with lakes and rock arrangements forming islands. From archaeological excavations, as well as from paintings and poetry of this period, we surmise that these were similar to the Tang models they sought to imitate, being <hi rend="italic">yarimizu</hi>, or river-style gardens. Their meandering streams furnished the opportunity to organize poetry competitions like the ones popular in contemporary Chinese gardens.</p><p>Upon ascending the throne in 781, <name type="pname">Emperor Kammu</name> decided to move the capital once more, probably in order to separate the government from the influence of priests at Nara, who, to his distress, had amassed considerable political power. After ten years of building this new capital, Nagaoka-ky&#x014D;, the notyet-finished city was abandoned in favor of another site nearby, Heian-ky&#x014D;, meaning the Capital of Peace and Tranquility, the original name of Kyoto. Once established, Kyoto became the imperial capital of <name type="place">Japan</name> for more than a thousand years until the Meiji Restoration in <date when="1868">1868</date>, when <name type="place">Tokyo</name> was made the capital.</p><p>In Kyoto, as at Nara, the gridiron plan of Chang'an formed the model for a new city roughly half Nara's size, or 3.5 miles (5.6 kilometers) north to south by 3 miles (4.8 kilometers) east to west (fig. 8.21).<ref target="#CH8-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref> Also, as at Nara, the imperial enclosure, known as the Daidairi, was placed at the end of a broad axis at the city's northern end. The surrounding city was subdivided into 76 large squares, measuring approximately 400 feet (122 meters) to a side. The eastern half of this residential grid became the location of choice for the nobility; however, the western half was never developed in accordance with its original outlines. In an attempt to avoid the political tensions that had existed at Nara, the emperor mandated that new temples be sited outside the city, and these were therefore built on the lower slopes of the surrounding hills, as were estates of the powerful nobility.</p><figure xml:id="fig-349"><graphic url="CH8_022.jpg"/><figDesc>8.21. Plan of Heian-ky&#x014D; (Kyoto), <name type="place">Japan</name> <hi rend="bold">A</hi> Imperial Court and Residence <hi rend="bold">B</hi> Imperial Garden <hi rend="bold">C</hi> Markets <hi rend="bold">D</hi> Diplomatic Reception Courts <hi rend="bold">E</hi> Temples</figDesc></figure><p>In the Heian period (781&#x2013;1185), a golden age for Kyoto, all the arts, including landscape design, were held in high esteem. Gardens in this period were ampler than later ones, and the lakes in them were generous in size. Fortunately for posterity, <name type="pname">Murasaki Shikibu</name> (970?&#x2013;1026?), a lady of the court, chronicled the aesthetic pursuits of the elite during the Heian era in <hi rend="italic">The Tale of Genji</hi>, a novel written around the year <date when="1000">1000</date>.<ref target="#CH8-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref> In it we read of <name type="pname">Prince Genji</name> in many beautiful garden settings as he enjoys such pastimes as rowing in Chinese-style boats around the islands in the lake or going on an outing to admire the fall foliage (fig. 8.22). Inspired by Chinese models, these islands consisted of arrangements of rocks, some intended to suggest the form of a symbolically meaningful tortoise or crane. Pavilions in the style known as <hi rend="italic">shinden-zukuri</hi> stood at the edge of the water. These structures, derived from<pb n="298"/><pb n="298" type="orig"/>Chinese architectural norms, were elegant in their lines but rustic in character, with reticulated two-part shutters that could be raised in summer. Their floors were polished wood, as tatami mats and other specifically Japanese conventions had not yet become established. These viewing platforms were actually projecting wings of a large central pavilion, or <hi rend="italic">shinden</hi>, that faced the lake. A swath of white sand at the lake's edge served as a stage for mime and dance performances, which could be enjoyed from a <hi rend="italic">shinden-zukuri</hi> pavilion. Raised covered passages linked the separate pavilions with each other and with the <hi rend="italic">shinden</hi>.</p><figure xml:id="fig-350"><graphic url="CH8_023.jpg"/><figDesc>8.22. Koch&#x014D; ("Butterflies") from <hi rend="italic">The Tale of Genji</hi>, <name type="pname">Mary</name> and <name type="pname">Jackson Burke</name> Collection. The elite pleasures of Heian court life are evident in this scene depicting a boating party held in <name type="pname">Lady Murasaki</name>'s section of Genji's estate, with musicians and costumed dancers entertaining the imperial consort who has returned home for a visit. This six-fold screen is attributed to <name type="pname">Tosa Mitsuyoshi</name> (<date when="1539">1539</date>&#x2013;<date when="1613">1613</date>).</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-351"><graphic url="CH8_024.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 8.23. Phoenix Hall of the By&#x014D;d&#x014D;-in, Uji, <name type="place">Japan</name></figDesc></figure><p>Within <name type="place">Japan</name>'s feudal social structure, the powerful <name type="pname">Fujiwara</name> clan had gained supremacy by 850, and in their role as regents for emperors in their minority, members of this family gradually appropriated much of the imperial power and married into the imperial family. Their chief, <name type="pname">Fujiwara no Michinaga</name> (966&#x2013;1027), held the title of <hi rend="italic">kampaku</hi>, a high governmental position in which he mediated between the emperor and court officials in affairs of state. As respected but powerless figureheads, emperors typically spent their lives engaged in cultural pursuits. Making a virtue of their relatively reduced circumstances, they refined their chosen style, which was derived from rustic vernacular architecture, into a vocabulary of elegantly crafted details and beautifully proportioned parts. By contrast, the <name type="pname">Fujiwara</name>, like the shoguns who followed them, liked to display their power in works of magnificence. The splendor of the Heian period is found in the By&#x014D;d&#x014D;-in, built as a villa by the <hi rend="italic">kampaku</hi> <name type="pname">Fujiwara Yorimichi</name> (992&#x2013;1074) on his estate south of Kyoto and converted into a temple in <date when="1052">1052</date> (fig. 8.23).</p><pb n="299"/><pb n="299" type="orig"/><p>The pond garden (now severely compromised in size) and serene <hi rend="italic">shinden</hi>-style, Phoenix Hall (H&#x014D;&#x014D;-d&#x014D;) of <date when="1053">1053</date> at By&#x014D;d&#x014D;-in&#x2014;so named because its soaring wings evoke those of the mythical bird as it alights&#x2014;were meant to depict Amida <name type="pname">Buddha</name>'s Paradise. It is the sole remaining structure of the twenty-six halls and seven pagodas that were once grouped around the pond at the By&#x014D;d&#x014D;-in.</p><p>As they became increasingly interested in cultural rather than military pursuits, the <name type="pname">Fujiwara</name> regents were challenged by other powerful clans, the Taira and Minamoto, and the emperor now more than ever governed in name only. Power first fell to the Taira, but their authority was upset by the Minamoto clan and their <hi rend="italic">samurai</hi> army. The Minamoto established headquarters at the town of Kamakura, which gave its name to the period of their ascendancy. Shoguns, in whom hereditary military command rested, continued to exert authority more or less continuously from the late twelfth century until the Meiji Restoration of <date when="1868">1868</date>.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Kamakura Gardens</hi></hi></head><p>The Kamakura period (<date when="1185">1185</date>&#x2013;<date when="1333">1333</date>) is notable for the widespread adoption of the Chinese sect of Chan Buddhism, known in <name type="place">Japan</name> as Zen Buddhism. Introduced as early as the seventh century by the priest D&#x014D;sh&#x014D; (629&#x2013;700) following his return from <name type="place">China</name>, Zen Buddhism was long overshadowed in <name type="place">Japan</name> by the powerful Tendai and Shingon sects. But the austerity and simplicity of Zen religion as professed by the monk Eisai (<date when="1141">1141</date>&#x2013;<date when="1215">1215</date>) upon his return from <name type="place">China</name> in <date when="1192">1192</date>, appealed to the warrior class. As it prospered under their sponsorship, its reductive aesthetic guided the design of certain temple gardens.</p><p>Equally important for designed landscapes at this time were the currents of aesthetic thought emanating from the Southern Song dynasty (<date when="1127">1127</date>&#x2013;<date when="1279">1279</date>) in <name type="place">China</name>. The vertical positioning of carefully selected rocks, typical of Song gardens, can be found in Japanese gardens of this era, whereas later stonework emphasized a horizontality that is less dramatic and more in keeping with the inherent quietude of <name type="place">Japan</name>'s natural landscape forms. More important than this, however, was the poetic idealization of landscape and the relationship between landscape design and painting found in Song garden art, qualities that exerted a strong influence on the development of the Japanese garden.</p><p>The Kamakura era and the subsequent Muromachi period effected a transition in landscape design from the great Heian residential lake gardens of the nobility to the Zen minimalism represented by the monastic garden of Ry&#x014D;an-ji, built between <date when="1500">1500</date> and <date when="1700">1700</date>. In the beautiful river district of Arashiyama in northwestern Kyoto, Tenry&#x016B;-ji, an estate garden built around <date when="1256">1256</date> and later converted into a monastery, exhibits the Song influence in its boldly conceived dry cascade and vertical rock arrangements. From a bridge made of three natural stone slabs, there is a view of a harmoniously balanced composition of seven rocks set in the water so as to suggest one of the Mystic Isles of the Immortals in Chinese legend (fig. 8.24). In <date when="1339">1339</date>, the estate was converted into a Zen Buddhist foundation by <name type="pname">Mus&#x014D; Soseki</name> (also known as <name type="pname">Mus&#x014D; Kokushi</name>, <date when="1275">1275</date>&#x2013;<date when="1351">1351</date>), one of <name type="place">Japan</name>'s most significant religious figures and a gifted garden designer. Some garden historians believe that this serene and paradisaical garden, which today is operated by the Rinzai sect of Zen Buddhism, was reworked by <name type="pname">Mus&#x014D; Soseki</name> and is an example of his artistry. Though less than an acre in size and containing a pond that is only 100 by 200 feet (30.5 by 61 meters), it has something of the atmosphere of the old Heian <hi rend="italic">shinden</hi> lake garden. Its surrounding views are now obscured by vegetation, but it originally drew into its small compass the distant crowns of Arashiyama and Kameyama mountains, providing what is possibly the earliest Japanese example we have of the technique of borrowed scenery.</p><figure xml:id="fig-352"><graphic url="CH8_025.jpg"/><figDesc>8.24. Garden of Tenry&#x016B;-ji Temple, Kyoto, rock arrangement suggesting Penglai (pronounced H&#x014D;rai in Japanese), one of the Islands of the Immortals, according to Chinese legend. Kamakura Period</figDesc></figure><p>Nearby, at Saih&#x014D;-ji, another temple of the Rinzai Zen Buddhist sect, <name type="pname">Mus&#x014D; Soseki</name> began in <date when="1339">1339</date> to reconstruct an existing garden after it had been practically destroyed during the civil wars that had recently wracked the country. Comprising an upper and a lower garden totaling 4.5 acres, it, too, has a lake, this one considerably larger than that of Tenry&#x016B;-ji. In the<pb n="300"/><pb n="300" type="orig"/>lower garden surrounding the lake, the atmosphere of the Heian pleasure garden has given way completely to a deeply spiritual environment derived from J&#x014D;do (Pure Land) Buddhism and intended as a metaphor for Amida's Paradise. The light-reflecting water, verdant moss, and the deep shade cast by lichen-covered trees induce a meditative mood that is an essential part of Zen practice (fig. 8.25).</p><figure xml:id="fig-353"><graphic url="CH8_026.jpg"/><figDesc>8.25. Garden of Saih&#x014D;-ji Temple, Kyoto, lake and mossy embankments. Kamakura Period</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-354"><graphic url="CH8_027.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 8.26. Garden of Saih&#x014D;-ji Temple, dry cascade with flat-topped rocks</figDesc></figure><p>The upper garden on the hillside extends the Zen experience. Here one finds a dry cascade, thought to be the first example of a <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi> composition in a Japanese garden. Its absence of water suggests <hi rend="italic">mu</hi>, or "no-thing-ness," which is emblematic of Zen teaching. Its flat-topped rocks, perfectly arranged so as to suggest a waterfall in nature, are unlike the vertically positioned rocks at Tenry&#x016B;-ji and mark the beginning in Japanese stone compositions of a preference for horizontal lines. These rocks are more sympathetically allied with the native landscape than upthrust ones, which were originally intended to evoke Chinese mountain scenery. As rock artistry continued to develop in <name type="place">Japan</name>, vertical stones were still used as accents, but handsome flat stones became increasingly prized by garden designers as an important means of creating effects of tranquil beauty (fig. 8.26). In other words, in Japanese garden design, as in painting, the influence of Chinese models remained present as a continuing source of inspiration, but local traditions and local imagery modified received forms into an indigenous cultural expression. The oxymoronic notion of a <hi rend="italic">dry cascade</hi> is like a Zen <hi rend="italic">k&#x014D;an</hi>, puzzling and without apparent logic, a means of frustrating rational thought and pushing the acolyte toward a deeper, more intuitive understanding.</p><p>The transcendent quality of this garden derives in part from <name type="pname">Mus&#x014D; Soseki</name>'s rockwork and in part from the patina of age. For the last hundred years or so, many varieties of moss have been encouraged to grow into a thick velvety tapestry that now covers the entire ground plane. Meticulously groomed, this soft blanket of gleaming green moss accounts for the garden's alternate name, Kokedera, or Moss Temple. Vigorous restraint, rich economy, and tradition-fed originality remained characteristic of Japanese gardens even as they continued to incorporate Chinese forms into a new idiom of elegant austerity.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Muromachi Gardens</hi></hi></head><p>Kamakura rule was superseded by that of the <name type="pname">Ashikaga</name> shogunate in what is referred to as the Muromachi period (<date when="1333">1333</date>&#x2013;<date when="1573">1573</date>), named after the northeastern section of Kyoto, where the third shogun, <name type="pname">Ashikaga Yoshimitsu</name> (<date when="1358">1358</date>&#x2013;<date when="1408">1408</date>), built his palace. Called Hana no Gosho, or Flowery Palace, it had a beautiful lake garden. Active trade with <name type="place">China</name> had brought renewed enthusiasm for Chinese Song arts to <name type="place">Japan</name>. Antique Song paintings and porcelains and Ming works in the Song style were eagerly sought, and in spite of famine, plague, and a series of earthquakes, connoisseurship flourished among the ruling elite.</p><p><name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name>, a Zen follower, left his office nominally in the hands of his nine-year-old son, and retired to a private estate outside the city where a fine old garden from the early thirteenth century already existed. He renamed the place Kitayama (North Hill) Villa. Here, around <date when="1397">1397</date>, he set about building Kinkaku, or Golden Pavilion, as his private chapel (fig. 8.27). In the Golden Pavilion and its successor, the Silver Pavilion, we see the effects of patronage by wealthy shoguns: garden designs derived from a fusion of Chinese Song and Japanese Zen aesthetics. The villa was converted to a Zen temple and renamed Rokuon-ji in <date when="1408">1408</date> upon <name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name>'s death. Popu<pb n="301"/><pb n="301" type="orig"/>larly known as Kinkaku-ji (Temple of the Golden Pavilion) by later generations, this remarkable three-storied structure (actually a mid-twentieth-century replica of the only remaining part of <name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name>'s original <hi rend="italic">shinden</hi>-style, mansion) is perched over the water of the lake.<ref target="#CH8-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref> The lower floor, Amida Hall, was used as a reception room; the second, Kannon Hall, as a place for conversation and connoisseurship; while the third story, with its bell-shaped windows, probably functioned as a Zen meditation room. The gold-leafed ceiling of this room as well as its gold-lacquered exterior furnished the pavilion with its name. The Golden Pavilion is a delicately poetic structure, especially when its soaring eaves are dusted with snow and the pines and pond beside it are similarly whitened.</p><p>Although converted into a temple foundation following <name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name>'s death, <name type="pname">Kinkaku-ji</name> was first and foremost a princely pleasure ground. Its lake may inspire a state of spiritual reverie, but it was also used for boating parties, and the proudest event of <name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name>'s life occurred when he entertained the emperor and members of the court at a house party upon the garden's completion in <date when="1408">1408</date>.</p><p><name type="pname">Kinkaku-ji</name>'s garden of only four-and-one-half acres was composed (it is thought by <name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name> himself) in two parts&#x2014;a lower lake garden and and upper "mountain" garden with tea houses&#x2014;with such artistry that it augments itself through illusion. The lake, which covers a third of the garden surface, is divided by a peninsula and related central island into a heart-character shape (<hi rend="italic">kokoro</hi>). Its waters reflect the Silk Hat Hill (Kinugasa-yama) that lies beyond its encircling pines. Song influence and Japanese aesthetics are evident in the careful selection and the placement of rocks into studied arrangements within the lake. Some of these are meant to evoke the nine mountains and eight seas in the Buddhist myth of creation. In addition, other interestingly formed rocks were placed as elements of islands. Several rock compositions take the shape of tortoises. The crane, another longevity symbol, is the motif for an island in front of the pavilion. Many of these beautifully arranged rocks were gifts to <name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name>; often they have flat tops, a form that was increasingly admired among Japanese garden rock collectors.</p><p>In subsequent periods of Japanese garden history, fine stones were frequently carted from a ruined or impoverished garden to a new one. For instance, in <date when="1474">1474</date>, following his retirement from the shogunate, Yoshimasa (<date when="1436">1436</date>&#x2013;<date when="1490">1490</date>), grandson of <name type="pname">Yoshimitsu</name>, had some of the stones and pine trees of the Flowery Palace and Muromachi Hall, both of which had been devastated by civil warfare, removed to his villa retreat at the base of Higashiyama (the Eastern Hills). There he lived from <date when="1483">1483</date> until his death, when the villa was converted to a Zen temple, <name type="pname">Jish&#x014D;-ji</name>, or <name type="pname">Ginkaku-ji</name> (the Temple of the Silver Pavilion), as it is better known. Rockwork became a professional occupation for a certain outcast segment of society, men who engaged in various kinds of necessary "dirty work." Some of these, such as Zen'ami (d. <date when="1482">1482</date>), who worked at several of the great Muromachi estates, were talented garden craftsmen and much in demand.</p><figure xml:id="fig-355"><graphic url="CH8_028.jpg"/><figDesc>8.27. Kinkaku-ji (Golden Pavilion), Rokuon-ji Temple, Kyoto. Kamakura Period, Pavilion rebuilt in the middle of the 20th century after the original of the <date when="1390">1390</date>s</figDesc></figure><p>The culture of Zen is perhaps more completely expressed in those gardens that were designed by and for the use of monks, practitioners of <hi rend="italic">zazen</hi>, or seated<pb n="302"/><pb n="302" type="orig"/>meditation, than in such opulent, shogunate-financed retreats as Kinkaku-ji and and Ginkaku-ji. Carefully controlled compositions in small defined spaces, these gardens were meant to serve as an aid in altering consciousness so as to encourage a state of enlightenment. They are therefore different in character from the shogunal estate gardens like Kinkaku-ji and Ginkaku-ji whose primary end was aesthetic enjoyment.</p><figure xml:id="fig-356"><graphic url="CH8_029.jpg"/><figDesc>8.28. Daisen-in, Kyoto, <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi> garden with bridge with bell-shaped Zen window. Garden built by <name type="pname">Kogaku</name>, the founder of the temple, perhaps with the help of the artist <name type="pname">S&#x014D;ami</name>. c. <date when="1513">1513</date></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-357"><graphic url="CH8_030.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 8.29. Garden of Ry&#x014D;an-ji Temple, Kyoto, a <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi> garden. Muromachi Period</figDesc></figure><p>Daisen-in is one of the subsidiary temple gardens in the great Zen monastery of Daitoku-ji built around <date when="1513">1513</date> by <name type="pname">Kogaku</name> (or <name type="pname">S&#x014D;k&#x014D;</name>, <date when="1464">1464</date>&#x2013;<date when="1548">1548</date>), the founder of the temple, perhaps with the help of the artist <name type="pname">S&#x014D;ami</name> (<date when="1485">1485</date>&#x2013;<date when="1525">1525</date>), whose landscape paintings adorn the interior walls. This small garden, only 12 feet (3.7 meters) wide and 47 feet (14.3 meters) long, is an exquisite rendition of the kind of mountain scenery found in Song painting (fig. 8.28). It is built in the <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi>, or dry garden style, which was perfected in the Muromachi period. Read as intended from left to right, it offers the viewer a "waterfall" of white gravel that comes spilling and pooling between a series of vertically placed rocks, to flow under a small stone "bridge" and then fan out into a beautiful raked gravel "river" where a stone "boat" is seen floating. The remarkable boat-shaped rock once belonged to the shogun-aesthete Yoshimasa, builder of the Silver Pavilion. A curious divider, a narrow roofed bridge, bisects the garden. It is a twentieth-century reconstruction based upon architectural and graphic evidence of a bridge that was in place during the Edo period (<date when="1603">1603</date>&#x2013;<date when="1868">1868</date>). From the side where the raked gravel river flows around rock islands toward an implied ocean beyond the garden wall, a bell-shaped window frames a view of the miniature mountains and waterfall where the "river" has its source.</p><p>Just as Western art at the beginning of the twentieth century transcended representation to achieve abstraction, a similar change occurred in <name type="place">Japan</name> at the beginning of the sixteenth century. This transition to a more reductive expression is evidenced by the creation of the Zen garden at Ry&#x014D;an-ji (Subdued Dragon Temple), which consists of nothing more than fifteen moss-fringed stones placed in a bed of white quartz gravel evenly scored with the long continuous marks of a rake (fig. 8.29).</p><p>Ry&#x014D;an-ji's minimalist <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi> garden has held great fascination for Western architects and garden historians since the <date when="1930">1930</date>s when, conditioned by modernism, they began to understand its formal principles. Some have sought to understand it in metaphysical terms as well. For these reasons it has been extensively analyzed both allegorically and as a set of mathematical relationships in which five groupings of stones are held within their gravel bed in an arrangement of perfectly balanced tension. Viewed from left to right, this arrangement reads as follows: five stones, then two, next three, again two, and finally three stones. Sitting at any point on the veranda, the viewer will always find one stone is hidden from sight. Like that of a painting by the Dutch artist <name type="pname">Piet Mondrian</name> (<date when="1872">1872</date>&#x2013;<date when="1944">1944</date>), the compositional balance of this garden can only be grasped intuitively, not analyzed logically. Neither mathematical explanation nor allegorical meaning can be attached to it. To achieve either would rob it of its enigmatic quality and thereby make it less satisfying from a Zen perspective, as the inexplicability it offers is fundamental to Zen experience and an intrinsic factor in its design. Its true power can only be felt if one is able to experience it over an extended period of quiet meditation and without the distraction of tourists. To appreciate fully its power as a work of art, one must suspend thought and enjoy not only the dynamic stasis of the rocks and the rhythmic lines running through the white gravel, but also the warm buff tones of the unassuming earthen wall with its tile roof and the borrowed scenery beyond it.</p></div><div type="subsection"><pb n="303"/><pb n="303" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Opulence and Restraint: <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> and <name type="pname">Sen no Riky&#x016B;</name></hi></hi></head><p>Japanese art, including garden art, demonstrates the richness of restraint and the power of understatement. But Japanese cultural history is not one unbroken chain of aesthetic refinement in which the modernist dictum of "less is more" is made continually manifest. At the opposite end of the spectrum from the austerity of Ry&#x014D;an-ji are the gardens such as the one at Samb&#x014D;-in, created during the rule of <name type="pname">Toyotomi Hideyoshi</name> (<date when="1536">1536</date>&#x2013;<date when="1598">1598</date>), the second of three generals who united <name type="place">Japan</name> in the late sixteenth century after a prolonged period of civil war. <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> quickly maneuvered himself into the title of <hi rend="italic">kampaku</hi>. From that position as intermediary between the emperor and court officials, he brazenly reduced them to impotence and dependency and made himself dictator. His alliances with, and dominance over, <name type="place">Japan</name>'s other feudal warlords concentrated much of the country's wealth in his hands. Of plebian birth rather than part of the samurai aristocracy, he lacked early training in Zen aesthetics, and it is thus not surprising that he often used this wealth to indulge his desire for opulence.</p><p>Architectural gilding was the order of the day in the huge buildings <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> erected. On the site of the old Imperial Palace, he put up the Jurakutei, his moat-surrounded Kyoto castle. There he amassed a huge collection of specimen rocks, gifts from his subject lords. But by <date when="1588">1588</date> he had the Jurakutei dismantled and some of its buildings moved to his residence, Osaka Castle, and to the new palace he had built at Fushimi. The latter was located in the southern Kyoto suburb known as the Momoyama district; from it comes the name of the Momoyama period (<date when="1573">1573</date>&#x2013;<date when="1603">1603</date>), which is synchronous with the hegemony of <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> and the rulers immediately preceding and following him. After <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name>'s death, Fushimi Castle and its exotic gardens containing sago palm trees were also dismantled. The stones from his lavish Tiger Glen, or Kokei Garden, were transferred to the temple of Nishi Hongan-ji, and the impressive ceremonial architecture of Fushimi was disassembled and redistributed to this and other temples in and around Kyoto.</p><p>In the Eastern Hills, not far from the site of Fushimi Castle, <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> decided to refurbish the garden of Samb&#x014D;-in, a subtemple of Dai-go-ji, in preparation for a massive spring outing to view cherry blossoms. Although <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> died before the garden could be finished, the abbot Gien of Daigo-ji supervised the completion of this richly conceived garden (fig. 8.30). Many of the choice rocks from <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name>'s garden at the Jurakutei were transferred to Samb&#x014D;-in, including a highly prized rectangular pale-colored one called the Fujito Stone, which had acquired a certain fame before <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> bought it for five thousand bushels of rice.</p><figure xml:id="fig-358"><graphic url="CH8_031.jpg"/><figDesc>8.30. Garden of Samb&#x014D;-in, Daigo-ji Temple, Kyoto. Momoyama Period</figDesc></figure><p>By this time, rock craftsmen, were employed in the selection and positioning of garden stones. Yoshir&#x014D;, known as Kentei, or Excellent Gardener, worked for twenty years, until <date when="1618">1618</date>, arranging the nearly eight hundred rocks found at Samb&#x014D;-in into a composition that, if somewhat restless, is nevertheless a boldly dynamic expression of the energy invested in garden design in the Momoyama period.</p><p><name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name>'s taste, though opulent, was also broad, and he was interested in the development of the Japanese tea ceremony, <hi rend="italic">cha no yu</hi>, by <name type="pname">Sen no Riky&#x016B;</name> (<date when="1521">1521</date>&#x2013;<date when="1591">1591</date>), who made this secular, aesthetic pursuit into a spiritual experience as well. Originated in Song <name type="place">China</name> and developed in <name type="place">Japan</name> at the Silver Pavilion by the Zen monk Murata Juk&#x014D; (<date when="1423">1423</date>&#x2013;<date when="1502">1502</date>) during the Muromachi era, the tea ceremony became one of the most important and lasting developments of the Momoyama period, deepening the ingrained aestheticism of Japanese culture and giving a new dimension to the refined rusticity of the Japanese garden in which <hi rend="italic">sabi</hi>&#x2014;the mellow agedness produced by weathered stone, mosses, and lichens&#x2014;is highly valued.</p><p>The ritual of the tea ceremony as formulated by <name type="pname">Sen no Riky&#x016B;</name> requires for its enactment a pattern of precise movements, a particular kind of setting, and certain elegantly simple utensils. It is conducted in a small, thatch-roofed hut with wattle-and-daub walls, the rustic simplicity of which is meant to induce a mood of <hi rend="italic">wabi</hi>, refined austerity. Only a small upper window covered with bamboo lattice admits light to the tearoom. Guests must stoop to enter. Inside the tea house, the garden view is intentionally blocked from sight, leaving the focus of the tearoom, which is commonly four-and-a-half tatami mats in size,<ref target="#CH8-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref> upon the <hi rend="italic">tokonoma</hi>, a small alcove wherein a partic<pb n="304"/><pb n="304" type="orig"/>ularly fine scroll and elegantly simple flower arrangement may be displayed. The host enters and begins to prepare tea, as the three or four guests attune their-senses to the gentle hissing of the steam kettle. The host places the tea in a ceramic tea bowl and, with a bamboo whisk, stirs it with precise and practiced motions into a light green foam, then hands the bowl to the most important guest. The tea bowl itself, like every other carefully positioned object in the room, is a focus of aesthetic admiration. After the tea has been drunk, the beauty of the bowl's form and glaze is silently admired. It is then returned to the host, who wipes it clean and prepares tea for the next guest.</p><figure xml:id="fig-359"><graphic url="CH8_032.jpg"/><figDesc>8.31. <hi rend="italic">Tsukubai</hi>, a stone basin for washing hands, Matsuo Tea Ceremony School, Nagoya, <name type="place">Japan</name></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-360"><graphic url="CH8_033.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 8.32. Stone lantern, Katsura Riky&#x016B; Imperial Villa, near Kyoto, <name type="place">Japan</name></figDesc></figure><p>The secluded intimacy of the tea ceremony did not require the same kind of well-composed garden space as that of a temple. What was sought was a means of separation from the busy surrounding world and a way of declaring entry into another realm. This was accomplished by the <hi rend="italic">cha niwa</hi>, or tea garden path, sometimes called <hi rend="italic">roji</hi>, meaning "dewy path." Typically, this is a narrow corridor leading from the street, through a gate made of open-weave bamboo, into a small area where a natural stone basin invites the guest to bend down and wash his hands before stooping again to pass through the small door of the tea house. A fence of bamboo twigs encloses this small garden. Understandably, azaleas or other showy plants are not grown in such a place; a tea garden's most notable aspect is the ground plane itself. Here flat stepping-stones are set within moss. These differ from the stones carefully selected for color, shape, surface modeling, and patina, which are found in other types of Japanese gardens. Strictly utilitarian, stones for the <hi rend="italic">cha niwa</hi> are usually rounded river-washed stones, which speak the language of nature and enhance the atmosphere of rusticity and mood of quiet expectation one experiences upon approaching the tea house.</p><p>The stepping-stone path of the small tea garden actually plays an important role in the development of the Japanese garden overall, being the precursor of the paths of the much larger stroll garden, such as those in the imperial garden of Katsura Riky&#x016B;. The laying of these and other kinds of stones in the ground, with attention paid to size, texture, form, and line, is an art form in itself. This accounts for much of the pleasure one experiences in viewing the ground plane of Japanese gardens.</p><p>Another important feature contributed by the tea garden to other kinds of Japanese gardens is the stone lantern (fig. 8.32). Originally found in Buddhist temples, where they were lit for votive offerings, these lanterns were appropriated by the tea garden in order to illuminate at night the path and the stone hand-washing laver near the tea house (fig. 8.31). They became admired objects in their own right and were soon being copied and then designed by tea masters in a manner that was different from that of their temple prototypes.</p><p>Today the separate schools for tea instruction begun by <name type="pname">Sen no Riky&#x016B;</name>'s three great-grandsons&#x2014;<name type="pname">Ura Senke</name>, <name type="pname">Omote Senke</name>, and <name type="pname">Mushan&#x00F4;koji Senke</name>&#x2014;still exist with their own tea gardens in Kyoto. Although many old tea gardens have vanished, the popularity of the tea ceremony is such that many new ones can be found both in <name type="place">Japan</name> and abroad.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Edo Period: Katsura Riky&#x016B;</hi></hi></head><p>Following <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name>'s death, his five-year-old son <name type="pname">Hideyori</name> inherited his authority. The samurai leader <name type="pname">Tokugawa Ieyasu</name> (<date when="1542">1542</date>&#x2013;<date when="1616">1616</date>), who had been appointed as one of the boy's five guardians, soon maneuvered himself into a position of supremacy. This provoked other barons into a power struggle against him, leading to civil conflict, a situation always imminent in <name type="place">Japan</name>'s feudal society. <name type="pname">Ieyasu</name> triumphed over his opponents in <date when="1600">1600</date>, assuming for himself the role of all-powerful shogun in <date when="1603">1603</date>. He moved to Edo, now <name type="place">Tokyo</name>, and from his castle there, he systematically circumscribed the actions of the country's other strong families.</p><p>The Edo period (<date when="1603">1603</date>&#x2013;<date when="1867">1867</date>), as the two-and-onehalf-century era of <name type="pname">Tokugawa</name> rule is called, was characterized by rigid control of every aspect of Japanese life. Whatever power remained to the emasculated emperor and court was further curtailed by official rules that limited their role exclusively to scholarship and the arts. As such, they were seen as respected custodians of Japanese aesthetics, nothing more. Furthermore, in the the <name type="pname">Tokugawa</name> shoguns' zeal for absolutist control over<pb n="305"/><pb n="305" type="orig"/>all aspects of Japanese life, they expelled all Christian missionaries and most foreign traders.</p><p>It is understandable that, under such circumstances, escapist impulses would drive the alienated aristocracy to new aesthetic enterprise. <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name> (<date when="1579">1579</date>&#x2013;<date when="1647">1647</date>), although himself a <hi rend="italic">daimyo</hi>, or feudal lord, was a student of <name type="pname">Sen no Riky&#x016B;</name>'s leading disciple, the tea master <name type="pname">Furuta Oribe</name> (<date when="1544">1544</date>&#x2013;<date when="1615">1615</date>). As a tea master himself, <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name> took a natural interest in ceramics, sponsoring the work of various kilns in his province, and as a student of poetry, a noted calligrapher and a garden designer, he was a leading figure in this chapter of <name type="place">Japan</name>'s cultural life.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Kirei sabi</hi> (elegant beauty infused with a weathered rustic quality) is the name that attempts to capture the aesthetic ideal promoted by <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name>. It is "beautiful" in that it harks back to the graceful grandeur of the Heian period and expresses an understandable longing on the part of the court in the Edo era for the days of Heian glory, before the emperor had been robbed of his power. It is "rustic" in that it expresses the pastoral simplicity and closeness to nature advocated by <name type="pname">Sen no Riky&#x016B;</name>.</p><p>Although as aristocratic in origin as the Italian and French gardens with which it is contemporary, the air of understatement in <hi rend="italic">kirei sabi</hi> is at the opposite extreme from the energetic grandeur of their related styles. In his garden designs, <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name> substituted a diagonal approach for the axial thrust found in Italian villa gardens and at <name type="place">Versailles</name>. This promotes a zigzag movement, creating scenic "surprises" as one travels along a prescribed garden route. The technique of hide-and-reveal is, in fact, the essence of the stroll garden, a concept that substitutes movement through a sequence of garden spaces for the stationary viewing mandated by the designs of most <hi rend="italic">shinden</hi>-style gardens and Zen temple gardens. Within the stroll garden, the stepping-stone path of the tea garden is therefore employed for a new purpose: the kinetic experience of landscape.</p><p>Because the spirit of Katsura Villa epitomizes <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name>'s style of <hi rend="italic">kirei sabi</hi> so perfectly, he has been frequently credited as its designer, although there is no record of his actual participation. Widely regarded as a paragon among gardens, Katsura demonstrates the flowering of aesthetic refinement that occurred when, deprived of all involvement in affairs of state, a member of the imperial family, handsomely supported by gifts from the shogun, devoted his life to building a private never-never land.</p><p>Katsura's origins as a garden derive from a problem presented by Imperial <name type="pname">Prince Toshihito</name> (<date when="1571">1571</date>&#x2013;<date when="1629">1629</date>), whom <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> adopted before the latter's own son and heir was born. When <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name> finally produced a biological heir in <date when="1590">1590</date>, he established <name type="pname">Toshihito</name> as the head of a collateral imperial line. In addition, he gave him a sizable grant of land, which was exchanged for another on the banks of the Katsura River to the west of the city around <date when="1605">1605</date>. A few years later, <name type="pname">Prince Toshihito</name> began building a modest country retreat there, and in the summer of <date when="1616">1616</date>, he invited a group of nobles, poets, and dancers to a festive outing in his "little tea house in the Melon Patch." <name type="pname">Prince Toshihito</name> enjoyed good relations with the shogun as well as a generous income. Thus secure, he was able to expand his building program on his Katsura estate, and by the time of his death in <date when="1629">1629</date>, the place had become a cultural mecca for poets, artists, and garden lovers.</p><p>Although the country house at Katsura was allowed to deteriorate immediately following <name type="pname">Prince Toshihito</name>'s death, its fortunes were soon revived by his son, young <name type="pname">Prince Toshitada</name> (<date when="1619">1619</date>&#x2013;<date when="1662">1662</date>). In <date when="1632">1632</date>, the thirteen-year-old boy was part of a delegation visiting Iemitsu, the third and most powerful shogun of the <name type="pname">Tokugawa</name> line, from which he came away with a farewell gift of a thousand pieces of silver and thirty kimonos. Apparently the young man continued to enjoy the shogun's largesse, and he was able during his lifetime to bring the estate to its full glory as an important cultural center and shining example of the <hi rend="italic">shoin</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">shoin zukuri</hi>, style of architecture and the <hi rend="italic">kirei sabi</hi> aesthetic in garden art (fig. 8.33).</p><figure xml:id="fig-361"><graphic url="CH8_034.jpg"/><figDesc>8.33. Aerial view of Katsura Villa, Kyoto. Early Edo Period</figDesc></figure><p>Almost from the beginning, <name type="pname">Prince Toshitada</name> conceived of the garden as a setting for a series of tea houses. The first, the Geppa-r&#x014D;, or Moon Wave Tower, was built close to the main house. Not far from this tea house, one of the villa's several rustic earth-covered bridges carries the visitor to the Inner Gate. The gate's quiet beauty resides in its harmonious proportions and the carefully crafted details of its<pb n="306"/><pb n="306" type="orig"/>simple bamboo-and-thatch roof. The design of the paths and the varied patterns of the stone paving around this gate and in the courtyard create a subtly textured ground plane (fig. 8.34).</p><figure xml:id="fig-362"><graphic url="CH8_035.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 8.34. Paving patterns, Inner Gate and courtyard, Katsura</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-363"><graphic url="CH8_036.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Far right:</hi> 8.35. Two earthen bridges, Katsura, Kyoto</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-364"><graphic url="CH8_037.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 8.36. Sh&#x014D;ka-tei, Katsura, Kyoto, with ascending stepping stones</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-365"><graphic url="CH8_038.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Bottom:</hi> 8.37. Katsura Villa Garden, from a room of the Old Shoin, looking across moon-viewing platform</figDesc></figure><p>In <date when="1645">1645</date>, <name type="pname">Prince Toshitada</name> journeyed to Edo to request further financial aid from the shogun and during his travels studied the architecture of several notable tea houses. Soon he was hosting tea parties as well as nocturnal moon-viewing and boating parties at Katsura, and by <date when="1649">1649</date>, documents record that there were, in addition to the Geppa-r&#x014D;, four more tea houses. Three of these can still be seen today: the Sh&#x014D;kin-tei, or Pine Lute Pavilion; the Sh&#x014D;ka-tei, or Flower Appreciation Pavilion; and the Sh&#x014D;i-ken, or Laughing Thoughts Pavilion. Katsura's tea house architecture derives from that of rustic farm buildings; the elegance and simplicity with which this vernacular style has been adapted to a refined purpose lies at the heart of the <hi rend="italic">kirei sabi</hi> aesthetic.</p><p>Stroll gardens like that of Katsura suggest prescribed routes. Stepping-stone paths direct the visitor's footsteps from one to another of these tea houses, each exquisitely sited as a feature within the larger landscape. The experience is delightfully disorienting as one repeatedly changes direction and appreciates each new and skillfully arranged view. Like the tea houses, the paths have poetic names such as Maple Riding Lane and Plum Riding Lane. Some of the villa's landscapes evoke such famous Japanese scenes as the Bridge of Heaven, here abstracted and depicted at a reduced scale. The topography is graded to produce "mountains," and the stepping stones, like those approaching the Sh&#x014D;ka-tei, are set into these hillsides so skillfully that one has the sensation of real ascent although the gentle topography rises only slightly (fig. 8.36). Where the grade is depressed, as in the Valley of Fireflies, wood and earthen bridges or stone slab bridges ease the way (fig. 8.35).</p><p>The same hide-and-reveal tactics, which pleasantly surprise with views that are unexpected, are employed within the house itself. One always approaches a house obliquely and, once inside, never approaches the main room axially, so that a view may be withheld until one comes upon it, perceiving it within a frame of <hi rend="italic">shoji</hi> (fig. 8.37). Elevated on a high foundation, the house loses connection with the ground plane; the sense of spatial interpenetration between interior and exterior is absent; and the framed garden views seem to be courtly paintings of nature, rather than the reality of nature apprehended at close range.</p><p>While the dreamworld of Katsura can be appreciated for its intrinsic qualities and without association, much of the scenery of this famous garden is probably based upon literary models, such as <name type="pname">Lady<pb n="307"/><pb n="307" type="orig"/>Murasaki</name>'s descriptions of Heian gardens in <hi rend="italic">The Tale of Genji</hi>. We may assume that, while <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name> may have advised <name type="pname">Prince Toshitada</name> from time to time, this great stroll garden, with its echoes of Heian beauty interwoven with rustic quietude, was the work of the scholarly prince himself, who, disenfranchised from affairs of state, found in the creation of Katsura a deeply engrossing pastime. In the <date when="1930">1930</date>s, Katsura was belatedly recognized by the Japanese as a national treasure. Preserved and maintained, it stands today as a monument to the prince and the triumph, in the long term, of art over the politics of power.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Edo Period: Shugakuin Riky&#x016B;</hi></hi></head><p>Kyoto boasts one other perfectly preserved imperial garden in the <hi rend="italic">kirei sabi</hi> style of <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name>: <name type="pname">Shugakuin Riky&#x016B;</name>. Here, in the scenic northeastern hills, an idyllic stroll garden with scattered tea houses incorporates to an even greater degree than Katsura does, the design technique of <hi rend="italic">shakkei</hi>, or borrowed scenery. This landscape with its carefully wrought views beyond the limits of the garden was created under similar circumstances and at approximately the same time as Katsura by <name type="pname">Prince Toshitada</name>'s uncle, the retired emperor <name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name> (<date when="1596">1596</date>&#x2013;<date when="1680">1680</date>).</p><p>Angered by the shogun's heavy-handed supervision of imperial affairs, <name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name> abruptly resigned in favor of his daughter in <date when="1629">1629</date>. Freed from ceremonial responsibility, he first turned his attentions to <name type="pname">Sent&#x014D; Gosho</name>, meaning "Retired Emperor's Villa," the palace and garden he planned with <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name>. After this project was completed, <name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name> was ready to search for a site for a country retreat. This was undertaken with the encouragement of <name type="pname">Tokugawa Iemitsu</name>, who, in an effort to ingratiate himself with the imperial court in Kyoto and appease <name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name>'s smoldering frustrations, had increased his income more than threefold.</p><p>Thus furnished with a generous stipend, <name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name> selected a site of seventy-three acres in the beautiful Mount Hiei foothills, approximately 450 feet (137 meters) above sea level, near Shugakuin Temple, and there, by the early <date when="1650">1650</date>s, he was at work creating a landscape garden. <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name> was dead by this time, but like Henry Hoare, the owner-creator of Stourhead&#x2014;the English garden that is most similar to Shugakuin&#x2014;<name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name> was a sufficient artist in his own right to apply the lessons of Ensh&#x016B; in a wholly original manner. Relying on the site's superior inherent scenic potential, he created a design that is more relaxed and natural than that of Katsura.</p><p>Shugakuin now comprises three separate villa gardens. Placed at different elevations among terraced rice fields, these were connected by simple trails, replaced at the end of the nineteenth century by the tree-bordered gravel paths we find today. The garden surrounding the Lower Villa contains a small pond and three carved stone lanterns. The Middle Villa was used by one of <name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name>'s daughters as an abbess's residence when she became a nun in <date when="1680">1680</date> and founded a temple nearby. Its garden also contains a pond, as well as a lawn and a wide-spreading umbrella pine. But the full range of <name type="pname">Go-Mizunoo</name>'s genius is not apparent until one passes through cultivated rice fields and ascends the slope to the Upper Villa.</p><figure xml:id="fig-366"><graphic url="CH8_039.jpg"/><figDesc>8.38. Upper Garden, view of borrowed scenery from Ry&#x016B;'untei Tea House to Yokory&#x016B;-chi Pond, Shugakuin, Kyoto. Late Momoyama / Early Edo Period</figDesc></figure><p>The passage upward from the Imperial Gate, the point of entry to this part of Shugakuin, is a narrow set of stairs constricted by tall hedges on either side. It is only after emerging into the sunlight at the top of the slope that one sees the panorama of the lake, called Yokury&#x016B;-chi, or Bathing Dragon Pond, and the borrowed scenery of the gently undulating mountains to the northwest (fig. 8.38). The lake is supported by a massive terraced dam on its west bank, which is concealed by a long, flat-topped, stepped hedge com<pb n="308"/><pb n="308" type="orig"/>posed of approximately forty kinds of shrubs, with an occasional tree growing in it. The vantage point for this sight is a delicate tea house, the Rin'un-tei, or Pavilion in the Clouds.</p><figure xml:id="fig-367"><graphic url="CH8_040.jpg"/><figDesc>8.39. Stone paving, <name type="pname">Senshi-dai</name>, or Poem-Washing Platform, in front of the Rin'un-tei Tea House, Shugakuin, Upper Villa</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-368"><graphic url="CH8_041.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 8.40. Aerial view of Shugakuin Villa Garden's lake with its circuit path and surrounding agricultural landscape</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-369"><graphic url="CH8_042.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Right:</hi> 8.41. Rock arrangement (called Kamejima, or Tortoise Island) and clipped shrubbery, Garden of Konchi-in Temple, Kyoto. Early Edo Period</figDesc></figure><p>Even here, where the technique of borrowed scenery reaches its consummate expression, the designer paid great attention to the texture of the ground plane. For instance, in front of the tea house at the <name type="pname">Senshi-dai</name>, or Poem-Washing Platform, built to offer the magnificent view, there is a paved apron embedded with stones set singly and in groups of two and three. It illustrates, like so many other design details, the casual-seeming, but carefully considered, artistry we have come to expect in Japanese gardens where almost nothing is left to chance (fig. 8.39).</p><p>A path descends from the hill of the Rin'un-tei to make a counterclockwise circuit around the lake. The lake was used for pleasure boating, and its islands, one of which has a small pavilion, could be visited. The bridges that connect them to one another and the shore are scenic elements in a series of continually shifting views as one continues around the lake (fig. 8.40). On the north shore, on the site of the present boathouse, stood the Shishi-sai, a summerhouse where guests might be carried upon arrival to refresh themselves before proceeding clockwise around the lake and up a circuitous path to the Rin'un-tei. Once arrived, they could enjoy, as a sudden surprise, the view of the scenic panorama that unfolds beyond the confines of the garden.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Other Edo and Modern Gardens</hi></hi></head><p>Increasingly, garden design became less the realm of Zen priests and gifted aristocratic amateurs and more the province of professional gardeners, whose guiding influence remained <name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name>. <hi rend="italic">H&#x014D;j&#x014D;</hi> gardens (gardens designed in conjunction with the main building of a temple, often called the Abbot's Quarters) increased during the seventeenth century. This is due in part to the priest <name type="pname">Ishin-S&#x016B;den</name> (<date when="1564">1564</date>&#x2013;<date when="1632">1632</date>), who served as an intermediary between the <name type="pname">Tokugawa</name> shogunate and the temple administrators, securing support for the latter's construction projects. Often these were <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi>, or dry gardens, although they might contain rock arrangements, frequently ones suggesting the legendary crane or tortoise. The designs of these Edo period gardens were therefore less austere and ethereal than those of earlier Zen gardens such as Ry&#x014D;an-ji.</p><p><name type="pname">Kobori Ensh&#x016B;</name> himself designed the gardens at Konchi-in, a subtemple of Nanzen-ji where <name type="pname">IshinSuden</name> had his headquarters, after one of the fine buildings from <name type="pname">Hideyoshi</name>'s Fushimi Castle in Kyoto was moved there in <date when="1611">1611</date>. His vigorous <hi rend="italic">kare sansui</hi> design employs rock arrangements that include crane and tortoise imagery. In addition to its rock compositions and bed of raked white gravel, the garden of Konchi-in contains a backdrop of carefully pruned shrubs (fig. 8.41). Clipped shrubbery, the massive stepped hedge of Shugakuin, and the extraordinary continuously curving one at Daichi-ji&#x2014;an undulating, pulsating animal-like mass, which is the entire focus of the garden&#x2014;are additional hallmarks of Ensh&#x016B;'s boldly original style (fig. 8.42). The use of meticulously clipped shrubs, rather than rocks, as the principal elements in garden design is also found at Shisend&#x014D; (Hall of the Immortal Poets), the garden retreat built by <name type="pname">Ishikawa J&#x014D;zan</name> (<date when="1583">1583</date>&#x2013;<date when="1672">1672</date>), a <name type="pname">Tokugawa</name> dissident who retired here to a life of scholarship in <date when="1636">1636</date> (fig. 8.43). This garden contrasts with the lofty remoteness of the framed views seen from the interior of the <hi rend="italic">shoin</hi> at Katsura; at Konchi-in, interior and garden space interpenetrate in delightful intimacy by way of the intermediate space of the wooden veranda.</p><p>Other characteristic features of Edo period gardens are the sand mounds with surfaces raked by Japanese priests into abstract designs that anticipate by<pb n="309"/><pb n="309" type="orig"/>nearly four centuries the patterned landscape scarification one observes in the earth art of our own time. One enters H&#x00F4;nen-in, a temple of the J&#x014D;do sect of Buddhism, from a roofed gate that provides a platform for viewing a pair of mounds, the surfaces of which are raked with subtle delicacy. Nearby, at the Muromachi period villa-turned-temple garden of Ginkaku-ji, there is a pair of sand mounds dating from the Edo era. One of these takes the form of a truncated cone, thought to recall Mount Fuji or the central mountain of Buddhist myth, and the other, a horizontal rectangle, is known as the "Sea of Silver Sand" because its reflective white surface provided an added attraction during moon-viewing parties (fig. 8.44).</p><p>By the eighteenth century, the tradition of Japanese garden art was becoming devitalized. Many gardens were built, but their designers substituted a more formulaic approach for the deeply felt spiritual and aesthetic impulses that had nourished the tradition in earlier times. The rise of <name type="place">Japan</name>'s prosperous merchant class created a large number of property owners, and this stimulated the demand for interior courtyard gardens. Nurseries and stone yards were established where plants, rocks, and lanterns could be purchased.</p><p>The appearance of the American naval commander <name type="pname">Commodore Perry</name> in <name type="place">Tokyo Bay</name> in <date when="1853">1853</date> brought about a decisive change in Japanese government and culture. Powerless in the face of this challenge to <name type="place">Japan</name>'s long-standing isolationist policy, the <name type="pname">Tokugawa</name> shogunate, whose iron grip depended upon military might, was unable to maintain its control. Thus ended two-and-a-half centuries of seclusion from the rest of the world. In <date when="1868">1868</date>, the emperor was restored to power and took up residence in Edo, which was renamed <name type="place">Tokyo</name>, meaning "Eastern Capital." The Meiji Restoration&#x2014;the remolding of Japanese culture during the last half of the nineteenth century&#x2014;instituted constitutional government, did away with many complex rules of social stratification, and brought about other changes.</p><p>Rapid Westernization transformed the Japanese garden. In <name type="place">Tokyo</name>, an English-style lawn was installed at the Shinjuku Imperial Garden, and businessmen and financiers built similarly hybrid landscapes. But a more profound design integration of two such opposite traditions would necessarily await a later day when the modernist movement made the West ready to receive inspiration from the spare and elegant compositional devices found in Japanese gardens&#x2014;a sympathetic alliance with nature, borrowed scenery, hide-and-reveal compositional technique, rock artistry, and focus upon ground-plane patterns and textures.</p><figure xml:id="fig-370"><graphic url="CH8_043.jpg"/><figDesc>8.42. Garden of Daichi-ji Temple, Shiga Prefecture. These undulating, rounded, closely clipped shrubs represent the Seven Lucky Gods.</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-371"><graphic url="CH8_044.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below</hi>; 8.43. Gardener pruning azalea, Shisend&#x014D; (Hall of Immortal Poets), Kyoto, garden built by <name type="pname">Ishikawa J&#x014D;zan</name>. Early Edo Period</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-372"><graphic url="CH8_045.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Bottom:</hi> 8.44. View from Ginkaku Pavilion of Ginshadan (white sand in a waved design) and Kogetsudai (mountain shape) in front of main hall, Ginkaku-ji Temple, Kyoto. Pavilion, Muromachi Period; sand garden, Edo Period</figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><pb n="310"/><pb n="310" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Chapter Eight</hi></hi></head><note xml:id="CH8-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p>Although the Chinese garden had in common with the Western Picturesque garden a penchant for irregularity and naturalistic effects, it was much more compressed and tightly coiled as a work of art, acting as a symbolic representation of the entire natural world. This aesthetic in turn provided the impetus for the creation of the Japanese garden, in which the nexus between art and nature was bolstered by the tradition of <name type="pname">Shinto</name> religion and by the further development of Buddhist philosophy after its importation from <name type="place">China</name>. That Buddhism coexisted with, rather than destroyed, <name type="pname">Shinto</name> religion only strengthened the Japanese bond with nature. This development, which began toward the end of the sixth century <hi rend="smallcaps">c.e.</hi>, displays a consistent Japanese ability consciously to assimilate foreign influences into its cultural core, in the process re-forming them into an authentically indigenous expression.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p><hi rend="italic">Kami</hi>, discernible only through faith, exert a mysterious creative and harmonizing influence (.<hi rend="italic">musubi</hi>) on human life. Tutelary <hi rend="italic">kami</hi>. which are associated with individual clans, are revered at shrines. They reveal to worshipers the truthful way or will (<hi rend="italic">makoto</hi>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p><hi rend="italic">Xian</hi> were also believed to inhabit the Kunlun Mountains in the distant west.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Claudia Brown</name>, "Chinese Scholars' Rocks and the Land of Immortals: Some Insights from Painting," <hi rend="italic">Worlds Within Worlds: The <name type="pname">Richard Rosenblum</name> Collection of Chinese Scholars' Rocks</hi>, ed. <name type="pname">Robert D. Mowry</name> (<name type="place">Cambridge, Mass.</name>: Harvard University Art Museums, <date when="1997">1997</date>), pp. 57&#x2013;83.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p>For a description of Shanglin Park and several other Chinese landscapes subsequently discussed in this chapter I am indebted especially to <name type="pname">Maggie Keswick</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Chinese Garden: History, Art &amp; Architecture</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Rizzoli, <date when="1978">1978</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p>The following encapsulated discussion and quotations are derived from <name type="pname">Ji Cheng</name>, <hi rend="italic">Yuan Ye</hi>. trans. <name type="pname">Alison Hardie</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Craft of Gardens</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, <date when="1988">1988</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p>For the best contemporary English translation of this literary masterpiece, see <name type="pname">Cao Xueqin</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Stone</hi> (Harmondsworth, Middlesex, <name type="place">England</name>: Penguin Books, vols. 1&#x2013;3, trans. <name type="pname">David Hawkes</name>, <date when="1973">1973</date>&#x2013;<date when="1980">80</date>; vols. 4&#x2013;5, trans. <name type="pname">John Minford</name>, <date when="1982">1982</date>&#x2013;<date when="1986">86</date>). The following quotations describing the building of the garden and the naming of its various parts are found in vol. 1, chap. 17.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Richard E. Strassberg</name>, trans., <hi rend="italic">Inscribed Landscapes: Travel Writing from Imperial <name type="place">China</name></hi> (<name type="place">Berkeley</name>: University of California Press, <date when="1994">1994</date>), p. 15.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p>The many pleasure pavilions built by <name type="pname">Khubilai Khan</name> and subsequent emperors around these lakes have fallen into ruin over the centuries. Fortunately for posterity, the Chinese garden scholar <name type="pname">Osvald Sir&#x00E9;n</name> was given permission in the <date when="1920">1920</date>s to wander at his pleasure within the precincts of the tea palaces before they had become accessible to the general public, and his beautiful photographs preserve for us at least an evocation of their haunting poetry. See <name type="pname">Osvald Sir&#x00E9;n</name>, <hi rend="italic">Gardens of <name type="place">China</name></hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: The Ronald Tree Press Company, <date when="1949">1949</date>), pl. 145&#x2013;76.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p>For an excellent summary of the <hi rend="italic">Sakuteiki</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Treatise on Garden Making</hi>, see <name type="pname">Loraine Kuck</name>, <hi rend="italic">The World of the Japanese Garden: From Chinese Origins to Modern Landscape Art</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Weatherhill. <date when="1968">1968</date>), pp. 91&#x2013;93. Kuck's history of the Japanese garden is an invaluable reference work.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p>Chang'an was approximately 6 miles (9.7 kilometers) from east to west and 5.25 miles (8.5 kilometers) north to south. Kyoto, hemmed in by hills, could only expand to the south.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p>See <name type="pname">Murasaki Shikibu</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Tale of Genji</hi>, trans. <name type="pname">Edward G. Seidensticker</name> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Alfred A. Knopf</name>, <date when="1985">1985</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p>The Golden Pavilion that one sees today is a generally faithful copy of the original, which was destroyed in <date when="1950">1950</date> by an arsonist protesting the post-World War II commercialization of the Buddhist Church.</p></note><note xml:id="CH8-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p>A tatami mat measures approximately 3 by 6 feet (.9 by 1.8 meters).</p></note></div></div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>