<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xslt" href="../../frameworks/tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/html/tei.xsl"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY</title>
                <author>ELIZABETH BARLOW ROGERS</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>HARRY N. ABRAMS, INC.,</publisher>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>LANDSCAPE DESIGN A CULTURAL AND ARCHITECTURAL HISTORY by ELIZABETH BARLOW
                    ROGERS</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div type="chapter"><pb n="402"/><pb n="402" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="bold">CHAPTER TWELVE SOCIAL UTOPIAS: MODERNISM AND CITY PLANNING</hi></head><figure xml:id="fig-498"><graphic url="CH12_001.jpg"/></figure><p>By <date when="1900">1900</date>, industrial power had vastly multiplied the products of human manufacture and consumption and greatly increased the speed with which goods and people were transported to both near and distant parts. Consequent social transformations accelerated the uprooting of age-old agrarian traditions, emptying villages of their young people and causing the continued exponential growth of cities beyond all previous conceptions of normative urban size. In spite of these dislocations and changes, a widely shared optimism and a broad belief in the possibilities for universal progress in the material conditions of human life prevailed. Many people had begun to fully comprehend the capability of Machine Age means of production to radically expand economies as industrial capitalism opened new markets for a growing abundance of lowcost goods. The ease of production had the obvious potential of raising the living standards of a broad spectrum of humanity, making the producers of wealth consumers as well. The rapid advances in industrial technology that added to individual well-being and made the domestic realm more comfortable also made possible the great public works projects that are the signal manifestations of the modern industrial city. Indeed, modern urbanism and industrial capitalism are inextricably allied, as we saw in our discussion of Haussmann's transformation of <name type="place">Paris</name> between <date when="1850">1850</date> and <date when="1870">1870</date>.</p><p>A growing democratic spirit and the moral purpose this implied inspired many visionary attempts to redress inequalities within existing and developing capitalist societies. Reformers wished to remedy the ills of poverty and plan optimal environments for all classes of humanity. Romanticism and its concomitant impulse toward revolution had already laid the cultural groundwork for respect of individual rights. Enlightenment rationalism&#x2014;now a broadly shared attitude toward scientific inquiry and technical problem solving&#x2014; assumed that reason could readily dictate remedies for the wants and injustices that had heretofore been the lot of humankind.</p><p>Although proponents of bourgeois capitalist culture&#x2014;the economic engine that propelled the Industrial Revolution&#x2014;refuted the theories of Karl Marx (<date when="1818">1818</date>&#x2013;<date when="1883">1883</date>), they were nonetheless seminal to the ethos of modern Western society. Marx proclaimed that the aspirations of civilization cloaked a class struggle for material power. He saw how industrialization had attracted workers from the land, forcing them into slums within hugely distended metropolitan areas. He conceived socialist communism as a comprehensive political system to replace capitalism and redistribute wealth so that working-class people would enjoy the fruits of their labor. Although he had nothing to say about urban planning, the movement to improve urban living conditions gained momentum through Marx's critique, and a spirit of Marxist progressive reform prevailed even among those who did not seek to radically alter the premises of capitalist societies and their governments.</p><p>The American economist Henry George (<date when="1839">1839</date>&#x2013;<date when="1897">1897</date>) had argued in <hi rend="italic">Progress and Poverty</hi> (<date when="1879">1879</date>) that the abolition of other taxes in favor of a single tax on the appreciation in value of unimproved real estate would transfer this unearned wealth to the government for redistribution in the form of public works. Although not supported by many political leaders or economists, George exerted a strong influence among reformers in Britain and <name type="place">America</name>, among whom Ebenezer Howard, father of the Garden City movement, figured prominently. Another American, Thorstein Veblen (<date when="1857">1857</date>- <date when="1929">1929</date>), a radical economist, teacher, and author, examined economic history through an evolutionary lens in his trenchant critique, <hi rend="italic">The Theory of the Leisure Class</hi> (<date when="1899">1899</date>). He coined the term "conspicuous consumption" to describe manifestations of nonproductive leisure as a means of displaying wealth. The individual breadwinner with a nonworking wife was the most obvious example of what Veblen meant by conspicuous consumption.</p><p>These arguments those put forth by Peter Kropotkin (<date when="1842">1842</date>&#x2014; <date when="1921">1921</date>), a Russian nobleman who advocated a protocommunist philosophy of social cooperation, and by British playwright George<pb n="403"/><pb n="403" type="orig"/><name type="pname">Bernard Shaw</name> (<date when="1856">1856</date>&#x2013;<date when="1950">1950</date>) and his fellow members of the Fabian Society,<ref target="#CH12-n1"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">1</hi></hi></ref>an organization promoting evolutionary socialism, provided the fertile ground that nurtured utopian visions as social thinkers focused their attention upon the problems of the recently formed mass society living in big cities. Middle-class mores still confined women's roles to the domestic sphere, although rates of labor-force participation for women grew steadily throughout the twentieth century. Of great importance in terms of urbanism, many women were active as professional volunteers in the reforms of the Progressive Era&#x2014;the period beginning in the early part of the twentieth century in which a number of social improvements in the areas of housing, education, parks, social welfare, and civil service were initiated. Jane Addams (<date when="1860">1860</date>&#x2013;<date when="1935">1935</date>), social worker, founder of the Hull House&#x2014;the model for other settlement houses in America&#x2014;feminist, and winner of the Nobel Peace Prize in <date when="1931">1931</date>, was perhaps the most notable among the numerous dedicated women reformers ministering to the urban masses.</p><p>As advocates of the potential benefits of technology and engineering&#x2014;provided these were applied to a broad social agenda rather than merely to amassing spectacular profits for capitalists&#x2014; Progressive Era social reformers did not recoil from the Machine Age. They viewed it hopefully as the long-awaited instrument of relief from human misery. They were confident that the forces of industrial progress, when applied rationally to the problems of urban development, could improve the human condition by offering wholesome housing alternatives to the immigrant hordes in crowded slums and by providing the swelling ranks of urban dwellers with ready contact with nature. Although private capital was essential, they saw municipal and state governments or special-purpose public corporations as the logical sponsors of large-scale, urban projects because these legally chartered bodies had the power necessary to assemble large parcels of land and undertake the construction of roads, rail lines, and utilities. Thus, their social agenda went hand in hand with enlargement of the responsibilities of government and the establishment of quasi-governmental authorities.</p><p>Transportation technologies have been hugely influential in fostering the process of metropolitan growth, which has often been guided by the agendas of corporations as much as by regional planners. Although railroads greatly altered cities, making possible the growth of suburbs and interurban transportation networks, the automobile has had even greater consequences, especially in the United States. Of particular significance to the subject of landscape design, automobile mass production after <date when="1913">1913</date> led to the multiplication of nonurban recreational parks and the creation of exurban automobile parkways of a different scale and design configuration than the intra-urban boulevardlike ones planned in an era of carriage transportation. In addition to opening the countryside to vacationers, the automobile expanded urban form beyond its previous enlargement by rail lines. The driver's ability to steer the car along routes of individual choice stimulated the infilling of open lands between previously established corridors of rail-related metropolitan settlement with new roadways and networks of local streets. With the spread of suburbs, which were no longer tethered to rail lines, the urban fabric was loosened to the point where, at least in the land-rich United States, freestanding dwellings surrounded by lawns became the norm, particularly after New Deal government-sponsored home mortgage programs and post&#x2014;World War II mortgage loans for veterans stimulated mass-produced tract housing. Cities as visibly discrete entities ceased to exist, becoming instead conurbations, or Standard Metropolitan Areas as census statisticians now refer to them.</p><p>Haussmann and Olmsted had demonstrated ways to conceptualize the city in technical and recreational terms. Now, at the beginning of the twentieth century, a second generation of urban planners applied this process to a more-than-metropolitan scale that encompassed the surrounding region. These planners went beyond the notion of greening the urban mass with landscaped squares and parks connected by intra-urban parkways. They envisioned the dispersal of industry and populations into the countryside, where living conditions could be made more humane and healthy than in the increasingly congested cities. Conceptual planning such as this was a first step toward zoning regulations and governmental policies affecting both public and private development.</p><p>While demonstrating an expanding social consciousness among industrial nations and the necessity to consider the needs of large, heterogeneous populations, the schemes presented by early-twentieth-century planners demonstrate significant differences in approach. On the one hand were the committed modernists, notably the architects Otto Wagner, Tony Garnier, and Le Corbusier, who approached the urban future with wholehearted optimism, untroubled by the transformation of the city's appearance into an expression of functional, machinelike order and practicality. On the other, there were urban theoreticians such as Ebenezer Howard and his disciples who tried to preserve some imagery from the preindustrial past. Thus, they retained picturesqueness in the form of individuated architectural elements and spatial configurations while fully embracing new engineering and industrial processes. They took as their mandate John Ruskin's words calling for "no festering and wretched suburb anywhere, but clean and busy street within, and open country without, with a [surrounding] belt of beautiful garden and orchard, so that from any part of the city perfectly fresh air and grass and sight of far horizon might be reachable in a few minutes' walk."<ref target="#CH12-n2"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">2</hi></hi></ref></p><p>The nostalgic impulses of Camillo Sitte and his followers, which we examined in Chapter Eleven, tempered some of modernity's zeal, giving birth to preservationism and the protection not only of monuments, but also of historic building ensembles and street patterns. But even the most committed preservationists of craft traditions and earlier design styles did not want to be deprived of such mechanical conveniences as central heating and indoor plumbing. Both progressive and historicist social utopians hoped that machine technology could help build a better world. This ambivalence about modernity and the desire to have both the fruits of technology and a sense of connection with the historical past continue to be reflected in the contemporary landscape, a subject we will consider in Chapter Fifteen. Here our task is to discuss the proposals and projects of the optimistic theorists and planners who sought to guide urbanism in the first half of the twentieth century.</p><div type="section"><pb n="404"/><pb n="404" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">I. Urban Expansion: Town Planning for the Machine Age in Britain and Continental Europe</hi></hi></head><p>With the rise of industrialization in the nineteenth century, some humanitarian capitalists built factories and workers' housing in new towns&#x2014;model communities in the countryside outside large cities&#x2014;thereby substituting sunlight, clean air, and greenery for the sooty congestion of the urban slum. These early planned communities with their individual houses, gardens, central parks, and local schools, all carefully separated from the industrial districts that were their raison d'&#x00EA;tre, provide a preview of later zoning practices. What is most apparent about several of these planned communities is the premium put on openness. The father of the garden city movement, <name type="pname">Ebenezer Howard</name> (<date when="1850">1850</date>&#x2013;<date when="1928">1928</date>), followed these forceful opponents of metropolitan gigantism, turning their impulse toward reform into an influential philosophy of decentralized planning. Regionalism became a new framework within which rural and urban space could be organized so as to create greenbelt-encircled new towns, thus providing the advantages of both the city and the countryside. The city as an expanding and loosening, but still discrete, entity would, if developed as Howard prescribed, henceforth become no longer a solid urban mass, but rather a constellation of population clusters.</p><figure xml:id="fig-499"><graphic url="CH12_002.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.1. Port Sunlight, <name type="place">England</name>, the model town built by Lever Brothers. <date when="1888">1888</date>. The community occupies 140 acres of the 230acre site. The central green spaces comprise ravines, which have been filled to stem tidal flooding. The road system follows the dictates of topography, curving in a picturesque manner, and the houses are placed with their backs to the railway line.</hi></figDesc></figure><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">British Social Visionaries and Industrial Philanthropists</hi></hi></head><p>While furthering the agenda of proletarian egalitarianism and denouncing the noisome squalor of the industrial city, Marx and his socialist collaborator <name type="pname">Friedrich Engels</name> (<date when="1820">1820</date>&#x2013;<date when="1895">1895</date>) paid no attention to urban form, believing that revolution must sweep away the old order before their utopian goals could be achieved. Without governmental means to foster the development of new towns, factory owners initially undertook to reform the living conditions of the industrial workforce. The light from Ruskin's <hi rend="italic">Seven Lamps</hi> illumined the path of many of these Victorian reformers, and their idealism reflected the influence of William Morris as they attempted to ameliorate and beautify the Industrial Age city through the application of an Arts and Crafts aesthetic rooted in the tradition of medieval artisans' guilds. Like Sitte, they focused on preserving past forms, and like him they codified what had been the organic growth patterns of an earlier time, thus creating a modern version of the Picturesque.</p><p>In <date when="1853">1853</date>, <name type="pname">Sir Titus Salt</name> (<date when="1803">1803</date>&#x2013;<date when="1876">1876</date>), a textile manufacturer, built Saltaire on the banks of the river Aire outside the city of Bradford in the Midlands of <name type="place">England</name>. About a quarter of a century later, George and Richard Cadbury, owners of Cadbury Brothers, manufacturers of chocolate, created Bournville, a workers' community, in conjunction with the construction of new plant facilities near Birmingham. The Cadburys designed Bournville as a town of spacious greenery; they gave all of its 313 cottages gardens and allocated a generous portion of the 330-acre site to parkland. Curving streets and variously styled houses contributed picturesqueness. Nonemployees were allowed to take up residence in Bournville, and in <date when="1900">1900</date> George Cadbury established the Bournville Village Trust, which subsequently turned the revenues from the cooperatively administered estate into further improvements, resulting in the addition of schools, churches, shops, and other amenities.</p><p>In <date when="1888">1888</date>, another philanthropically inclined industrialist, <name type="pname">William Hesketh Lever</name> (<date when="1851">1851</date>&#x2013;<date when="1925">1925</date>), founded Port Sunlight near Liverpool as a company town for the employees of Lever Brothers, manufacturers of soap (fig. 12.1). Lever's humanitarian impulse to improve the living conditions of his industrial workforce and to bestow upon it the amenities of the countryside resulted in tree-lined streets, a network of pedestrian paths, allotment gardens, a central park and sports fields, and community buildings and houses designed in the English vernacular style of older country villages. Sunlight and fresh air were obvious antidotes to the grimy, tubercular conditions of the great coal-burning cities such as Birmingham, Manchester, Liverpool, and <name type="place">London</name>.</p><p>Turning the palliatives of philanthropic industrialists into a more general and broad-scale prescription, the English reformer Ebenezer Howard promoted a vision of population dispersal into a series of planned communities in his influential book <hi rend="italic">To-morrow: A Peaceful Path to Social Reform</hi> (<date when="1898">1898</date>), republished as <hi rend="italic">Garden Cities of To-morrow</hi> (<date when="1902">1902</date>). Considered the<pb n="405"/><pb n="405" type="orig"/>father of the garden city movement, Howard saw how, thanks to the proliferating network of railroads, it was possible to leap over the city's no-longer-fixed boundaries and systematically create within the larger regional framework communities that combined the natural advantages of the country with the amenities of urban life.<ref target="#CH12-n3"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">3</hi></hi></ref></p><p>As a young man Howard earned his living as a stenographer in <name type="place">Chicago</name>, which then enjoyed the Latin epithet <hi rend="italic">Urbs in Hortus</hi> (the City in a Garden). He was probably familiar with Riverside, the garden suburb designed by Olmsted and Vaux. This hugely influential British social thinker went to great pains to prove that within the current capitalist system both social benefit and sound economic return could be gained through community ownership of land. Though not a designer, his diagrammatic model for a garden city became the schematic basis for the layout of actual new towns (fig. 12.2). Autonomous urban entities&#x2014;full-scale communities with industrial and commercial employment&#x2014; not suburbs, Howard's garden cities were conceived as an interconnected network of population centers linked by electric rail to one another and to a larger central garden city. He envisioned each satellite town as having a 1,000-acre core and a 5,000-acre rural belt, with a population of 30,000 living in the center and 2,000 in the agricultural surroundings. Each town was to be divided into wards containing 5,000 inhabitants, and each ward was to contain a school. In the heart of the town, civic and cultural institutions would ring a green open space, and between these and the inner ring of houses and gardens was to be a spacious Central Park. A second ring of houses and gardens lay beyond a wide Grand Avenue. Conveniently encircling these was a local railway looping off the main line. Factories were to be placed adjacent to this railway spur, with agricultural allotments, pastures, orchards, woodlots, and institutions for orphans, epileptics, and convalescents located in the greenbelt beyond it.</p><figure xml:id="fig-500"><graphic url="CH12_003.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.2. Diagram of one ward of the Garden City by <name type="pname">Ebenezer Howard</name> and sector of Howard's schematic plan. <date when="1898">1898</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-501"><graphic url="CH12_004.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below left:</hi> 12.3a. Plan of Letchworth Garden City, <name type="place">England</name>, designed by Raymond Unwin. <date when="1903">1903</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-502"><graphic url="CH12_005.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below right:</hi> 12.3b. A group of massed cottages, Letchworth Garden City</hi></figDesc></figure><p>In <date when="1899">1899</date>, Howard founded the Garden City Association, the organization that fostered the two primary manifestations of his ideal: <name type="pname">Letchworth</name> (<date when="1903">1903</date>) and Welwyn Garden City (<date when="1919">1919</date>). To launch Letchworth, Howard obtained the assistance of <name type="pname">George Cadbury</name> and <name type="pname">William Lever</name>. The Garden City Pioneer Company Limited, which they incorporated, acquired 4,000 acres of land 35 miles north of <name type="place">London</name> and created a subsidiary joint stock company to raise capital for construction. <name type="pname">Sir Barry Parker</name> and <name type="pname">Sir Raymond Unwin</name>, who were half cousins, brothers-in-law, Fabians, and devoted followers of Howard, planned the town, adapting Howard's diagram to the conditions of the site (figs. 12.3a, 12.3b). Because the land was to be transferred to the community at a future date, the restricted dividend stock was not secured with equity and therefore sold sluggishly. But with the establishment of industry, the town did get under way, and its sponsors were able to withstand pressure to sell off parcels of property and to develop Howard's experiment much as originally envisioned until World War I curtailed their efforts.</p><p>Unwin, an architect much concerned with establishing optimal density ratios, championed codes setting a maximum of twelve houses per acre. These were designed as attached units, with steep<pb n="406"/><pb n="406" type="orig"/>pitched rooflines and structural massing reminiscent of the Arts and Crafts style of <name type="pname">Edwin Lutyens</name> or <name type="pname">Charles Francis Annesley Voysey</name> (<date when="1857">1857</date>&#x2013;<date when="1941">1941</date>), a British architect expert in attractive, functional design for the modest home. Unwin's illustrations for his book <hi rend="italic">Town Planning in Practice</hi> (<date when="1909">1909</date>) demonstrate his meticulous attention to various planning schemes and the details of design at Letchworth. He worked also in Hampstead Garden Suburb, which he designed within the confines of metropolitan <name type="place">London</name> in <date when="1907">1907</date> as a corollary to the effort local citizens mounted to extend Hampstead Heath and to frustrate the construction of a planned underground city railway station. Borrowing from the German and English vernacular traditions, he employed irregular and nonuniform street alignments and an Arts and Crafts architectural vocabulary for his building blocks in order to create a richly picturesque environment for the working- and middle-class smallhome leaseholder (fig. 12.4). The garden city ideal upheld by Unwin placed a premium upon clearly articulated pedestrian and vehicular circulation, street and building composition, and the provision of ample and carefully arranged greenery and recreational facilities. His circulation plan reduced the amount of land occupied by roads from a typical 40 percent to 17 percent. Hampstead Garden Suburb reinforced a British preference for living at low densities and at ground level within metropolitan areas rather than in high-rise apartment blocks, as was the practice on the Continent. It did not, however, serve the varied classes for whom it was intended, as its attractiveness soon caused it to be occupied more or less exclusively by the well-to-do.</p><figure xml:id="fig-503"><graphic url="CH12_006.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.4. Hampstead Garden Suburb, <name type="place">London</name>, <name type="place">England</name>, designed by Raymond Unwin. <date when="1909">1909</date>. A street and its picturesque alignment of cottages, which have been massed in order that they may resemble larger-scale houses built in the Arts and Crafts style.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-504"><graphic url="CH12_007.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 12.5. Proposal for Vienna's urban center, by Otto Wagner. <date when="1911">1911</date></hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">Urban Planning in Austria and France</hi></hi></head><p>Like the fathers of the garden city movement in Britain, Camillo Sitte had sought in Austria to preserve the flavor of a cozier, older way of life by applying the aesthetic of the Picturesque to the modern industrial city. Others, however, equated beauty with Machine Age functionality. Among these were Sitte's Viennese contemporary Otto Wagner (<date when="1841">1841</date>&#x2013;<date when="1918">1918</date>). Wagner envisioned the modern metropolis in terms of highly systematized regimental order, with uniform building blocks, wide transportation corridors, and spacious greenery arranged according to a Neoclassical monumental planning paradigm (fig. 12.5). Thus, within an apparently similar design framework, Wagner's proposal for the new metropolis was even more resolutely modern in orientation than Baron Haussmann's radical reinvention of <name type="place">Paris</name>.</p><p>Showing greater sensitivity to the texture of everyday life than did Wagner, the Beaux-Arts-trained, protofunctionalist French architect Tony Garnier (<date when="1869">1869</date>&#x2013;<date when="1948">1948</date>) made an important contribution to the development of visionary urban planning. In <date when="1899">1899</date>, Garnier won the Prix de <name type="place">Rome</name>, the prestigious fellowship to study at the French Academy in <name type="place">Rome</name> where he was a <hi rend="italic">pensionnaire</hi> until <date when="1904">1904</date>. Rather than following the prescribed didactic program of classical architectural study, however, Garnier, who was attracted to the growing liberalism of the times, used his stay in <name type="place">Rome</name> to work on a plan for "Une Cit&#x00E9; Industrielle." This would be located in southeastern <name type="place">France</name>, the region of his native Lyons, a center for textile manufacturing, metallurgy, and the nascent automobile industry. In design terms, Garnier's plan expressed his belief that the past was morally bankrupt and that historicizing architecture was an affectation and therefore suspect, a premise shared by others who also were attempting to develop the building forms of a new democratic age. These architects postulated a radical break with history, eschewing design continuity with the past.</p><p>Although Garnier's architecture boldly em-braced<pb n="407"/><pb n="407" type="orig"/>modern construction technology, relying especially upon reinforced concrete as a building material, as an urban planner he was far less polemical and doctrinaire than several architectural modernists of the succeeding generation. Conceptually, he was closer in spirit to the proponents of the garden city movement. Its tenets were undoubtedly familiar to him, for in <date when="1902">1902</date>, Howard's <hi rend="italic">Garden Cities of To-Morrow</hi> was published in a French translation. Garnier's classical training at the &#x00C9;cole des BeauxArts ensured a more geometrically ordered approach than that of his British contemporaries with their lingering taste for the irregularities of the Picturesque. While he lacked their proclivity for vernacular architectural style, the problem he wished to solve&#x2014;that of building economically sound, livable communities&#x2014;was the same.</p><p>Garnier's Cit&#x00E9; Industrielle was oriented to the natural landscape as well as to a social ideal. Although its site was not specific, he imagined a particular topography, locating his imaginary town on hilly terrain overlooking a valley formed by the Rhone and one of its tributaries. Industry would guarantee it a viable economic foundation, and common ownership of land and intelligent planning, including the provision of educational, civic, cultural, athletic, and medical facilities, would offer the intellectual and physical amenities appropriate to the democratic social values of a new age. Designed for a population of 35,000, it was to have no defined perimeter boundaries and ample amounts of unbuilt land between functionally separate areas. These reservations of open space would allow for some necessary expansion. This type of zoning according to land use, now commonplace in cities, was innovative in the early twentieth century. Innovative, too, were the proposed sanitary and traffic standards, regulations providing for eminent domain, and controls over the supply of water, bread, milk, and medicines.</p><p>Garnier drew voluminous plans and produced numerous perspective drawings that have an engaging quotidian specificity (fig. 12.6). His laconic text is explanatory, not hortatory. In proposing a site, he considered the availability of hydroelectric power to generate electricity for the factories and the town and the presence of minerals and other raw materials for manufacturing. He then arranged the town in three well-spaced tiers: its industrial zone containing blast furnaces, steel mills, assembly plants, engineering laboratories, and workshops in the plain beside the river and the railway line; residential blocks and the town center on a plateau above these; and, higher still, hospital buildings arranged on a series of sloping terraces. Like the houses of the town, these would have southern exposures and be shielded from the wind. Overall, Garnier's plan called for construction to occupy less than half the site with the remainder devoted to landscaping and a public pedestrian way.</p><figure xml:id="fig-505"><graphic url="CH12_008.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.6. Domestic quarter, <hi rend="italic">Une Cit&#x00E9; Industrielle.</hi> The strippeddown appearance of Garnier's houses did not mean a banishment of ornament and color, only a more neutral background to heighten the expressive potential of freestanding works of art than was the case when decoration was conceived as integral with architecture. Garnier felt that the use of poured concrete and cement resulted in "large horizontal and vertical surfaces, endowing the buildings with a sense of calm and balance in harmony with the natural contours of the landscape." He established a web of connecting footpaths independent of the street system throughout the entire town so as to create "a huge park, free of enclosures and barriers delimiting individual plots of land."</hi></figDesc></figure><p>With its places of public assembly, Greek-style open-air theater, gymnasiums, fields for sports, running and cycling tracks, areas for discus throwing and high jumping, and other athletic facilities, the Cit&#x00E9; Industrielle illustrated both a spiritual and physical kinship with the ancient Greek city. There is, moreover, a pleasing Mediterranean-style modernity to Garnier's cubelike, unornamented buildings of reinforced concrete. In addition to the primary schools planned for each of the town's neighborhoods, there were to be secondary schools for industrial, administrative, and professional trade studies. One professional school was intended to train those seeking careers in the fine and commercial arts&#x2014; architecture, painting, sculpture, and related areas of design, including decorative and practical work in fabric, ceramic, glass, and metal.</p><p>Unlike later radical modernists who saw the destruction of historical building fabric and artifacts as liberating, Garnier's vision made room for the old town, and his cultural quarter was to contain in addition to a botanical garden, greenhouse, library, and exhibition hall, a museum for "historical collections and important archaeological, artistic, industrial and commercial documents relating to the town." Moreover, Garnier decreed that "monuments will be erected in the park surrounding the rooms containing the archives." For the secular and peaceful society he envisioned, there was no need to provide churches or military barracks.</p><p>Garnier's plan languished, although he managed to get it published twice&#x2014;in <date when="1914">1914</date> when he was director of the International Urban Exhibition in Lyons and again in <date when="1931">1931</date>. As a practicing architect in Lyons with strong ties to the socialist mayor Edouard Herriot (<date when="1872">1872</date>&#x2013;<date when="1957">1957</date>), Garnier obtained commissions to build some of the components envisioned in<pb n="408"/><pb n="408" type="orig"/>his Cit&#x00E9; Industrielle. These included a hospital, sanitarium, sports stadium, post office and telecommunications headquarters, art college, weaving school, employment exchange, the &#x00C9;tats Unis residential district, and memorials to war victims. Although he never saw his comprehensive plan for a parklike town realized, it nonetheless became a landmark in the history of twentieth-century city planning. Garnier's pioneering concept of low-rise housing, separate systems of vehicular and pedestrian circulation, and an array of facilities addressing the diverse needs of people for environmental safety, health, education, employment, recreation, entertainment, and politics remains a notable expression of the belief in rational, comprehensive, socially oriented planning that characterized the architectural profession in the first half of the twentieth century.</p><figure xml:id="fig-506"><graphic url="CH12_009.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.7. Ildefons Cerd&#x00E0;'s Plan for the expansion of Barcelona, Spain. <date when="1859">1859</date>. The tangled web of pedestrian-scale streets of the old city, the Barr&#x00EC; Gotic, is axially penetrated in only a few places by the new street pattern. Traversing the entire city, now greatly increased in size, are two intersecting diagonal boulevards.</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-507"><graphic url="CH12_010.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 12.8. Linear City, proposal by Arturo Soria y Mata. <date when="1882">1882</date></hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">Urban Planning in Spain</hi></hi></head><p>In Spain, Ildefons Cerd&#x00E0; (<date when="1816">1816</date>&#x2013;<date when="1876">1876</date>), an engineer and the author of <hi rend="italic">Teor&#x00ED;a General de Urbanizaci&#x00F3;n</hi> (<date when="1867">1867</date>), saw circulation as the primary definer of city form. He grasped how predominant modes of locomotion catalyzed urban transformations as cities built with narrow ways for foot traffic changed their street patterns and widths to accommodate equestrians and later wheeled vehicles. In <date when="1859">1859</date>, Cerd&#x00E0; designed the Eixample, the planned extension of the city all around medieval Barcelona, as checkerboard blocks with each square having chamfered corners to accommodate better the turning radii of carriages (fig. 12.7).</p><p>In Madrid, a generation later <name type="pname">Arturo Soria y Mata</name> (<date when="1844">1844</date>&#x2013;<date when="1920">1920</date>) carried Cerd&#x00E0;'s interest in locomotion a step further. Realizing that the rapid-transit line linking city and suburb could establish yet another urban form, Soria proposed in <date when="1882">1882</date> <hi rend="italic">La ciudad lineal,</hi> a linear city with a single <date when="1640">1640</date>-foot-wide (500-meter-wide) street of indeterminate length (fig. 12.8). Boldly, Soria envisioned this artery not only as a transportation corridor but also as an immense belt of utilities and services including water, gas, and electric lines, reservoirs and public gardens, and stations for various municipal services. Settlement was to occur in orthogonal blocks along secondary streets perpendicular to the central spine, with houses occupying only one-fifth of each building lot. A small piece of Soria's scheme was realized: 13 miles (22 kilometers) of a 34-mile (55-kilometer) planned linear city outside Madrid.</p><pb n="409"/><pb n="409" type="orig"/><p>In contrast to the purely technological approach of Soria, the Catalan industrialist <name type="pname">Eusebi G&#x00FC;ell</name> (<date when="1846">1846</date>&#x2014; <date when="1918">1918</date>) and his architect <name type="pname">Antonio Gaud&#x00ED;</name> (<date when="1852">1852</date>&#x2013;<date when="1926">1926</date>) attempted in the construction of Park G&#x00FC;ell between <date when="1900">1900</date> and <date when="1914">1914</date> to express Barcelona's transformation into a modern industrial city still tied to its indigenous cultural, spiritual, and technological heritage (figs. 12.11&#x2013;12.15). Park G&#x00FC;ell was originally intended as a suburban alternative to the increasingly crowded city that the magnate saw filling the blocks outlined by Cerd&#x00E0;'s Eixample. G&#x00FC;ell had already exhibited a concern similar to Lever's at Port Sunlight in the construction of Col&#x00F2;nia G&#x00FC;ell to house his textile workers. His new project would allow middle-class Barcelonans to escape the city's growing clamor and congestion. Perhaps more important, it would encode into its architectural fabric emblems of the Catalan "regional soul" as promoted by the Catholic revival in which both G&#x00FC;ell and Gaud&#x00ED; were active participants.</p><p>Park G&#x00FC;ell's creation occurred within the period of the <hi rend="italic">Renaixen&#x00E7;a,</hi> the renascence of Catalan traditions, including that of religious pilgrimage and penitential piety, led by Barcelona's cultural elite. Neither this movement nor the park is as anomalous as one might imagine at first. They sprang from a regional variant of the impulse to revalidate folkways, ancient rituals, craft traditions, and vernacular idioms of language, architecture, ornament, and dress that was occurring simultaneously in other places. Not unexpectedly, given the rapidly changing, increasingly rootless, secular nature of the times, conservative men such as G&#x00FC;ell and Gaud&#x00ED; sought to reconnect their society with history, as powerfully represented by the Catholic Church. Religious societies planned excursions by rail into the surrounding countryside where members visited thousand-year-old Romanesque churches, cave shrines, and mountain sanctuaries. Barcelonans revived the <hi rend="italic">sardana,</hi> a regional folk dance still performed in the city's cathedral square. The Joc Florals, a poetry and rhetoric festival established in <date when="1859">1859</date>, celebrated the Catalan language and the tradition of Proven&#x00E7;al troubadours. The architect Llu&#x00ED;s Dom&#x00E9;nech y Montaner (<date when="1850">1850</date>&#x2013;<date when="1923">1923</date>) led a crafts revival that successfully integrated craft technologies&#x2014;particularly those of ceramics and metalwork&#x2014;with the industrial arts, resulting in the robust ornamental plasticity that characterizes many of Barcelona's buildings today (fig. 12.9). That Gaud&#x00ED; was a scion of coppersmiths was an important factor in his development as an architect.</p><p>Park G&#x00FC;ell occupies an especially interesting position in the history of landscape design because of G&#x00FC;ell and Gaud&#x00ED;'s attempt to synthesize cosmopolitan progress and ethnic conservatism. Gaud&#x00ED; combined modern industrial technologies and ancient craft traditions to create forms that are both witty and soberly pious. He built upon the symbolical identification of the steep site&#x2014;located on the southeast side of Muntanya Pelada (Bald Mountain), also referred to as Mount Carmel&#x2014;with the sacred mountain of Montserrat. After the fortuitous discovery of a cave and mineral spring on the property, he used the natural materials of the site to fashion other forms suggestive of an antediluvian holy landscape. Elevated to greatness by Gaud&#x00ED;'s genius and the superbly imaginative craftsmanship of Catalan artisans, Park G&#x00FC;ell is a landscape curiosity, a failed utopian experiment and Industrial Age vision of paradise. It is also a more elegant and refined, but not-too-distant, cousin to the midway plaisances of the world's fairs&#x2014; low-brow amusement areas such as the one that provided a piquant counterpoint to the elevated cultural ambience of the <date when="1893">1893</date> <name type="place">Chicago</name> World's Fair&#x2014;and the delightfully garish amusement parks such as Luna Park and Steeplechase at Coney Island with which it is contemporary. Like these, it sought to imbue landscape with evocations of the fantastic and supernatural.</p><figure xml:id="fig-508"><graphic url="CH12_011.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.9. Passeig de Gracia, Barcelona, with lamp standard and seat designed by Gaud&#x00ED; and, in the backgound, his Casa Mila</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Without the appropriate frame of cultural reference and knowledge of Park G&#x00FC;ell's historical background, the visitor will find it inexplicably bizarre in much the same way as the untutored tourist finds bafflingly enigmatic the sixteenth-century park of Count Orsini at Bomarzo with its riddling allusions to Ariosto's <hi rend="italic">Orlando furioso,</hi> Dante's <hi rend="italic">Inferno,</hi> and Virgil's <hi rend="italic">Aeneid.</hi> In Barcelona, patron and architect attempted to combine the social program of the garden suburb with the symbolical and thematic allusions of the pleasure garden. To achieve their objective G&#x00FC;ell and Gaud&#x00ED; drew upon the architecture of the late-nineteenth-century international expositions in which they had played significant roles, including the one held in <date when="1888">1888</date> in Barcelona's Ciutadella Park. Increasingly, these had become showcases for fanciful kiosks and<pb n="410"/><pb n="410" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-509"><graphic url="CH12_012.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.10. Plan of Park G&#x00FC;ell, Barcelona, designed by Antonio Gaud&#x00ED;. <date when="1900">1900</date>&#x2013;14</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-510"><graphic url="CH12_013.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.11. Tile mosaic in <hi rend="italic">trencad&#x00ED;s</hi> pattern on the walls of Gaud&#x00ED;'s grand stairway, Park G&#x00FC;ell</hi></figDesc></figure><q>Upon entering the park, one passes between two gatehouses <hi rend="bold">C</hi>. Designed practically to accommodate residents, arriving guests, and concierge, they nevertheless have a fairy-tale aspect with their candylike encrusted surfaces. Gaud&#x00ED; created the fluid parabolic curves of their surging roof lines using the traditional Catalan masonry called <hi rend="italic">b&#x00F3;veda tabicada</hi> in which thin bricks or flat rectangular tiles are laminated to form vaulting.</q><q>Beyond the gatehouses lies the entry vestibule with its enigmatic clues and teasing symbols. As festive and welcoming as a contemporary theme park, like Disney World's Magic Kingdom, this space is replete with pseudo-Gothic heraldic motifs. A grand stairway <hi rend="bold">D</hi>, which splits in two halfway down, is encased by low walls embellished with reassembled pieces of broken tile in a pattern called <hi rend="italic">trencad&#x00ED;s,</hi> a traditional Catalan mosaic technique (fig. 12.11). It is framed by tall side walls with overhanging crenelated parapets and decorated with a bold checkerboard design using the same mosaic technique. Gaud&#x00ED;'s deliberate smashing of newly fired tile and its application to curving surfaces exemplifies his creativity in adapting traditional craft forms to new and original artistic ends.</q><q>This space, while essentially cheerful, is also vaguely disquieting. It is made ambiguous by the presence of a shadowy grotto in the triangle created by the bifurcation of the grand stairs, a bronze ceramic serpent head protruding from a round shield adorned with the colors of the Catalan flag, and a brilliant mosaic-covered, water-spouting dragon (fig. 12.12. Artificial caves on either side of the ceremonial stairs serve the practical functions of stor<pb n="411"/><pb n="411" type="orig"/>age, shelter, and carriage turnaround, but the rough masonry of these vaulted recesses gives them the appearance of geologic wonders. They constitute, it turns out, a prelude to the architectural and symbolical double entendres one encounters in moving through Park G&#x00FC;ell's richly programmed landscape.</q><figure xml:id="fig-511"><graphic url="CH12_014.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.12. Dragon, Grand stairway and entrance grotto, Park G&#x00FC;ell</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-512"><graphic url="CH12_015.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Above:</hi> 12.13. Upper Bridge, Park G&#x00FC;ell</figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-513"><graphic url="CH12_016.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.14. Greek Theater, Park G&#x00FC;ell</hi></figDesc></figure><q>The grand stairs <hi rend="bold">D</hi> ascend to the imposing Market Hall <hi rend="bold">B</hi> with its forest of columns. If the sixty families projected to take up residence there had done so, this hypostyle hall might have functioned as intended. It remains, instead, a curious and impressive untenanted space, a demonstration of Gaud&#x00ED;'s virtuosic technical skills and protean imagination as an architect. Monumental Doric columns rise to support a massive roof platform. This acts as the floor surface of the Greek Theater <hi rend="bold">B</hi>, a large elevated plaza intended for civic and religious rituals and such expressions of Catalan folk culture as the popular <hi rend="italic">sardana</hi> dances. Like a Mannerist conceit, a wide, high-backed, curving bench blocks immediate entrance from the stairs into this open hall, and the architect has provided no visible clue as to any means of entry into it. Once the visitor has found the route inside, the powerful fluted columns, the pearlytoned <hi rend="italic">trencad&#x00ED;s</hi> work in the ceiling's multiple shallow domes, and the great round ceiling medallions by the artist Josep Maria Jujol vie for primacy in producing the strongest impression.</q><q>The wavy entablature of the Market Hall is surmounted by a serpentine bench, added after <date when="1909">1909</date> when Park G&#x00FC;ell's construction program was coming to a close. Here, surrounding the entire perimeter of the Greek Theater, Jujol created a ceramic masterpiece, sheathing Gaud&#x00ED;'s gently undulating, biomorphic balcony and continuous seat with a boldly brilliant mosaic containing numerous liturgically symbolic colors, emblems, and inscriptions (fig. 12.14).</q><q>Adapted to the steep topography of the site, the circulation system consists of gently inclined promenades or principal avenues 33 feet (10 meters) wide; somewhat steeper carriage roads having a width of 16.5 feet (5 meters); 10-foot- (3-meter-) wide connector paths for pedestrians; and <hi rend="italic">dreceras,</hi> or narrow ways with steps to facilitate climbing, in areas too steep for conventional pedestrian paths.</q><q>While Gaud&#x00ED;'s circulation system conformed generally to the dictates of topography, to avoid narrow switchbacks and hairpin turns he made the roads loop broadly, creating the need for structural support where there was no ground plane beneath them. He treated the undersides of the bridges that carry these sections of the roadbed as vaulted porticos dressed with rough-hewn masonry, making them appear as cavelike chambers, integral parts of the surrounding stony landscape. Here he employed the same Catalan <hi rend="italic">b&#x00F3;veda tabicada</hi> system used in the gatehouses, canting support columns and splaying their capitals so that they merge with the portico ceiling, dressing the whole in rough-hewn native stone and creating in this fluid parabolic interior an impression that is almost geological, rather than architectonic (fig. 12.13). In the upper bridge/portico <hi rend="bold">A</hi>, spiky agave plants grow from the tops of the capitals of the columns, which here function as large rustic jardinieres.</q><pb n="412"/><pb n="412" type="orig"/>other exotic structures outside the architectural mainstream as well as a means of demonstrating innovations in industrial technology.</p><p>The fact that G&#x00FC;ell anglicized the name of his real-estate development, spelling it "park" instead of <hi rend="italic">parc</hi> (Catalan) or <hi rend="italic">parque</hi> (Spanish), indicated a conscious association with the English landscape tradition, both in its eighteenth-century manifestation in such gardens as Stowe and Stourhead and in its contemporary garden city one, as at Letchworth. Gaud&#x00ED; used an indigenous symbolism to create a twentieth-century sacralized Catalan version of <hi rend="italic">the jardin anglais.</hi> Here, instead of valorizing the industrial present with evocations of a classical Arcadia, he dramatized the sacredness of the rough prehistoric Catalan landscape with emblems of a pilgrim's progress toward Paradise combined with a vividly organic imagery derived from regional nature.</p><p>In planning their residential refuge, G&#x00FC;ell and Gaud&#x00ED; rejected the orthogonal lines of Cerd&#x00E0;'s Eixample in much the way that Olmsted and Vaux rejected the grid in their plans for Central Park and the suburb of Riverside, <name type="place">Illinois</name> (fig. 12.10; see figs. 9.34, 9.48). Not only did they follow the dictates of topography in the Park G&#x00FC;ell's curvilinear road system, but because it represented a paradisiacal place, they also demarcated the development with walls and an elaborate entrance gate to set it apart from the rest of the city.<ref target="#CH12-n4"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">4</hi></hi></ref> They made the experience of coming into the park akin to participating in a mystical pageant by furnishing its entrance with an elaborate set of symbols appropriate to the as yet uninitiated pilgrim embarking on a journey of pious discovery&#x2014;Poliphilus in Colonna's <hi rend="italic">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili,</hi> Dante in <hi rend="italic">The Divine Comedy,</hi> and Prince Tamino in Mozart's <hi rend="italic">The Magic Flute</hi> come to mind. These are embodied in several original and highly plastic forms (fig. 12.12). In designing them Gaud&#x00ED; did not rely on blueprints. Instead, he was there, on the job, sketching, directing, and continually innovating&#x2014;creatively marrying ancient craft with contemporary industrial technology.</p><p>Park G&#x00FC;ell's functionally segregated circulation system, like that of Central Park, was an object of considerable attention, also providing the opportunity for a series of bridges of great originality and design distinction. While the spiritual benefits intended to be derived from passage through Central Park on foot, horseback, or carriage were characterized by Olmsted as being of a "poetic" nature&#x2014;the benign influence of nature operating on the senses and the soul&#x2014;Gaud&#x00ED;'s system of roads and paths had a more specifically religious intent and program. All routes wound upward to a stone cairn surmounted by three stone crosses symbolizing Calvary, or Golgotha, the hill of Jesus' Crucifixion. Gaud&#x00ED; intended the climb to this highest point in the park, an energetic Sunday promenade, to recall the famous pilgrimage routes in the Pyrenees, particularly the one leading to Montserrat, Catalonia's holy mountain and refuge of monks and martyrs. Visible from this high point are the spires of Gaud&#x00ED;'s Church of the Sacred Family and much of the rest of Barcelona's urban landscape.</p><p>For the mystically inclined architect as well as for the proprietor of Park G&#x00FC;ell, the site was <hi rend="italic">both</hi> allegorical and invested with its own sacred significance. The bishop of Vic actively encouraged the spread into Catalonia of the nineteenth-century cult of grotto sanctuaries that originated in <name type="place">France</name> and was conspicuously manifested at Lourdes. The network of caves within Muntanya Pelada, discovered shortly after G&#x00FC;ell had ordered work to begin on the site, validated his belief in a thematic treatment and gave Gaud&#x00ED;'s improvisatory genius the opportunity for fresh flights of architectural fantasy. Not only was Gaud&#x00ED; cooperating in the creation of a hieratic landscape, he was also countering Enlightenment rationalism and its corollary, modern industrial engineering, with a seemingly organic architecture that used local craft technique to fashion indigenous building materials into an expression that appeared to be deeply rooted in the land. Inventively seeking ways of making architecture appear organic, Gaud&#x00ED; employed the helix in his spiral ramp for the portico adjacent to the Greek Theater. Here, one of nature's most elegant and prevalent patterns is used to ingenious effect.</p><p>Although Gaud&#x00ED;'s style is sometimes associated with the curvilinear forms and vegetal motifs of the Art Nouveau movement, his goals were different. Perhaps the greatest and certainly the most ardent practitioner of Expressionism, the architectural style that flourished during the first quarter of the twentieth century, Gaud&#x00ED; sought to find an idiom outside of any cultural conventions or historical references, to evoke sensations from free-form sculptural elements. Because he mystically associated nature with the symbolism of a Catalonian nationalism deeply rooted in Roman Catholicism, the existence of real caves on the site merely impelled him further in a direction prompted by religion. Taking his cues from the "book of nature," which he believed was the creation of God, he intended to deny Darwin and scientific rationalism and to substantiate creationism through a biomorphic and geomorphic architectural imagery expressive of the prebiblical, prehistoric landscape. At the same time, though laden with this symbolic intent, the structures attached to the roads and other cavelike recesses served quite practical, nonmeta-phorical ends, providing sheltered seating, storage space, and other amenities.</p><pb n="413"/><pb n="413" type="orig"/><p>Inherent problems thwarted the complete realization of G&#x00FC;ell and Gaud&#x00ED;'s visionary plan. Title to the parcels G&#x00FC;ell planned to sell was hedged with regulations stating that only one-sixth of a lot could be covered with buildings, that building height and location be set according to a formula that ensured the view lines of all other residences, that walls along property lines be no higher than 32 inches (80 centimeters) from the ground, that no trees over six inches in diameter be removed. Unlike Howard, G&#x00FC;ell did not set up a corporation to administer his proposed community in perpetuity. Rather, he left vague his commitment to the future provision of services and maintenance, inserting in his proposed contract of sale an escape clause for the proprietor, specifying that the residents were to form an association for such purposes. As a result, the lots remained unsold, and the estate became the private refuge of G&#x00FC;ell, Gaud&#x00ED;, and another family closely related to G&#x00FC;ell. In <date when="1923">1923</date>, five years after G&#x00FC;ell's death, his heirs transferred the property to the municipality of Barcelona to administer as a public park. Today it is one of the most visited parks in the city.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">European Modernism</hi></hi></head><p>Though secular rather than religious in their outlook, European radical modernists possessed a fervor equal to that of the Catalonian Renaixen&#x00E7;a leaders in their attempts to create new human environments appropriate to the Industrial Age. They romanticized the speeded-up future enabled by machine technology. The Futurists, as a group of young Milanese artists and intellectuals called themselves, were particularly enamored of high-speed motion and mechanized power. Among their ranks was the architect <name type="pname">Antonio Sant'Elia</name> (<date when="1888">1888</date>&#x2013;<date when="1916">1916</date>) whose <hi rend="italic">Cili&#x00E0; Nuova</hi> proposal abandoned Haussmannesque urban retrofitting for the modern age in favor of a clean start. All traces of the past are swept away to allow skyscrapers to rise boldly above circulation corridors arranged on multiple levels (fig. 12.15). Engineering, rather than social concern, characterizes Sant'Elia's proposal: intersecting layers of underground railways, highways, pedestrian skyways, and even an airport runway passing above and below one another by means of great viaducts and bridges. Elevators provide vertical access between levels and within the tall buildings.</p><p>At the same time, in <date when="1903">1903</date>, Austrian architect Josef Hoffmann (<date when="1870">1870</date>&#x2013;<date when="1956">1956</date>) founded the Wiener Werkst&#x00E4;tte with painter and furniture designer Koloman Moser (<date when="1868">1868</date>&#x2013;<date when="1918">1918</date>). This studio of collaborative architects and artisans offered an Arts and Crafts alternative to Machine Age modernity. In <name type="place">Germany</name>, early modernism united the Arts and Crafts tradition as practiced by architect Peter Behrens (<date when="1868">1868</date>&#x2013;<date when="1940">1940</date>)&#x2014;a follower of William Morris and one of the founders in <date when="1907">1907</date> of the Deutscher Werkbund in Munich&#x2014;with a the Machine Age aesthetic and a purely functionalist approach.</p><figure xml:id="fig-514"><graphic url="CH12_017.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.15. Proposal for a skyscraper city with gradeseparated transportation channels, by Antonio Sant'Elia. <date when="1914">1914</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p><name type="pname">Walter Gropius</name> (<date when="1883">1883</date>&#x2013;<date when="1969">1969</date>), a student in Behrens's office, followed the Belgian architect and designer <name type="pname">Henry van de Velde</name> (<date when="1863">1863</date>&#x2013;<date when="1957">1957</date>) as director of the arts and crafts school founded in Weimar by the grand duke of Saxe-Weimar in <date when="1906">1906</date>. Gropius premised the curriculum of the Bauhaus, as he named the school, upon the Werkbund's ethos of developing an indigenous German art based on sound construction and the collaborative effort of architects, artists, and artisans. Students were trained to respect the particular characteristics of wood and other natural materials. By <date when="1923">1923</date>, however, Gropius had abandoned the Expressionist mood that had infused early Bauhaus instruction in architecture and had turned away from the Werkbund's belief that craft ideals should influence industrial design toward an emphasis upon machine technology. The functional design and industrial materials of the school's new quarters that Gropius built in Dessau (<date when="1925">1925</date>&#x2013;26) became a visible manifesto of the Bauhaus's evolved mission to promote new building methods. Socialism was implicit, too, in Gropius's architecture. He saw machine technology as the carrier of a different kind of design beauty from that of the more labor-intensive, and thereby more expensive, Arts and Crafts aesthetic. By abandoning handiwork ornament in favor of a more abstract architectural aesthetic based on composition alone, architects could bring a more commodious life to more people than ever before. Industrial building parts were relatively inexpensive, especially compared with ornamental, hand-carved stone, and less-skilled architects than Gropius could achieve satisfactory, if not particularly inspired, results employing them in modular designs.<ref target="#CH12-n5"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">5</hi></hi></ref></p><pb n="414"/><pb n="414" type="orig"/><p>Subsequently characterized as one of the progenitors of a new International Style, Bauhaus architecture and that of kindred designers now discarded regional design vocabularies and traditional building materials in favor of steel-frame construction, curtain walls, open floor plans, and asymmetrical planar elevations.<ref target="#CH12-n6"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">6</hi></hi></ref>The early practitioners of this classless and often rigorously utilitarian architecture were polemical in their anti-authoritarianism. For them, ornament&#x2014;the carrier of iconographies of power and of symbolism associated with aristocratic grandeur and monarchical rule&#x2014;appeared superfluous and possibly even immoral.</p><p>Their avant-garde cosmopolitanism was anathema to political conservatives, particularly to nationalists, and to members of Adolf Hitler's Nazi (National Socialist) Party, who preferred a traditional style rooted in the German Picturesque and, in the case of monumental public buildings, a sober classicism that glorified the power of the State. Gropius's new Bauhaus in Dessau existed barely a decade before he and his colleagues became part of the diaspora of German intellectuals who left Europe after <date when="1933">1933</date> when Hitler came to power. Gropius became the head of the architectural program at Harvard, and this, along with the exodus of many other German and Austrian modernists, hastened the acceptance of the International Style as an architectural idiom in the United States.</p><p>Gropius's contemporary, the Swiss-born architect <name type="pname">Charles Edouard Jeanneret</name>, known as Le Corbusier (<date when="1887">1887</date>&#x2013;<date when="1965">1965</date>), extended the premises of the International Style to the most traditional of human structures, the home, which he memorably defined as "a machine for living." He shared with the Futurists an enthusiasm for dynamic motion and boldness of scale, which he manifested in city-planning schemes that welcomed the automobile with wider roadways, while expanding traditional city blocks into a superblock grid scaled to provide abundant light and air around tall residential towers.</p><figure xml:id="fig-515"><graphic url="CH12_018.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.16. Le Corbusier's sketch plans for <name type="pname">Rio de Janeiro</name>, <name type="place">Brazil</name>. <date when="1929">1929</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>While his indifference to specific economic, political, and social realities ensured that his plans remained largely on paper, Le Corbusier's Olympian pronouncements and his tireless program of publication assured lasting and far-reaching influence for his planning paradigms and proposals. Like Sant'Elia, he saw that the city might be more dense and also more open if motorized transportation systems operated both vertically and horizontally, and, like Soria, he appreciated the linear spine as a means of planned decentralization and industrial dispersal. He held in contempt Sitte and other practitioners of the Picturesque style in architecture, and he deplored <name type="place">New York</name>'s skyscrapers because these were placed cheek by jowl within a preexisting street pattern rather than set upon a much more loosely woven grid of spacious superblocks filled with sunlight and greenery.</p><p>Without subscribing to its proponents' density ratios or proposed satellite clusters, Le Corbusier appropriated the virtues of the garden city&#x2014;plentiful sunlight, abundant recreational open space, and ease of movement&#x2014;as his principal objectives. Biology furnished him with numerous images&#x2014;"BIOLOGY! The great new word in architecture and planning," he once declared&#x2014;but his idea of organic planning was metaphorical and, above all, architectural rather than environmental. The stunning setting of Rio de Janeiro, for instance, provoked in him "the strong desire, a bit mad perhaps, to attempt here a human adventure&#x2014; the desire to set up a duality, to create the affirmation of man' against or with the presence of nature.'"<ref target="#CH12-n7"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">7</hi></hi></ref> He then sketched a 328-foot- (100-meter-) high motorway looping the city in an arc around its beautiful harbor, the upper deck a continuous structure containing apartments, the lower band of which would begin almost 100 feet (30 meters) from the ground, presumably clearing the tops of any existing buildings (fig. 12.16).</p><p>But this modernist, romantically homocentric response to setting characterized only Le Corbusier's encounters with real sites such as that of the Villa Savoye (<date when="1929">1929</date>&#x2013;31) at Poissy, where he designed a structure raised on pilotis with views across a broad meadow, an intended evocation of the Latin poet Virgil's urbane pastoralism. His theoretical plans, on the other hand, envisioned flat, featureless plains upon which to inscribe rationalistic architectonics. Classicism, Cartesian geometry, and admiration for authoritarian leaders&#x2014;exemplified in his respect for the achievements of Louis XIV (Place V&#x00EA;ndome, Invalides, Versailles), Louis XV (Place de la Concorde) and Napol&#x00E9;on I (Champ de Mars, L'&#x00C9;toile)&#x2014;underlie his bold proposal for a Contemporary City for Three Million Inhabitants (fig. 12.17). Exhibited at the Salon d'Automne in <date when="1922">1922</date>, it envisioned a grid of<pb n="415"/><pb n="415" type="orig"/>superblocks occupied by tall, freestanding, slablike buildings where people would live in practically identical two-story "freehold maisonettes" furnished with terraces (fig. 12.18). Employing one of his favorite biological metaphors, Le Corbusier, who felt that the highly mobile population of the modern age need no longer harbor sentimental notions of home and hearth, called these residential units "cells." Industry was to be located outside the city proper, and workers, comprising two million of the three million inhabitants, would be located in "garden cities" nearby.</p><figure xml:id="fig-516"><graphic url="CH12_019.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.17. Plan and perspectives of a Contemporary City for Three Million Inhabitants, by Le Corbusier. <date when="1922">1922</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-517"><graphic url="CH12_020.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 12.18. Facade of a residential unit with a two-story maisonette with terrace in the Contemporary City for Three Million Inhabitants.</figDesc></figure><p>Besides providing a paradigm for the contemporary servantless apartment dwelling, Le Corbusier's plan of a City for Three Million Inhabitants anticipated the fitness culture of today with its plethora of athletic facilities: tennis courts, swimming pools, soccer fields, and rooftop running tracks and sunbathing areas. As the buildings were raised on pilotis, paths could pass beneath them, forming a network of pedestrian ways independent of the arteries for vehicular circulation. An underground commuter railroad linking the center with the industrial suburbs and a metropolitan subway would provide mass transit. Like Sant'Elia, Le Corbusier was fascinated with the idea of landing airplanes in the middle of the city and designed a platform for this purpose on the upper level of his multilevel transportation center.</p><p>In <date when="1923">1923</date> he published <hi rend="italic">Vers une architecture</hi> (translated in <date when="1927">1927</date> as <hi rend="italic">Towards a New Architecture)</hi> in which he enunciated "three reminders to architects." These principles exerted a profound influence on modernist landscape architects, some of whose work we will examine in Chapter Thirteen. Here Le Corbusier maintained that architecture is an art of mass based on cubes, spheres, cones, cylinders, or pyramids&#x2014;forms revealed to our eyes by light; that surfaces should be modulated to accentuate these simple forms; and that architecture should have nothing to do with "the styles" but allow the plan, an abstraction based on mathematics, to serve as a generator of design, a harmonizing force, and the carrier of sensation.</p><p>In <date when="1930">1930</date>, at the third Congr&#x00E8;s Internationaux d'Architecture Moderne (CIAM) congress in Brussels where the theme was "Rational Methods of Site Planning," Le Corbusier exhibited a plan that he called <hi rend="italic">The Radiant City</hi> (fig. 12.19). Originally conceived as a response to Soviet officials in Moscow who wanted to reorganize the capital, the plan elaborated and refined the repetitive cellular structure within a geometric superblock grid that he had previously developed for the City for Three Million Inhabitants. Here Le Corbusier created a plan that was capable of expansion on either side of its axial spine. He placed the towers of the administrative and business district on this axis but away from the urban center in much the same position that the corporate office buildings of the La D&#x00E9;fense district occupy in relation to <name type="place">Paris</name> today.</p><pb n="416"/><pb n="416" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-518"><graphic url="CH12_021.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.19. Plan for The Radiant City, by Le Corbusier. <date when="1930">1930</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>With the exception of the new capital cities of Chandigarh in the Punjab province of India, begun in <date when="1950">1950</date>, and Bras&#x00ED;lia, where in <date when="1956">1956</date> Le Corbusier's disciples L&#x00FA;cio Costa (<date when="1902">1902</date>&#x2013;<date when="1998">1998</date>) and <name type="pname">Oscar Niemeyer</name> (b. <date when="1907">1907</date>) began erecting a South American version of the Radiant City, the CIAM planners did not see their visionary urbanism come to fruition. In Chandigarh, Le Corbusier assigned to his cousin <name type="pname">Pierre Jeanneret</name> responsibility for planning the layout of the city. In a country that had scarcely begun to industrialize, Jeanneret conceived a sophisticated road system far in advance of the demands of actual motorized traffic. In the end, the city's achievements were not those of planning but rather of architecture, notably the capitol complex of monumental government buildings Le Corbusier designed around a vast pedestrian plaza. These include the High Court and the Legislative Assembly with its monumental portico and massive flaring roof, which demonstrate the architect's movement away from the International Style toward a new definition of modernism based on bold experimentation with the sculptural potential of exposed concrete. In Bras&#x00ED;lia, although Niemeyer brought a similar dramatic verve to the major buildings, the geometric regularity underlying Costa's plan imposed a sense of artificiality on the city. Moreover, the prestigious monumental architecture of the civic centers in these cities was counterbalanced by the autocratically planned residential areas where people tried with much inconvenience to accommodate their daily movements and living patterns to the monotonously repetitive housing and windswept emptiness of the superblock scale.</p><p>In spite of such evident disjunction between the ideal and everyday reality in these early examples of modernist planning, Le Corbusier's reputation and influence upon the contemporary city remained potent. The years following World War II saw the rapid dissemination of the International Style<ref target="#CH12-n8"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">8</hi></hi></ref>throughout the capitalist world as the bomb-ravaged cities of <name type="place">Europe</name> and <name type="place">Japan</name> rebuilt themselves and as rapidly urbanizing nations elsewhere appropriated its aesthetics and architectural forms as the most economical means of building on a large scale within a compressed time frame. Among the generation of architects who came of age in this period, Le Corbusier was revered as one of the principal progenitors of the modernist movement they now carried forward. As industrial cities from <name type="place">New York</name> City to <name type="place">Toyko</name>, from Stockholm to Madrid, continued to attract huge populations, increasing numbers of people lived in high-rise slabs modeled superficially on Le Corbusier's Unit&#x00E9; d'Habitation in Marseilles, which was one residential block of a proposed "vertical garden city" for local industrial workers, or in cruciform towers like those of his Radiant City.</p><p>No one, certainly not Le Corbusier and the other leaders of the modernist movement, understood the full dimensions of the role of the automobile in transforming cities and the effect that highways and superhighways would have on cities and countryside alike. The scale of the superblock facilitated motor age traffic, but, because the open space that was to become a network of greenways in the Radiant City usually became parking lots instead, the pedestrian was thwarted. Instead of strengthening the social bond, this loosened the communal fabric and diminished personal security. Born of the twentieth century's enthusiasm for personal mobility and automobile transportation, the highways carrying cars into the hearts of cities made old urban centers very different kinds of places from what they had been previously, raising the question of how much besides a lengthy commute had been gained. Nowhere was the effect of modernism's failed promises more evident than in the United States. There, tremendous industrial growth, much of it stimulated by consumer demand for automobiles, accelerated the impact of the machine on the landscape, though at first there was an era of promise as planners and landscape architects sought to design better communities for a new age.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb n="417"/><pb n="417" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">II. Greenbelt Towns or Suburbs?: Creating the American Metropolis</hi></hi></head><p>In <name type="place">America</name>, urban planning, which had first been conceptualized and practiced by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux as a means of guiding and shaping metropolitan growth around a green armature of parks and parkways, had become by the end of the nineteenth century an exercise in Beaux-Arts Neoclassical monumentalism. As we saw in the previous chapter, only <name type="place">Washington</name>, <name type="place">D.C.</name>, which already had in place its Neoclassical urban framework, achieved a comprehensive urban redesign at this time. Elsewhere pragmatic city leaders settled for a few Beaux-Arts monuments, buildings, and squares. The second generation of urban planners in <name type="place">America</name>, which included Frederick Law Olmsted, Jr., who had been a major participant in the McMillan Commission's report outlining <name type="place">Washington</name>'s aggrandizement as a monumental city, gradually abandoned the ideals of the City Beautiful for what has been termed the City Functional, the City Practical, and sometimes the City Social. Although socialism never became as strong a force in <name type="place">America</name> as in Europe, there were some who hoped to place the values of society as a whole above those of Darwinian capitalist competition. Ebenezer Howard's influential garden cities movement helped define economic well-being in social, rather than mere monetary, terms. But any broadening of its aims would require large-scale social and economic reform backed by political policy.</p><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">American Visionaries</hi></hi></head><p>The generation of visionary reformers that came of age during World War I in <name type="place">America</name> grasped just how profoundly industrialization was transforming society. The economic theories of Henry George and Thorstein Veblen influenced and supported their belief that land profits should be directed toward the common good and that land planning should rationally partner nature with engineering and technology to provide livable communities. Some recoiled from the impending future of vastly enlarged cities and were uneasy with the purely architectural solutions of European modernists like Le Corbusier, while others embraced skyscraper-scale metropolitanism. Both decentralists and metropolitanists felt that regional planning involving vast engineering projects was now a necessity and that industrial technology provided the means of harnessing nature's resources for human ends. As planners conceived the new towns and suburbs, the highways and bridges, and the hydroelectric dams and transmission lines that would create an entirely new urban scale, social reformers drew up their plans for remedying the ills of existing cities. Recreation as a means of acculturation for immigrant groups gave birth to the playground movement, and in the early years of the twentieth century the recreation director became a certified professional along with the social worker.</p><figure xml:id="fig-519"><graphic url="CH12_022.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.20. Plan for Yorkship Village, now <name type="place">Fairview</name>, <name type="place">Camden</name>, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, by <name type="pname">Frederick Lee Ackerman</name>. <date when="1918">1918</date>. Ackerman, who was assisted by Henry Wright, focused his plan with BeauxArts radials and Picturesque curvilinear roads upon a village green. A system of footpaths separated pedestrian from vehicular traffic, and varied setbacks for the neo-Georgian two- and three-story row, twin, and triplex houses illustrate the designers' attention to streetscape.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>World War I provided urban planners with a convenient link to the social reform agenda of the Progressive Era as well as a means of transferring British garden city and regional planning ideals to the United States, where the federal government sponsored villages to house war-industry workers during World War I. Frederick Law Olmsted, Jr., served as chief of design for the United States Housing Corporation, and architect and planner Henry Wright (<date when="1878">1878</date>&#x2013;<date when="1936">1936</date>) was one of three designers hired by the government-sponsored Emergency Fleet Corporation headed by architect Frederick Lee Ackerman (<date when="1878">1878</date>&#x2013;<date when="1950">1950</date>), to plan Yorkship Village (<date when="1918">1918</date>), now Fairview, <name type="place">New Jersey</name> (fig. 12.20). The plan was based upon the neighborhood-unit outlined of Clarence Perry (<date when="1872">1872</date>&#x2013;<date when="1944">1944</date>), a sociologist-planner who learned the values of good community design firsthand as a resident of Forest Hills Gardens.</p><p>Partly inspired by examples of German garden cities, such as Krupp and Essen, Forest Hills Gardens in Queens, <name type="place">New York</name>, was a garden suburb in the Picturesque tradition. The Russell Sage Foundation, the project's sponsor, intended it to be a cozy domestic landscape built according to the latest "scientific principles" of town planning, an educational demonstrtion to developers of the profitability of an archi- tecturally integrated, exclusively residential community built for middle-class homeowners. Here, in <date when="1909">1909</date>, Olmsted, Jr., laid out three wide principal roads for through traffic and a series of gently winding, narrow residential streets (fig. 12.21). By paying close attention to the smallest details of design, including the mellow reddish tint of stucco and sidewalk cement, the color and<pb n="418"/><pb n="418" type="orig"/>size of brick, which looked aged, not new, and the contrasting effect of white trim and dark, creosote-coated oak timbers, architect Grosvenor Atterbury gave the community's structures a harmonious Gothic-Tudor or German-Tudor, pseudo-medieval appearance. Though quaintly styled, the planned community was innovative in promoting neighborly living in attached row and two-family houses. These were grouped together so that residents shared front lawns and backyards. There were conventional single-family houses as well. Although Olmsted's design failed to account for the growing trend in automobile ownership, the generously planted curving streets and the attractively landscaped common ground&#x2014;including a central mall leading to Flagpole Green&#x2014;and the mellow picturesqueness of Atterbury's architecture made this rail- and, later, subway-served garden suburb an especially desirable place to live.</p><figure xml:id="fig-520"><graphic url="CH12_023.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.21. Bird's-Eye View of Forest Hills Gardens, Queens, <name type="place">New York</name>, designed by Frederick Law Olmsted, Jr., and Grosvenor Atterbury. <date when="1909">1909</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Perry saw the neighborhood unit as a means of re-creating the kind of environment conducive to the face-to-face relationships that impersonal big cities were perceived to be destroying. From his Forest Hills Gardens experience he developed a demographic-based formula that provided necessary educational, recreational, and service facilities based on convenient walking radii. Using this model for Yorkship Village, he specified that houses were to be located within a half mile of the local elementary school and its playground and no more than a quarter mile distant from local shops, which would be at the juncture of contiguous neighborhood units. A landscaped village-greentype square, complete with flagpole such as the one found in Forest Hills Gardens, would serve as the focal point for community institutions.</p><p>The neighborly, greenbelt-buffered community of low-cost housing approximating Perry's ideal at Yorkship Village was sufficiently attractive to disturb some congressmen who felt that this government-sponsored development reflected badly upon the nation's private housing industry. As a result, Congress passed legislation mandating that wartime workers' villages be auctioned for sale after the emergency was over, thus curtailing the experiment in public ownership, in the manner of Howard's garden city, based on financial management structured to maintain low rents and turn profits back into community improvements.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">The Regional Planning Association of America</hi></hi></head><p>Throughout the first half of the twentieth century, social philosopher, architectural critic, and urban historian Lewis Mumford (<date when="1915">1915</date>&#x2013;<date when="1990">1990</date>) was America's most passionate and articulate proponent of metropolitan decentralization and the creation of new towns. To understand Mumford's planning philosophy and that of his friends and colleagues who formed the Regional Planning Association of <name type="place">America</name>, we must first examine the life and work of Mumford's adopted mentor, <name type="pname">Patrick Geddes</name> (<date when="1854">1854</date>&#x2013;<date when="1932">1932</date>). The Scottish biologist, sociologist, professor, and pioneer of regional-scale urban planning was the author of <hi rend="italic">Cities in Evolution</hi> (<date when="1915">1915</date>). Geddes's views were influenced by the science of geography, the study of the earth's topography and resources in relation to human settlement and economic activity. He read the work of pioneers in this field: &#x00C9;lis&#x00E9;e Reclus (<date when="1830">1830</date>&#x2013;<date when="1905">1905</date>), the French anarchist, geographer, and author of the nineteen-volume <hi rend="italic">La Nouvelle G&#x00E9;ographie universelle, la terre et les hommes</hi> (<date when="1875">1875</date>&#x2014;94), and Paul Vidal de la Blache (<date when="1845">1845</date>&#x2013;<date when="1918">1918</date>), professor of geography in <name type="place">Paris</name>, editor of the periodical <hi rend="italic">Annales de g&#x00E9;ographie,</hi> and author of <hi rend="italic">Atlas g&#x00E9;n&#x00E9;ral; histoire et g&#x00E9;ographie,</hi> (<date when="1894">1894</date>). Geddes was also indebted to the ideas of Fr&#x00E9;d&#x00E9;ric Le Play (<date when="1806">1806</date>&#x2013;<date when="1882">1882</date>), the French mining engineer, sociologist, and author of <hi rend="italic">La R&#x00E9;forme sociale en <name type="place">France</name></hi> (<date when="1887">1887</date>). Le Play placed the family rather than the state at the center of the social structure.</p><p>Geddes realized that aerial perspective&#x2014;a prerogative that tall buildings and later airplanes conferred on twentieth-century denizens&#x2014;was a boon for planners in a mass society in which large industrial cities were becoming the norm. Aerial views allowed one to conceive cities whole and to more easily envision urbanism at a metropolitan scale. To see far and wide from on high the shapes of Earth&#x2014;its mountains, valleys, winding river courses, and coastlines, as well as the houses, roads, bridges, and other works of human beings&#x2014;fostered regionalism. The panoramas thus offered were an enormous aid to the geographer, demographer, and urban reformer. As we saw in<pb n="419"/><pb n="419" type="orig"/>Chapter Ten, the meaning of the Eiffel Tower lay both in its demonstration of the engineering and building technologies of structural steel and in the fact that it allowed visitors to grasp <name type="place">Paris</name> entire, while on their vertiginous descent the city was turned into a kaleidoscope of striking new perspectives.<ref target="#CH12-n9"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">9</hi></hi></ref></p><p>For Geddes, historical information about a city's past could also become comprehensible as, from an elevated perspective, streets and buildings coalesced into patterns describing its habitation in different periods of time. To translate the concept of planning at a regional scale into a graphic plan, Geddes set up his Outlook Tower, equipped with a camera obscura, on the roof of a building at the end of the Royal Mile in Edinburgh, where he could physically survey the town and its surrounding river basin. He urged what he termed <hi rend="italic">synoptic</hi> vision, "a seeing of the city, and this as a whole; like Athens from its Acropolis, like city and Acropolis together . . . from hill-top and from sea."<ref target="#CH12-n10"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">10</hi></hi></ref>Obviously, more was needed than an overview from an aerie such as the Outlook Tower in order to understand Edinburgh or any other city or region. Geddes advocated what he termed the "Valley Survey" and the "City Survey" to study local landscapes in all their physical, social, economic, and historical dimensions. He aimed to eliminate the artificial separation between town and country.</p><p>Geddes thought in temporal as well as spatial terms. Evolutionary biology provided a popular nineteenth-century metaphor for cultural transit, and like others of his day, he adopted the notion of cities and civilizations going from dawn to noon to sunset, or from birth to maturity to decline. He saw urbanism as a socially organic process associated with increasing occupational specialization and organizational complexity. In this fashion he charted the growth of cities in successive stages, from "polis" to "metropolis" to "megalopolis" and, finally, to "necropolis." He also drew a distinction between "paleotechnic" and "neotechnic" societies. The former denoted the early Industrial Age with its workers living in polluted, crowded, coal-burning towns, their lives directed "toward money wages instead of Vital Budget."<ref target="#CH12-n11"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">11</hi></hi></ref>The latter possessed new sources of power, including hydroelectricity, which would make possible decenralization of populations and the decongestion of existing industrial centers. The cities that were already spreading and coalescing into conurbations were prime candidates for Geddes's recommended "Regional Survey." At the very least, on sanitary grounds and to assure a pure water supply, sensible planning was mandated.</p><p>Geddes called the paleotechnic economic order "Kakotopia," a market-driven heedless scramble for profits, whereas the neotechnic order he labeled "Eutopia,... a place of effective health and well-being, even of glorious and in its way unprecedented beauty, renewing and rivaling the best achievements of the past."<ref target="#CH12-n12"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">12</hi></hi></ref>Geddes clearly had in mind the new garden cities and planned communities then being built in <name type="place">England</name>, which, following Howard's prescription, extended industrial prosperity to working-class families. He also wanted to reverse the dynamic of the metropolitan organism so that instead of the city's spreading into the country along rail and highway lines and then amorphously infilling the land in between, the country could gain on the city by wedging itself inward in the form of nature preserves (fig. 12.22). Geddes admired the urban parks that had made the nineteenth-century city a greener place, but he saw the need for forestry&#x2014;"no mere tree-cropping, but sylviculture, arboriculture too, and park-making at its greatest and best"<ref target="#CH12-n13"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">13</hi></hi></ref>&#x2014;as creating opportunities for real freedom in nature unavailable in the metropolitan parks with their fences and palings and their rules designed to maintain decorum befitting the grounds of a mansion.</p><figure xml:id="fig-521"><graphic url="CH12_024.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.22. Diagram by Patrick Geddes from <hi rend="italic">Cities in Evolution</hi> (<date when="1915">1915</date>) showing the desirability of reversing unchecked growth and infilling of green space as cities spread outward along the lines of transportation corridors</hi></figDesc></figure><p>The concept of the city as a complex and evolving social organism captivated the imagination of the young Mumford, who, with his superior and more disciplined literary gifts, elaborated Geddes's message and carried his ideological influence to an American audience in tones that echoed the Scot's fervently moral voice. Geddes's evolutionary categorization prompted Mumford in his prejudice against "megalopolis," the city grown gargantuan or what we today call "Spread City." In adopting Geddes as his mentor, Mumford distanced himself from European modernism, promoting instead planning concepts derived from Howard and the village-inspired British new towns. On the whole, architects and planners in <name type="place">America</name> aimed to give homeowners and tenants a more personal experience of nature and a more community-focused environment than that provided by Le Corbusier's broad, geometric grid of superblocks with regularly spaced, identical towers. Their site planning bore traces of both the Picturesque and Beaux-Arts styles in which they had been trained, although they eschewed Neoclassical architecture with its costly materials and ornament in favor of a simpler building vocabulary more suited to their aim of providing affordable housing and functional communities.<pb n="420"/><pb n="420" type="orig"/>Thus, they usually employed brick with white trim and often evoked American Colonial vernacular forms in their neo-Georgian buildings and village greens.</p><p>In <date when="1922">1922</date>, Mumford met the Beaux-Arts-trained architect Clarence Stein (<date when="1882">1882</date>&#x2013;<date when="1975">1975</date>), who shared his ideal of planning according to Geddes's regional survey methods. With the moral and financial support of developer Alexander Bing (<date when="1878">1878</date>&#x2013;<date when="1959">1959</date>), who added business sense to this agenda, they hoped to demonstrate the concept and means of providing better living conditions for a wider social range than had been possible previously. For Stein, this meant improved housing for modest-income families in environmentally sound communities in which schools, shops, and parks were within the easy walking radii recommended by Perry.</p><p><name type="pname">Charles Harris Whitaker</name> (<date when="1872">1872</date>&#x2013;<date when="1938">1938</date>), editor of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Institute of Architects</hi> (JAIA),_???shared the Progressive Era reform agenda of these two men. He sought to expand the public concerns of architects beyond the City Beautiful movement toward a social-service orientation that addressed more fundamental needs than ennobling the urban landscape with monuments symbolizing civic pride. Benton MacKaye (<date when="1879">1879</date>&#x2013;<date when="1975">1975</date>), a trained forester, an environmentalist, and the father of the Appalachian Trail, reinforced the group's regional and conservationist perspectives. In <date when="1923">1923</date>, with a handful of others, they formed the Regional Planning Association of <name type="place">America</name> (RPAA).</p><p>A native of Shirley, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>, MacKaye felt that the <name type="place">New England</name> town with its compact settlement around a village green and proximity to rural nature offered the best possible model for regional urbanism. He viewed with horror the side effects of the new automobile culture on the landscape, as tacky roadside stands, billboards, and filling stations sprang up along rural highways, blighting the natural scenery as well as graceful old towns. He conceived the creation of the "townless highway," his term for the limited-access throughway that bypassed urban centers and eliminated grade crossings with underpasses. New towns, too, would benefit from being constructed away from, yet in reasonable proximity to, this special-purpose artery. Further, the visionary MacKaye was a proponent of Giant Power, as he and other regionalists called their idea for transmitting electricity via high-voltage lines from coal- and water-powered stations located at mines and dams. He saw the Tennessee Valley Authority the New Deal program for damming the Tennessee River to harness hydroelectric power for distribution throughout the region, as an administrative model and means for channeling urban growth into discrete, park-surrounded cities.</p><p>Perhaps the most effective contribution of the RPAA&#x2014;in addition to the body of literature Mumford produced&#x2014;was the demonstration of new principles for community planning by the City Housing Corporation. The socially motivated real-estate developer and RPAA member Alexander Bing set up this limited-dividend company in order to build Sunnyside Gardens (<date when="1924">1924</date>) in the Borough of Queens, <name type="place">New York</name>, and Radburn (<date when="1928">1928</date>) in the Borough of Fairlawn, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>. In the absence of the government support that helped to underwrite later housing programs, the City Housing Corporation was a small, privately capitalized instrument designed to demonstrate the benefits of regional planning and the value of limited-dividend financing in returning a fixed profit to investors while also funding further community improvements.</p><p>However modest the scale of Sunnyside and Radburn, the entire RPAA fraternity applied assiduous attention and deep moral commitment to their design and building. Clarence Stein, planner and architect of these projects, collaborated with his partner, Henry Wright, as well as with Frederick Lee Ackerman, the architect of their houses. All three men were founding members of RPAA. Ackerman and Wright brought to bear their experience from Yorkship Village and other wartime emergency housing developments and with it their commitment to Clarence Perry's neighborhood unit as the fundamental community building block. As editor and writer, Whitaker and Mumford broadcast the philosophy of regional planning pioneered at Sunnyside and Radburn. Further, Mumford and his family took up residence in Sunnyside Gardens, remaining there for eleven years. MacKaye bolstered the other RPAA members' belief in technology as a powerful tool for social improvement and strengthened their commitment to natural areas preservation.</p> <p>In <date when="1924">1924</date>, on property Bing purchased from the Long Island Railroad to the east of Forest Hills in Sunnyside, Queens, Stein and Wright applied Perry's neighborhood-unit principles to the planning of Sunnyside Gardens. Ackerman served as architect for the blocks of houses, and Marjorie Sewell Cautley was hired as the project's landscape architect. Within the constraints of the preexisting grid, the design team developed a plan that maximized the amount of open space for private gardens, public greenery, and recreational commons, also providing an internal pedestrian circulation system for each block (fig. 12.23). Thus, their plan abandoned private property lot lines in favor of row houses with small individual backyards that faced a large communal parklike space where children could play. The Sunnyside commons were in time abandoned as land was sold to adjacent homeowners, who divided most of the once-shared<pb n="421"/><pb n="421" type="orig"/>landscape into individual parcels. But this early garden suburb was an important foundation for the work of Stein and Wright at Radburn, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, and for such later new towns as Reston, <name type="place">Virginia</name>.</p><figure xml:id="fig-522"><graphic url="CH12_025.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.23. Plan of two blocks with inner courts, Sunnyside Gardens, Queens, <name type="place">New York</name>, designed by Clarence Stein and Henry Wright. <date when="1926">1926</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-523"><graphic url="CH12_026.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Below:</hi> 12.24. Plan of residential districts, Radburn, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, by Clarence Stein and Henry Wright. <date when="1929">1929</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>Radburn, undertaken as a successor to Sunnyside Gardens, carried the garden-city concept forward. The community was billed as a New Town for the Motor Age. As Stein explained in <hi rend="italic">Toward New Towns for America</hi> (<date when="1957">1957</date>), "We believed thoroughly in green belts and towns of a limited size planned for work as well as living. We did not fully recognize that our main interest after our Sunnyside experience had been transferred to a more pressing need, that of a town in which people could live peacefully with the automobile&#x2014;or rather in spite of it."<ref target="#CH12-n14"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">14</hi></hi></ref>Traffic engineers soon became important professionals within the new fields of city planning and municipal administration.</p><p>The Radburn Idea was embodied in a layout that reduced the length of the roadway to the minimum necessary for automobile access, while providing abundant commonly held open space and a system of circulation routes modeled after the one developed by Olmsted and Vaux in Central Park (figs. 12.24, 12.25). To achieve this, Stein and Wright developed within the town's principal streets the super-block of 35 to 50 acres, a larger and more irregularly shaped area than that of a traditional city block. The savings associated with fewer linear feet of roadway made the provision of parkland cost-effective. Houses were turned so that their living rooms and bedrooms faced not the street but the green commons, which was continuous throughout the community.</p><p>Radburn was to have had a band of industrial development adjacent to the Erie Railroad lines and a new express highway. Then, in <date when="1929">1929</date>, when the first families moved into Radburn, the nation was plunged into the Great Depression. Industry did not materialize, and home buying and home building everywhere came to a halt. Banks foreclosed the mortgages of some Radburn residents, and only two superblocks were completed. Still, Radburn as an idea lived on. In the United States it served as a direct model for the Greenbelt Towns (<name type="place">Greenbelt</name>, <name type="place">Maryland</name>; <name type="place">Greenhills</name>, <name type="place">Ohio</name>; and<pb n="422"/><pb n="422" type="orig"/>Greendale, Wisconsin) built during President Franklin Roosevelt's New Deal administration under the economist Rexford Guy Tugwell (<date when="1891">1891</date>&#x2014; <date when="1979">1979</date>), the ardent disciple of Ebenezer Howard and member of the U. S. president's "Brain Trust" who served as administrator of the Resettlement Administration.</p><figure xml:id="fig-524"><graphic url="CH12_027.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.25. Plan of a single residential cul-de-sac, Radburn. The 18- to 20-foot-wide service road lead to the garages and service areas of fifteen to twenty homes. These face a commons, the green interior portion of a superblock. Foot ways connect residents to parks and athletic facilities.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>The idea of rational planning by a diversified consortium of professional disciplines represented by the most skilled technical experts became something of an article of faith by the <date when="1920">1920</date>s, even in the democratic United States with its free-market economy. The authoritarianism implicit in such planning was more acceptable than it would be today. The prevailing notion was that a new social order was being born and that modern technology in the service of democratic values could produce a more humane society and a higher standard of living for almost all classes. The United States was becoming a manufacturing titan, adding to its abundant natural resources unprecedented industrial wealth. Under these circumstances, people were optimistic that the solutions to social and physical problems could be found through financing and technical expertise, and they were willing to trust those in power to provide the benefits of modernity to society as a whole. The notion of an enlightened and beneficient mastermind arranging a total environment geared to the new working patterns and rising living standards of the times was an attractive one as people grappled with the rapid technological advances and complexity of modern society. In <name type="place">America</name> as well as in Europe, certain architects were beginning to think of themselves as suited for this role, none more so than Frank Lloyd Wright, who well understood that the fundamental gift of the motor age was mobility.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">Frank Lloyd Wright's Usonian Vision for Broadacre City</hi></hi></head><p>The members of RPAA, Peter Kropotkin, and H. G. Wells had early intuited one of the most important aspects of modernity: ease of movement and the consequent liberation from being bound in place. Similarly, the architect Frank Lloyd Wright (<date when="1869">1869</date>&#x2014; <date when="1959">1959</date>) saw decentralization as a positive force for improving the human condition. Unlike the RPAA group or the builders in the newly created Soviet Union, Wright did not promote a communal vision but one that celebrated individual freedom in the tradition of the transcendentalists Ralph Waldo Emerson, Henry David Thoreau, and Walt Whitman. He saw how mass automobile ownership, widespread communications enabled by radio, telegraph, and telephone, and easily distributed electric power could make possible a complete redistribution of population. At least in <name type="place">America</name> with its abundance of developable land, it was now theoretically possible for people to live at very low densities, with each family occupying an entire acre. Wright also saw how standardization of industrial production creating inexpensive new building technologies and utilities construction could foster large-scale, low-density urbanization. According to his Usonian Vision, as he called his utopian scheme for Broadacre City, instead of living in a hive of nearly identical apartments or garden-city row houses, residents would occupy distinctive freestanding houses. Wright's anti-urban utopia was thus completely unlike that of Le Corbusier or the planners of Radburn except in its willing embrace of great systems of conveyance&#x2014;distribution lines for power and utilities and transportation corridors for the movement of people and goods.</p><p>Publication of Wright's scheme for Broadacre City probably furthered his reputation as an architectural genius, but his proposal had little chance of being realized. In the United States, perhaps more than in other countries, the kind of civic leadership and initiative Tocqueville had observed a century earlier defied authoritarian visions and singular solutions. Planning, particularly on a regional scale, to be successful, necessitated close cooperation between the public and private sectors, and men such as Lewis Mumford and Frank Lloyd Wright were not temperamentally equipped to struggle and compro mise within the political arena in order to advance a<pb n="423"/><pb n="423" type="orig"/>partial agenda. Nor were they willing to forsake an ideal premised upon low-density settlement in garden cities or on broad acres for one that served merely to guide the already forceful trend toward metropolitanism. Nowhere in the <date when="1920">1920</date>s and <date when="1930">1930</date>s were the implications of this dichotomy more evident than in the fast-growing counties surrounding <name type="place">New York</name> City.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">The Regional Plan for New York</hi></hi></head><p>In contrast to Mumford and his fellow members of the Regional Planning Association of <name type="place">America</name>, the Regional Plan Association (RPA) proposed no radical agenda of garden-city decentralization. This group instead undertook the preparation of a plan to <hi rend="italic">guide</hi> the growth of metropolitan <name type="place">New York</name> City, which was rapidly spawning suburban development in several counties of the tri-state (<name type="place">New York</name>, <name type="place">New Jersey</name>, and Connecticut) region surrounding the five boroughs that constitute the incorporated city. Unlike the RPAA garden-city idealists who wished to retard metropolitan growth and foster discrete urban communities set well apart and separated by open space, the founders of the RPA recognized the momentum for cities to grow into massive regional complexes.<ref target="#CH12-n15"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">15</hi></hi></ref> Planning, in their view, was essential to predict statistically, then guide rationally, not rearrange, this growth. Underlying the new urban scale they envisioned was a constant increase in automobile ownership, opening up the possibility of ever-expanding rings of residential settlement and the birth of the commuter society. Their metropolitan vision also implied increased density at the urban core with office skyscrapers thrusting ever higher into the air.</p><p>The Regional Plan Association, though not yet known by that name, had its beginning in <date when="1921">1921</date>. That year <name type="pname">Charles Dyer Norton</name> (<date when="1871">1871</date>&#x2013;<date when="1923">1923</date>), a trustee of the Russell Sage Foundation, the philanthropic fund that had sponsored Forest Hills Gardens, helped initiate the preparation of a privately financed plan for the rapidly growing region encompassing all of the counties of Long Island and those elsewhere within a twohour rail commuting distance of <name type="place">New York</name> City.<ref target="#CH12-n16"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">16</hi></hi></ref>In some respects both independent, nongovernmental advocacy groups&#x2014;RPAA and RPA&#x2014;were likeminded. They addressed some of the same social issues, and RPA welcomed RPAA's Radburn Plan and other similarly innovative planning approaches, including the creation of the motor parkways that made MacKaye's vision of the "townless highway" a reality. But Norton was part of a business and philanthropic elite that maintained, when possible, a close working relationship with government. Understandably, RPA pragmatically focused on the physical, economic, social, and legal surveys that would guide political and corporate decision makers and help direct existing market forces toward coherent, rational ends. Accepting as natural and inevitable the enlargement of the metropolis beyond the boundaries of the five-borough polity of Greater <name type="place">New York</name> that had been created in <date when="1898">1898</date>, RPA hoped to transform the city and its several surrounding counties into a better planned multigovernmental regional entity.</p><p>Although British garden-city planner Thomas Adams brought his professional experience in <name type="place">England</name> to the Regional Plan Committee, the precursor of RPA, <name type="place">New York</name> City's course of metropolitan regional growth was already set. Its destiny was to remain that of a commercial and entertainment core with vertically expanding skyscrapers and horizontally extending rings of commuter suburbs, none true garden cities. Unwin's Hampstead Gardens, which Norton had praised as "the best subdivision of suburban land ever I saw or heard of,"<ref target="#CH12-n17"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">17</hi></hi></ref>was a leafy dormitory within the <name type="place">London</name> metropolis, and it, rather than Letchworth, served as a paradigm for <name type="place">New York</name>'s expansion. Adams must have realized that the complexity and size of <name type="place">New York</name> City and its environs, as well as the region's political fragmentation, militated against a British reformist approach to planning. In the United States, growth might be guided by infrastructure improvements and the reservation of certain lands for public use, but it would be practically impossible to mandate and locate new town construction within the context of a free-market real-estate economy.</p><p><name type="pname">Thomas Adams</name> and <name type="pname">Frederick Law Olmsted</name>, Jr., a principal consultant on the plan, proposed that the task be addressed by individual team members taking responsibility for different geographical areas. Adams was chosen to chair and coordinate the activities of this Advisory Group as they tackled in their regional sectors problems of land use and population density; subdivision, land development, and housing; circulation and communication; and open spaces and recreation. Informing their inquiry was the work of the directors of the Economic, Legal, and Social Surveys. Olmsted was responsible for the important sector comprising all of beach-rich Long Island, and Adams made Westchester and Fairfield Counties his purview.</p><p><name type="pname">Adams</name> tried to synthesize the many studies, a task made difficult by the application of each man's independent approach and individual set of planning values to his particular sector. Altogether, however, their reports set forth the need for regional zoning, including agricultural zoning; for circumferential roads rather than more radial transportation corridors; for centralization of some activities and decentralization of others according to their functional requirements; for increased parkland, especially along the waterfront; and for reservation of land for airport sites.</p><pb n="424"/><pb n="424" type="orig"/><figure xml:id="fig-525"><graphic url="CH12_028.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.26. A proposal to increase street capacity, Advisory Committee of the Regional Plan Committee of Architects of the Regional Plan of <name type="place">New York</name> and Its Environs. <date when="1923">1923</date>. This drawing by Hugh Ferriss, a product of his collaboration with Harvey Wiley Corbett, is an affirmation of skyscraper modernity that weds the former's romantic urbanism with the latter's pragmatic belief in a multilevel city.</hi></figDesc></figure><p>At this point, four committees of architects set to work sketching plans for various Manhattan projects, ranging in style from Beaux-Arts Neoclassicism to a visionary modernism emphasizing technology and movement (fig. 12.26). The drawings of <name type="pname">Hugh Ferriss</name> (<date when="1889">1889</date>&#x2013;<date when="1962">1962</date>) and <name type="pname">Harvey Wiley Corbett</name> (<date when="1873">1873</date>&#x2013;<date when="1954">1954</date>) made especially clear that, far from withering away as the city became more decentralized, the Manhattan core would become aggrandized as a transportation hub and commercial center.</p><p>Unfortunately, the planners studied traffic and transportation issues separately, and they therefore never achieved an integrated approach to the movement of people and goods by both highway and rail. Their proposals to integrate suburban rail and urban transit services also foundered because of political, administrative, and technical problems. Governmental fragmentation made it difficult to favor one jurisdiction over another. Private ownership of rail lines created rivalry for tax revenues and profits, rendering impossible any serious cooperation between companies. Furthermore, city transit officials refused to plan on an interstate regional basis. For these reasons, Adams oriented the Regional Plan toward the newer technology represented by the motor vehicle. It was simply easier to concentrate on building new highways to serve the anticipated growth in commuters and goods. Travel by automobile was also by now a form of recreation, as installment-plan financing made cars available to people of average means. Recreational parkways were therefore an important part of the Regional Plan. Here Adams followed a trend Olmsted, Sr., had begun and Olmsted, Jr., had followed in his work for the <name type="place">New York</name> City Improvement Commission in <date when="1907">1907</date> when he proposed limited-access, landscaped parkways linking the city's larger parks.</p><p>In <date when="1929">1929</date>, the <hi rend="italic">Graphic Regional Plan</hi> was published and presented to public officials with considerable fanfare. A document of overlays synthesizing several proposals, it was nevertheless without a unitary vision, clear objectives, or a set of strategies for implementation. To work toward the realization of the plan's carefully balanced and essentially pragmatic proposals, the Committee of the Regional Plan was reconstituted as the Regional Plan Association. With RPA's official birth as a permanent advocacy organization, the group now focused on publishing the eight volumes making up the Regional Survey and <hi rend="italic">The Building of the City</hi> (<date when="1931">1931</date>), Adams's companion volume to the <hi rend="italic">Graphic Regional Plan.</hi> It also worked to build broad regional support among civic leaders and elected officials.</p><p>In spite of harsh criticism from Mumford and other members of RPAA who harbored as their ideal a less market-oriented and less politically circumspect plan&#x2014; one embodying their utopian vision of community at the scale of the town&#x2014;and even though the organization was merely advisory and not legally constituted as a public authority with broad jurisdictional powers, the work of the RPA was influential. By <date when="1933">1933</date>, the RPAA had disbanded; it had only been a loose consortium of like-minded visionaries unsupported by financial resources to staff a professional planning effort. But the RPA stayed in existence because its proposals were attuned to political circumstances and compatible with general market trends. The work of Adams and his colleagues lived on in the form of the official recognition of city planning as a profession. Harvard University expanded its landscape architecture department to include studies in this area and began offering a master's degree in planning in <date when="1928">1928</date>; the <name type="place">Massachusetts</name> Institute of Technology, Cornell University, and Columbia University established similar programs in the <date when="1930">1930</date>s. In addition, in <date when="1936">1936</date>, Mayor Fiorello LaGuardia created the <name type="place">New York</name> City Planning Commission, and by <date when="1937">1937</date>, 139 municipal planning boards had been established and 308 zoning ordinances adopted in the <name type="place">New York</name> Region.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">The Great Era of Park and Parkway Building</hi></hi></head><p>The greatest physical result of the <date when="1929">1929</date> Regional Plan was the creation of numerous state parks and regional parkways in <name type="place">New York</name> and other states throughout the nation. Beginning in <date when="1933">1933</date>, President Franklin Delano Roosevelt stimulated park and parkway building through the National Planning Board and federal public works programs. In making their recommendations for new regional parks and parkways in the <name type="place">New York</name> Region, the RPA planners were in fact following a trend already in progress, giving it voice and rational<pb n="425"/><pb n="425" type="orig"/>shape through their studies.</p><p>As an outgrowth of Olmsted's <date when="1907">1907</date> report, the Bronx River Parkway, built between <date when="1912">1912</date> and <date when="1923">1923</date>, had become America's first grade-separated highway. Unlike the intra-urban, boulevard-style parkways designed by Olmsted, Sr., and Vaux to provide a green framework for residential growth and to link several major parks within a city, the Bronx River Parkway was regional, rather than municipal in scale. More than a ribbon of tree-lined roadway with numerous intersections, it was planned as a landscape, an uninterrupted stretch of park scenery with widely spaced entrance points. The park-making motive was, in fact, initially paramount, and the road was the result of a secondary impulse. Only after the commissioners in charge of the project had launched it as an effort to clean the waters and beautify the banks of the Bronx River, as it flowed from the Kensico Dam in West-chester County to enter Bronx Park, did they decide that it should contain a roadway. The landscape architect, <name type="pname">Hermann W. Merkel</name>, and the principal engineer, <name type="pname">Leslie G. Holleran</name>, designed it for pleasure driving to various regional park destinations and to provide a dignified entrance into <name type="place">New York</name> City from the north (fig. 12.27). They divided the roadway with a median of irregular width that accommodated grade changes and such topographical features as rock outcrops and particularly fine stands of trees. Construction, stopped during World War I, resumed after <date when="1919">1919</date>, by which time more powerful automobile engines made greater speeds possible. This explains why the radii of the parkway's curves, designed for the pace of a carriage in its southern portion, become elongated as the road progresses northward. An ample right-of-way containing an entire "viewshed," its densely planted borders varying in width from 190 to 1,000 feet (57.9 to 304.8 meters), discouraged the erection of billboards at a time when there was no legislation banning them from adjacent properties. Landscape architect Gilmore D. Clarke (<date when="1892">1892</date>&#x2013;<date when="1982">1982</date>) designed the individually distinctive bridge overpasses of rough-finished fieldstone.</p><p>So successful was this project as a work of landscape design and as a stimulant to nearby property values and taxes, that even before its completion a Westchester County Park Commission was set up in <date when="1922">1922</date>. Its technical staff included Clarke and the engineer Jay Downer, who had also worked on the Bronx River Parkway. Over the next ten years these men collaborated on the construction of more than a dozen parks and several new parkways including the Saw Mill River and the Hutchinson River Parkways. In Putnam County, the Taconic State Park Commission was responsible for the extraordinarily inventive and beautiful Taconic State Parkway sweeping northward into Dutchess and Columbia Counties (fig. 12.28).</p><figure xml:id="fig-526"><graphic url="CH12_029.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.27. Bronx River Parkway, <name type="place">New York</name> State, landscape design by <name type="pname">Hermann W. Merkel</name>, roadway design by <name type="pname">Leslie G. Holleran</name>, principal engineer. <date when="1912">1912</date>&#x2013;23</hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-527"><graphic url="CH12_030.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Left:</hi> 12.28. Northern section, Taconic State Parkway, <name type="place">New York</name> State, designed by Charles J. Baker of the <name type="place">New York</name> State Department of Public Works. <date when="1940">1940</date>&#x2013;50</hi></figDesc></figure><p>Although frequently dismissive of the work of Adams and his colleagues, <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name> (<date when="1888">1888</date>&#x2014; <date when="1981">1981</date>) became responsible, more than any other individual, agency, or municipality, for transforming <name type="place">New York</name> City into a regional entity by means of a 416mile network of parkways.<ref target="#CH12-n18"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">18</hi></hi></ref>Pragmatic and politically astute, <name type="pname">Moses</name> was adept at manipulating the media and encouraging the desires of the rising middle class for increased recreation facilities. Ruthless in the way he maneuvered his way to success, when it suited his ends, <name type="pname">Moses</name> co-opted the planning expertise of the Regional Plan Committee (later the Regional Plan Association). Many of the parkways and the related parks that <name type="pname">Moses</name> built were outlined in the Regional Plan. Nevertheless, he could also portray the group as protective of elitist class interests. Brooking no opposition, he amassed sufficient power to become a force equal to the elected officials whom he served, dominating government bureaucracies and often bending to his will business leaders, including the sponsors of the Regional Plan.</p><p>In <date when="1924">1924</date>, <name type="pname">Governor Alfred E. Smith</name> appointed <name type="pname">Moses</name> chairman of the Long Island Park Commission and chairman of the <name type="place">New York</name> State Council of Parks. In <date when="1934">1934</date>, Governor <name type="pname">Herbert H. Lehman</name> named him commissioner of the <name type="place">New York</name> City Department of Parks, which <name type="pname">Moses</name> immediately reorganized, con<pb n="426"/><pb n="426" type="orig"/>solidating individual borough park administrations into a centralized citywide agency. <name type="pname">Jones Beach</name>, a palatial bathing and recreational complex built during the <date when="1920">1920</date>s on Long Island's Great South Bay, is perhaps his most important landscape design achievement (fig. 12.29). Completed in <date when="1929">1929</date>, the 2,245-acre oceanfront park had a 1-mile-long boardwalk, a 14-mile-long boat channel, archery ranges, an 18-hole golf course, pony tracks, bathhouses, wading and swimming pools, lawns, shrubbery, and sixty-four parking lots accommodating 12,000 automobiles. <name type="pname">Moses</name> thought of Jones Beach as an American Lido, a deluxe middle-class family resort, intentionally devoid of the honky-tonk concessions found at such beachside amusement parks as Coney Island. Here he converted a necessity into an icon, adopting Harvey Wiley Corbett's idea of turning the 200-foot (70meter) water tower for pumping fresh water from 1,200 feet (366 meters) below sea level into a streamlined imitation of the campanile of Saint Mark's in <name type="place">Venice</name>. Rising from the middle of a lavishly landscaped traffic circle containing reflecting pools with floral borders at the far end of the causeway linking the barrier beach with the mainland, this architectural beacon, washed by floodlights at night, could be seen from a distance of 25 miles away.</p><figure xml:id="fig-528"><graphic url="CH12_031.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">2.29. <name type="pname">Jones Beach</name>, <name type="place">Long Island</name>, <name type="place">New York</name>, built by <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name>. Completed <date when="1929">1929</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p><name type="pname">Moses</name> was indifferent to the interests of the wealthy men who owned large estates and belonged to hunt clubs and country clubs. With the creation of numerous public parks, he substituted middle-class recreational ideals for the upper-class ones that had governed land use and shaped landscape design in the past. Not surprisingly, Jones Beach was an instant and huge public success. By <date when="1936">1936</date>, <name type="pname">Moses</name> had built 100 miles of parkways on Long Island and in <name type="place">New York</name> City, and by the end of the decade he had created 255 new city playgrounds, added several miles of urban beaches, given Central Park a major facelift, and renovated several other historic parks.</p><p>But <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name> did not single-handedly bring the modern park and recreation era into being in <name type="place">New York</name> State. Since the turn of the twentieth century, the old elite had made the general public the beneficiary of several enlightened philanthropic actions. <name type="pname">J. Pierpont Morgan</name> had saved the Palisades across the Hudson River from <name type="place">New York</name> City from traprock mining, and in <date when="1910">1910</date> the Harriman family gave the state more than 40,000 additional acres along the Hudson River, a gift that included Bear Mountain State Park. William Letchworth donated his <date when="1000">1000</date>-acre tract along the scenic Genesee River in western <name type="place">New York</name> State, and the American Scenic and Historic Preservation Society successfully campaigned to have the state acquire the geologically fascinating Watkins Glen at the southern end of Seneca Lake.</p><p>While there was a great deal of sporadic action in other states at this time, only <name type="place">New York</name>, Connecticut, Wisconsin, <name type="place">California</name>, and Indiana had anything like an organized approach to acquiring and managing state parks. Nowhere was there a system of state parks until, in <date when="1921">1921</date>, Stephen Mather, the director of the National Park Service, saw the need to protect the national parks from being overrun by automobile tourists. He sought to provide recreational opportunities in less spectacular settings closer to urban centers and set to work organizing the National Conference on State Parks. His efforts resulted in the creation of seventeen state park boards or commissions between <date when="1921">1921</date> and <date when="1927">1927</date>.</p><p>During the Great Depression, the Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC) and the Works Progress Administration (WPA) provided vast numbers of workers to build parks and parkways all over the country. Building upon principles embodied in the National Park plan authored by Frederick Law Olmsted, Jr., in <date when="1916">1916</date>, the National Park Service assumed increasing design responsibility, particularly after the Park, Parkway, and Recreational Study Act of <date when="1936">1936</date> authorized federal involvement in metropolitan and state park planning. Its own aesthetic, Government Rustic&#x2014;an unpretentious style intended to harmonize with nature and to express an American pioneer ethos through the use of rough-hewn timbers, hatchet-cut stone, or boulders&#x2014;offered an alternative to the stripped-down Beaux-Arts classicism characteristic of much park building design of the period (fig. 12.30).</p><p>By the <date when="1920">1920</date>s, even where there were no parkways or state parks to serve them, Americans were taking to the road in increasing numbers.<ref target="#CH12-n19"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">19</hi></hi></ref>Complaining about the confinement of the railroad&#x2014;a confinement both temporal and spatial as one was a prisoner of both schedules and routes&#x2014;they gamely coped with unmarked, often impassable dirt roads, cooked their meals over open fires, and slept under<pb n="427"/><pb n="427" type="orig"/>the stars as their frontier forebears had done. They gave their Ford Model Ts names like Lizzie or Belle, and they identified these wonderful machines with the adventurous and leisurely stage coach. They called their style of travel "gypsying" and enjoyed the serendipitous companionship of fellow motorists with whom they formed an instantaneous fraternity as they passed on directions and assisted one another with mechanical and roadbed repairs. These hardy souls were the first to adopt the slogan "See <name type="place">America</name> First" when World War I made European travel impossible. Even after the war, cultural chauvinism and pride in America's scenery promoted this new form of vacation, and the growing popularity of automobile touring increased the demand for national and state parks. As more and more Americans took to the road, it became necessary to set up municipal campsites. Soon entrepreneurs built roadside cabins to provide campers with basic amenities, and from this humble beginning, the motel industry was born.</p><p>The new regional mobility spelled the end of the Olmstedian ideal of the park as a pastoral refuge in the heart of the city as people with automobiles increasingly sought their bucolic pleasures in excursions to the new county and state parks, enjoying the drive there on landscaped parkways. Veblen's definition of the leisure class had been extended to a broad social spectrum, and <hi rend="italic">leisure</hi> as a term was gaining common currency. Ball fields, golf courses, swimming pools, ice-skating rinks, bathing beaches, tennis courts, riding stables, and archery ranges assumed the status of public entitlements, accoutrements of the American way of life. This was the logical outcome of the movement that from the beginning of the twentieth century had placed playgrounds, along with housing, at the forefront of the social reformers' agenda.</p><p>Accurately reading the temper of the times, <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name> had a parks vision to match society's appetite for play. For him, transportation planning and park planning went hand in hand. During his thirty-year tenure as commissioner of the <name type="place">New York</name> City Department of Parks and Recreation, he converted carriage drives into wider roadways for automobiles, turned meadows into ball fields, and built playgrounds and other recreational facilities.<ref target="#CH12-n20"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">20</hi></hi></ref>Audaciously, he claimed that the nearly 3,000 acres of parkways and other transportation corridors he commissioned in <name type="place">New York</name> City were really linear parks because of the addition of marginal playgrounds, foot and bicycle paths, and waterfront promenades within their rights-of-way. <name type="pname">Moses</name>' position as commissioner of parks, together with his chairmanship of the Long Island State Park Commission and the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority, allowed him to reshape the <name type="place">New York</name> metropolitan region according to an ethos of mass leisure.</p><figure xml:id="fig-529"><graphic url="CH12_032.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.30. An example of the Government Rustic style of architecture, designed by the National Park Service</hi></figDesc></figure></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">Jens Jensen and the Parks of Chicago</hi></hi></head><p>As the urban sociologist and American parks historian Galen Cranz points out in <hi rend="italic">The Politics of Park Design,</hi> the factory system of industrial efficiency and Reform Era play, with its emphasis on physical exercise and sports, were contemporary phenomena, and both were organized in a highly regimented way.<ref target="#CH12-n21"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">21</hi></hi></ref>Thus, increased recreational opportunities afforded by the shorter workweek, longer vacations, earlier retirement, and higher pay went hand in hand with highly structured play environments that were, ironically, as pragmatically focused and utilitarian as industrial factories&#x2014;implicitly acknowledged as the dominant paradigm for the organization of modern life. Thanks to the efforts of early-twentieth-century reformers, the profession of recreational leader had been created. In the sphere of park administration as elsewhere, the basis for social reform shifted from reliance on sheer moral fervor and presumed class superiority to dependence on technical expertise and professional skill. Park departments hired recruits of upright character and instituted training programs for directors of playgrounds, as those parks emphasizing recreational activities were now called.</p><p><name type="place">Chicago</name> was the standard-bearer in the creation of Progressive Era playgrounds or neighborhood parks. Along with the branch library, the field house was an original <name type="place">Chicago</name> recreational institution that also served as a neighborhood cultural and educational center. Social reformers saw it as an important instrument of civic improvement, and they vigorously sponsored the construction of both libraries and field houses in the city's poorest sections.</p><p>In <name type="place">Chicago</name>'s West Park District, where some of the city's least affluent residents lived, Jens Jensen (<date when="1860">1860</date>&#x2013;<date when="1951">1951</date>), a Danish immigrant, served as chief landscape architect and general superintendent. Because of his agrarian background and education in Danish folk schools where teachers emphasized indigenous culture, Jensen had a natural sympathy for<pb n="428"/><pb n="428" type="orig"/>native scenery and local cultural mores. He deeply loved the <name type="place">Illinois</name> prairie as an especially beautiful landscape. In his own work he developed plans that evoked prairie rivers and produced what he called "sun openings," small glades to serve as miniature prairies within parks. Although he integrated such geometrical elements as circular rose gardens into his park plans, and although in keeping with contemporary demand his meadows were designed for ball playing, golf, and tennis, Jensen subscribed to Olmsted's quintessentially American vision of landscape creation with its implicit transcendentalist objective of bringing city people into closer contact with nature. He employed some of the same design strategies as Olmsted &#x2014; creating long views in which loosely arranged clumps of trees allow the eye to be beckoned from one landscape space to another, building large irregular lakes or lagoons, looping park interiors with circuit drives, and concealing park borders with densely planted vegetation (fig. 12.31).</p><figure xml:id="fig-530"><graphic url="CH12_033.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.31. Plan for Garfield Park, <name type="place">Chicago</name>, <name type="place">Illinois</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Jens Jensen</name>. <date when="1912">1912</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p><name type="pname">Jensen</name> also subscribed to the goals of the Regional Planning Association of <name type="place">America</name> and adhered to the social reform ideas of <name type="pname">Jane Addams</name>. Inspired by Addams's use of pageantry as a means of fostering ethnic pride and inculcating democratic values, he borrowed this idea to promote conservation and spiritual bonds with nature. Anticipating the theories of Ian <name type="pname">McHarg</name> (<date when="1920">1920</date>&#x2013;<date when="2001">2001</date>), author of <hi rend="italic">Design with Nature</hi> (<date when="1969">1969</date>), he ardently promoted a naturalistic style of landscape design at a time when BeauxArts formality enjoyed favor nearly everywhere.</p><p>Although Jensen's refusal to accommodate the political machine that controlled park operational policy cost him this position in <date when="1900">1900</date>, he continued to serve the Special Park Commission that had been established to develop plans for a metropolitan park system similar to the one Charles Eliot had envisioned for <name type="place">Boston</name> (see Chapter Nine). Brought back into office as the head of the West Park District in <date when="1905">1905</date> by a reform administration, Jensen prepared new plans for Douglas, Garfield, and other partially built parks. In Garfield Park, he built what was then the world's largest conservatory, installing a naturalistic brook with water threading its way musically from one fern-embowered rocky ledge to another.</p><p><name type="pname">Jensen</name> also designed the new small parks of the West Park District, all of which were under 8.5 acres in size, in a more informal manner than those of the South Park District. In the same vein, he urged William Carbys Zimmerman, the state architect and designer of the West Park District field houses, to consider the <name type="place">Chicago</name> Prairie style that Wright and other architects were then developing as an expression compatible with the regional landscape. The Prairie style in architecture is characterized by broad, low, ground-hugging planes; a forthright expression of structure; and respect for native building materials.</p><p><name type="pname">Jensen</name>'s later work was often paired in exhibitions with that of such Prairie-style architects as George Grant Elmslie, William Purcell, and Wright, as well as with that of another likeminded landscape architect, Ossian Cole Simonds, who also favored open, naturalistic designs employing native plants. Along with Simonds, Jensen felt that the relatively featureless landscape of the Midwest held a particular subtle beauty. Its flatness was for him something to be celebrated, which he did with shelving planes of rocks beside winding stream courses and the horizontal branching patterns of hawthorns and crab apples (see fig. 12.33). He imitated natural plant communities in his choice and placement of these and other native species, and he sometimes attempted to achieve the appearance of plant succession, the sequential colonization by different species of a particular region until<pb n="429"/><pb n="429" type="orig"/>the species first there have given way to the region's natural climax situation, or ecological maturity. He also gave attention to effects of natural light, creating sun openings framed by groves of trees and planting in a way that made one's passage along gently winding roads an experience of alternating light and shade.</p><p>In <date when="1916">1916</date>, near the city's western boundary and the town of Oak Park, Jensen designed Columbus Park, a square parcel comprising 144 acres. Characterized by his friend and follower Alfred Caldwell as "the finest and most complete of all the Jensen parks,"<ref target="#CH12-n22"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">22</hi></hi></ref>it epitomized his original contribution toward developing a Prairie style in landscape architecture while still incorporating facilities for popular forms of recreation (fig. 12.32). Tennis courts, swimming pool, playground, and an athletic field are located between the park periphery and the interior circuit drive. Inside the drive is a large meadow&#x2014;the prairie in miniature&#x2014;designed to also serve as a golf course. Curving around its eastern edge is a lagoon, created when Jensen deepened a small watercourse, turning it into a "prairie river," which he bordered with wetland vegetation: irises, rose mallow, cordgrass, cattails, rushes, arrowheads, and water lilies. Around the source of this waterbody Jensen, who prided himself on his rockwork compositions, laid several irregular, horizontal layers of native limestone to give the appearance of a low, stratified prairie bluff (fig. 12.33). On a small hill near the lagoon, Jensen created a players' green&#x2014;a clearing designed to serve as a performance area&#x2014;orienting the position of the audience, who sat in the grass on the opposite side of one of the two brooks flowing into the lagoon, west toward the setting sun.</p><p>An admirer of the remaining traces of Native American occupancy in the natural landscape, Jensen used the Indian trail as inspiration in the design of his paths. He used rough-cut stone to build council rings, circular stone benches with a fire pit in the center. Council rings were gathering places where park visitors could converse, listen to stories, or participate in pageants. Players' greens&#x2014;clearings designed to serve as settings for performances in nature&#x2014;served a similar purpose.</p><p>In <date when="1935">1935</date>, Jensen designed the Lincoln Memorial Garden in Springfield, <name type="place">Illinois</name>. Here, on a gently sloping and undulating site that he helped select on the shore of Lake Springfield, he contrasted densely planted copses of native species&#x2014;redbud, dogwood, hawthorn, crab apple, maple, cherry, sumac, birch, oak, ash, and locust&#x2014;with open greens and broad grassy lanes leading to the water's edge in several places. In addition, he built eight council rings (fourteen were originally planned), including the Lincoln Council Ring set within a grove of white oaks overlooking the lake. Volunteers, especially schoolchildren and garden club members, were instrumental in collecting native plants not available in nurseries and in carrying out the details of Jensen's plan.</p><figure xml:id="fig-531"><graphic url="CH12_034.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.32. Plan for Columbus Park, <name type="place">Chicago</name>, <name type="place">Illinois</name>, designed by <name type="pname">Jens Jensen</name>. <date when="1916">1916</date></hi></figDesc></figure><figure xml:id="fig-532"><graphic url="CH12_035.jpg"/><head>12.33. Spring in Columbus Park, <name type="place">Chicago</name>, illustrating Jensen's stratified Prairie-style rockwork</head></figure><p><name type="pname">Jensen</name> had long been an advocate of this kind of citizen participation in landscape stewardship. In <date when="1913">1913</date>, to promote awareness of indigenous natural beauty, he had organized the Friends of Our Native<pb n="430"/><pb n="430" type="orig"/>Landscape, an early conservation group that led a citizen effort to have preserved in public ownership the Indiana Dunes along the southern shore of Lake Michigan and other portions of the natural heritage of the Midwest. Several state parks resulted from the staunch environmental commitment and protracted efforts of this group.</p><p>After the death of his wife in <date when="1934">1934</date>, Jensen decided to leave <name type="place">Chicago</name> to realize his cherished dream of founding a school similar to the Danish folk and agricultural schools of his youth. Its mission was to promote civic responsibility and environmental stewardship. At Ellison Bay, Wisconsin, where he had a vacation cabin, he established The Clearing, a non-degree-granting school in nature where students learn ecology and basic horticultural and landscape-design practices. Because he believed in a humanistic approach to education, his curriculum also included drawing, painting, sculpture, music, drama, poetry, and architecture.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">Urban Parks in Transition</hi></hi></head><p>Increasingly, park designers were, as <name type="pname">Jensen</name> had been, employees of park agencies, rather than outside firms. But few held the Olmstedian ideals that Jensen did, and charged with retrofitting older parks with new facilities&#x2014;notably ball fields and children's playgrounds&#x2014;they displayed little of his sensitivity in harmonizing utilitarian and natural landscape elements. Once-broad park vistas were interrupted with fencing to restrain errant baseballs, protect the young, and serve as a barrier to intruding dogs. With the increased social emphasis on sports, playing fields rather than meadows, recreation facilities rather than views, and active rather than passive use became ever greater public priorities.</p><p>The multiplication of parks and recreational services in an effort to keep up with market forces in the manner of a commercial enterprise led "to an increased emphasis on the efficiency with which [park departments] could deliver services on demand, and this emphasis led to systems thinking and bureaucratization."<ref target="#CH12-n23"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">23</hi></hi></ref>Greatly expanded in their scale of operations and no longer with any real sense of moral purpose, only efficient service delivery, as their raison d'&#x00EA;tre, parks agencies in <name type="place">New York</name> and elsewhere fell behind in the budgetary competition with other city agencies, failing to attain sufficient funding to ensure necessary maintenance and programming. Working at a system scale rather than an individual park scale, agency designers sought economy through standardization, thereby making municipal parks conventional and stereotypical in appearance as they minimized shrub plantings and other costly horticultural aspects of parks, paved paths with asphalt, and replaced grass with more apshalt in order to accommodate basketball, handball, shuffleboard, and other types of hard-surface, equipment-based recreation. Fences and regulatory signs proliferated as managers with constrained budgets substituted these for on-site supervision. It was no longer acceptable for parks to be merely tranquil; they had to be entertaining as well.</p><p>Landscape as entertainment had already been demonstrated at the several world's fairs that had taken place since the middle of the nineteenth century. Perhaps no other fair captured people's futuristic imagination or nourished their consumeristic hunger for the fruits of technology so successfully as the <date when="1939">1939</date> World's Fair in <name type="place">New York</name> City. As with other earlier fairs, the sponsors of this one intended to leave behind a permanent park after its temporary structures and exhibitions had been dismantled. But now landscape design and the world's fair were merging in another way. More than a showcase of many cultures and new developments in industrial science and technology, this fair was billed as a visionary preview of the coming attractions of modern urbanism. It was called the World of Tomorrow.</p></div><div type="subsection"><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">The World of Tomorrow: The <date when="1939">1939</date> World's Fair</hi></hi></head><p>The <date when="1939">1939</date> World's Fair held at <name type="place">New York</name> City's Flushing Meadow&#x2013;Corona Park presented Depression-ridden Americans with a consumerist vision of a future in which many electric gadgets and labor-saving household appliances would become commonplace. Moreover, there would be nearly universal automobile ownership, fast commuter highways, and single-family homes in leafy suburbs. Fairgoers thrilled to the possibilities of technological modernity as symbolically portrayed by Harrison &amp; Fouilhoux's highly visible all-white Theme Center composed of the 610-foot-high (190-meter-high) Trylon and 180-foot-diameter (55-meter-diameter) Perisphere, embraced by the Helicline, a gently sloping, curving ramp almost a 1,000 feet (305 meters) long (fig. 12.34).<ref target="#CH12-n24"><hi rend="sup"><hi rend="bold">24</hi></hi></ref></p><p><name type="pname">George McAneny</name>, head of the Regional Plan Association, Grover Whelan, business leader and former police commissioner, and Percy Straus, chief executive of Macy's department store, were the principal sponsors of the <date when="1939">1939</date> fair. They saw it as a means of stimulating the economy and promoting <name type="place">New York</name>'s leadership as a commercial capital. Parks Commissioner <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name> saw visitors' need to come to it by automobile as well as by subway as an opportunity to further his agenda of parkway building. He also saw the fair as a means of turning the destroyed Flushing Meadow salt marsh&#x2014;described<pb n="431"/><pb n="431" type="orig"/>by <name type="pname">F. Scott Fitzgerald</name> in <hi rend="italic">The Great Gatsby</hi> as the "Valley of Ashes," a cindery wasteland where the city dumped its garbage&#x2014;into "the Versailles of America" after the fair was over. He hired <name type="pname">Gilmore D. Clarke</name> to design the park in advance of the fair and then fit the fair's building program to its outlines.</p><p><name type="pname">Moses</name> never fully realized his original dream of Versailles-in-Queens because World War II postponed the construction of parks and other public improvements. Estimated profits earmarked for the undertaking failed to materialize by the time a second fair on the same site, the World's Fair of <date when="1964">1964</date>, closed in <date when="1965">1965</date>. But the <name type="place">New York</name> City Parks Department did build a park, minus some of its intended grandeur, within the retained footprint of the two fairs. Within its boundaries, a new science museum, botanical garden, zoo, ice-skating rink, boating lake, art museum, outdoor concert bowl, sports stadium, and several works of sculpture&#x2014;all legacies from the two world's fairs&#x2014; enriched the Borough of Queens. In design terms, the park bears the stamp of the <name type="pname">Moses</name> era when BeauxArts-trained landscape architects such as Clarke grappled with the influence of modernism, producing the type of stripped-down Neoclassical layout that still prevails in many of <name type="place">New York</name> City's parks.</p><p>But it was not the design of the fairgrounds or the modernism of the architecture that created the almost breathless wonder that some people still remember experiencing at the <date when="1939">1939</date> fair. It was the exhibits. Visitors ascending the Helicline and entering the Perisphere found themselves to be giants overlooking a miniaturized 11,000-square-mile planned metropolis for 1.5 million people. Called Democra-city and created by industrial designer Henry Dreyfuss with Wright's Broadacre City in mind, it segregated residential, commercial, and industrial activities into sectors linked by expressways. Here the commuters of the future saw satellite suburbs surrounding Centerton, the business, educational, and cultural hub of Democracity. Some of these suburbs were called Millvilles because, in the tradition of the garden-city movement, they were intended to contain sites for industry. Others, called Pleasantvilles, were purely residential and prefigured the suburbs that would blanket the agricultural fields of Long Island and other parts of the country after World War II.</p><figure xml:id="fig-533"><graphic url="CH12_036.jpg"/><figDesc><hi rend="bold">12.34. Trylon and Perisphere, designed by Harrison &amp; Fouilhoux, Flushing Meadow, <name type="place">New York</name> City. <date when="1939">1939</date></hi></figDesc></figure><p>An even more exciting exhibit at the fair was Norman Bel Geddes's Futurama housed in the General Motors Pavilion. Here was a 35,700-square-foot (3,320-square-meter) model of <name type="place">America</name> in <date when="1960">1960</date>, a technologically marvelous place crossed by seven-lane, continental-scale highways upon which lowcost, air-conditioned, diesel-powered, teardrop-shaped automobiles traveled at speeds up to 100 miles per hour. In a manner that suggested Frank Lloyd Wright and the metropolitan decentralists, there were self-sufficient farming and industrial communities. There were large cities, too, and these had tall skyscrapers set in an expanse of low-rise buildings with roof gardens. With its separate pedestrian and vehicular circulation systems, this was an urban scheme that Le Corbusier would have admired. Vast acres of nature<pb n="432"/><pb n="432" type="orig"/>were set aside in federally protected areas, and there were dams and mines built according to advanced engineering technology. The visitor to Futurama viewed this model of the imaginary new American landscape from a moving aerial "carry-go-round" with upholstered seats. It was almost like taking a cross-country ride in an airplane, certainly a rarity in <date when="1939">1939</date>.</p><p>The <date when="1939">1939</date> World's Fair marked a pivotal mo-ment in American life when the United States stood on the brink of World War II. Following the war, American business and industry led the nation to unparalleled prosperity, in the process rising to the status of powerful political entities within the national life as they allied with government to form what became known as the military-industrial complex. By the time the <date when="1964">1964</date> fair took place on the original fairgrounds at Flushing Meadow, the United States had already begun its fateful participation in the Vietnam War, following policies that would seriously undermine trust in government.</p><p>Not long before the popular will asserted itself nationally in protest against the war in Vietnam, there arose in <name type="place">New York</name> a popular reaction to <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name>' authoritarian style of planning public works projects. Jane Jacobs, the magazine editor turned urban critic and theorist, saw the small-block scale and mixed residential and commercial uses in older neighborhoods as sources of irreplaceable human vitality. She organized her community to fight successfully against <name type="pname">Moses</name>'s proposed Lower Manhattan Expressway, which would have destroyed much of the urban fabric of the West Village, where she lived, and the area of the city now known as SoHo. At the same time, she built the case against superblock urban renewal projects&#x2014;the descendants of Le Corbusier's Radiant City&#x2014;in her influential book <hi rend="italic">Death and Life_of Great American Cities</hi> (<date when="1961">1961</date>).</p><p>While Jacobs and others were calling for a revaluation of the American city, many middle-class residents were abandoning it, choosing the life of the commuter suburbs alluringly portrayed at the <date when="1939">1939</date> World of Tomorrow. Postwar affluence and the pent-up demand for material goods, delayed by the Great Depression and the prolonged national emergency, caused a fever of consumerism that idealistic social thinkers such as Mumford and Stein probably found appalling. Mumford's vision of the regionally planned future was evocatively portrayed in his contemporary documentary film <hi rend="italic">The City,</hi> directed by <name type="pname">Pare Lorentz</name> and with music by Aaron Copland. But forces other than planning ideals were at work, shaping the urban region. Government-sponsored loan programs designed for veterans and other qualified buyers abetted single-family home ownership. The federal interstate highway building program increased the commercial value of rural land, especially near expressway interchanges, and this had a powerful and broad-scale effect upon the entire American landscape. A new type of development, the shopping center, began to drain business vitality from the centers of cities and a new term, <hi rend="italic">suburbia,</hi> was coined to denote the sprawling residential mass formed by the bedroom communities of the commuter generation. From the perspective of urban sprawl, as the most recent manifestation of this free-market trend is called, one may look back with admiration and some regret at the failed dreams of those who followed in Ebenezer Howard's footsteps.</p><p>After World War II, Americans became more receptive to European modernist architecture. Although popular eclectic taste still caused houses to be built in a variety of pseudohistorical idioms, there was a growing appreciation of the stylistic possibilities, construction economies, and functionalism of modern architecture in the United States as well as in Europe and South America. Landscape architects used garden design as an experimental laboratory to develop a style that was similarly emancipated from past tradition. Their efforts produced a new, if at times uncertain, direction for the profession. Whether they worked to create a regional idiom informed by local topology as did Jens Jensen, borrowed ideas from abstract art, or adhered to the architectural precepts of such exponents of European modernism as Le Corbusier and Gropius, these designers shared one characteristic: They were polemical. They would not warm their talents in the sunset glow of BeauxArts tradition as did the landscape architects who worked for <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name>. Modernism put a premium on iconoclasm, invention, and the new. It encouraged them to be original. They sought to address the needs of their time through rational, scientific problem solving. Contemporary lifestyle&#x2014;especially the leisure-loving one being invented by culturally unfettered Californians&#x2014;replaced past style as the modernist landscape designers' touchstone. Innovation, not tradition, became their watchword.</p></div></div><div type="section"><pb n="433"/><pb n="433" type="orig"/><head><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="bold">Notes for Chapter Twelve</hi></hi></head><note xml:id="CH12-n1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">1.</hi></seg><p> The Fabian Society derived its name from the Roman general Fabius Cunctator, who was known for his patient, nonconfrontational, and ultimately victorious strategies.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">2.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">John Ruskin</name>, "Of the Mystery of Life," Sesame <hi rend="italic">and Lilies: Three Lectures</hi> (<date when="1871">1871</date>, <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>: <name type="pname">Henry Altemus</name>, <date when="1892">1892</date>), pp. 219&#x2013;20.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">3.</hi></seg><p> In <date when="1919">1919</date>, twenty years after its founding by Howard, the Garden City and Town Planning Association officially defined the subject of its advocacy as "a town designed for healthy living and industry: of a size that makes possible the full measure of social life but no larger: surrounded by a rural belt&#x2014;all of the land being in public ownership or held in trust for the community."</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n4" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">4.</hi></seg><p> A more pragmatic explanation for enclosing the development is given in Eusebio G&#x00FC;ell's <date when="1904">1904</date> handwritten petition to the city of Barcelona for a building permit four years after work had begun. Here he declared, "Park conditions require special attention for maintenance and attention to the residents' security, given the fact that this is a city. For that purpose, it is necessary to surround the park with walls with large gates opening at convenient places and giving access to the main street leading to the park."</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n5" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">5.</hi></seg><p> In his influential book, <hi rend="italic">Theory and Design in the First Machine Age</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Praeger Publishers, <date when="1960">1960</date>), <name type="pname">Reyner Banham</name> points out Gropius's pivotal and even ambivalent-seeming role in the transition from an Expressionist and crafts approach to a functionalist design method. Gropius continued to seek the expressive potential of architecture in abstract, holistic terms within a functionalist context. According to him, "the objective of all creative efforts in the visual arts is to give form to space ... [in which] the laws of the physical world, the intellectual world and the world of the spirit function and are expressed simultaneously." See op. cit., p. 280. In a similar vein, the modernist Le Corbusier declared, "Architectural abstraction has this about it which is magnificently peculiar to itself, that while it is rooted in hard fact it spiritualizes it, because the naked fact is nothing more than the materialization of a possible idea." See Le Corbusier, <hi rend="italic">Towards a New Architecture</hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: The Architectural Press, <date when="1946">1946</date> ed.), p. 28.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n6" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">6.</hi></seg><p> Gropius's work before he assumed the directorship of the Bauhaus, notably the protomodern housing at Golzeng&#x00FC;t and the Fagus Factory at Alfeld-an-der-Leine, <name type="place">Germany</name>, which he designed in <date when="1911">1911</date> with Adolph Meyer (<date when="1881">1881</date>&#x2013;<date when="1929">1929</date>), displays a thorough command of various hallmarks of the International Style: mass production of housing; curtain walls of glass; unornamented, flat-roofed, cubic building blocks; and corners extending beyond the building's structural support system.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n7" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">7.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Le Corbusier</name>, <hi rend="italic">Pr&#x00E9;cisions,</hi> pp. 234&#x2013;36, as translated by and quoted in Norma Everson, <hi rend="italic">Le Corbusier: The Machine and the Grand Design</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: George Braziller, <date when="1969">1969</date>), p. 26.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n8" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">8.</hi></seg><p> The term <hi rend="italic">International Style</hi> was coined in <date when="1932">1932</date> by the architectural historian <name type="pname">Henry-Russell Hitchcock</name> (b. <date when="1903">1903</date>) and the architect Philip Johnson (b. <date when="1906">1906</date>) when they organized an exhibition of European modernist architecture at the Museum of Modern Art in <name type="place">New York</name> City.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n9" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">9.</hi></seg><p> See Chapter Ten, footnote 4 for a brief discussion of Roland Barthes' essay, "The Eiffel Tower," which discusses the Tower's oneiric function as <hi rend="italic">sign</hi>, a symbolic structure without utilitarian purpose other than that of providing visitors a panoramic view of <name type="place">Paris</name> along with such quotidian commercial amenities as food and souvenirs.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n10" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">10.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Patrick Geddes</name>, <hi rend="italic">Cities in Evolution</hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: Ernest Benn Limited, <date when="1915">1915</date>), p. 13.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n11" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">11.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 71.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n12" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">12.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 73. Geddes, and Mumford after him, distinguished between "Utopia," translated as the idealistic "No Place," and "Eutopia," the good place in reality.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n13" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">13.</hi></seg><p> Ibid., p. 95.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n14" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">14.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Clarence S. Stein</name>, <hi rend="italic">Toward New Towns for America</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Reinhold Publishing Corporation, <date when="1957">1957</date>), p. 37.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n15" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">15.</hi></seg><p> For the history of the Regional Plan of <name type="place">New York</name> I am indebted to David A. Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Planning the Great Metropolis: The <date when="1929">1929</date> Regional Plan of <name type="place">New York</name> and Its Environs</hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: E &amp; FN Spon, An Imprint of Chapman &amp; Hall, <date when="1996">1996</date>), the source of much of the information in this section.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n16" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">16.</hi></seg><p> The area of the plan's purview comprised 5,528 square miles spread over three states and 436 local governmental jurisdictions.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n17" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">17.</hi></seg><p> Letter to Frederic Delano, <date when="1922-08-21">August 21, 1922</date>, Regional Plan Papers, as quoted in Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Planning the Great Metropolis: The <date when="1929">1929</date> Regional Plan of <name type="place">New York</name> and Its Environs</hi> (<name type="place">London</name>: Chapman &amp; Hall, <date when="1996">1996</date>), p. 79.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n18" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">18.</hi></seg><p> Although the parkways built by <name type="pname">Robert Moses</name> had generously landscaped medians and margins, they were unlike the urban, boulevard-style parkways conceived by Olmsted and Vaux, being in effect MacKaye's "townless highways," with limited access points, no at-grade crossings, and a regulatory ban on truck traffic. The Saw Mill River Parkway (<date when="1926">1926</date>); the Hutchinson River, Southern State, and Wantagh Parkways (<date when="1929">1929</date>); the Sunken Meadow, Meadowbrook, and Sagtikos Parkways linking a series of large parks and bathing beaches (<date when="1929">1929</date>&#x2013;52); the Northern State Parkway (<date when="1931">1931</date>); the Henry Hudson Parkway (<date when="1933">1933</date>); the Grand Central, Interborough, and Laurelton Parkways (<date when="1936">1936</date>); and the Belt Parkway along the southern perimeter of <name type="place">Brooklyn</name> and Queens (<date when="1938">1938</date>&#x2013;40) were realized under <name type="pname">Moses</name>' authority.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n19" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">19.</hi></seg><p> For a good account of these automobile tourist "pioneers," see Warren James Belasco, <hi rend="italic">Americans on the Road: From Autocamp to Motel, <date when="1910">1910</date>&#x2013;<date when="1945">1945</date></hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>: MIT Press, <date when="1979">1979</date>).</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n20" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">20.</hi></seg><p> In <date when="1964">1964</date>, three decades after <name type="pname">Moses</name> became parks commissioner of <name type="place">New York</name>, his chosen successor, Newbold Morris, could boast that "recreation facilities have increased sevenfold in these thirty years. ... In <date when="1934">1934</date>, there were 14,827 acres of park lands of which 928 acres represented land under water. Today there are 35,760 acres, of which 9,670 acres represent land under water reserved for wildlife and used for boating, bathing and fishing, and another 2,970 acres devoted to roadways in our parkway system. The total acreage represents approximately 17.5 per cent of the total area of the City of <name type="place">New York</name>." This statistical emphasis reflected the agency's service attitude, one of keeping up with demand. Under the heading of "Golf," the <date when="1964">1964</date> Department of Parks reported that during the previous two years it had kept pace with demand: "The completion of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge will enable Brooklynites to travel easily to Richmond's less congested golf facilities. Longrange plans have been made to provide an 18-hole golf course ... in Idlewild Park and another is contemplated in Edgemere Park in Rockaway." But it was the 861 park playgrounds, some of which were built adjacent to schools and jointly operated with the Board of Education, that were the "hub of <name type="place">New York</name> City's recreational system." Two recently constructed golf courses in Marine Park, <name type="place">Brooklyn</name>, covered 210 acres of what had been "low salt marshlands, which were filled with sanitation refuse and covered with manufactured topsoil under our land reclamation program." The report further announced a contract "for the preparation of the site to receive sanitation fill in the area east of Shore Road in Eastchester Bay, in Pelham Bay Park [which] after completion of the landfill, ... will be developed as a park for recreational purposes." See <hi rend="italic">30 Years of Progress: <date when="1934">1934</date>&#x2013;<date when="1964">1964</date></hi>, Report to the Mayor and Board of Estimate (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="place">New York</name> Department of Parks, <date when="1964">1964</date>), pp. 5&#x2013;7, 69.</p><p>In <date when="1964">1964</date>, altogether 1,466 acres of parkland had been, or were being, "created by landfill with refuse wastes." Here at the beginning of the environmental movement, the author participated in a battle led by the Parks Council, a civic association, to prevent this action and preserve the salt marsh in Pelham Bay Park. For the history and ecology of Pelham Bay Park, see Elizabeth Barlow, <hi rend="italic">The Forests and Wetlands of <name type="place">New York</name> City</hi> (<name type="place">Boston</name>: Little, Brown and Company, <date when="1971">1971</date>).</p><p>To understand how <name type="pname">Moses</name> fulfilled his vision and created a park system containing 14,000 acres of landscaped and natural parkland, 861 playgrounds, 17 swimming pools, 18 miles of public beaches, 12 golf courses, and 459 tennis courts, see Robert Caro, <hi rend="italic">The Power Broker</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: <name type="pname">Alfred A. Knopf</name>, <date when="1974">1974</date>). Caro writes of the boldness and breadth of <name type="pname">Moses</name>' regional-scale vision, of which the <name type="place">New York</name> City park system was merely the nucleus, and of how its implementation involved a complex nexus of appointments to offices that permitted him to weld transportation and recreation improvements into a unified construction program.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n21" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">21.</hi></seg><p> Galen Cranz, <hi rend="italic">The Politics of Park Design: A History of Urban Parks in America</hi> (<name type="place">Cambridge</name>, <name type="place">Massachusetts</name>: MIT Press, <date when="1982">1982</date>), pp. 98&#x2013;99. This work of interdisciplinary scholarship by an architectural sociologist is an excellent study of the ways in which cultural values shape public space.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n22" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">22.</hi></seg><p> <name type="pname">Dennis Domer</name>, ed., <hi rend="italic">Alfred Caldwell: The Life and Work of a Prairie School Architect</hi> (<name type="place">Baltimore</name>: The Johns Hopkins Press, <date when="1997">1997</date>), p. 183.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n23" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">23.</hi></seg><p> Cranz, <hi rend="italic">The Politics of Park Design</hi>, p. 107.</p></note><note xml:id="CH12-n24" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol"><hi rend="bold">24.</hi></seg><p> For vivid accounts of the fair and and the impression the Trylon and Perisphere made on visitors, see E. L. Doctorow's autobiographical novel <hi rend="italic">World's Fair</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Random House, <date when="1985">1985</date>); Robert Rosenblum, "Remembrance of Fairs Past" in Rosemarie Haag Bletter, et al., <hi rend="italic">Remembering the Future: The <name type="place">New York</name> World's Fair from <date when="1939">1939</date> to <date when="1964">1964</date></hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: The Queens Museum/ Rizzoli, <date when="1989">1989</date>); and David Gelernter, <hi rend="italic"><date when="1939">1939</date>: The Lost World of the Fair</hi> (<name type="place">New York</name>: Avon, <date when="1995">1995</date>).</p></note></div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>